<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-09">Dec. 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1279</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1279.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-09">Dec. 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance continually receives letters from its members and from friends of the organization which indicate that where work to sustain national consciousness progresses in full force, where Alliance groups are being created, and where our people gather willingly under the Polish national banner--even there--the demon of hatred, lies, and abusive name-calling sows its obnoxious seeds and attempts to weaken the good work of the faithful sons of our motherland. Our brethren and sympathizers inform the Dziennik Zwiazkowy that, if a group of the Polish National Alliance is formed where a pastor is an opponent of national organizations, thunderous abusive words soon fall upon the Alliance and such affiliated organizations as the Falcons and the Polish Military Alliance. The pulpit, where the word of God should be preached--words of love and Christian truth--becomes a place where terms of hatred and abusive names <pb facs="5423968_8_1280.jpg" n="2"/>are frequently uttered against....seventy thousand good Catholics, simply because, besides being religious people, they also wish to be Poles and to work to the best of their ability for our oppressed Poland. These attacks are not as intense or as frequent now as they were during the past several years, but that they are still being made is proved by the letters which the Alliance receives from authoritative people, who are properly indignant against the attackers.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance has recently received letters to the effect that pastors obstruct the Alliance's development, place curses upon it, call its members atheists, unbelievers, Masons, and God knows what else. The most intense attacks are made against the administration of the Alliance--those leaders chosen by the people of the Alliance. Such tactics are antiquated and have often disappointed opponents of our organization. Now, too, they will have a result contrary to the one anticipated by our opponents. Groups of the Polish National Alliance and affiliated organizations continue to form in these localities where thunderous attacks are <pb facs="5423968_8_1281.jpg" n="3"/>most intense. The people in church listen calmly to their pastor's words of denunciation and think to themselves: "Talk all you want but we will be members of the Polish National Alliance, because this organization proves by its work on every occasion that it honestly fulfills its obligations for the welfare of Poland and our own people." And they enroll! The Alliance increases its numbers monthly, and will continue to do so, because it is great enough with its work, its national ideals, and its justice, to overcome every type of evil. The numerous attacks aimed at this organization are dispersed like ocean waves against a granite wall.</p>
   <p>The news also reaches the organization that here and there some misguided "comrade," who follows the international banner, also attacks the Alliance with poisonous words. These individuals denounce the organization's national ideals, its best workers, its patriotic activity. As a substitute they recommend to our Polish people false mottoes, which would tear out the sacred love of our motherland and respect for everything that is ours--that is Polish. Then again, apostate priests utter pretenses about the <pb facs="5423968_8_1282.jpg" n="4"/>Polish National Alliance, make unsuccessful attempts to harm our organization, and endeavor to misguide people in order to attract them to their aimless Union, to foster the reading of their "Sentinels" and "Dawns," and to gain followers for their church. The first, as well as the second and third, are concerned only with gaining control over people. Their primary interest is to obtain material gains from their followers. Their sole aim is to enlist in their ranks as many people as possible and to blindfold the poor man so that he cannot see beyond a given realm of ambitious people, who care more for themselves than for the welfare of the people.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance does not recognize castes parties, or convictions. It receives Poles, regardless of their political, religious or social beliefs, as long as they are honest in their lives and wish to work on behalf of our motherland according to their best abilities and strength. In every nation there are political parties, partisanship, and people of various political convictions, and yet a nation, by wise government and the diligent work of the whole people, is able to develop, become wealthy, <pb facs="5423968_8_1283.jpg" n="5"/>and grow in power. Likewise, in the Polish National Alliance there are people of various convictions and political parties, and yet that does not hinder them in the least from working side by side for the organization's welfare. There is a place and work in the Alliance for every sincere Pole. He can easily embrace all our Polish-Americans without harm to anyone and with benefit to us all. In the Alliance, besides co-operative work in behalf of our people, everyone has freedom of action in fields which best suit his taste. Let the spiritual leaders pray and be solicitous for the salvation of the souls of lambs entrusted to their care. Let the socialists spread their economic doctrines in a sincere and noble manner. A member of the Alliance of Polish Falcons should develop his muscles and his staunchness of spirit. A follower of the Polish Singers' Alliance should spread the love of Polish songs. Members of the Polish Military Alliance should develop military discipline. But in national matters, everyone in the Alliance must be equal, zealous, and guided by one thought. To those who themselves are unwilling to work in behalf of the Polish cause, and even hinder others from doing so, who attack their people, their own historic past, and patriotic feelings, or who would rather <pb facs="5423968_8_1284.jpg" n="6"/>be affiliated with foes of our nationality than with their own brethren-- to those, naturally, the Polish National Alliance is distasteful.</p>
   <p>A person would have to be basically evil, limited, and a betrayer of his own people to persecute the Polish National Alliance for the deeds it performs--for assuring an existence to widows and orphans left by deceased members and for working in the field of national and social endeavors. But every good and useful thing will always be attacked by evil-thinking people--spiritual dwarfs, who are blinded by the brightness of an ideal which they cannot comprehend or are unable to feel. The Polish National Alliance really must be a good and great thing for the Polish people, since it is attacked so vehemently by the various knights of industry or giddy-heads, whose activity it unmasks and from whose quakery it saves people. It teaches our people to love Poland, and thus spoils the business of many people who are not interested in Polish affairs but are primarily concerned about their own person. These individuals desire to rule our people without any intervention on the part of the Polish National Alliance, and to profit from the generosity of the people. The patriotic, ideological, and progressive <pb facs="5423968_8_1285.jpg" n="7"/>Alliance, therefore, must conduct a battle on several fronts. It is attacked on all sides by extreme clericals, as well as extreme radicals, and a mixture of all types of ravers--people who have never been satisfied anywhere with anything or anybody. But the mass of our people, in all their power, see where justice is, where good work is being accomplished, where a pure national ideal exists, over and beyond the ravings; and with a feeling of human indignation they join the order of the day. In the meantime, right-thinking Poles gather under the national standard of Poland, because that insignia is the best and dearest to them. That the ideal of the Alliance is great and sacred is proved by the fact that no human enmity is in a position to harm it.</p>
   <p>If an organization built upon unsound foundations, without a definite idea and devoid of activity, were subjected to such avalanches of abuse, attack, and underhandedness, it could not last a year, it would be destined to ruin. But the idea of the Polish National Alliance is great, and holy to every right-thinking Pole. As a result of this our people gather to it; <pb facs="5423968_8_1286.jpg" n="8"/>they increase the lines of workers for our national cause and create miracles in a foreign land.</p>
   <p>The old, worn-out strategy of the Alliance's enemies is to attack primarily those who stand at the head of the organization. They even explain hypo-critically that they have nothing against the Polish National Alliance as a whole, but oppose only the leaders or officials. Supposedly the reason for directing the attacks against the administration is the ficticious notion that it is responsible for the Polish National Alliance's failure to be sufficiently clerical to please some and sufficiently, radical to please others. Throughout the existence of the Alliance and its various administrations it has ever been thus, that these people were first to be attacked. The disruptive element thinks that if it were possible to kill off the officers the army would be dispersed. The present administration of the Alliance, and the editorial staff, is not the first, nor will it be the last, against whom abusive terms, calumnies, and attacks are directed. Whoever stands at the head of this organization--even if he be a man of the <pb facs="5423968_8_1287.jpg" n="9"/>greatest intelligence, the most righteous character, and the greatest spirit, will be attacked by the poisonous darts of spiritual dwarfs. Moreover, the better a given official is and the more sincerely he works for the Alliance and its high ideals, the more bitterly he is fought by various individuals whose purposes he does not wish to serve and whom he will not permit to besmirch our clean national banner. But people of the Polish National Alliance are honest and wise; they have usually rewarded with their continued trust those whom the career-seekers and madmen attacked most.</p>
   <p>In the last analysis, we are not so much concerned here with the officials as with the entire Polish National Alliance and its development. Various personages can attack us as individuals working in the Polish National Alliance; they can insult us and make false statements. That does not bother us in the least; we have a clear conscience and have the conviction that our work is sincere in behalf of our beloved national organization. We defend not ourselves but the Polish National Alliance against the attacks of its enemies. Every official called to work by our people--especially editors of the Polish National Alliance newspapers--knows that <pb facs="5423968_8_1288.jpg" n="10"/>he will be sent into the lines of first attack. They are aware that they will be showered with dirty, abusive terms and calumnies, that various paid agents will attempt to make them appear odious to society and even to their own brethren of the Alliance. Before going into the Alliance headquarters, every newly-elected official knows that he is going there to listen not to hymns of praise but to the roars of mobs opposed to the Alliance. These roars will be especially loud when he defends the organization bravely and energetically against the attacks of its enemies. The only things that alleviate the torment of this noble fighter are words of recognition and encouragement that he receives from his fellow members of the Alliance in all parts of the United States, and the conviction that he works on behalf of our people and that he suffers persecution for Poland's cause. Let the band of madmen and enemies of national ideals direct their attacks against us--we will not yield. We will not surrender our post even if we fall in the battle, as many of our predecessors have fallen, whose lives were poisoned by various degenerates. Whether it be in the rank of officer or in the capacity of ordinary soldiers of our nationality, we shall fearlessly fight every type of meanness and human perversion that centers its attack on the integrity of such an idealistic <pb facs="5423968_8_1289.jpg" n="11"/>national organization as is the Polish National Alliance. The Polish people in America are, therefore, urged not to lose faith but to work even more diligently in behalf of Poland's cause, and thus to defeat the purposes of the enemies of our nationality. This our people can accomplish by joining the Polish National Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
