<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-06-21">June 21, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">We Should Assist Our Younger Generation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item><item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-06-21">June 21, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">WE SHOULD ASSIST OUR YOUNGER GENERATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In several articles we have pointed out the needs of our younger generation, but without any appreciable success, for the reason that the upbringing of children is done on the lowest level where it suffers shame, damage, loss, and despair. Polish quarters in American cities, outside the Italian, breed the greatest number of delinquents. The average American hesitates to pass, in the late hours of the evening, through streets that are inhabited by Polish people, for even during the day some misfortune is liable to occur to him. We see all this, are very hurt, and yet do nothing to right the wrongs.</p>
   <p>In a recent article, under the title "Parents, Wake Up," we made a formal appeal to Polish parents, an appeal to help their children, as much as possible, obtain an education or training in some particular field. Their conduct was pointed out, along with the losses suffered by them, which are tremendously high among Polish-American youth, due to the negligence of the parents who permit them to loaf about the streets, which is the cause of <pb facs="5423968_8_0194.jpg" n="2"/>their degradation and vagrancy. We have brought out the importance of training children in their early years, especially at school, where they come in contact with American customs. This is typical of metropolitan centers and has an important bearing upon the child's later years.</p>
   <p>Within a short time the vacation period will be here. Tens of thousands of Polish children will leave the confines of the school room to rest for two months and absorb enough energy for further study. Among those that take interest in the younger generation, various activities are sponsored to aid them physically and morally. As an example we have the American people who look after the best interest of their children. They organize, during the vacation period, many kinds of activities conducive to the children's well-being. This is one of the reasons why we see so many of them attending summer school. Here they receive valuable training. After school they are found at many clubs organized for them. These social and athletic club rooms assist them to better sportmanship, give them training in executive position and help them come in contact with prominent people through their social activities. These youths find no time to mingle with the loafers and the hoodlums of the streets. Their chosen activity builds strong character, domineering personalities, which in later years become <pb facs="5423968_8_0195.jpg" n="3"/>priceless gifts.</p>
   <p>Poland in recent years has done a great deal for her younger generation. During the vacation periods manual training courses have been set-up, many activities in various parks have been created where the youth can obtain healthful physical training. Many lodges offer disciplinary courses for those who are about to enter the army. For the younger and physically unfit, colonies are offered where thousands are sent to be built up, to gather strength and knowledge, to keep physically fit. In this respect they not only become good citizens but become healthful specimens for posterity.</p>
   <p>It is only the Polish people in America that do not do anything to improve the conditions of their youth. Up to now not a thing has been done. If only they would organize some sort of classes that would give this youth a chance to be better fitted morally and physically: Never has this generation needed such guidance as at the present time in America. The Polish youth in reality is facing a rather precarious position, and is awaiting a worse fate. Their degeneracy is not only affecting us but also American youth, American traditions. The American press daily publishes news about <pb facs="5423968_8_0196.jpg" n="4"/>the wrong-doing of our youth, which is on the increase. These articles have damaging effects and tend to put the entire Polish population before the public eye. This kind of publicity does not help the position of the Polish people. We cannot protest, for the facts tell the story.</p>
   <p>We ought to get together and organize forces to hold in check the fatalities and crimes perpetrated by our youth. This should be done on a great scale. It would benefit both the parents and the children. This project can get a foothold through the churches, schools, and lodges. The priests and sister teachers can promote and sponsor many kinds of classes and activities that would be beneficial to our children. To check crime and foster good citizenship, we should follow the examples set by American and European countries.</p>
   <p>In Galicia, for example, there are societies that promote social athletic activities in the form of Sokols. Their work is really outstanding, youth is trained physically and morally. They are well organized, for the entire population supports their activities. The events are managed by capable <pb facs="5423968_8_0197.jpg" n="5"/>teachers and public spirited individuals. As a result their energetic work is greatly rewarded, for the events and programs are always a success.</p>
   <p>This helps stimulate interest, good health, and good citizenship.</p>
   <p>If the older people of Europe can produce such fine results, and America duplicates this example, then why cannot we become the same spirited people and help out our own children? Why cannot we organize Sokols where education in health, morals, and citizenship can be had? Why cannot our youth find prominence with the rest of the nationalities?</p>
   <p>A few of our Polish priests have started something in this direction. The results are being awaited. At the Holy Trinity Parish, in Chicago, Father K. Stuczko has arranged a boy's Sokol, under the management of a trained Gymnast. This step has produced pleasing results. Over 200 young boys are participating. This takes out this number from the streets, where they were apt to do wrong, and places the group into the guidance of the parish. Here they enjoy wholesome games, learn to be sociable, build themselves physically, and most of all, learn discipline. If this was followed by all the parishes, in several years Polish youth would find a leading place in <pb facs="5423968_8_0198.jpg" n="6"/>American life. They would become the pride of the family, the club, the church, and would also be respected by other citizens. Therefore this is one of the important steps to save our children, our youth, for the betterment of our nationality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
