<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 8,
<date when="1911-02-22">Feb. 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Chorus Girls</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0188</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0188.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 8,
<date when="1911-02-22">Feb. 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CHORUS GIRLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many American chorus girls are either Polish or of Polish descent but we know little about it because none of them bears their real family name. According to the rumors a number of our "Katies" have joined the ranks of the tucked up Muse. On that account we are going to give a few words of warning taken from a memoir of a Polish chorus girl who, although very pretty and greatly admired by many adorers, left the stage and returned to her poor mama, preferring house or office work to a stage life diversified by all kinds of adventures.</p>
   <p>Here are some excerpts from her very interesting memoirs: "Please send me all girls who think that the stage is something extraordinary, romantic and pleasant, and I shall cure them of this malady. Where have I been? I have been in every city along the main railroad line crossing the states of Illinois, Michigan and Wisconsin, while I was a show girl with a traveling theatrical company. I acted in Elgin, Davenport, Peru <pb facs="5423968_8_0189.jpg" n="2"/>and other cities. At the head of our group stood a 45 year old battleaxe with her husband who was not very young. Once she was supposed to be beautiful, and he, a good actor. The picture of that star was displayed on every corner of the street. The part of soubrette was played by a used-to-be young who blamed us girls if she did not get enough applause. The husband of the principal played the part of the manager and had to be obeyed instantly. Some of the chorus girls were intelligent, educated and had alluring personalities. All of us led a moral life and kept away from the local millionaires.</p>
   <p>Once we were invited to a supper by the son of a rich manufacturer from Valparaiso. He treated us to portions of oysters, such as are sold by local grocery stores, without shells, called sandwich oysters and one cocktail.</p>
   <p>For such a royal reception each one of us patted him on the shoulder and told him stories that he will remember for a long time; they were intended for his kind. We put on plays, but what kind? In old costumes falling to <pb facs="5423968_8_0190.jpg" n="3"/>pieces. In our group we had an old undergraduate dentist who should never have appeared on the stage.</p>
   <p>The show was supposed to start at eight but it never did till nine; up till that time the public ate pounds of peanuts. The manager of our group held us in "regard" chartering very early trains. At three A. M. they woke us up. The hotel clerks always charged us lower rates, that is, fifty cents more than anybody else. After the hotel bill was paid we were rushed into a dark room. As soon as we fell asleep we were awakened by a hotel clerk. We had to dress up and hurry to get the train. We would not even think about washing or taking a bath. Occasionally some important personage from the farming district bought us a cheap box of candy or paid our fare if we lied to him that we lost it. The kindness of those small town sports was repaid by a sweet smile. For $18 per week we could not afford to live any better. How many times we slept in a 4x4 unheated room, water leaking on top of our heads. As to the meals we had no choice and were obliged to eat what they gave us.</p>
   <p>As to our wardrobe, ten girls had to dress and undress in a small room <pb facs="5423968_8_0191.jpg" n="4"/>suited for only two persons. As to supper, we could not even think of it for at that time we were on the train.</p>
   <p>Our conversation consisted of quarrels about hangnails, etc. In other words, it was a miserable life without proper nourishment or rest.</p>
   <p>Now you knew why I left the stage. Not because our soubrette was jealous of my beauty. No. I am home now and our modest home is dearest to me. I will be happy when I find some employment and earn enough to pay for my meals. I lost my taste for the stage."</p>
   <p>Let this story be a warning for those girls who leave home for the stage. The stage is not what it appears to be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
