<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-02">Apr. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Citizens of the Seventeenth Ward, Let Us Unite!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0485</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0485.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-02">Apr. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CITIZENS OF THE SEVENTEENTH WARD, LET US UNITE!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow we will have the opportunity of proving whether we understand our duties as citizens of this free land of Washington, and whether we are worthy of a free Polish republic. In order to accomplish this, we must prove that none of us carries his vote in his pocket, and that we cannot be bought with a glass of beer.</p>
   <p>Time and again we have been told that we are not able to govern ourselves because we can never agree with one another. This accusation has always been hurled against us after elections--city or national--just after we have got through helping a non-Pole defeat one of our own countrymen.</p>
   <p>And these non-Poles whom we have helped into office have laughed at us after elections, saying that we are weak-minded and have no conception of American politics.</p>
   <p>Mr. L. Sitts and Mr. Stanley Adamkiewicz are running for alderman of the Seventeenth Ward. Which name is dearer to your hearts? Ask your conscience. Think, <pb facs="5423968_8_0486.jpg" n="2"/>even though some people are urging you not to vote for a fellow Pole--will you not regret later that you denied a Pole your vote?</p>
   <p>Dear citizens, we have had enough shame, treachery, and disgrace as it is. Rouse your spirit that it may guard your actions, that we may not disgrace our Polish names, names which we all have inherited from our forefathers. Let us rejoice that although we have been persecuted in the homeland for our names, here in our adopted country we are not persecuted because of them. Therefore, we should try to the utmost of our power to have Polish names as well known as possible in the public offices of this country.</p>
   <p>Today, dear citizens, we cannot be accused of being incapable of holding public office, because our community has in many cases men who are much more capable than those of other nationalities. And the more of our own people that we elect, the more we will show in actions, not in words, that we have worthy and capable people, and the more will we be respected.</p>
   <p>Therefore, to work, citizens of the Seventeenth Ward! When you go to the polls <pb facs="5423968_8_0487.jpg" n="3"/>tomorrow morning to fulfill your civic duty, be honest with your conscience. Do not let yourselves be led astray, but look for Stanley Adamkiewicz' name and place your mark beside it. In this way we will elect him alderman, to our glory.</p>
   <p>Men and Women's Citizen Committee of the Seventeenth Ward:</p>
   <p>Mrs. A. Florkowski</p>
   <p>Mrs. M. Makowski</p>
   <p>M. Wojtecki</p>
   <p>J. Helminiak</p>
   <p>T. Weyna</p>
   <p>Mrs. H. Szymanski</p>
   <p>R. Kosinski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
