<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 10,
<date when="1923-03-08">March 8, 1923</date><title level="a">The Duties of the American Citizen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 10,
<date when="1923-03-08">March 8, 1923</date><title level="a">THE DUTIES OF THE AMERICAN CITIZEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Quite often we write and speak about citizenship, about taking out naturalization papers, but not very often do we consider the duties and obligations of a citizen. Some American bigots think that good citizenship depends on reading, writing and speaking the English language and despising all other languages and nationalities. A person speaking English beautifully and writing it correctly is not always a good citizen; neither the one who speaks it poorly is a bad citizen.</p>
   <p>In order to be a good citizen, regardless whether it be a citizen of the United States, England, Poland, or any other country, it is necessary to love that country. The one who loves the country will try to acquaint himself with the constitution and laws of that country and, if necessary, be ready to defend it.</p>
   <p>Every good citizen, not only knows all what is going on in polities in his country, but also during elections investigates the characters and <pb facs="5423968_8_0403.jpg" n="2"/>views of the candidates; he votes during all elections, city, county, state and national, for such a candidate who in his opinion will render the best service to the country.</p>
   <p>A good citizen considers it his duty to belong to some political party which in his opinion serves the country most efficiently and he himself should work in that direction. He has always courage to voice his opinion in political matters and works for the country with determination. It is the duty of a citizen to defend his country in case of need and serve in the army during war. It is understood that it should be considered an honor for every citizen to observe and abide by the laws of his country, pay taxes, and give true account of his income.</p>
   <p>Every citizen who wishes to be called a good citizen should get acquainted with the function of every department of the government. He should spread among his neighbors and fellow workers the principles of good citizenship. He should promote education and loyalty among those <pb facs="5423968_8_0404.jpg" n="3"/>who have not yet taken out citizen papers. He also should study the economical problems of his country and its foreign policy.</p>
   <p>Finally, a good citizen will try to give his children a good education in a national and religious spirit, so that they in turn night serve their country and their God.</p>
   <p>When we become citizens of any country we inherit the fruit of many generations who lived before us, but we also inherit the obligations which we must fulfill and hand down to our children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
