<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-12">Feb. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Tenth Anniversary of Nest 105 of the Alliance of Polish Falcons</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1029</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1029.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-12">Feb. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TENTH ANNIVERSARY OF NEST 105 OF THE ALLIANCE OF POLISH FALCONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday Nest 105 of the Alliance of Polish Falcons, Group 962 of the Polish National Alliance, celebrated its tenth anniversary at its meeting place, Pulaski Hall, 4831-38 South Throop Street, with impressive exercises.</p>
   <p>Shortly before 3 P. M. many groups of Falcon children, Falcons, and Falcon women, a group of the Alliance of Polish Military Societies and several local groups of the Polish National Alliance marched to St. John of God's Church, 52nd and Throop Streets, despite the cold. The parade marched in the following order. It was led by Mr. W. Lagoski's band, composed of twelve pieces, which was followed by the tenth anniversary committee, composed of the following: J. Korczewski, W. Lencki, S. Streysman, A. Wojcischowicz, S. Rozanski, S. Stachowski, W. Slowinski, A. Wasylik, and A. Tygielski. This committee carried the banners of Nest 105. Then followed the group of school children, numbering twenty-six girls and thirty-four boys. These were followed by the Falcon Women's Nest 133 of the Alliance of Polish Falcons, Group 1141 of the Polish National <pb facs="5423968_8_1030.jpg" n="2"/>Alliance, with Lucy Konecka, its commandant, at its head. These were followed by a division of King Sigismund I's Hussars, Group 1860 of the Polish National Alliance, resplendent in their uniforms. Then followed Nest 105; Falcon Nest 37, the Society of the Sons of the Polish Crown, Group 681 of the Polish National Alliance; the Valiant Thousand Society, Group 1378; the Victory at Grunwald Society, Group 1192 of the Polish National Alliance; the God Save Poland Society, Group 1955 of the Polish National Alliance; and the K. Brodzinski Dramatic Circle.</p>
   <p>Vespers were celebrated by Reverend S. Bubacz, assistant at St. John of God's Parish, and Reverend L. Grudzinski, rector of the parish, delivered a speech from the pulpit appropriate to the occasion, mentioning the work of the nest celebrating its tenth anniversary and the work of Polish societies and organizations in general. After the services everyone repaired to Pulaski Hall, where the tenth anniversary celebration was held.</p>
   <p>The exercises were opened by B. Kowalewski, well-known banker of Town of Lake <pb facs="5423968_8_1031.jpg" n="3"/>and member of the local nest, who called on Z. Szmidt, president of the nest, to preside over the gathering, and on Joseph Korczewski to act as secretary. The chairman, in a short speech, recalled the founding of the nest, its work, and experiences during the ten years of its existence, after which the program was begun.</p>
   <p>The first number on the program was "Sygnaly Wojenne" (War Signals), played by Mr. W. Lagocki's orchestra. This was followed by a long speech lasting almost an hour by John Przyprawa, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, who was constantly interrupted by enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>The Druzyna Choir under the direction of B. J. Zalewski sang "Wiazanka Piesni Narodowych" (Medley of Polish National Songs), for which the audience rewarded the singers with enthusiastic applause, forcing them to sing an encore. The encore was Rzepki's "Mazurek". Miss Lucy Konecki, commandant of Falcon Women's Nest 133, recited "Badz Gotow Sokole" (Falcon, Be Ready). The chairman then asked Miss Harriet Rozanski, Lucy Konecki, and Gertrude Eichman to take up a <pb facs="5423968_8_1032.jpg" n="4"/>collection for relief, while Mr. W. Lagocki's orchestra played "Bukiet Melodji Polskich" (Bouquet of Polish Melodies). The collection yielded $17.23, for which chairman Z. Szmidt thanked the audience. He then invited Mr. A. Wojciechowicz, one of the founders of the nest, to come up on the stage, and after an appropriate speech, gave him a gold medal as a gift of Nest 105 in appreciation of his work. Then gifts and good wishes were tendered by nests and societies. The gifts were as follows: King Sigismund I's Hussars Society, Group 1860 of the P. N. A., gave $5; Falcon Women's Nest 133, $10; Falcons Nest 37, $10; Boze Cos Polske (God Save Poland) Society, Group 1955 of the P. N. A., $5; Zwyciestwo Pod Grunwaldem (Victory at Grunwald) Society, $5; Brodzinski Circle, $5; Tysiac Walecsnych (Valiant Thousand) Society, Group 1378 of the P. N. A., $10; Synowie Korony Polskiej (Sons of the Polish Crown) Society, Group 681 of the P. N. A., $5; Foresterki Serca nnnWomen Foresters of the Sacred Heart of Mary) Society, $5.</p>
   <p>In conclusion everyone joined in the singing of the Falcon anthem, "Ospaly i Gnusny" (Sleepy and Lazy), to the accompaniment of the orchestra. It should be <pb facs="5423968_8_1033.jpg" n="5"/>added that all the numbers on the program came out very well, and the audience applauded enthusiastically. The dancing which followed the exercises lasted far into the night.</p>
   <p>It should be stated here that the committee in charge of the celebration has prepared an anniversary booklet containing photographs of the members of Nest 105 of the Alliance of Polish Falcons, the present officers of the nest, the members of Women's Nest 133, and the committee in charge of the tenth anniversary celebration. All of these photographs were taken by Walter Narozny, well-known photographer, member of Nest 37 of the Alliance of Polish Falcons, who has his studio at 4841 South Ashland Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
