<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-11">Jan. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Unity of the People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0508</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0508.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-11">Jan. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">UNITY OF THE PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In one of the Warsaw daily journals, The Morning Gazette, appears an article favorable to the Polish people in America. Although some parts of the article do not approve of our present position there is a marked indication that our people abroad take interest in our affairs. They are greatly concerned about our interests, because some day we may be of great help to them and their torn country.</p>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that the Poles in America have the interest of Poland at heart. We are continuing the everlasting fight for the freedom of Poland just as our people are in Europe, despite the constant efforts of those who have been trying to wipe us out of existence.</p>
   <p>The Morning Gazette has found out through private sources that the Polish people in America have organized forces, numbering several thousand men, that are ready to aid the already fighting English, French, and Belgian soldiers. These men are willing to sacrifice their lives for the cause of <pb facs="5423968_8_0509.jpg" n="2"/>our fathers, our country.</p>
   <p>The paper rejoices because of this. It is happy to hear that fathers and sons, who unable to make a living left their crippled motherland and found shelter and peace in America, are now ready to fight for that which was rightfully theirs. They laud these volunteers for being willing to give up their lives and leave behind their work, their homes, and their families.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the Morning Journal (Gazeta Poranna) does not know that this kind of demonstration and activities are against Washington's wishes. This endangers the neutrality of the United States. The Journal did not know that thousands of our young Poles were ready to go across the seas to help Poland. However, circumstances did not permit their leaving. Perhaps at a later time this will be possible. These young men will still be fired with the same desire to give Poland a helping hand.</p>
   <p>We are not in despair because of this. Perhaps this has happened for the <pb facs="5423968_8_0510.jpg" n="3"/>best. These ready volunteers are in constant preparation and when the day comes for them to do their share for Poland, they will be ready. We are not permitted to fight on foreign soil for Poland; we are barred from the territories of Belgium and France. Therefore, it is wrong for anyone to say that the ardor of the American Poles has cooled, that the fire that was burning for our mother country has slowly turned to ashes, and the stigma brandished by our enemies, forgotten.</p>
   <p>However we agree with the Warsaw paper that our attitude towards Poland, that is, preparedness within our ranks to aid our country, has not been influenced by any agitation through anyone in the United States or abroad. Although the stand we have taken on immigration is to a certain extent a result of the ideas our Polish-American representatives acquired while in Europe, the aims and purposes of our immediate political policy are truly American. Our present relations today, instead of having a different outlook, are also due to different causes.</p>
   <p>The Morning Gazette points out that our position is a direct result of the <pb facs="5423968_8_0511.jpg" n="4"/>close contact of our people, despite the fact that nations and oceans separate us, or the passing of the many years of separation. As long as the people are of one nationality, as long as there is active life in the Polish organizations, the Polish spirit will not weaken and the ties will not be severed. No matter where the Polish people may be, the same relations are prevalent. Across rivers and mountains, across the seas, faster than the impulses of the telegraph, invisible magnetic impulses flash and tend to move the souls and hearts of the sons of a common blood. Agitation is useless, mail and telegraphic communications are of no advantage.</p>
   <p>When the masses of people met with abusive treatment by the German warlords in Galicia and Posen, when the Teutonic wrath fell upon those in Kalish, Kielce, Nieszawa, and Czestochowa, all those of the former kingdom of Poland, though scattered over many parts of the world and separated by distant seas, became aware of these disasters instinctively. They not only became aware of what has occurred but also had a feeling of the impending crisis. Although the Poles are separated and live in many countries, they are mentally preparing for the inevitable.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0512.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Polish people at the present time may not be leaving their jobs and their homes to give their lives for Poland, yet they are ready to give assistance as soon as time warrants it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
