<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-07">Jan. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Discussion on Russian Violence. Do the Poles Love Their Own Country?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0676</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0676.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-07">Jan. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">DISCUSSION ON RUSSIAN VIOLENCE. DO THE POLES LOVE THEIR OWN COUNTRY?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Text of Szczesny Zahajkiewicz's speech given at the mass meeting January 1, at the Polish Hall of St. Stanislaus Kostki's parish at Bradley and Division Streets.)</p>
   <p>"This is a superfluous question! Ask those still living on the soil of old Poland which through the many decades has become saturated with the blood of her toiling defenders; ask those in the enemy camps, in cold and dark dungeons; and those on the desolate frontiers of Siberia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0677.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These poor unfortunate Poles despite their persecution and inevitable death raise their eyes heavenward and pray for the freedom of their kind.</p>
   <p>"Do only those Polish people love their native land that live on its soil and those that make a profit from it? Do those that are scattered over many parts of the world cherish warm thoughts of Poland? One of our well known poets answers these questions in fine style.</p>
   <p>"Although a Pole becomes renown,</p>
   <p>Or becomes chained to the ground,</p>
   <p>Beaten to death or kept in jail,</p>
   <p>Or left in exile on the pale</p>
   <p>Fronts of Siberia or fights for his land,</p>
   <p>He is able to smile at the thoughts of his fatherland!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0678.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Those of us who have braved the elements to come to this country, in many cases were like the debris of a wrecked ship that has reached shore. It was through the will of God that we were able to come to a democratic country. Our native land is left far behind. We can only picture this once great country in our minds, this country that was once the pride and joy of our father's,' for today its fate is darker than ever. We cannot fathom the struggle these oppressed souls are making to continue in the tracks of traditional Poland. How can we picture the pity of it all, how can we visualize the heart rendering suffering, the sacrifices of life, and the pillaging of homes. These people are in the shackels of the enemy and are having their energy sapped and their hopes dulled like a monster in chains whose blood is being constantly tapped by brutal wounds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0679.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>" That we are true Poles, that we love our native land and our people is proven by the fact that we have followed and moulded the same traditions and beliefs of our fathers. We have not discarded any of our characteristics because we were deprived of them in Europe. Instead we have built solid foundations for them. Churches were built and our religious fervor restored. These new pillars are not weak among new peoples and surroundings. They are sound. It shows that we are Polish.</p>
   <p>"However, we did not stop here. Our progress continued.....continues. We have managed to organize schools in our parishes in order that our children could be taught our religion, have an understanding of our language, become familiar with the history of our people and above all to have the children of our Polish people remain Polish!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0680.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Furthermore, we have gatherings and parades, we commemorate our national holidays,along with those of this country. Through these demonstrations we show that deep in our hearts the love of our people is very warm-that we love our country.</p>
   <p>The poet Krasicki says:</p>
   <p>"The holidays in our native land</p>
   <p>Are observed with solemnity,</p>
   <p>Admidst the taste of bitter cruelty,</p>
   <p>Admidst prison walls and bleak steepes,</p>
   <p>Only to show us that in these unjust roles,</p>
   <p>Our people are not sorry to exist-not sorry to be Poles!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0681.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"I know that if any of you were told that you are not patriotic-not a Pole, you would feel offended and consider this an insult.</p>
   <p>"It shows that this love, this patriotism is reproduced and expressed by the Poles on foreign soil. I repeat once again, that through our solidarity, the building of schools, through national organizations we are trying to preserve and spread our Polish tongue and traditions.</p>
   <p>"But this is only being done for self-preservation and for the betterment of our position in American affairs. Is this enough? Listen fellow brothers ! In order to find a permanent place for ourselves and the freedom of our oppressed people abroad we must think of Poland as a whole.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0682.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>We must not forget the less fortunate across the sea because they are putting up a fight far nobler than ours. Let us remember that this is what has kept us alive and will keep us alive. Remember, in unity there is power!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
