<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-02-11">Feb. 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Naturalization Schools in Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-02-11">Feb. 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">NATURALIZATION SCHOOLS IN CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish Naturalization Schools in Chicago are filled with prospective candidates for citizenship. A notice of the various changes in naturalization laws and requirements in a recent edition of Polish newspapers is the principale reason for this capacity attendance. The largest of these schools is conducted by S. Kolanowski. It is located at Walsh's Hall at Noble and Emma Sts., the only school of its kind on the North Side. Upon the invitation of Mr. S. L. Kolanowski the School will have a prominent guest speaker, the Hon. Edmund J. Jarecki, who will appear on Feb. 13, 1928; on this date the birthday of president Lincoln and Thaddeus Kesciuszko will be celebrated.</p>
   <p>Judge Jarecki, has not, as yet, announced the subject of his lecture, but the birthday of these two great men will undoubtedly be associated with the importance of citizenship and naturalization proceedings. Judge Jarecki has, on many occassions, used this vital subject of citizenship as a text for his lectures. The classes of this School are open every Monday evening, from 7:30 p.m. to 10:30 p.m.; there are also branches of the School, one of which is located at 46th and Lincoln Sts., in the Town of Lake District, the other is located at 43rd and Rockwell in Brighton Park, where classes are open every Sunday afternoon, between the hours of one and 4 p.m.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0388.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At least 250 Poles have filed the Declaration of Intention as compared with the total 135 which were filed but a short time ago, a fact that points to the School's merits.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kolanowski announces that those who entered the United States illegally are not eligible for naturalization unless the date of the entry was prior to June 3, 1921. Those arriving after this date, are not eligible for naturalization and are hereby requested, in the spirit of fairness to others, not to enroll in the already crowded classes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
