<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-05">Apr. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting of Union of Lublin Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1017</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1017.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-05">Apr. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING OF UNION OF LUBLIN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Union of Lublin Society, Group No. 1 of the Polish National Alliance, held a mass meeting for the purpose of getting new members for itself and the Polish National Alliance. The meeting was held last Sunday, April 1, at Pulaski Hall, and was well attended.</p>
   <p>The program was carried out according to plan. Mr. Stanley Zukowski, a member of the group who is well known to the public, opened the meeting with a speech in which he explained the purpose of the gathering and invited the speakers, the presidents of groups, and all the performers to come up on the stage. He also asked the undersigned to act as secretary.</p>
   <p>The entertainment was as follows:</p>
   <p>(1) Professor Swierczynski's orchestra played a medley of Polish songs. The audience applauded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1018.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(2) Mr. Majchrowicz, secretary of Circuit 15 of the Polish National Alliance, demonstrated, in a long speech, the benefits which the Poles can derive by belonging to the Polish National Alliance and other Polish societies. His speech was rewarded by deserved applause.</p>
   <p>(3) Young Mr. Rozmyslowicz, accompanied by Miss Mary Rozyslowicz, played "Swiss Aria" on the violin. He was forced to give an encore.</p>
   <p>(4) Mr. S. Peplawski, president of the committee, delivered a short speech in which he urged the audience to join the ranks of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>(5) Miss Louise Chmielinski, accompanied by Miss Rosalie Nowaczewski, sang a Polish nursery rhyme. Her charming voice pleased the audience and she was forced to give an encore.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1019.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>(6) Attorney Kobrzynski, still a very young man but already a valiant Pole, spoke on the subject of the Union of Lublin and urged the people to unite. He was applauded enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>(7) Little Miss Kujak gave a recitation, which was very well liked and applauded.</p>
   <p>(8) Mr. Walkiewicz, member of the group, well known in the young people's circles of St. Adalbert Parish, proved in his very patriotic speech that, although small in stature, he possesses a great patriotic spirit.</p>
   <p>(9) Professor Swierczynski's orchestra played "The Poet and the Peasant Overture."</p>
   <p>(10) Mr. Sass, member of the group and president of the local commune, briefly explained the requirements for admission to the Society and to the Polish National Alliance, and urged the people to join.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1020.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>(11) Mr. Zukowski, chairman of the meeting, took this opportunity to suggest that a collection be made for Polish relief. Miss J. Bielinski and Miss Reklikowski collected eight dollars, which sum was handed over to Mr. Majchrowicz.</p>
   <p>At the end of the program, the chairman thanked the audience and the performers for the success of the meeting.</p>
   <p>The Union of Lublin Society is greatly obliged to Professor Swierczynski for supplying his orchestra free of charge, to Mr. Szczepkowski, who did not charge anything for the use of the hall, and to the speakers, soloists, etc., all of whom gave their services gratis.</p>
   <p>Twelve new members joined the Society and the Polish National Alliance at this meeting.</p>
   <p>A. Mazylewski, secretary of the meeting</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
