<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-29">Aug. 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">From the Political Portfolio</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-08-29">Aug. 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE POLITICAL PORTFOLIO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most important office for us American Poles, an office for which several Poles are running, is that of congressman, or representative, in Washington. Although there are about four million Poles in America, we have never had a representative. We should now exert every effort to gain one or more.</p>
   <p>For us to have such a representative in Washington now, would be a very good thing. Surely the American Government will play no small role in the conferences after the close of the European war. Therefore, if there were a Pole in Congress at that time, we should have an official who could do a great deal toward helping our cause. Who knows, fate might decree that we shall have not one, but several, representatives at the next Congress.</p>
   <p>Having all of this in mind, the Poles in Chicago and in the state of Illinois, especially, should look about them and through united and wise action raise several of our countrymen to this honorable post. That we have never before <pb facs="5423968_8_0772.jpg" n="2"/>had such a chance to elect Polish congressmen is an absolute fact. Today we want to call your attention to one of the Polish candidates for Congress who stands a good chance of being elected. We mention him separately because, of all the Polish candidates for this office, he alone must conduct his campaign throughout the entire state of Illinois, not merely in a congressional district, as is the case with the four other Polish candidates.</p>
   <p>After the census was taken in this country in 1910, the state of Illinois, according to the law, had the right to elect two additional congressmen, because of the large increase of population in this state. Since the congressional districts have not yet been changed and each district has the right to elect only one congressman, the two additional congressmen must be elected by the voters of the entire state. They will receive the title Representative at Large. There are at present fifteen candidates running for these two congressional posts for the state of Illinois. Among them <pb facs="5423968_8_0773.jpg" n="3"/>there is only one Pole, Mr. Albert J. Danisch, of 1025 Milwaukee Avenue, Chicago, brother of the well-known Francis P. Danisch, who as Chief Clerk of the Municipal Court in Chicago has given jobs to more than fifty Poles in his office and other city, state, and county, offices, with salaries ranging from twelve hundred to four thousand dollars yearly.</p>
   <p>Knowing Mr. Albert J. Danisch intimately, we know that if he is elected to Congress, he will work with all of his energy for the Polish people and will discharge his duties honorably.</p>
   <p>He is not a Pole just for business reasons, nor did he just become one when he saw that association with his own people would benefit him. From earliest childhood, both he and his brother Francis have worked continuously with Polish organizations and for the Polish cause. We need just such people in higher offices, in order to be able to exert our due influence where it is most needed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0774.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Therefore, let us not allow the war to absorb all of our interest and time. Let us make an effort to give several thousand votes to Mr. Albert J. Danisch, as well as to others of our compatriots, at the primaries on September 9.</p>
   <p>Since the two candidates for Representative at Large are nominated at the primaries, one of them should be a Pole, because we have several thousand Polish votes in Chicago and an appreciable number outside of Chicago, in places like Hawthorne, Grant Works, West Hammond, Kankakee, Lemont, Radom, Chicago Heights, Harvey, North Chicago, and Waukegan, in the coal mining settlements, and in many small towns and villages scattered throughout the entire state of Illinois. All citizens in this state can vote for Mr. Danisch. Let everyone place a check mark on the ballot on September 9. These check marks will send a Polish congressman to Congress. To work then, countrymen. "Let everyone do all he can in his own circle, and the whole will take care of itself."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
