<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I No. 53,
<date when="1897-12-29">Dec. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">With the New Year</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1423</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1423.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I No. 53,
<date when="1897-12-29">Dec. 29, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">WITH THE NEW YEAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The coming year will be well remembered in the history of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, which has shaken off harmful influences, forsaken a dangerous read, and taking at present a new way; no doubt the crowds will follow, favoring our organization, those faithful who can differentiate between right and wrong.</p>
   <p>Doctors insist that every organism needs a shakeup after which it can grow better.</p>
   <p>In nature, for instance, a storm although destructive refreshes the atmosphere. The learned say that the soul of man is great, flaming and bright, when it has suffered greatly.</p>
   <p>The more it suffers, the more it is strengthened and rises above the temporal. Shall sufferings are like sparks from a flaming torch.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1424.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If our organization were weak, we would have undoubtedly fallen under the weight which fell upon us unexpectedly, we would not have lived through and awakening of finding that those in whom we believed, fled with the first alarm, betraying their institutions and causing a loss of widows and children.</p>
   <p>Like a great oak strongly rooted does not bend with every breeze and in a storm stands proudly while slight trees bend in every direction so the Polish Roman Catholic Union weathered the storm and came out triumphant.</p>
   <p>We see no clouds, indeed a rainbow has risen bright and refreshing. Polish Roman Catholic Union, like an oak, is spreading now roots, over all America, gathering its countrymen - people of good will, who are flocking under its protective wings, knowing they will find protection, and brotherly love and, in case of trouble, help and sympathy, knowing that nothing threatens them under the protection of the Sacred Heart of Jesus.</p>
   <p>We greet the New Year with a peaceful consciences, with great hopes and a sincere resolve to work for the good Polish affairs, stirring up wherever we can the sacred fires of Faith, and brotherly love, asking for nothing in return, but confidence and adherence, and so unite still closer in the coming year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1425.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us love one another, defend each other, because if we do not stand up in our own defense of our countrymen, who will come to help us in a strange land.</p>
   <p>Remember always that we are Poles, and have from our forefathers a command: Our sacred faith, language and national customs. This we must obey and leave to our children as it was given to us. Let us follow the examples of other nationalities in good things, let us adopt their good or useful customs, but not lose our own and not deny our Roman Catholic Faith and the Polish language.</p>
   <p>Things have come to such a pass that a charlatan dressed in clerical garments misleads the people, saying he is a priest, holds, sacriligious ceremonies, and easily take advantage of the faithful.</p>
   <p>There have been found two such sacriligious bishops. The Buffalo imposter is now in prison, and the one in Chicago is awaiting the same fate.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to know what to do, to laugh at the case with which the people were taken in, or to cry at their blind stubbornness.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1426.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Under these circumstances faithful Poles should unite in a strong chain and strive towards one goal, especially when they have an organization where they can unite. Polish Roman Catholic Union has worked for a long time to unite all our countrymen in a strong Catholic organization. If we have not gained this end it is the fault of the Poles, who interpret their American freedom wrongly and think they can discard conscience, faith, God and man given laws.</p>
   <p>God gave man free will, but also gave him brains to control the will. He also gave laws which everyone must follow, if he does not want to end miserably.</p>
   <p>To those, who create or uphold such, taking advantage of American freedom, we remind again - watch for the end! Mend your ways in the New Year and you will see that you will be at peace and be of help to the Polish American public.</p>
   <p>Do not listen to people of ill-will, follow your own conscience, it will advise you best. These words are not for our brothers who are members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1427.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>These have taken the right road and will not swerve. We refer to the stray ones who are on the wrong path, to those who go on without an aim, not knowing where they are going. These we would like to gather, show them the right road, to take the road together.</p>
   <p>We began our work in the name of God. This work will be difficult at first, but we have no doubt that groups of our organization will aid us.</p>
   <p>Every machine, especially a complicated one, needs co-operation of all its parts.</p>
   <p>So the new system of the Polish Roman Catholic Union will function properly when all groups work together with the officers of the organization, who do not begrudge time and work to bring our aims to success.</p>
   <p>That we will succeed, we have no doubt. Let us begin then the New Year with unbending faith and we will rejoice not only in our twenty-fifth anniversary of the existence of the Polish Roman Catholic Union but also over the triumph of truth over falsehood, faith over atheism, orderliness over havoc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1428.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We greet the New Year merrily, with hope, in good will, and to our beloved brothers wish the best of health, good will and success in all undertakings. Let us work in the New Year quietly and sincerely, and God, the good, who weighs on the scales of justice and love, our good and bad deeds, will bless us, and that blessing of God we wish to ourselves and you brother members in the New Year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
