<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-03-05">Mar. 5, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Honor to Men of Good Will</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0821</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0821.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-03-05">Mar. 5, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">HONOR TO MEN OF GOOD WILL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The destruction by fire of the Polish National Alliance College's main edifice, at Cambridge Springs, Pa., has evoked among our competitors different comments, both friendly and adverse. Some of our adversaries went even so far as to recommend that the P.N.A. College should be permanently closed and the students sent to other educational institutions.</p>
   <p>Such voices, noisy as they are, seem, however, to produce no ill effects among the Alliance men of good will, in view of the fact that there are flowing into the hands of the P.N.A. Central Board, numerous and liberal donations for the purpose of restoring and enlarging the College buildings, making them more beautiful yet and also fire-proof. The first such donations have been received from communes six and eighty-eight at Cleveland; soon followed by communes thirty-eight at Buffalo, forty-one and forty-eight at Chicago and by others.</p>
   <p>The P.N.A. Group 205 at Pittsburg, has donated $250; the Communes 120 and <pb facs="5423968_8_0822.jpg" n="2"/>seventy-five at Chicago have donated $50 and $100, respectively, and the Commune eighty-three at East Chicago donated $25, with a promise to give more later.</p>
   <p>These groups and Communes are to be recommended for their good deeds, for their truly patriotic attitude, for their sense of duty towards their institution and for not giving an ear to the seducers. Let there be honor to the men of good will, who, in spite of the sinster agitators, contribute their benevolent donations for the benefit of their most beautiful and most noble institution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
