<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-05">Oct. 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Co-Operation]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-05">Oct. 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[CO-OPERATION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everyone knows, or should know, through experience that collective effort has a powerful influence upon the social and economic affairs of a given social order, of a given nation. The moral strength of societies, their influence upon political, social, and economic affairs, is so great that it is self-evident to all and must convince everyone. Whoever fails to recognize this is either a narrow, unenlightened person or a man of ill will, a rugged individualist. Every sincere newspaper summons people to unity--although there are also those which, for personal reasons, attempt to destroy it. All honest and sane people call upon their fellowmen to unite.</p>
   <p>It would be useless to point to the individual benefits derived from unity in a given scope of activity; they are quite clear. Unity and cooperation, is necessary to us Poles, who are confronted by so many <pb facs="5423968_8_0566.jpg" n="2"/>enemies. It is essential if we are to stand upon a higher level, the level upon which all the better nations stand.</p>
   <p>Everyone knows the tale of the dying father who, before his death, summoned his seven sons and ordered them to break a bundle composed of seven twigs. Each of the sons attempted to break the pack, but none succeeded. When the father then ordered them to untie the bundle and break each twig separately, they accomplished it with great ease. By this example the father wished to impart a final lesson to his sons, that strength can be found only in unity.</p>
   <p>We should aspire to unity because strength lies in the group. Let us not divide our power. We should have a variety of convictions because without difference of opinion there can be no progress, but should our opinion fail to be acknowledged by others, we should not withdraw from co-operative work in the future, nor should we destroy what has been accomplished by others acting with the best intentions. With a self-denying effort, let us work for the welfare of our national, social, and political causes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
