<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-26">Oct. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">How Poles Should Work in Behalf of the Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-26">Oct. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">HOW POLES SHOULD WORK IN BEHALF OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of the Polish National Alliance proudly repeat on every occasion that the people govern the Alliance, and only people organized under the banner of the motherland. It is so: no individual can force his will upon the organization. Every two years the people themselves select those who are to fulfill the popular wish, and this will is formulated, and decided upon, in the enactments and recommendations at the time of conventions.</p>
   <p>Nothing more than that is demanded in countries having a republican form of government. Selecting honest and able people to legislative offices, electing those to the executive offices who are deemed best to fill such offices, paying taxes imposed by the legislative authority, abiding by, and conforming to, the legal recommendations of the executive authority, respecting self-enacted <pb facs="5423968_8_1305.jpg" n="2"/>laws, and behaving in such a manner as befits free and enlightened citizens of a free nation--that is all that a nation can demand of its people during normal times. If the people fulfill only these obligations, the nation will grow in power and wealth, and everyone will benefit.</p>
   <p>Conditions, however, are entirely different with groups that do not as yet embrace the entire nation, that only show a tendency to embrace all, that have many opponents and competitors, that, in a word, are as yet in the process of achieving self-sufficiency. Members of such organizations have far greater and more numerous obligations. It is not sufficient to elect officials, to criticize them, to replace them at conventions, to pass upon laws, and to pay assessments. In such cases it is necessary also to strive to have the organization grow in strength, numerical and financial.</p>
   <p>The officials--of whom there are only a few, and each of whom has his own special duties to fulfill and is forced to remain in one city--cannot accomplish a great deal more beyond the fulfillment of their obligations. They do <pb facs="5423968_8_1306.jpg" n="3"/>as much as possible and they accomplish a great deal. They go about and travel to make speeches on the Alliance, but all that is like a drop in the bucket, to use the vernacular, in comparison with what should be done. In order to grow rapidly, the Alliance should have a considerable number of capable people in its service--people who would do nothing but travel to various Polish settlements and acquaint the people with the principles of our organization. But it seems that the Alliance cannot allow itself such a service. True, there will come a time when this will be made possible, but at present the duty of endeavoring to increase the membership of the Alliance rests upon all members of the organization, upon all the people of the Alliance. No member should shirk this duty, for fear of injuring his own organization and hence of harming himself. Let no one say, "What is that to me? Why should I work? Let the officials work. I pay my dues and that is enough." It is very well that you pay your dues and that you demand work from the officials, dear brother. But you should also work with all your energy. Then conditions will be far better than they now are. The work of eighty thousand people, although it is limited, can accomplish more than the <pb facs="5423968_8_1307.jpg" n="4"/>utmost efforts of one, or ten, or even one hundred, of the most active workers. The articles contained in the newspapers of the Polish National Alliance remind the Polish people frequently of the way to work in behalf of the organization.</p>
   <p>One of the first duties of our people is to enroll their children in the Polish National Alliance. The sons and daughters should become members of this organization as soon as they attain the acceptable age provided by the constitution. Whatever the parents decide is good should also be good to their sons and daughters. The children's belonging to the same organization as the parents tightens the bonds of mutual love and respect in the family. Common interests and tendencies and political, social, and national ideals are a great power in maintaining a well-founded relationship between the adolescent youth and the older generation. If our people allow their children to act freely and carelessly, and permit them to enroll in some organization of another nationality, they will be lost forever to their parents and to our nationality. If, on the other hand, they follow in the footsteps of their respectable parents and become members of Polish organizations, the children will always remain at the <pb facs="5423968_8_1308.jpg" n="5"/>side of their parents.</p>
   <p>Early membership in a highly ideal, and noble, national organization has a great significance for, and bearing upon, the youths themselves. The very fact of sharing in the control of such an organization, and the making of monthly contributions of a few cents for national and philanthropic purposes, elevates the spirit of the youth and saves him from joining many harmful escapades. After persuading his children, who are closest to him, a member of the Polish National Alliance should convince his relatives, also, to become members of the organization. There are many Polish families in which one or two members belong to the Alliance while the other members-brothers, sisters, or more distant relatives--are perhaps unaware that such an organization as the Polish National Alliance exists. A good, thoughtful member of the Alliance should not be at rest until he has succeeded in enrolling all his relatives in the organization. It is his duty, not only to the Alliance and the national cause, but also to all the people who bind him with <pb facs="5423968_8_1309.jpg" n="6"/>bonds of consanguinity and friendship. It is good for everyone to belong to the Alliance. No one suffers any injustice and everyone benefits--some from one department, others from another, and all together from the safe kind of insurance that is offered. Besides this, a person commands greater respect from his own and other people when he is a member of a great national legion that works so bravely and accomplishes so much good. Every Pole should take part directly or indirectly in the national work, if he wishes to retain his own honor and to increase his own worth. If anyone is still unacquainted with the manner of accomplishing this, he should consult a member of the Alliance, who may be his relative or friend, and it is certain that proper and adequate information will be given.</p>
   <p>Beyond his family, every member of the Alliance, therefore, has a wide field of activity in behalf of the organization. He might extend his activity to friends of his own profession, to the acquaintances with whom he spends his leisure moments, to his business acquaintances, with whom he comes in daily contact, and to all fellow patriots in general whom he meets here and there.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1310.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>There is no topic of conversation which could not be used to teach others of the Polish National Alliance and to encourage them to join our ranks. If someone should be opposed to the Alliance and if, in his conversation, he should attack the organization, the proper reply would be: "You talk of things you do not understand: Become acquainted with the Alliance and you will change your views." Then, again, there are various means of converting various people. It is necessary to argue with some, reason with them, and defeat their arguments; while it is sufficient to educate others,--the type of people who are themselves willing to accomplish good deeds but simply do not know where to look for this good.</p>
   <p>In either case, members of the Polish National Alliance should understand this fact well: that the duty of working in behalf of the organization also lies upon their shoulders. Nothing is accomplished by itself, and little can be done through the efforts of tens or hundreds of people. The efforts of hundreds of thousands, however, can, in a short space of time, create an organization so vast that the workers will gain the admiration and respect of the entire nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
