<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-12">Sept. 12, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution of the Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-12">Sept. 12, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION OF THE CENTRAL ADMINISTRATION OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whereas, The late Dr. John Enander, who died in Chicago on September 9, 1910, brought great honor to his people as a renowned poet, historian and publisher;</p>
   <p>Whereas, He was a sincere friend of Poland and the Polish people, which he continually proved, namely in the fact that in the year 1863, while still residing in his own native land, in Sweden, he influenced the public opinion of his people in behalf of Poland's struggle for independence;</p>
   <p>Whereas, When at the same time, when the turbulent waters of the sea cast the refugees of the Polish division upon the shores of Sweden--[the refugees] who, after leaving London on an English ship, had intended to land on the Latvian seacoast so that military operations could be started from that location against the Russian forces, the late John Enander was the first to come to their aid and organized a hospitable reception for the Polish soldiers in Sweden;</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1349.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whereas, As an editor and public speaker, he always proclaimed his sympathy with the rights and political tendencies of Poland; [Therefore] in recognition of all this he was nominated as an honorary member of the Polish National Alliance, which honor he has always prized highly, always appearing publicly with the insignia of the Alliance upon his breast. And therefore, the central administration of the Polish National Alliance has unanimously resolved:</p>
   <p>To express high esteem to the memory of an honorable man and a feeling of sympathy to the family of the deceased, as well as to the entire Swedish nation, on the occasion of the death of so worthy and distinguished a citizen;</p>
   <p>To place a floral wreath upon his bier with an appropriate inscription and to participate in the funeral procession of the late John Enander.</p>
   <p>M. B. Steczynski, president,</p>
   <p>J. S. Czechowicz, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
