<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-01">Jan. 1, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Prospects for the Polish National Alliance in the Year 1931</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0848</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0848.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-01">Jan. 1, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROSPECTS FOR THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE IN THE YEAR 1931</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judged by the interest in their organizations, and the enthusiasm displayed heretofore by the membership of the Polish National Alliance, this society may expect in the New Year 1931 greater blessing than in any previous year.</p>
   <p>Such judgment of ours is strengthened by the fact that our Brethren show an unusual fervor in soliciting new members for our organization, proving thereby that they deeply desire to keep the Polish National Alliance ahead of all other Polish organizations in this country. They are steadily encouraged in their good work not only by words, but also by the excellent example of their highest officials, headed by censor K. W. Sypniewski, <pb facs="5423968_8_0849.jpg" n="2"/>and by president Jan Romaszkiewicz, who with their co-workers and colleagues in the Central Board are earnestly endeavoring to enlarge the Alliance and to hold high its standard.</p>
   <p>As the result of zealous cooperation and of brotherly efforts, the Polish National Alliance, counts in the year of its golden jubilee, nearly three hundred thousand members, both old and young.</p>
   <p>While observing the beautiful New Year custom of making the best of promises and resolutions for the future, pertaining to our personal interests, we should also make on New Year's day, an additional decision for the benefit of the Polish National Alliance, namely; to continue in the good work of still further increasing its ranks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0850.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It will be a splendid and noble resolution. Every effort in that direction will not be forgotten by the Polish National Alliance Central Board, which at every given opportunity is rewarding the sincere workers and confers a badge of honor upon them for the good work done by them. A good work shall always be rewarded!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
