<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-15">Nov. 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">War against Crime</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-15">Nov. 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">WAR AGAINST CRIME</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the coming of winter in the larger cities of the United States a wave of crime seems to appear regularly, virtually inundating peaceful and law-abiding people. A glance at the newspapers convinces one that, especially in Chicago, with the beginning of November there is an outburst of something that resembles civil war between the criminal elements on one side and the rest of humanity on the other.</p>
   <p>The situation at times becomes so dangerous that after sunset the city takes on the appearance of Petrograd, Russia, or Warsaw, Poland, in time of war. Criminals shoot at passers-by, the police fight with criminals and sometimes kill a law-abiding citizen who is not sufficiently quick at becoming oriented and fails to stop at the command of a detective.</p>
   <p>Several days ago the neighboring town of Cicero witnessed a gory battle in <pb facs="5423968_8_0085.jpg" n="2"/>which one policeman lost his life and six persons were critically wounded. Day before yesterday a certain citizen seriously wounded a policeman, whom he mistook for a thief. In addition, there are several ordinary murders perpetrated each night.</p>
   <p>Despite the ban placed upon carrying firearms, every suspicious character has a revolver upon his person. Because of this, peaceful citizens, also, are compelled to arm themselves for their own protection. The chief of police of the city of Chicago has discovered that the police lose their guns and that these are later found in the pockets of arrested culprits. Because of such occurences he has ordered all his men to register the number of their guns and mark the bullets with special markings. This was done for the purpose of ascertaining later, when some victim was murdered, if the officials could state definitely whether the bullet was fired by a bandit or a policeman.</p>
   <p>In considering the various causes of these criminal orgies the local press points insistently to the inadequate parole system as one of the main reasons for this disorder. A culprit, for example, is sentenced to serve ten years <pb facs="5423968_8_0086.jpg" n="3"/>in jail, and after some two or three years--even sooner in some cases--certain pressures are exerted that liberate this criminal after he takes a solemn oath to conduct himself properly from that time on. It has been proved that seventy-five per cent of the crimes in large cities, especially in Chicago, are committed by gentlemen who have thus been freed upon their word.</p>
   <p>The most recent incident of that type in Chicago is a typical example. A certain Jennings was sentenced to prison for criminal assault. With time he was freed on his word. After a few weeks he was again apprehended in the act of committing a crime and was sent back to prison for failing to keep his word. After several months had passed, Jennings again obtained his liberty on parole. But this time things have not gone smoothly; he has not only robbed but also murdered his victim. He was captured and most probably will have to pay the death penalty. Had there been no parole system, Jennings would have remained in prison and worked there at some useful task. His victim would perhaps still be enjoying life and health.</p>
   <p>The system of paroling criminals is not peculiar to America. So far as we know, <pb facs="5423968_8_0087.jpg" n="4"/>it is also practiced in France and Russia. But in these foreign nations, authorities do not send criminals paroled from prison directly to the city, where it is impossible to find employment for a person with a prison record, even if he wants work, and where, on the other hand, it is very easy for him to find his former associates and return to his former trade. France and Russia settle criminals who have been freed from enforced hard labor on soil in the vicinity of the prison, far from the place of their former residence. Russia uses Siberia, France, New Caledonia. A paroled criminal obtains a piece of land, a cottage, tools, and seeds. There he can marry a woman who has also been a criminal, or even a woman without a criminal record, if he can find one of that type. He is forced to become a farmer in order not to die of hunger, but often he continues to be a farmer by choice. Some of these settlers, namely, the gravest criminals, remain in that state till the end of their life. Others, who have received a lighter sentence, after a certain period of good behavior, regain their full freedom and return to their former homes as people completely reformed.</p>
   <p>Nothing elevates a man as much as cultivating land and raising domestic animals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0088.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Even the worst man attaches himself to his own land, to his field, to his trees, to creatures raised and cared for by himself. He becomes interested in work, acquires a respect for ownership, and by becoming an accomplished farmer and provider he gains respect among people and is admitted to their company.</p>
   <p>Nothing is gained by the American criminal who is freed from Joliet to roam the streets of Chicago, even if his freedom is based on his word or if he has served his sentence to the full letter of the law. Hunger, misery, lack of employment, and human contempt more often force him to repeat his crimes than do inborn criminal instincts. Could not the State Governments, therefore, come to an understanding with the Federal Government in the matter of establishing some large agricultural colonies in such distant places as, for example, Alaska, for paroled criminals or for those who have served their sentences--criminals of low caliber, even murderers? There is a sufficient amount of uncultivated land that now awaits development. Let former convicts cultivate that distant land where they will be segregated from peaceful people, and then we can rest assured that Mother Nature will transform a huge majority of them into people deserving of society's respect.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0089.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This matter could well be taken up by philanthropists here--those people who spend huge sums of money for the conversion of civilized Chinese or for the foundation of American schools somewhere in Syria, Armenia, or other such countries where the natives knew how to read and write, and wrote rather good volumes, some three thousand years before the arrival of American missionaries in their land.</p>
   <p>Something must be done with the criminals leaving prison after completion of their sentence or before its completion. After all, it is impossible to remain constantly on a war basis with people who most often need only sincere work or proper direction to become peaceful and useful members of society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
