<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-04">Jan. 4, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Children of Town of Lake Feted by Lodge No. 143 of the Polish National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0868</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0868.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-04">Jan. 4, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">CHILDREN OF TOWN OF LAKE FETED BY LODGE NO. 143 OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Town of Lake community celebrated the end of the Christmas holidays by attending a special children's program arranged by Lodge No. 143 of the Polish National Alliance at the hall of Julius Slowacki, 48th and Paulina Streets, Monday evening. Over eight hundred children took part in the affair. Because a large number came with their parents, the hall was filled to capacity. Time and work were not sacrificed in preparing the program and decorating the hall.</p>
   <p>Felix Tylinski started the program. After a touching talk to the children and parents, he called upon the chairman of the entertainment committee, John Krolewczyk, president of Lodge No. 143. Eugenia Lesniewicz was the first entertainer. In her declamatory role, she greeted everyone, and wished all the best of everything throughout the New Year. The children of the Juvenile Department of the Polish National Alliance sang a number of Christmas carols, and concluded with the singing of "Welcome Polish National Alliance." They <pb facs="5423968_8_0869.jpg" n="2"/>received a fine hand from the audience.</p>
   <p>The following numbers followed in order: Sylvia Wcislo, member of the K.L.D. [Kolko Literackie i Dramatyczne] Ognisko (Hearth Literary and Dramatic Club), recited a poetical verse, Zolnierz Nieznany (Unknown Soldier), by Arthur Oppman. Felix Tylinski sang a Polish song, "Chociaz Mi Zazdroszcza Ludzie" (Although the People Begrudge Me). Theodora Bujanowska recited a poem, "Dobranoc" (Goodnight). M. Kropidlowski gave a beautiful presentation of "Jestem Polakiem" (I am a Pole). A classical dance was presented by Theodosia Rakowska in fine detail.</p>
   <p>"Kochajmy Sie Bracia" (Brothers, Let Us Love One Another). The poem, "O, Gwiazdeczko" (O, Little Star), was presented by Stanislaus Tylinski. Two musical compositions were given by Stas Mielzynski on his violin; he was accompanied on the piano by his sister, Clara. These two young people are members of the Hearth L.D.C. of Town of Lake. "Biala Pajeczyna" (The White <pb facs="5423968_8_0870.jpg" n="3"/>Cobweb), a poem, was rendered by Isabella Kropidlowska. "Jak Ja Urosne" (When I Grow Up), a poetical verse, was declaimed by Sigismund Kropidlowski. The final recitation was given by Clara Mielzynska, "Garsc Ziemi Polskiej" (A Handful of Polish Soil). Miss Eugenia Lesniewicz and her sister, Helen, garbed in native costumes, sang several numbers typical of the Polish Mountaineers. Then they danced a mazurka.</p>
   <p>All the numbers presented by the Polish youth were received with applause by the audience. The audience felt greatly gratified with this fine presentation of Polish entertainment. What pleased the people most was the execution of the numbers in flawless Polish. They worshipped the fact that the children of Polish extraction are not forgetting the Polish language, and that they take an interest in Polish organizations.</p>
   <p>Credit for arranging this program should go to Miss Pearl Lesniewicz of Town of Lake. This aggressive young lady is the founder and president of the ladies society, Zwyciestwo Polski (Poland's Victory), of the P.N.A. <pb facs="5423968_8_0871.jpg" n="4"/>Miss Lesniewicz did not sacrifice time, work, or money to make this affair a success.</p>
   <p>While the Polonaise was played, the children received presents. Over eight hundred children wore happy smiles after they received the gifts. During the interim of the presentation of gifts, decorum prevailed. The idea of giving out gifts was a pleasant surprise to all.</p>
   <p>The program committee consisted of: Pearl Lesniewicz, Felix Tylinski, and Louis Czerwiec. This committee actually worked several days to get every detail in order.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
