<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 22,
<date when="1916-05-31">May 31, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Hard Facts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Reprint from Glos Polek, Polish Women's Voice)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 22,
<date when="1916-05-31">May 31, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">HARD FACTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Reprint from Glos Polek, Polish Women's Voice)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This week brings us exceptionally hard facts. Polish criminality was increased by a few great, notorious crimes, in which cases murders perpetrated by Poles will lead them surely to the disgrace of the Polish name and to the electric chair. A husband killed his mate, a married couple together murdered a "boarder", that disgraceful excrescence of Polish life over here, whose source is greediness, the lust for dollars by women for luxuries and often for adornments of dress, then, in consequence, the demoralizing of life, the breaking of faith and honor, and as a result crime abuses and pushes everybody over a precipice to ruin. And the reason? So trifling and innocent it appears - the cause, because of a dress, luxuries, greediness, which makes them blind. Then further consequences which come from this small reason, striving for men, taking in "boarders," betrayal of the husbands, disgrace, fall and crime. Guard yourselves, Polish <pb facs="5423968_8_0054.jpg" n="2"/>women, from small seedlings grow terrible evils which ruin everything.</p>
   <p>And here, further a few more flowers, poisoned from the moral blindness of our women and the demoralization in general here of Polish life. The chronicles of the past few weeks have brought several names of Polish women, who, as a result of criminal operations, died suddenly, leaving their children motherless and the husbands widowers. How terrible this is, for this well known crime perpetrated in the bosom of a mother by the mother on that which has been dearest to a woman for ages, on her own child, on that sacred matrimony, on which is uplifted a sacrilegious hand, homicidal.</p>
   <p>Murderesses, killers, here you have the only expression fit for the murderesses of innocent infants, that sacred spark of life from which possibly would come into the world, good, blessing, perhaps a genius, or some sort of prodigy of virtue. Ignominy, to dare kill a life within yourself. Unheard of monstrosity. That is what the Polish women are <pb facs="5423968_8_0055.jpg" n="3"/>learning in America, because there is no such thing with us in Poland, in the Fatherland. And will there not rise among the women a moral court which would tell everybody to turn their backs on the murderesses of maternity within their bosom and their rapacious dirty helpers?</p>
   <p>Disgrace, every upright woman ought to withdraw from giving a hand to those murderesses of innocent life. If mercenary justice cannot reach there in this country, let a righteous court reach them, boldly stigmatizing the women in general. The victims of blindness and a terrible mistake most often pay with their lives and horrible torture for attempted crimes, but their female assistants, those supposed midwives, supposed "lady doctors," who come in contact with us and are among us collecting bloody dollars. Disgrace, let us turn from them with solidarity and with contempt. Stigmatize those dark, murderous nocturnal birds. Away with them from our life; let us have courage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
