<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-02-14">Feb. 14, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Russian Extradition Treaty with America Opposed</title><title level="a" type="sub">Fight against the Treaty Continues; Efforts Made to Abolish it (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0795</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0795.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-02-14">Feb. 14, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN EXTRADITION TREATY WITH AMERICA OPPOSED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Fight Against the Treaty Continues; Efforts Made to Abolish It (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The problem of extraditing Russian criminals is not yet settled, although the extradition treaty between the United States and Russia was concluded not long ago. That this treaty is legal is a fact; yet it is being fought continually and energetic measures are being taken to abolish it.</p>
   <p>We are cognizant of the fact that the United States is governed by the people through their representatives, who are elected for this purpose. Since this is the case, this treaty with Russia--ratified at St. Petersburg on April 21, 1893, in spite of numerous protests--would become invalid if the majority of the people would declare that it is unconstitutional and not in agreement with the spirit of American freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0796.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This treaty is of great importance to the Poles living in the United States. The Poles were very interested in it prior to its ratification and opposed it energetically.</p>
   <p>It will not be amiss to acquaint our readers with all the details of this problem up to the present moment.</p>
   <p>It is interesting to know that the opponents of this treaty did not lay down their weapons after its ratification, but promptly organized the so-called R. E. T. A. S. (Russian Extradition Treaty Abrogation Society), an association whose purpose is to abolish the agreement made between the United States and Russia, which provides for the extradition of criminals. This society, with headquarters at 100 Broadway, New York City, has thousands of members and supporters throughout the United States and even among the lovers of freedom in other countries.</p>
   <p>For about a year, the R. E. T. A. S. has been preparing a plan to fight this treaty, which is not in accord with the spirit of American freedom. Its plan <pb facs="5423968_8_0797.jpg" n="3"/>is to prepare a huge petition, signed by thousands of American citizens, and present it to the President of the United States and both houses of Congress. In this manner, both the President and Congress, in accordance with the will of the people, will be obliged to take the necessary measures for abolishing the Russian extradition treaty.</p>
   <p>The R. E. T. A. S. expects to obtain at least five hundred thousand signatures for the petition.</p>
   <p>The R. E. T. A. S. has already taken the first step in this direction by preparing and distributing a draft of the general petition to be sent to the President of the United States, the Senate, and the House of Representatives. This document, according to the reports of the American press, has been carefully prepared. By legal and philosophical argumentation, the document proves that the Russian extradition treaty with the United States is unjust, unnecessary, and unconstitutional. The truth of this contention is proved by many arguments and quotations taken from several sources, such as Leroy Beaulieu's L'Empire <pb facs="5423968_8_0798.jpg" n="4"/>des Tzars et les Russes, George Kennan's works, the Constitution of the United States, the United States court decisions, opinions of the Attorney-General, and other legal sources.</p>
   <p>In the draft of the general petition all provisions are very carefully analyzed, and the faults [of the treaty] are explained in detail. It advances many facts about Russian judicature. However, the most important argument is based on the general principle that such a treaty cannot be made between a free and constitutional government and a government ruled by a despot, whose subjects, according to the old accepted theory of John Locke, have a right to revolt.</p>
   <p>We are sorry that so far we have not received a copy of the draft of the general petition. We have made a request for it, and as soon as we receive it we will take up this subject again, to which we only wish to attract the attention of our countrymen today. In our opinion, if so much effort is made by other people in order to abolish this treaty, then we American Poles should also give a helping hand. Signatures of American citizens of Polish <pb facs="5423968_8_0799.jpg" n="5"/>extraction should appear on this petition, which our countrymen should support with their whole might.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
