<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-02">Dec. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">(Chronicle)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-02">Dec. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">(Chronicle)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sentence was passed by American courts a few days ago, in two cases; that, imposed on a woman charged with the murder of her husband, the other case, we regret to state, was that of 6 degenerate youths of Polish origin who murdered a poor, innocent farmer. The case of the woman in Denver, was disposed of by acquittal, whereas, for a similar crime of cold blooded murder, the 6 boys were convicted; four were sentenced to death by hanging, and the other two, who are minors, to life imprisonment. In both cases the murder was premeditated and cold blooded; therefore, as a matter of justice the guilty should pay the penalty, yet, four boys were sentenced to the gallows for their crime, while in the other case, the woman who admitted a love affair with a millionaire, and had slain her invalid husband in cold blood was acquitted. In both cases the crime committed was murder, and the penalty should have been the same.</p>
   <p>We are not in favor of the extreme death penalty, but to set free a murderess is an invitation to other women to commit crime. But the woman had a rich lover who could use his money and influence in her favor. The decision in both cases indicates that American courts are a long way from impartiality and absolute justice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
