<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-01">Aug. 1, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Societies in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Introduction)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0666</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0666.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-01">Aug. 1, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIETIES IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Introduction)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have decided, as our readers already know, to publish in Dziennik Chicagoski a history of the Polish societies in America. Anyone who has attempted such a task is well aware of the difficulties encountered in gathering the necessary material, and for this reason our readers will forgive us if we fail to present these histories in the order in which we would like to. We should either compile the material chronologically--that is, give the history of each society, starting with the oldest--or group the societies according to the larger organizations with which they are affiliated.</p>
   <p>Both methods are impractical, however. If we delayed publishing the histories <pb facs="5423968_8_0667.jpg" n="2"/>until the secretary of each society prepared a report, it would surely take years, and even then it would be found that many things were lacking, that additions and corrections must be made. [On the other hand,] if we do not wait for the material to be sent in, then compilation is impossible.</p>
   <p>We have decided, then, to publish the histories in the order in which we receive them from the secretaries, that is, without trying to keep any chronological order. After all of the material has been submitted to us, we will probably present a general survey, with the societies in proper order. At that time we will also present histories of the large organizations.</p>
   <p>In this introduction it is our intention to describe the kinds of societies according to the purposes for which they were organized.</p>
   <p>We will try to enumerate the many different kinds of societies. In the first <pb facs="5423968_8_0668.jpg" n="3"/>place, all of the societies can be classified under two main heads: fraternal aid societies (insurance, paying benefits on either illness or death), and societies not having this aim. Among the Poles, the first type is most numerous.</p>
   <p>We can classify the societies in accordance with the principles by which they are guided, thus: 1) Purely religious societies, devoted to religious exercises and church activities. These are church fraternities, lay religious orders, and so on. 2) Religio-patriotic societies, whose motto is "God and Homeland," and with whom patriotism and the faith of their forefathers, the Holy Catholic faith, are inseparable. These societies occupy themselves with nationalistic matters, and their members are all staunch Catholics. 3) Patriotic societies, the members of which regard faith as a secondary matter. These societies profess respect for the Catholic Church,but they do not require that their members be Catholic. They are guided by the principle that "religion has nothing in common with patriotism". 4) Societies organized for <pb facs="5423968_8_0669.jpg" n="4"/>social or educational purposes, under which head would come gymnastic societies, dramatic circles, library societies, and so on. 5) Societies organized for business reasons,....that is, building and loan associations, businessmen's associations, trade unions, and so on. 6) Political societies. 7) Welfare societies.</p>
   <p>Societies can also be classified according to their affiliation with larger organizations. There are a few such organizations--such unions of several or several hundred societies into one large organization--in the United States. They are: 1) The Polish Roman Catholic Union, under the protection of the Sacred Heart of Jesus. 2) The Polish-American Union. 3) The Polish National Alliance. 4) The Polish Roman Catholic Union, under the protection of the Holy Virgin of Czestochowa. A fifth division would include Polish societies affiliated with non-Polish organizations as, for example, the Catholic Order of Foresters, political clubs, and so on. A sixth would list independent societies not affiliated with any larger organization.</p>
   <p>When we have completed these histories, at least to a certain extent, we <pb facs="5423968_8_0670.jpg" n="5"/>will be able to group the societies in our [prospective] "Review of Societies" according to the above classification. But an additional lead will yet be necessary, namely, classification according to the state, city, parish or community in which the society exists.</p>
   <p>This will provide interesting material from which quite a book on Polish societies in America could be compiled. It will also be possible to prepare from this material a history of Polish settlements and parishes in America.</p>
   <p>We respectfully ask the secretaries of societies not to delay in submitting reports to this paper. A copy of Dziennik Chicagoski will be sent to each secretary as the history of his society appears. It is hoped that this work will prove both useful and interesting.</p>
   <p>So far, we have received thirty letters, and more are coming in daily. Tomorrow we will present the history of the Society of the Sacred Heart of the Sorrowful Mother [Towarzystwo Najswietszego Serca Matki Boskiej Bolesnej], <pb facs="5423968_8_0671.jpg" n="6"/>of St. Adalbert's Parish, Chicago. The secretary of this society was the first to reply to the letter of which we sent copies to the secretaries of all societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
