<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-22">Sept. 22, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Reception for Mr. M. B. Steczynski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1338</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1338.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-22">Sept. 22, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">RECEPTION FOR MR. M. B. STECZYNSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About two hundred and fifty members of the Polish National Alliance gathered last night at Walsh's Hall. Acting on the invitation extended by the Civic Committee, the members arrived to participate in the reception accorded to Mr. M. B. Steczynski, president of the Polish National Alliance, upon his return from the Motherland. Those present were mostly the presidents and secretaries of various groups affiliated with the Polish National Alliance of Chicago and vicinity. Besides these, there were also representatives of the Falcons Alliance, Singers Alliance, The Polish Military Alliance, the former and present officials and workers at the offices of the Polish National Alliance, the former and present members of the Central Committee, the young and old recruits of the Alliance, doctors, workers, journalists, merchants, lawyers, businessmen, in one word the entire Alliance population was well represented. There were also guests from more distant vicinities--from South Chicago, Hammond, Joliet, Lemont. Even the neighboring city of Milwaukee was represented by such prominent members of the Alliance as Dr. K. Wagner, Messrs. I.Czerwinski, W. Zalewski and several others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1339.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After consuming an excellently prepared dinner, Mr. S. Czechowicz, a member of the reception committee, took the floor and after briefly greeting all those congregated, called upon Dr. K. Wagner to be master of ceremonies; Dr. Wagner, after expressing his gratitude, took over his official duties. After an introductory song, given by the Filaret Choir, the chairman called upon Mr. F. Ksycki, vice-resident of the Polish National Alliance, who, as an aide to the president, conducted the affairs of the organization. In a sincere message he welcomed the president back to his duties. He thanked Mr. M. B. Steczynski in behalf of the Alliance, for the hardships he had undergone, and for the excellent accomplishment of the mission imposed upon him by the decision of the Eighteenth Convention of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>And now followed the most important moment of the meeting. Mr. Steczynski called upon for a speech, in a voice trembling with emotion, began by thanking his fellow members for this surprise. He stated that, although unprepared, he would endeavor to give those present a resume of the impressions which he had acquired while in Poland. Then followed a moving and excellent narration about Mother Poland, about all its annexed parts, Warsaw, Torun, Posen, Cracow, Lwow <pb facs="5423968_8_1340.jpg" n="3"/>and Rappersville, about the sincerity and hospitality of the Polish people, the respect with which they greeted the representatives of the Polish National Alliance--thousands of incidents which neither time nor space allow us to enumerate here. The picturesque portrayal of the homeland before the deeply interested audience lasted for more than an hour and a half. He depicted the sufferings of the people, their endeavors, strifes and hopes. This was not a strict, formal and official report, for which there will be a time and place at the Nineteenth Convention in St. Louis. It was an excellent description of the travel of a man who was everywhere, saw, felt, lived through and contemplated everything, one who encompasses within himself an entire universe of impressions, observations and emotions. Thus he spread this wealth of information before his brethren, taking the minds of the audience to their native land.</p>
   <p>The people have had an opportunity to hear Mr. Steczynski on previous occasions, but never has he attained such heights of eloquence as he did on this occasion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1341.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He repeatedly stressed the fact that it was not he himself, as an individual, nor his colleague, Mr. Abczynski, the assistant censor, who were greeted in Poland, but that the people there were welcoming the Polish National Alliance, an organization which was not sufficiently known by the people of our Motherland and with which they first began to become better acquainted during the Washingtonian festivities. Through the Polish National Alliance, Poland welcomed and gathered to its bosom all of the Polish immigrants in America.</p>
   <p>The honorable guest was greeted with thunderous applause before commencing his speech. The most important points of his narration were underscored by waves of applause. As an external manifestation of gratitude for his efforts, shown by his-bringing so vivid a narrative and description of his travels through the Motherland, the audience gave the speaker a rising vote of confidence.</p>
   <p>Brief speeches then followed by Mr. T. Siemiradzki, who spoke in behalf of <pb facs="5423968_8_1342.jpg" n="5"/>the Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance; Mr. Ignace Czerwinski, representing the guests from Milwaukee; Dr. Adam Szwajkart, Mr. Anton Czarnecki, Mr. W. Perlowski, Mrs. Josephine Zembal, in behalf of the singers; Messrs. K. Zychlinski, Stephen Gorecki, Leon Mallek and Dr. K. Zurawski, representing the Polish Falcon Society. The lateness of the hour did not permit the chairman to summon other speakers. This inspiring festivity came to a close after the singing of the "March of the Polish Falcons" and the national anthem.</p>
   <p>A collection was made at the hall for the purpose of founding a group of the Polish Falcons organization. A sum of thirty-seven dollars was thus gathered, which amount was then given to the authorized persons.</p>
   <p>We can truthfully say that rarely have we had the opportunity to participate in a meeting of such fraternal spirit. The entire occasion was marked by a profound enthusiasm, sincere satisfaction and mutual understanding. The <pb facs="5423968_8_1343.jpg" n="6"/>speakers expressed many sound, sane and inspirational thoughts which were eagerly accepted by the entire audience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
