<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 15,
<date when="1898-04-14">April 14, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Julius Andrzejkowicz</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 15,
<date when="1898-04-14">April 14, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">JULIUS ANDRZEJKOWICZ</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not quite a month has passed since we were in deep sorrow for the death of Julian Lapinski, one of the founders of the Z. N. P., when again we are met with sorrow, this time through the death of Julius Andrzejkowicz, also one of the organizers of the Z. N. P. Thousands of people, many of them members of the Z. N. P., bow their heads in this hour of sorrow on account of the death of Mr. Andrzejkowiez, for his unblemished work in behalf of this great society.</p>
   <p>He is the first man in America who said, "All the Polish societies unite as one; in unity there is strength." Thus this was the first step toward organizing the Z. N. P. He is often referred to as the true founder and the father of this great society. Although his body lies in a tomb hill today, he will always remain in the hearts of the Z. N. P. members as an unforgotten and undying memory.</p>
   <p>Julius Andrzejkowicz was born in August 1821. In the year 1848 he toured through the different Polish towns and spoke about patriotism and the love <pb facs="5423968_8_1419.jpg" n="2"/>for his native land, but he was greatly opposed to being under the rule of Russia. He formed a group of young men to rebel against Jankowski's tyrannical rule, but they met with defeat, many of these men were killed, some were sent to Siberia, others fled to the land of freedom. After his defeat at the hands of Jankowski, he went to France where he lived a few years, but the urge to go to the land of freedom was so strong that he left France and arrived in America in 1854. He resided in Philadelphia for many years. Through his kind words and work, because of his undying love for the Polish people, he organized this society of Z. N. P. He was elected the first censor of the Z. N. P., the highest office of this new organization. He was re-elected to this office three terms, but declined to accept the fourth time because he had too much work, not enough sleep and the advancing age kept him from fulfilling this position to the best of his ability. He was a true Polish patriot; always willing to devote his time for the sake of the Polish people.</p>
   <p>A few years back, the urge to visit his fatherland was so great that he could not resist it. He left Philadelphia for n, his native province, <pb facs="5423968_8_1420.jpg" n="3"/>but his work and love for America was greater, and in a few months he was back in America.</p>
   <p>At the last meeting of the Polish parliament of the Z. N. P. Mr. Andrzejkowicz was present despite his old age. He enjoyed being among his own people and listened to the conversation, ideas and aims of our young people groups. The people paid him the utmost respect and applauded him when he was called upon the stage to speak.</p>
   <p>Our hearts are heavy with sorrow every time his name is mentioned; his work on this earth has ended; he has fulfilled his good intentions; he has given strength to his followers, who are continuing this work in his footsteps.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Andrzejkowicz was also a member of group No. 1, of which he was the organizer. In their books he was member No. 1. At the fourth meeting of the Polish parliament he was made honorary member of the Z. N. P.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Andrzejkowicz died April 3, 1898, and was laid in eternal rest and <pb facs="5423968_8_1421.jpg" n="4"/>peace April 6, 1898. Many members of Z. N. P. groups from out of town were present, among them two of his colleagues, Mr. John Blachowski and Mr. John Popielinski. They are the only two members alive of the original five who have received credit for helping to organize the Z. N. P.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
