<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-10-05">Oct. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Independence Mass Meeting at Town of Lake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1149</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1149.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-10-05">Oct. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">INDEPENDENCE MASS MEETING AT TOWN OF LAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon an independence mass meeting arranged by Group 39 of the Polish National Alliance was held at Pulaski Hall, West 48th and Throop Streets. The meeting brought together many residents of St. John of God Parish.</p>
   <p>Mr. Francis Ratajczak called the meeting to order in the name of the committee and invited the presidents of groups and speakers on to the platform.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Przyprawa, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, delivered the first address. He summarized the progress of the war on Polish soil and in Europe, describing the horrible situation in which our brethren across the sea find themselves. Then, having mentioned the [need for] uniting all our organizations here, he appealed to the people to exert all their efforts in working at the reconstruction of the homeland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1150.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The next speech was delivered by Mr. [W.] Jankowski, well-known citizen of this district, who also asked the people to work for the homeland in these unusual times.</p>
   <p>The third and last speech was made by Mr. J. Smulski, president of the Polish Bank, who spoke with his usual vigor and enthusiasm. He said that in the present times no one can call himself a Pole who is lazy in taking part in national work or who does not want to offer even the greatest sacrifices on the altar of the homeland.</p>
   <p>"Agreeing in spirit and in our aims, because it was disagreement which brought about our ruin, we should all now exert our efforts to the utmost to aid our homeland, which needs help." He believes that the historic hour has struck for our homeland and that Poland must arise, because a nation of 25,000,000 which lives its own spiritual and cultural life will be able to demand the <pb facs="5423968_8_1151.jpg" n="3"/>righting of its wrongs.</p>
   <p>The speaker was frequently interrupted by enthusiastic applause. The collection for the Independence Fund brought in thirty-seven dollars.</p>
   <p>Then the secretary read the resulution, which was unanimously accepted. The resolution reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Considering that in the present European war the fates of monarchs are in the balance, and that bloody battles are being fought on Polish soil to which our nation has the first right of ownership, and that the present war will undoubtedly change the map of Europe; and,</p>
   <p>"Considering that the present war is the result of Prussian intrigue, which pushed Austria into a war on all Slavic nations; and,</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1152.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Considering that the victory of the Prussians would increase the persecution of our brethren living under Prussian rule, whereas the victory of the Slavic nations, together with France and England, forecasts the union of our homeland, which was divided into three parts, into one whole, and would strengthen our nation for further battle for its rights and the freedom of independent Poland; and,</p>
   <p>"Considering that we Poles living here in a foreign land, although in body we are beyond Poland's borders, nevertheless with our hearts and souls are with our brothers in the homeland, and feel together with them the horrible situation in which our country finds itself, since it is forced to sacrifice its bravest young men to the butchery of its enemies, to have millions of them serve against their will in the invader's armies, and to have a thousand of them killed daily for the greater glory of the military prowess of our enemy;</p>
   <p>"We, Polish men and women in the district of Town of Lake, within St. John <pb facs="5423968_8_1153.jpg" n="5"/>of God Parish, gathered together this fourth of October at Casimir Pulaski Hall, declare before the entire world and the countries now at war that not for a moment does our nation of 25,000,000 people give up its rights to Polish lands and to the freedom of the nation.</p>
   <p>"We condemn the military system with which Germany rules itself as the undoing of the inhabitants of the country, since following its example other countries have had to arm in order to protect their borders against Teutonic aggression which, believing in its military strength, has declared war on almost the entire world.</p>
   <p>"With all our hearts we wish the Slavic nations and France, Belgium, and England, which have raised their swords against the Prussians in order to humble them, success and a great victory. We express our sincere sympathy to our brothers in the homeland, whom the bloody war has so sorely affected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1154.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"We demand for the people living on Polish soil, divided into three parts, the unification of this land into one whole, and the freedom and liberty to which our ancient Polish culture entitles us. We want not favors granted by the Czar, but only the rights due us.</p>
   <p>"We solemnly swear that we will support the Independence Fund of the Polish National Alliance to the best of our ability and strength.</p>
   <p>"Long live free and independent Poland!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
