<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-03-15">Mar. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Crisis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-03-15">Mar. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CRISIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the life of individuals there often comes a time when even the strongest and healthiest body falls prey to infection. It falls victim to some disease germ, which, working upon a healthy body, causes decay, which spreads until the strong constitution defeats the intruder and gets rid of it once and for all, in one moment of decisive crisis.</p>
   <p>The same holds true for societies in general, even the most powerful. A society sometimes encounters similar crises, when depraved individuals succeed in entering into it. The only reason that such destructive individuals enroll in any organization is to bring dissension, brawls, and moral gangrene into its midst.</p>
   <p>A crisis in the sickness of an individual is usually very dangerous to that person. Such a crisis may result in the defeat and the expulsion of infectious <pb facs="5423968_8_1127.jpg" n="2"/>germs from the organism of the sick person; nevertheless, it saps the strength and, in general, subjects the victorious organism to a lasting and slow convalescence. This hold true also of an organization which is based upon strong and sound principles. A crisis brings about an immediate and complete cure and becomes the beginning of an even stronger development and growth.</p>
   <p>Luck is the crisis that the Polish National Alliance is now undergoing. Its strong and powerful organism fell prey to an infection. Parasitic germs in the form of whole mobs of more or less red "comrades" have entered the organization. These undesirable individuals are filled with ambition, and are interested only in the jobs that are avilable to self-styled "professors," "doctors," "editors," and the like. And so they proceed to undermine, gnaw, render asunder, slander, and infect that giant (Polish National Alliance). This great organization, conscious of its power, patiently allows itself to be infested with this vermin, although it <pb facs="5423968_8_1128.jpg" n="3"/>could, by a little stronger effort, crush its attackers most decisively.</p>
   <p>Everything, however, has its limits. The strings and bites to which the Polish National Alliance submitted were a bit too frequent and too poisonous to be entirely ignored even by such a gigantic organization as is the Alliance. It began to feel the aftereffects upon its strong and healthy organism. The poison, injected in seemingly insignificant but frequent doses, has done its work, and has infected the strong body. To allow the gangrene to spread any further would be [criminally] careless. The sooner the crisis comes the less will the whole organism suffer, and the sooner it will be rid, once and for all, of every type of vermin.</p>
   <p>The role of a doctor, in this instance, will be played by the Advisory Board of the Polish National Alliance. In the immediate future it will start a thorough disinfection of the organism of the Alliance, to rid the organization of the parasitic microbes that are so dangerous to the normal development of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1129.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This task of disinfection will not be so very difficult. The source from which the infectious vermin has spread over the whole body of the Polish National Alliance is but too well known and evident to all.</p>
   <p>The moment is, therefore, not too distant when the Polish National Alliance will rid itself of every type of undesirable. It will then shine forth in the full strength of its ideals and organizational creativeness. Then the Polish National Alliance will be able to lead, unhindered, its one hundred thousand members toward the high goals which it has maintained uninterruptedly from the very beginning of its existence. These goals are the preservation of national consciousness in our Polish immigrants, and the leading of our people to the realization of a free, united, and independent Poland, which is not merely a buffer state, with a Hohenzollern or a Hapsburg at its head.</p>
   <p>Every organization is exposed to unpleasant and critical transitions. Each has its enemies either from competition or factional hatred or because of <pb facs="5423968_8_1130.jpg" n="5"/>politics. The Polish National Alliance is, therefore, so much the more exposed to various and numerous attacks because it is a financial as well as a nationalist organization, and is prominent in political affairs. In addition to that, it is a large organization, one that is large enough to awaken jealousy. Consequently, it is little wonder that numerous storms befall the Polish National Alliance, that certain brawling elements or individuals, hostile to the Alliance for factional or political reasons, force themselves into that organization. Their aim is to undermine the Alliance and cause dissension in it. This they do with apparent sincerity, a quality of which they have not the slightest knowledge. But the Polish National Alliance laughs at all these attempts because a majority of the organization is honest and is sincerely attached to it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
