<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-20">Jan. 20, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">From the Educational Department of the Polish League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1494</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1494.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-20">Jan. 20, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE EDUCATIONAL DEPARTMENT OF THE POLISH LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(We have received the following announcement with a request that we publish it in the Dziennik Chicagoski.)</p>
   <p>We are glad to announce that last week we shipped one hundred books to form the new branch library of the Polish League, in care of Mr. B. Conrad, at Antrim, Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>The shipment consisted of the following books [Translator's note: A long list of books is omitted in translation].....</p>
   <p>The complete library consists of one hundred bound volumes, comprising over one hundred and fifty stories, etc. These are all moral and patriotic <pb facs="5423968_8_1495.jpg" n="2"/>books, written by well-known polish authors.</p>
   <p>We wish to extend our sincere thanks to all those who have in any manner helped to complete this library, and we respectfully request further donations either of books or of each.</p>
   <p>Let us remember that only enlightenment, based on the foundation of our Holy Faith, can lift us out of our present incompetence, and that all those who sincerely have the welfare of the Polish people at heart should not limit themselves to mere words of praise for the hard and troublesome labors of this Educational Department of the Polish League, but should endeavor to support it materially.</p>
   <p>We have still many books on hand, and are completing the ninth library, but, because we lack financial means, the work is progressing slowly. We are, <pb facs="5423968_8_1496.jpg" n="3"/>therefore, appealing to the hearts of our prominent Poles, and especially to the reverend priests, to contribute to this Educational Department. We respectfully ask our young people and the various agencies of the Polish League to help us, and God will repay you for your kindness.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Educational Department,</p>
   <p>Reverend John Kasprzycki, vice-president,</p>
   <p>Ignatius Kowalski, secretary,</p>
   <p>141-143 W. Division Street,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
