<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-28">Sept. 28, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Poles Organize to Aid Homeland]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1333</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1333.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-28">Sept. 28, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[POLES ORGANIZE TO AID HOMELAND]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are many Polish military groups in various cities of the United States. There is even the well-known Polish Military Alliance. This, however, does not mean that these groups represent a standing army patterned after those of Europe. To begin with, these groups are not trained or organized adequately, and they lack arms of the latest make. Our Polish divisions are composed of volunteers who, after first organizing the military societies, have to furnish their own uniforms and equipment. From time to time these volunteers are called upon to take part in various celebrations. This is done for the purpose of reminding our people of the military splendor that existed once upon a time in Poland. The main purpose, however, is to maintain in our people the faith that Poland will some day become a free and independent nation through the armed efforts of hers sons on foreign soil.</p>
   <p>The Polish military organizations, as previously stated, do not constitute an <pb facs="5423968_8_1334.jpg" n="2"/>army ready for military action. There are no Polish military academies in America from which we could be supplied with qualified officers. The command of our military divisions here is in charge of soldiers who gained military rank while serving in the armies of other European nations. The privates are volunteers of various ages and professions, most of whom never completed their military service in Europe. The military drills here don't follow as yet any fixed schedule, nor are they uniform in all the groups. Our entire Polish-American "army" numbers several thousand soldiers, scattered throughout the United States. So far no provision has been made for maintaining paid officers and leaders or for building a military school to train these soldiers.</p>
   <p>The sacrifices made by our brethren belonging to these Polish military groups are enormous and worthy of admiration. These soldiers, although employed at hard labor during the day, are willing to devote their evenings and holidays to the drills. They purchase their own uniforms and go into other expenses just for the sake of retaining our military tradition and spirit, thus awakening a desire among our youth to take part in these military drills. It is perfectly all <pb facs="5423968_8_1335.jpg" n="3"/>right for our fellow-countrymen who have settled here permanently to create military groups, but they should not think of maintaining paid officers and creating a regular army ready to leave against an enemy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
