<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-17">Sept. 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Local News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-17">Sept. 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A school census report conducted in Chicago has been forwarded to the Polish newspaper, Dziennik Zwiazkowy. We find many interesting statistical comparisons, although possibly they are not completely accurate in certain instances. This census pertains to children and students below the age of twenty-one. It has also taken into consideration the individual nationalities which the statisticians have listed under proper headings. We find from these statistics that there are a total of 814,115 children and students under twenty-one years of age in Chicago, or an increase of 66,768 over that of the census taken in 1908. The statisticians have ascertained that racial suicide is unknown in Chicago because there are 166,503 children under four years of age, that is a number which was not expected. The female sex exceeds in this vast army of Chicago children, because 402,957 boys were counted and 411,158 girls. Among this vast number of children, there are 523 completely deaf, 287 mute, 298 blind and 294 cripples of various types.</p>
   <p>Also interesting is the comparison of children according to nationalities, <pb facs="5423968_8_0568.jpg" n="2"/>although the children born of parents also born in America were considered Americans, regardless of what language they spoke, or what nationality they professed. This list is presented as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Americans</cell>
     <cell>248,102</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Germans</cell>
     <cell>132,223</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Poles</cell>
     <cell>94,432</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Russians (?)</cell>
     <cell>54,827</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Irish</cell>
     <cell>48,015</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Bohemians</cell>
     <cell>44,037</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Swedes</cell>
     <cell>39,825</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Italians</cell>
     <cell>37,319</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Austrians (?)</cell>
     <cell>18,416</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>[Translator's note: This list continues, thirty-three different nationalities being presented; the enumeration of all would have no bearing on the purpose and aim of this article.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0569.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The number of Russian children listed above strikes us as being highly improbable. As is known, there are very few real Russians in America, and even if Ukrainian children were included in this figure, the number would still be too high. Most likely some of the less enlightened Poles coming from the part of Poland annexed by Russia listed themselves as Russians and not as Poles, and hence this huge number. The number of German children also seems to be exaggerated and most probably many Poles from under the Prussian rule listed themselves as being German. The census this year was, in every way, more encouraging to the Poles than it had been previously. The number of Polish children, 94,432, of parents born in Europe and the number of parents born in America taken together, allows us to believe that there are more than a quarter-million Poles in Chicago. Consequently, after the Germans, our people occupy second place with regard to the number of children. If the number of children of the other Slavic peoples were included with the Poles, it could then be said without fear of contradiction that the city of Chicago is half Slavic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0570.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The block, or square of homes, in which the greatest number of children reside is located in the Sixteenth Ward, between Holt, Division, Dickson and Blackhawk Streets. There are 1,126 children in that locality. It is a purely Polish neighborhood, taking in St. Stanislaus Parish and many families belong to the Holy Trinity Parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
