<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 36,
<date when="1909-09-08">Sept. 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Language</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0578</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0578.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 36,
<date when="1909-09-08">Sept. 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH LANGUAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We hear always not one but thousand voices that the beautiful language of ours is like the sun, which ought to shine with all its splendor--in the family home and in our social life. But alas! our youth does not care to hear these voices of good judgment, but instead is willing to express themselves with the crumbs of the English language. We know that the knowledge of the English language in needed by everyone, because the better one knows this country's language, the easier is his struggle for a livelihood in his intercourse with Americans. We call upon our readers quite often, and tell them to learn the English language just as soon as possible, but on the other side we warn and criticize those who, becoming acquainted with the English language, forget about the beautiful Polish language.</p>
   <p>Our youth of both sexes forgets that our parental language is like a dear spring and quite often, without cause, they throw into this pure spring clumps of foreign mud, contaminating and making dirty its true purity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0579.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Rarely, very rarely, the youth uses our language in conversation between themselves, and that is why it is so difficult for them to express themselves in that language.</p>
   <p>Now, you know that Polish language is a stronghold built for us by God, and it is unbecoming for us to stir it up. When will we ever understand that only a complete national peculiarity can prevent the extermination of our national existence.</p>
   <p>The parents themselves are at fault who permit their children to speak English at home, and the growing youth is at fault by expressing themselves only in English and not reading Polish books and newspapers. This is happening, most likely, automatically, unwillingly; and it is so much sadder, because it is evidence that some sort of spirit of unwillingness has penetrated them to the bone marrow.</p>
   <p>We should all struggle against this thoughtless neglect of our mother tongue <pb facs="5423968_8_0580.jpg" n="3"/>and influence our youth that beside the language of this country they should also become acquainted and learn to love the language of their parents, because beautiful as a foreign language is, it is shameful not to know your own.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
