<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-06">Apr. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To Arms!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1014</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1014.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-06">Apr. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO ARMS!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>War has been declared between the United States and Germany!</p>
   <p>By a large majority both Houses of Congress have passed a resolution recognizing the existence of a state of war between the United States and Germany.</p>
   <p>War is not something which can be postponed indefinitely, as we all realize. In this tremendous conflict of nations, we Poles cannot remain on the side lines. In Pittsburgh, where a Falcon convention is being held at this time, Ignace Paderewski has given us the task of raising a "Kosciusko Army" of 100,000 men. The United States Government will accept our services.</p>
   <p>Authorized by the Falcon convention, and following the impulse of all the Poles in the United States, the president of the Alliance of Polish Falcons sent yesterday the following telegram to President Wilson:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1015.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"To His Excellency Woodrow Wilson</p>
   <p>President of the United States</p>
   <p>Washington, D. C.</p>
   <p>"At their extraordinary meeting of April fourth, the Polish Falcons of America conferred upon the great honor of offering to you, Mr. President, their high appreciation of your wisdom and equity, their sincere admiration for the supremely noble and humanitarian spirit which is dictating all your words and acts. Prompted by loyalty and devotion to their adopted country, they have unanimously decided to raise an army of one hundred thousand men and to tender its services to the Government of the United States. This army, composed of men whose forefathers inscribed the cry for our liberty and yours on their banners, will gladly follow the American flag in the sublime effort to secure liberty and justice for all nations and democratic freedom for mankind. The Polish Falcons of America only ask and hope that the Government, considering the glorious ties that bind their ancestry with this country of ours, allow the fighting force to be named the 'Kosciusko Army' and they beg of you, Mr. President, to accept the assurance of their profound respect, gratitude, <pb facs="5423968_8_1016.jpg" n="3"/>and affection.</p>
   <p>Dr. T. A. Starzynski"</p>
   <p>These are today the words of all the Poles in America, words which must soon turn into action.</p>
   <p>This is not the time for useless disagreements, but for the concentrated effort of all our immigrants, whose duty it is to raise a "Kosciusko Army" of 100,000 men.</p>
   <p>As soon as all formalities are settled, the mobilization order will be issued. Let us all join the ranks in order to fulfill our duty toward this country and toward Poland, our homeland.</p>
   <p>So help us God!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
