<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-06-04">June 4, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Military Societies of Chicago and Vicinity Meet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-06-04">June 4, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH MILITARY SOCIETIES OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY MEET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members of the Polish military societies of Chicago and vicinity, affiliated with the Polish military organizations, held a meeting yesterday.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Sigmund Schmidt, and J. M. Przymorski was secretary.</p>
   <p>After a long discussion over the form and other details of the organization, the members decided to choose a commander and adjutant general of the Polish military organization in Chicago, and to divide military societies into units according to the settlements and kind of weapons. Sigmund Schmidt was chosen commander, and J. M. Przymorski adjutant general. A committee for dividing the societies into units according to settlements and weapons was chosen; it consists of the following members: Terczewski, Kaminski, and Lama.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, it was decided to name the new organization "II Korpus Wojsk <pb facs="5423968_8_1608.jpg" n="2"/>Polskich w Ameryce" (The Second Corps of the Polish Army in America). An application for membership in the organization was drawn up and signed immediately by those representatives of the Polish military societies of Chicago and Lemont, Illinois, who were present. The others will undoubtedly sign it.</p>
   <p>A managing body of the new organization was also formed, as follows: S. Terczewski, president; J. N. Przymorski, general secretary; F. X. Rydzewski, treasurer; Malinowski, Gizela, and Plocharz, counselors.</p>
   <p>The newly elected officers were instructed to draw up more detailed regulations, and to obtain a charter for the now organization. This concluded the meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
