<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-21">May 21, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Boys Thieves</title><title level="a" type="sub">Musical Instruments Stolen from Local Firm</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-21">May 21, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH BOYS THIEVES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Musical Instruments Stolen from Local Firm</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night a bold robbery was staged at the Champion Auction House, corner of Emma and Noble Streets, dealers in musical instruments. Over 120 pieces of musical instruments, valued at one thousand dollars, were stolen.</p>
   <p>An inventory revealed that the following musical instruments were taken: 2 music boxes, 11 harps, 12 guitars, 25 accordians, 2 concertinas, 31 violins, 6 tambourines, 10 flutes, 7 fifes, 12 harmonicas, and 2 cornets.</p>
   <p>The thieves entered the store through a rear window which they broke.</p>
   <p>When Lieutenant Kandzia, of the North Avenue Station, received a report of the robbery at 8 A. M., he immediately went to the scene, and after a close examination came to the conclusion that the crime was perpetrated by a group of boys. Officers Sullivan and Schultz were assigned to the case. At 9 A. M. they spotted <pb facs="5423968_8_0123.jpg" n="2"/>a boy, Anthony Stanczewski, on Milwaukee Avenue. When they tried to detain him for questioning, he fled. Chase was given and he was caught. At the station he readily admitted that he had taken part in the robbery, and gave a complete story of it. On the grounds of his confession Frank Hellman was arrested. Both boys said that the robbery was committed by a group of Polish boys under sixteen years of age.</p>
   <p>The names of the seven boys who took part in the robbery are Matz, Otto Kelma, Anthony Stanczewski, John Rose, Paul Peterek, Frank Helman (sic), and W. Polfus. The leader and plotter was Matz.</p>
   <p>The thieves gathered about ten o'clock last night at the rear of the building; two remained as lookouts, while the others, after having broken the rear window with a stone, entered the building with the aid of a wire. Matz collected the instruments and the others took them out under their shirts or otherwise and hid them in sheds, basements and other hideouts.</p>
   <p>Lieutenant Kandzia managed to find one of these places and recovered 12 violins, <pb facs="5423968_8_0124.jpg" n="3"/>5 guitars, and a music box; other instruments were also found near by. So far over three hundred dollars' worth of the instruments have been recovered.</p>
   <p>Besides these seven boys, others are implicated, including the fathers. This, however, is not very clear at the moment. More details will be given when the entire robbery is cleared up.</p>
   <p>It is with regret that we must say that within recent times Polish boys have been found in gangs, and to our regret it is getting to be a common thing.</p>
   <p>Almost daily a robbery is reported, and many times our Polish boys are responsible. Such action on their part only brings shame and disgrace to the Poles of Chicago. The parents who allowed their children to follow such paths are greatly to blame. It will be more difficult for them now to direct them on the road to righteousness, but if they do not make this effort they will be responsible to society and to God.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
