<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 3,
<date when="1915-01-20">Jan. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Protest - in Defense of the Oppressed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0766</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0766.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 3,
<date when="1915-01-20">Jan. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST - IN DEFENSE OF THE OPPRESSED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Copy of protest form sent out during the past week to all societies of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union. It is to be signed by the president and secretary of the society and with the seal of the society attached, for warded to the congressmen of the district. The protest form reads as follows:</p>
   <p>Protest</p>
   <p>To the kind attention of the United States Congress:</p>
   <p>Whereas, there is now before the Congress of the United States a bill providing for the regulation of the entry of aliens into the United States known and described as the Smith-Burnett Immigration Bill, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the said bill contains among other, provisions requiring educational tests to which all aliens desiring admission to this country will be subjected, and their inability to meet the said tests will constitute a bar to their admission to the United States, and</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0767.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whereas, conditions in many foreign lands render it impossible for countless thousands of people to secure an education in the land of their birth, as a result of the tyrannical attitude of foreign governments towards the people of countries that have been taken by force and deprived of their liberty, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, many people residing within the boundaries of the former commonwealth of Poland are among those, who, as a result of years of oppression on the part of hostile foreign governments and their despotic desire to destroy them as a nation and a people, have been deprived of the rights and opportunity to attend schools and colleges in their native land and have at their first opportunity sought liberty and freedom by immigrating to the United States , and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the downtrodden and the oppressed of every clime for years have looked upon these United States as a land where all honest people irrespective of nationality and creed could enter and enjoy the blessings of liberty, freedom and justice, and</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0768.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Whereas, the history of our country shows that from its very foundation its most trying moments the vote, work and efforts of immigrants have been the support of this American nation and this American country and its institutions, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the people coming here from Poland and in fact the peasants, artisans and workingmen of European countries, in general have upon their arrival proven themselves to be industrious, home loving, moral, not parasites upon the country and not exploiters of their fellow men, but a desirable, healthy and strengthening element which has worked hard not only to better their own conditions, but to make this country great and to perpetuate this free government and its great principles, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, so far as the Polish and other Slavonic people are concerned there has been no fair, just and intelligent investigation or report made of the immigration problem by any commission of our government, for no commission and no government report upon the subject has included <pb facs="5423968_8_0769.jpg" n="4"/>in these conducting the work any one who was of, in sympathy with or familiar with either the language, customs, conditions or principles of the Polish or other Slavonic people, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, a healthy moral, honest, industrious immigrant coming to this country, after the period of helpless childhood, as an adult is an asset and not a drain to this country for the expense of bringing such immigrant to the condition of becoming a self-supporting producer has been borne before his coming here by the country from whence he comes, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, we know that liberty or educational tests do not indicate the morals, conscience, honesty, integrity or industry of an immigrant, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the present immigration laws and restrictions which are being rigidly enforced are sufficient to keep out of our country all vicious, unhealthy and undesirable elements.</p>
   <p>Therefore be it resolved that we the members of ....(name of society)... residing in the .... (name of city) .... and state of .... (name of state)... <pb facs="5423968_8_0770.jpg" n="5"/>citizens of these United States of America, having the well being and future of this great country and its government and institutions at heart, and as a part of that element of this country's population which came here from Poland hereby protest against the enactment of the proposed restrictions requiring educational tests as being unfair, unjust, and un-American.</p>
   <p>Be it further resolved that a copy of these resolutions be forwarded to the Hon..... (name of congressman)..... congressman from the state..... (name of state) ..... for submission to Congress.</p>
   <p>(Name of President of Society)</p>
   <p>President of ... (name of society)...</p>
   <p>Secretary of ... (name of society)</p>
   <p>Adopted by the............. members of the ..........</p>
   <p>SEAL</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
