<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-26">Oct. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Convention of the National Department of the Polish Central Relief Relief Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0945</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0945.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-10-26">Oct. 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL CONVENTION OF THE NATIONAL DEPARTMENT OF THE POLISH CENTRAL RELIEF RELIEF COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At 3:15 in the afternoon, the annual convention of the National Department was called to order by its chairman, Attorney K. Sypniewski. The following delegates were present: Attorney Sypniewski, T. Blachowski, F. Nowak, Dr. Wagner, Dr. Starzynski, the Reverend Celichowski, Casimir Zychlinski, J. Rybicki, J. Horodyski, Attorney Koscinski, T. Wronski, the Reverend Lemke, F. Porzuczek, K. B. Czarnecki, J. Magdziarz, the Reverend Bona, the Reverend W. Zapala, Dr. Heller, the Reverend Budzik, A. Tomkiewicz, R. Wisniewski, T. Polanski, S. Szwajkart, N. K, Zlotnicki, M. Pijanowski, A. E. Rakoczy, F. Grutza, J. Singer, A. Czerwinski, J. Zawilinski, the Reverend S. Bubacz, Mrs. A. Neuman, Mrs. M. Sakowski, Mrs. M. Milewski, Mrs. K. Obarski, Mrs. L. Wolowski, T. Olsztynski, J. Missal, W. Wrzesinski, J. Samulski, J. F. Smulski, Mrs. M. Osuch, H. Setmajer, the Reverend Sohieniowski, T. M. Helinski, Miss E. Napieralski, P. Rostenkowski, Dr. Starzynski [sic], Dr. Drobinski, N. L. Piotrowski, <pb facs="5423968_8_0946.jpg" n="2"/>J. J. Chrzanowski, and S. Orpiszewski.</p>
   <p>In the absence of Dr. W. Fronczak of Buffalo, secretary of the National Department, who had written to explain why he was unable to be present, Dr. Wagner of Milwaukee was named secretary. Chairman Sypniewski then named an executive committee of three.</p>
   <p>It developed that the Polish National Alliance and the Polish Roman Catholic Union had a right to twenty votes each, and the Polish Falcons' Alliance to three. The rest of the votes were distributed as follows: the Polish Womens' Alliance: three and a half, the Polish Priests' Association: fifteen, the Polish Alma Mater: one half, the Polish Union of Wilkes Barre: one, the Polish Union of Buffalo: one, the National Center of Detroit: two, the National Center of Trenton: one quarter, the Alliance of Poles of America: two, and the Union of St. Joseph of Pittsburgh: one half a vote. In addition to these, J. J. Horodyski had the right to an advisory voice in the proceedings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0947.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After taking the oath from the new members of the National Department H. Setmajer, secretary of the Polish Central Relief Committee read the minutes of the last convention and presented a report of the activities of the Executive Committee of the National Department as well as the financial report. Then followed the treasurer's report, given by Rostenkowski, and the Committee's report, given by J. Rybicki. After acceptance of the executive committee and officers' reports the session was adjourned until 7:30 in the evening.</p>
   <p>Evening Session</p>
   <p>The evening session began at the scheduled time with a report from the military commission, presented by T. M. Helinski. He stated that the commission planned to establish forty [Polish Army] recruiting stations throughout the United States. At present, twelve are functioning and twenty additional stations will open shortly. The rest will be opened before the first of the following month. He further reported that the commission had received assurances from the French <pb facs="5423968_8_0948.jpg" n="4"/>government that it [the French government] would cover all recruiting costs. Finally, he stated that there are at present two thousand volunteers in training at Niagara-on-the-Lake and, as far as can be judged now, seven hundred more will be added to these next week.</p>
   <p>Then followed discussion and finally, acceptance of the military commission's report.</p>
   <p>A letter from His Excellency Bishop Paul Rhode was next read to the convention.</p>
   <p>The secretary then presented the budget for the following year and the chairman named a committee on amendments to the constitution.....A recess of a few minutes was called to give the committee time to prepare a report. With the resumption of proceedings, J. F. Smulski brought up the matter of sending telegrams to President Wilson and Paderewski. It was referred to the executive committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0949.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Election</p>
   <p>Dr. Drobinski of New York was elected president, Dr. Wagner of Milwaukee first vice-president, Attorney Koscinski of Detroit second vice-president, and Miss E. Napieralaski of Chicago secretary. The executive committee consists of the following: Sypniewski, the Reverend Celichowski, J. F. Smulski, and T. Blachowski for eighteen months, Mrs. M. Sakowski and Mrs. M. Milewski for twelve months, and J. Rybicki for six months.</p>
   <p>The next plenary convention of the National Department will be held in April, 1918, the exact date to be determined at a future time. The convention was adjourned at about 11:30 P.M. with the singing of "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
