<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 42,
<date when="1897-10-21">Oct. 21, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Language</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 42,
<date when="1897-10-21">Oct. 21, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH LANGUAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dearest treasure for us is the treasure that no one can take away from us; a treasure of great value, it is our language, our wonderful Polish language.</p>
   <p>And yet, do we guard and protect this treasure as we are supposed to do, do we keep vigil upon its entire worth? No!</p>
   <p>Due to the carelessness of others who think nothing of the morrow, not only kinder our language, but deny themselves of this language in the presence of the public.</p>
   <p>And so then we ask you in what case is the English language greater than ours? Maybe our follow men, who amongst themselves speak English, think they speak the true American language. In such a case we would like them to know that when Poland was a strong and great empire, in America there existed no civilization. When Poland was fighting wars for its faith and <pb facs="5423968_8_0627.jpg" n="2"/>glory, these uncivilized Indians ever here were murdering themselves needlessly. If they imagine or think that by speaking amongst themselves in another national tongue, portraying their extinetiveness of their American citizenship, well, let them try and speak the original American language, try to speak the tongue of the Sioux, Apaches, as they were the original inhabitants of this country.</p>
   <p>And so, where is there any sense? Also, where is our national pride? And what is the most saddening fast above all this? That frequently, aside of the men folks and women, our girls and boys scorn our native tongue. It is a sad fast, it harts us, and reminds us of being something on the order of the Roman gladiators who, before a fatal duel in the circus arena, passed before the Caesar's throne, bowing and calling out: "Caesar, the dying are greeting you." This being an example of us as we pass also the arena, this arena being the world with Poland seated in the throne, we likewise call out to her: Poland, do not count on us, we are lost to you!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0628.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For what purpose do we boast in the presence of others that we possessed a great part, that we also possessed such great men as Copernicus, Kechanowski, Czarniecki and Sobieski. Why do we at every opportunity remind the Americans of Kosciuszko and Pulaski if we are ashamed to speak our language, and in some cases even denying our nationality? If we would only commit ourselves to the fact and admit that we are Poles, if everyone would speak without fear and combat the shame held upon us, our entire nation would receive the greatest of all respects.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
