<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-01-14">Jan. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Danger in the Immigration Laws</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0571</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0571.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy, Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1910-01-14">Jan. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">DANGER IN THE IMMIGRATION LAWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many Poles who have settled in the United States, but have failed to obtain their naturalization papers, are living in a world of uncertainty.</p>
   <p>According to the immigration laws, all non-citizens of three years residence or less in the United States, are subject to deportation for all violations of the law. The Secretary of Commerce and Labor, is authorized to order the arrest of all such persons, then to deport them and bar their re-entry to the United States. It is a fact that these laws do exist, and are in force at the present time. According to the New York Herald, the Times, and the World, Jos. V. Ueberall, Hungarian, living in this country more than three years, is about to be deported. Ueberall was arrested by the New York police, while connected with some shady transaction. He gained his freedom by convincing the judge with his smooth talk, that he was innocent. Due to lack of evidence, he was permitted to go free; but because of the gravity of the offense, the police decided to watch his movements.</p>
   <p>At the same time the Austro-Hungarian Consul, remembered that a Ueberall was charged with similar swindles and was wanted in both Austria and Germany. This man was therefore, rearrested and held until further information, pertaining to his indentity could be obtained. He was indentified through pictures, as the man wanted in Austria and in German. He is now awaiting deportation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0572.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The articles in the above mentioned New York newspaper, bring to light the fact that all aliens, including those who have applied for their first papers, are subject to deportation for various infactions of the law.</p>
   <p>When you visit Canada, Mexico or any territory outside of the United States, you are compelled upon your return to make a new entree into this country; and it is necessary to again apply for your first papers. Five years residence is then again required before final papers are obtainable. When you become a naturalized citizen, you are not subject to deportation or such other inconveniences.</p>
   <p>We must admit this immigration law has advantages because of its aid in the apprehension of murderers, thieves, swindlers, and undesirables.</p>
   <p>But there are many other dangers awaiting the non-citizen, even though he may be a fine law abiding and respectable person, who has resided here fifty years or more. Theoretically speaking, he is a fine person, but he cannot vote, therefore cannot take part in the affairs of the government under which he resides.</p>
   <p>Some time ago, the Secretary of Commerce and Labor, made a statement, that immigrants entering this country should be classified as, "returning aliens," or <pb facs="5423968_8_0573.jpg" n="3"/>"a newly arrived alien". The immigration law specifies that a person must reside in the United States five years, in order to qualify for citizenship; it would be better, however, to specify five years of continuous and uninterrupted residence in the United States. Congress should make this point clear so that non-citizens will know exactly where they stand, and those of a long uninterrupted residence take the necessary steps, to become citizens.</p>
   <p>There is no question or doubt that the defenders of immigration are sincere in their aims; nevertheless the American chauvinist movement should be curbed. Hatred toward the foreigner is growing daily. Every year sees new restrictions on immigration, and it is becoming more and more difficult to obtain citizenship.</p>
   <p>Let us, therefore, strive to become American citizens, as soon as possible, and avoid the danger and uncertainty that awaits the alien on every hand.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
