<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 55,
<date when="1922-03-07">March 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">American Citizenship</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 55,
<date when="1922-03-07">March 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN CITIZENSHIP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have heard the claim more than once, from quite important people here and there, that now since the Polish state exists, a Pole ought not to try for American citizenship, because by this very thing he voluntarily renounces Polish citizenship and somehow shows contempt for the land of his ancestors, for which the Polish authorities can avenge themselves upon him if he desires to return to his Fatherland.</p>
   <p>This is in the main a false comprehension of Polish patriotism. The man who speaks that way and conducts such agitation among his countrymen, demonstrates likewise to them as well as to Poland a "bear like service." (Translator's note: "Bear like service," a Polish saying based on the story of the bear, who upon espying a fly on the face of its master, in an attempt to kill the fly, struck at it, hitting its master in the face and killing him).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0421.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have before us a statistical circular of the Census Bureau of the Department of Commerce in Washington, issued on the third day of March, which shows the number of persons born beyond the United States boundaries and living in the state of Illinois, together with the number of those who have accepted American citizenship and those who are not yet citizens.</p>
   <p>The statistics given, based on the 1920 census, point out that for a population of 6, 485,280 in the state of Illinois, the number of white persons born outside of the United States amounts to 1,206,951, of which 1,117,928 are over 21 years of age. From this number 200,449 were born in Germany; 149,985 in Poland, 102,258 in Sweden, 101,722 in Russia, etc.</p>
   <p>Of the persons arriving from Germany 79.6% acquired citizenship papers; from Poland 35.2% had endeavored to receive their citizenship papers; from Sweden 73.1%, and from Russia 43.9%.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0422.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From the computation table of all immigrants, according to the government computation, the most negligent toward acquiring their citizenship papers are the Greeks, because the percentage of Greek immigrants receiving them amounted to 24.8%. After the Greeks come the Lithuanians, because the number of those naturalized amounts to 30%. Fourth in line in respect to American citizenship are the Hungarians, 35.1%, and fifth, the Poles, 35.2%. The quickest and the most numerous in acquiring American citizenship are the German immigrants, amounting to 79.6%.</p>
   <p>That is why the Germans have a strong influence in politics, that is why they are successful here. Everybody here takes them into account, but the Polish immigration, the largest after the German, is held lightly.</p>
   <p>Polish immigrants in their own well-understood interests and even in <pb facs="5423968_8_0423.jpg" n="4"/>the interest of their fatherland, ought to receive citizenship, take a great voice in American politics, and improve their influence and recognition over here, because in only this way can they best help Poland.</p>
   <p>The Polish government which would avenge itself on the Polish emigrants for receiving American citizenship, plainly does not understand Polish government interests and will act to the detriment of Poland. American citizenship does not compel anyone to renounce one's sympathy for the land of one's birth. It gives the immigrant a voice in the internal and external affairs of American politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
