<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVII, No. 129,
<date when="1923-06-02">June 2, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Plea to the Polonia in Chicago a Manifestation in Honor of Kosciuszko</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0898</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0898.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVII, No. 129,
<date when="1923-06-02">June 2, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A PLEA TO THE POLONIA IN CHICAGO A MANIFESTATION IN HONOR OF KOSCIUSZKO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fellow-citizens!</p>
   <p>This year as in formers years, we set aside one day so that we may pay tribute to the illuminating memory of our chieftain, a hero of two worlds, by attending a solemn parade before his monument in Humboldt Park.</p>
   <p>We shall pay him homage just as we have done during the past years. He taught us how to combat our enemies and how, with the aid of a sword we may hew out our future.</p>
   <p>When the chests of thousands swelled with the pleading hymn. "Oh God! Free Our Fatherland", which was before we gained our freedom, that was the time when we pined for the liberty of today. But today we may express ourselves proudly with the phrase, "Oh God! Preserve Our Independence".</p>
   <p>This gigantic manifestation before the monument of T. Kosciuszko will be held tomorrow.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0899.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This manifestation will include participants representing various organizations and societies, which include our world war veterans, together with the army of Uncle Sam; Gen. J. Haller and his men; the P.N.A.; the P.R.C.O.; the Polish Women's All.; the Falcons; the Polish Army Organization; and the representation of all our Polish patriotic parishes - in one word, everyone shall participate beneath the standards, as we have done in the past years.</p>
   <p>We strongly appeal to you all to participate in this great manifestation, declaring your love for everything of Polish origin. We beg you to share in the feat of honoring our dead heroes, those who died fighting for the independence of our fatherland.</p>
   <p>Many of Chicago's prominent people have offered their services in this festivity. Some of the volunteers are - M. Tomaszkiewicz, Judge E. K. Jarecki, J. Niemiec, Father S. Bubacz, John F. Smulski, Judge M. Mokinley, James S. Davis, G. Barthel and C. Zyohlinski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
