<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-01">Jan. 1, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish National Alliance's Golden Jubilee Festival</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0855</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0855.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-01">Jan. 1, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE'S GOLDEN JUBILEE FESTIVAL</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance, founded on February 15, 1880, in Philadelphia, and now seated in Chicago, is celebrating throughout the country the Golden Jubilee of its existence and of its important activities among the Polish immigrants.</p>
   <p>One of the numerous Golden Jubilee celebrations will take place on the 11th of January, 1931, in Philadelphia, the cradle and the original seat of that organization. One of the notable speakers on the occasion will be Dr. Raczynski, a delegated representative of the Polish Consulate from New York. The program of the day will be diversified by songs, music and declamations.</p>
   <p>It should be pointed out that the Polish National Alliance, the largest of all Polish organizations in the world, has been originated in 1880 by five men: Juliusz Andrzejkowicz, Jan Popielinski, Julian Lipinski, Jan B. Blachowski and Julian n. Within fifty years of its existence the Alliance has grown so steadily that it has nearly 300,000 members throughout the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0856.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Incomparably brighter yet is the future of the Polish National Alliance, opened with the Jubilee Contest, which is expected to bring 40,000 additional members to the organization.</p>
   <p>The jubilee festivals, celebrated in numerous towns and cities, wherever there are groups of members of the Polish National Alliance, are being used as a means of propagating the original idea of the Alliance's founders and pioneers, who pursued the aim of the largest possible number of American Poles in the Polish National Alliance. These celebrations are also useful in another respect. By presenting to the forum of the Alliance's members matters of actual organizational value they reduce the propensity to brawls and quarrels about matters of little importance - quarrels which were of common occurrence in the past. New reforms and regulations are also suggested and enacted, particularly such as are adapted to the native born young generation, which already constitutes a considerable part of the membership of the Organization.</p>
   <p>It is expected that the Golden Jubilee festivals will leave behind them a still more marked revival of the national and organizational spirit, and thereby enable the Polish National Alliance to fully accomplish its mission.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
