<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-11">Mar. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Circuit Ii of Polish Falcons' Alliance Holds Great Mass Meeting</title><title level="a" type="sub">Women's Alliance Hall Filled to Capacity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0928</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0928.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-03-11">Mar. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CIRCUIT II OF POLISH FALCONS' ALLIANCE HOLDS GREAT MASS MEETING</title><title level="a" type="sub">Women's Alliance Hall Filled to Capacity</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday evening a great patriotic mass meeting was held at the Polish Womens' Alliance Hall, on North Ashland Avenue, under the auspices of Circuit II of the Polish Falcons' Alliance. The patriotic Polish public attended in great numbers, and shortly after seven o'clock the hall was completely filled. The mass meeting could not begin on time, however, because of another Polish patriotic demonstration taking place on the South Side, namely, the consecration and unfurling of colors of the Fourth Regiment of the Polish army, at which all the officers of Circuit II were present. Because of this delay, Zukowski, chairman of the committee in charge of the mass meeting, requested the orchestra, under the direction of F. Przybylski, to play a few numbers until the meeting could be formally opened.</p>
   <p>During this time, the childrens' and women's Nests of Circuit II arrived and took <pb facs="5423968_8_0929.jpg" n="2"/>their places at the front of the hall on both sides of the platform. It was exactly eight o'clock when Zukowski, chairman of the committee, called the meeting to order with the following address:</p>
   <p>"Countrymen! When at any time it was necessary to give an account of the activity of those who were engaged in nationalistic work, or when it became necessary to ask the will of the people, it was done by the age-old custom--at a mass meeting; so that great and small alike knew their place in society and were given direction for future work.</p>
   <p>"Falconry, holding to this plain and honest custom, has called this mass meeting to report the results of its work, to seek your counsel, and to urge ourselves and you onward to further effort for our homeland, for never before in the history of our country did such a need exist as today.</p>
   <p>"Today's meeting has been called partly for you to decide whether the continued existence of Falconry is justified. We have been startled by the statement <pb facs="5423968_8_0930.jpg" n="3"/>made by a Pole in conversation--one who, I will not say occupies an important place, but, at any rate, one who occupies a responsible place in nationalistic work--that since the greater portion of Falcons have joined the army, Falconry can no longer justify its existence. This is not the opinion of merely one man; we heard it again in private conversation at the Morrison Hotel during last Sunday's manifestation--it was repeated to us by those who were once opposed to Falconry.</p>
   <p>"The further work, then, of those under whose influence developed our first, most beloved, and never-to-be-forgotten soldier Falcons of the Polish army has no right to exist?</p>
   <p>"Then the tens of thousands of dollars, in part contributed by the Falcons and in part begged from others by them and given steadily for the needs of our homeland--are these dollars to be wasted?</p>
   <p>"Then the physical development of Polish children, and drawing them into Falcon's <pb facs="5423968_8_0931.jpg" n="4"/>nests so that they should not become denationalized, so that they should become such sons of Poland as those who are now in the ranks of the Polish army--can it be that this development is no longer needed?</p>
   <p>"It is our opinion that the Falcons, out of pure love for Poland, have done more disinterested work for that country than those who would destroy Falconry.</p>
   <p>"It is our opinion that Falcons, by giving steadily and never asking support of the people, have a right, loving their homeland, to continue their efforts in its behalf.</p>
   <p>"This mass meeting, which I hereby open, should encourage the Falcons for the future, and should be a warning to those who find Falconry an obstacle to their own purposes. Czolem! (Hail)."</p>
   <p>After he had concluded his address, Zukowski called upon John Rybicki, president of Circuit II, to preside over the meeting, and upon Kornaszewski to act as <pb facs="5423968_8_0932.jpg" n="5"/>secretary. He also invited the presidents of Polish societies and representatives of Bohemian Falcons to take places upon the platform. The program was executed in the following order:</p>
   <p>The orchestra, conducted by F. Przybylski, played the American and Polish national anthems, to which the audience listened attentively, standing.</p>
   <p>Following this, the married women's chorus, Kalina, directed by Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch, sang "Medley of Polish Songs," and, as an encore, "Spring," by Kondziorski. These beautiful songs were rewarded by the thunderous applause of the audience.</p>
   <p>The next number was a violin solo by S. Bialoruski, who played Dredel's "Mazurka," with piano accompaniment by Mrs. Wanda Krzyczewski-Zaklikiewicz, former commander of Circuit II. Enchanted by this beautiful number, the audience forced the artist to return to the platform for an encore.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0933.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Following this number, the chairman named a commission to formulate a resolution. The commission consisted of Miss Matilda Zwierkowski, S. Krzywonos, and Louis B. Haduch. Then followed the statistical report on the activities of Circuit II since the outbreak of the war, and its program for the future. The report, read by President Rybicki, followas</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Nest</cell>
     <cell>Number of Members</cell>
     <cell>Recruits to Polish Army</cell>
     <cell>Recruits to American Army</cell>
     <cell>Donations to Polish Cause</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2</cell>
     <cell>176</cell>
     <cell>50</cell>
     <cell>6</cell>
     <cell>$1,833.46</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3</cell>
     <cell>88</cell>
     <cell>6</cell>
     <cell>6</cell>
     <cell>366.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>9</cell>
     <cell>58</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
     <cell>4</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>18</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>9</cell>
     <cell>9</cell>
     <cell>631.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>27</cell>
     <cell>109</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>250.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>48</cell>
     <cell>18</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>3</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>71</cell>
     <cell>42</cell>
     <cell>5</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>150.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>100</cell>
     <cell>(Women's Nest - 65 members)</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell>185.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>105</cell>
     <cell>73</cell>
     <cell>7</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
     <cell>265.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0934.jpg" n="7"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Nest</cell>
     <cell>Number of Members</cell>
     <cell>Recruits to Polish Army</cell>
     <cell>Recruits to American Army</cell>
     <cell>Donations to Polish Cause</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>189</cell>
     <cell>113</cell>
     <cell>19</cell>
     <cell>14</cell>
     <cell>$1,045.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>192</cell>
     <cell>49</cell>
     <cell>11</cell>
     <cell>23</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>213</cell>
     <cell>55</cell>
     <cell>8</cell>
     <cell>9</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>242</cell>
     <cell>30</cell>
     <cell>2</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>2,000.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>429</cell>
     <cell>18</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>6</cell>
     <cell>135.95</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>507</cell>
     <cell>13</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>1</cell>
     <cell>25.36</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>566</cell>
     <cell>60</cell>
     <cell>6</cell>
     <cell>11</cell>
     <cell>157.81</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>701</cell>
     <cell>22</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>3</cell>
     <cell>830.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The report was accepted by the audience with prolonged applause. Dr. Rybicki explained the report in the following manner:</p>
   <p>"Since there are about fifty Falcon Nests in Circuit II, and for various reasons only eighteen [sic.] The report lists only seventeen Nests reported, an estimate can be taken on those Nests that have not yet reported, but which have <pb facs="5423968_8_0935.jpg" n="8"/>been equally active in nationalistic work, that Circuit II has supplied seven hundred men to the Polish and American armies for the struggle against the Germans, and has contributed $27,213 to the Polish cause. Of the children receiving physical training, there are 534 boys and 285 girls. This is a detailed report of the activities of Circuit II for the period of the present war.</p>
   <p>"The program of Circuit II of the Polish Falcons' Alliance for the future is as follows:</p>
   <p>"Standing always in the ranks of loyal citizens of the United States, we will make every effort to co-operate with the local recruiting center to obtain as many soldiers for the Polish army as possible.</p>
   <p>"We will be a 'home' for the entire Polish army now in the field, remembering the needs of all its members, and satisfying them to the greatest possible extent. We will enlist those who are as yet standing on the sidelines.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0936.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"We will draw the Polish children of both sexes into the Falcon Nests in order to protect them against denationalization, to develop them physically, and at the same time, imbue them with a love for the Polish language and for Poland. And you, dear countrymen, we ask for your sincere co-operation and support, of the same kind that the Falcons have enjoyed to this day. Czolem! (Hail)."</p>
   <p>The next number following the report and explanation by Rybicki, which were rewarded by great applause, was a piano solo, Leybach's "The Palms," Op. 180, played by Miss Mary Slawinski. Miss Slawinski was unknown to the local Polonia, having completed her course at the music conservatory only recently. This first public appearance of the young pianist was a real success, for by rendering so difficult a number, she showed not only excellent technique but true understanding of the composition. The audience rewarded her with great applause, and she was presented with two bouquets of flowers. As an encore, she played a Schubert composition, with equal feeling and artistry. A third bouquet and a storm of applause were her reward.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0937.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Henry Lokanski, an editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, then delivered an address. Since lack of space prevents us from giving this patriotic address in its entirety, we will present only its high lights.</p>
   <p>The speaker, in considering the question raised by enemies of the movement in the East, as to whether Falconry has a right to continue in existence (since the majority of its members have enlisted in the Polish and American armies) asserted that now, more than ever, this useful organization is necessary, for it must create a reserve for those who are now on the battle front. The speaker emphasized the fact that at the outbreak of the war the Polish Falcons' Alliance had a membership of about twenty thousand, and of these about ten thousand joined the Polish army, while about six thousand volunteered in the American army. Altogether, about sixteen thousand Falcons hastened to the struggle, against Poland's age-old enemy, for the freedom of nations. The speaker showed further that, thanks to the Falcon organization, the Polish youth born in this country, as well as those who came here from Poland, did not lose their Polish characteristics, but instead, remained Polish, filled with the spirit of our <pb facs="5423968_8_0938.jpg" n="11"/>forefathers, the spirit of our national heroes. The speaker then pointed to Poland's natural wealth--the great coal, salt, and zinc deposits, the oil, and the other resources. He advised that the Poles remaining in this country at the close of the war be a connecting link between the free and independent Republic of Poland and this great republic, the United States. Lokanski's speech had tremendous effect upon the audience, as the frequent and sustained applause testified.</p>
   <p>A collection was next taken up for the relief of war sufferers in Poland. It netted $97.05.</p>
   <p>After the orchestra, directed by Przybylski, played the "Medley of Polish Songs," the chairman introduced the representatives of the Bohemian Falcons, Dr. Icinski, as one who had done such to organize the first Polish Falcon societies in Chicago, and Paskowski, commandant of the Bohemian Falcons. Following these introductions, the orchestra played the Bohemian national anthem, to which the audience rose from its seats. Paskowski spoke first, and was followed by <pb facs="5423968_8_0939.jpg" n="12"/>Dr. Icinski. Both speakers were generously applauded and, as they spoke in Bohemian, they were understood by everyone.</p>
   <p>Miss Emily Napieralski, secretary-general of the Polish Women's Alliance, then delivered a lengthy address. The public frequently interrupted her patriotic speech with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>A. Wolski then spoke in behalf of the Polish army, after which Miss Zwierkowski read the resolution. It was accepted unanimously.</p>
   <p>Chairman Rybicki spoke a few more words, and this great mass meeting concluded with the playing of "Jeszeze Polska Nie Zginela" (Poland is not yet Lost) and the Falcon hymn by the orchestra.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
