<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-12">June 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">To the Agencies and Members of the Polish League of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-12">June 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE AGENCIES AND MEMBERS OF THE POLISH LEAGUE OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>June 6, 1895.</p>
   <p>The undersigned most kindly begs the agencies and members of the Polish League of America to send their dues for the Polish National Fund of the League. As is well known, one of the assessments which every member is obliged to pay is the payment of one penny per month, or twelve cents per year, toward the Polish National Fund. Because a majority of the members have paid their assessments in advance, that is from May 1, 1894, to May 1, 1895, or from June 1, 1894, to June 1, 1895, the time has come to start payment for the next fiscal year. Naturally, this does not apply to those who joined recently, since their dues were paid in advance--it applies only to those who are paid up until June 1, 1895, or some period before then.</p>
   <p>The secretaries of the agencies are requested to start the collection of these <pb facs="5423968_8_1521.jpg" n="2"/>contributions and to send the same to the secretary of the League. All these members who have made payments directly to me are requested to do so again or else pay the secretary of the agency in which they have enrolled.</p>
   <p>In view of the fact that this assessment is so small and the members of the Polish League so many, and since the money of the Polish National Fund cannot be used for correspondence, it is impossible for me to write to every member whose assessment is in arrears; that is why this reminder is directed to the secretaries of the agencies and the members of the Polish League through the means of the Polish press.</p>
   <p>I ask that all Polish papers kindly reprint this notice.</p>
   <p>Stanislaus Szwajkart, secretary of the Polish League</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
