<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-21">Dec. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Demoralization of the Young</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-21">Dec. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">DEMORALIZATION OF THE YOUNG</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"We are a nation producing thieves, murderers, and criminals." These are the words hurled by a certain Henry Hansen, of the Soldiers Home in Kansas, at his own American nation.</p>
   <p>By means of pamphlets sent out by the hundred thousands--to newspapers, pastors, city, state, and county officials, representatives, senators, and many other important personages--Hansen is trying to prove that this nation produces criminals of the worst order and does nothing to improve conditions in spite of seeing evil and scandal everywhere.</p>
   <p>The accuser bases his charge on the fact that schoolbooks, instead of protecting the children from evil, pointing to it as a bad example, encourage them <pb facs="5423968_8_0174.jpg" n="2"/>to it with immoral stories.</p>
   <p>In the cities, saloons are open day and night, where bacchanalian orgies demoralize young people. As if the saloons were not enough, gambling places, dance halls, and houses of prostitution are found in residential districts, so that street corners are dotted with gangs of drunken adolescents who swear and accost everyone, while the policemen quietly stroll about, doing nothing to scatter this rabble to the four winds. Those arrested for grave offenses are not punished by the courts; they are set free so that they can go on misbehaving worse than ever.</p>
   <p>Besides these dens of iniquity in the larger cities, we have the nickel shows, in which disgusting and demoralizing pictures are shown, to say nothing of the shameless songs and dialogues that issue from the stage. Posters of half-naked women and all sorts of pictures that provoke indignation and insult one's moral sense are posted on fences, billboards, and walls. Mothers allow their daughters to wear idiotic clothes, in which they appear half-naked, and let them go out alone to stay out until late hours of the night in the company <pb facs="5423968_8_0175.jpg" n="3"/>of foul and licentious hoodlums.</p>
   <p>In the bookstores, again, every adolescent, every young girl can buy repulsive and demoralizing stories which stifle and poison their spirit.</p>
   <p>Such and similar conditions are causes of scandal. The young people brought up in such an inferno, in such an atmosphere of moral depravity, grow up into bad people, depraved to their very marrow, finally developing into bandits and criminals of the lowest order.</p>
   <p>The words of Mr. Hansen contain a great deal of truth, because actually more is done here to encourage young people to evil and depravity than to elevate them morally. Why, even those four young Poles who are to be hanged tomorrow for murder would never have developed into criminals had they been brought up in a different environment and under different living conditions. They were depraved by the streets and bad environment--by the negligence of the law, which allows hoodlums to be at large at all hours of the night <pb facs="5423968_8_0176.jpg" n="4"/>and do mischief, until, in the end, they commit crimes. If these adolescents had been brought up in Poland in accordance with our virtues and with the severe rules of Polish culture, they would have grown up into useful members of society instead of criminals.</p>
   <p>American chauvinists who complain about immigration try to stop its flow under the pretext that most of the criminals are found among the immigrants. What they do fail to see is that in their own country, the greatest [number of] criminals are found. The immigrants here contribute a very small percentage of actual criminals, and this small percentage is the result of bad conditions and lack of order. A young man brought up in Europe rarely descends to a life of crime, as do those who are born and bred here, who are demoralized at every step by scandalizing sights, by a demoralizing press, and by short stories; who behave on the streets like wild men, without any restraint, going astray and becoming criminals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
