<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol.17. No.247.
<date when="1906-10-26">October 26, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Will the Poles be Denationalized in America</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol.17. No.247.
<date when="1906-10-26">October 26, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Will the Poles be Denationalized in America</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have a few Polish-American newspapers, which take the place of "screech owls", and that continually "resound a death knell", about the Poles in America who will shortly be denationalized. There are statements that the Poles in America stand today at their highest point of development, so then, in a short time they must begin to slowly but surely denationalize in agony and, finally, in debt.</p>
   <p>One of these newspapers predicts that twenty-five years will be sufficient for the Poles in America to completely become Americanized, and others allow us with "grace" a half century which is fifty years. A certain number of Polish-American newspapers have pronounced a death sentence for the Poles over here. Is this, without any stipulation, in reality so bad with us as certain periodical "screech owls" howl, that are hatched on the Polish-American plain? We judge, that it is not so bad with us, and some American statisticians share this conviction with us. The Washington statistician, George Slocum, in a pamphlet recently edited by himself, threatened the Americans with a "Slav danger", and predicted, that at the latest in one hundred years, they will receive a monopoly and will be the ruling nationality.</p>
   <p>Another statistician, William Stevenson, agreeing with the conclusion of his <pb facs="5423968_8_0587.jpg" n="2"/>predecessor, decides that we do not need a hundred years for this, because fifty years will be sufficient for Slavs in the United States to outnumber all others, and take a ruling position. Both statisticians base their conclusions on the large influx of Slav immigrants from Europe, and the natural increase of Slavs in America. There is no other nationality in the United States which is multiplying itself so vigorously and rapidly as the Slavs. Because of the fact that Poles, living in the United States, are the most numerous amongst the Slavs, therefore to them belongs a future.</p>
   <p>Neither Slocum nor Stevenson is our friend, so in publishing their pamphlets they wish to incline the lawmakers of the United States to enact such laws as would hinder Slav coming to settle in this country.</p>
   <p>This all depends on the Slavs themselves, primarily, from the Poles who exceed by three times the number of all other Slavs living in the United States. Poles therefore are the ones to decide, today, about the future of all other Slavs in the United States.</p>
   <p>Now we are confronted with the question: Will the Poles denationalize themselves? And whether they will denationalize in a short time? There is no doubt, that <pb facs="5423968_8_0588.jpg" n="3"/>thousands and, in fact, hundred of thousands of Poles will denationalize but all of the Poles in America will not be denationalized and if they do became denationalized it will take ages. If the immigrant from Europe will strengthen the Poles in America, and by this make a natural growth as great as at the present time, there will not be any need for talk about the Poles denationalizing themselves.</p>
   <p>If we should take into consideration, the present development of the Poles in America, we could only congratulate ourselves on a most promising future. There never was an instance where any kind of nationality in America has developed and multiplied, so quickly as the Polish nationality.</p>
   <p>From the beginning of the present year, we have taken the trouble to notate relative information about the organizing of new parishes, the consecration of newly built churches, and schools, and about the Polish priests either newly ordained or just arriving from Europe. Our notations are not, however, exact, because they depend only on information gathered from newspapers, or from private correspondence.</p>
   <p>But even these inaccurate notations convince us as to the huge growth and development of the Poles in America. Here is definite data: Ten months have not elapsed since the beginning of the year and already there are established sixty-seven new <pb facs="5423968_8_0589.jpg" n="4"/>Polish parishes and practically the same number of schools. This year, already, we have taken on a hundred and nine newly ordained Polish priests; these coming from the old country. In thirty-seven Polish parishes, small churches were changed into magnificent stone edifices, and the construction of some of them cost between $100,000 to $150,000. At the same time there were built a few convents, where nuns will educate themselves to be teachers in parochial Polish schools. Counting everything as conservatively as possible we can say, with certainty, that within these ten months the Poles in America have donated to the building of churches, schools, and Polish benevolent institutions, at least $3,000,000. In this time, there have come from the old country at least 90,000. Poles and our natural growth has almost doubled itself. Shall this be a sign of life? Or of death as predicted by the "screech-owls"?</p>
   <p>He who so lives, the way we are beginning to live, has indeed a very long life. Why are they continually threatening us with denationalization, when this question: "To be, or not to be", depends only upon ourselves. Just as the individual man is the "master" of his own future and good fortune, the "masters" are comprised of the entire society and nationalities. Why should we concern ourselves on how we should perish, when it is better to deliberate on how we should live. And having all these stipulations to conform with, and not being able to live forever, let us live in our own future generation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
