<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-03-25">Mar. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Capital Punishment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0184</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0184.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-03-25">Mar. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CAPITAL PUNISHMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It seems strange that highly civilized countries, such as France, England, Germany, and the United States, punish criminals with the death penalty when seemingly less civilized Italy and Japan,and even backward Russia, have abolished it; the only exception to this rule is made in Japan, when an attempt is made either upon the life of a royal person or a threat against the form of government.</p>
   <p>However, not every state in the United States, uses hanging or the electric chair as its means for capital punishment; it is, nevertheless,inflicted by those States which boast of their superior culture. It appears that the more civilized people have a greater craving for blood in times of peace, than do those who are less civilized. The proof of this appears in the fact that in highly civilized countries, criminals are dispatched to the next world by hanging, firing squads or electrocution.</p>
   <p>It is not our purpose to defend criminals who commit murders, rapes, robberies, <pb facs="5423968_8_0185.jpg" n="2"/>and other abominable deeds, for they are not human beings, but beasts. Punishing by death, however, is very shocking, terrible, and often dangerous. It happens sometimes that an innocent man is arrested for an offense which he did not commit. Frequently it is very easy to find witnesses who will testify against such a man, especially policemen, detectives, or his enemies, who will testify under oath that he committed the crime. Policemen and detectives like to show their zeal in such cases and, furthermore, they do not care to devote any more of their time to looking for the right man. False witnesses revenge themselves on the accused person by testifying falsely, and the crime is confirmed.</p>
   <p>The prosecuting attorney, in addressing the jury, describes the horrible crime very forcibly, depicting the guilt of the unfortunate man in many details, and the jury, convinced that they have before them a real criminal, find him guilty and the judge condemns him to death. Appeals and protestations of the innocent man are of no avail, for the judge and the prosecuting attorney will say, "We know birds of your feather very well."</p>
   <p>Occasionally, and after a considerable length of time, the real criminal is <pb facs="5423968_8_0186.jpg" n="3"/>discovered; the courts are convinced that a terrible mistake has been made; but the life of the innocent victim cannot be restored; neither can the harm done to his family be repaired. In many cases, however, the actual criminal is never discovered, and the family of the executed man is disgraced forever. God's judgment is infallible, but human judgment is not only faulty, but some times unpardonable. It is better to imprison a hundred criminals on some uninhabited island than to execute one innocent person. Capital punishment should, in consideration of these facts, not be used.</p>
   <p>Statistical records prove that the death penalty does not prevent or reduce crime; since the number of crimes in those countries where capital punishment is used, is no smaller than in those where crime is punishable by life imprisonment. More persons are killed each year in Chicago than in all Italy or Japan, where capital punishment is not practiced. The degenerate criminal has no qualms about the harm his crime will cause, for he is determined to follow his own course of activities. Dozens of criminals were hanged in Chicago, but the crimes are still being committed as heretofore. Many criminals prefer death to hard labor in prison. To such criminals a prison term is a <pb facs="5423968_8_0187.jpg" n="4"/>hundred times worse than death, because, in addition to the hard labor imposed on him he suffers a guilty conscience, from which only death can free him.</p>
   <p>The mere thought of having in our midst, individuals who will take a human life to commit robbery, is terrifying, but, it is far worse to compel an honest man to take the life of a man so that the law, made by fallible man be filled; and to inflict on him thereby, the guilty conscience of whether or not he took the life of an innocent man.</p>
   <p>Criminals should be punished for their evil deeds, but other methods than staining our hands with their blood should be used. If we can keep wild beasts in cages, we can also keep dangerous criminals in safe places without taking their lives. Civilized nations should not crave the blood of even dangerous criminals, as this measure does not promote civilization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
