<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-29">May 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Participate in Demonstrations</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 3 (a)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-29">May 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LET US PARTICIPATE IN DEMONSTRATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Decoration Day, a great many solemn parades and demonstrations of loyalty to this country, its government, and its social system will be held in Chicago, and probably in other cities. If these manifestations have been on a very high plane in previous years, this year's should greatly surpass them. After all, we shall be decorating the graves of heroes who died long ago in the struggle for this country's freedom, of those who gave their lives for the rights of man in the Civil War, and finally, of those who died in other wars that were waged by the United States in defense of its rights; they died in the same cause for which the United States entered the present war, and for which it is preparing for a decisive struggle, with all its power.</p>
   <p>In times past, the Poles always have manifested their loyalty, on every possible occasion, to this powerful Republic that has been a haven to us, that <pb facs="5423968_8_0475.jpg" n="2"/>has taken us to its heart--the more so because we are not only linked by many mutual virtues and a mutual love of freedom, but because,as exiles, we came here not with the purpose of hatching plots and aiding our homeland in a criminal way, but came as exiles who desired to escape the persecution and tyranny to which they were subjected by the conquerors of their native land.</p>
   <p>If, however, we ever had an opportunity of demonstrating our unlimited loyalty, it is today, at a time when this country demands loyalty of us, finding itself in the difficult position of being at war with the greatest enemy not only of ourselves, but of the world, of freedom and humanity. No one can doubt our loyalty even for a moment. We would not need to demonstrate that which we know to be true, but since all other nationalist groups want to manifest their loyalty, we must, too. If we are to manifest anything, let us do so in a way that will become us as Poles, and in keeping with our culture.</p>
   <p>We take this occasion to address ourselves to all the Poles in Chicago and vicinity where, on Decoration Day, great loyalty manifestations will be held <pb facs="5423968_8_0476.jpg" n="3"/>by all nationalist groups that people this great metropolis of ours. Polonia has decided to participate in tomorrow's demonstration.....</p>
   <p>Let it be on the conscience of every Pole that the Polish division in the parade look Polish. Let every participant in the parade take to heart the instructions of the marshal, and remember that a parade requires military obedience and discipline. Let every one be responsible for his conduct, not to the marshal but to himself, so that our appearance will be creditable and will not bring us shame.</p>
   <p>We ought to make an imposing spectacle, both in numbers and type of participants; we have given proof of our loyalty more than once, and we shall do it again tomorrow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
