<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1897-09-16">Sept. 16, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">To My Brothers of the Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1897-09-16">Sept. 16, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">TO MY BROTHERS OF THE ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 12th Polish parliment conferred upon me another presidential administration with the central government. Upon a new and very burdensome and responsible, or answerable as you may have it, position, I shall avow those same principles and the same ideas that I have for the past four years done as an editor of our organ. I shall, above all, stand by and respect the resolutions of the parliment.</p>
   <p>In public affairs I know of no acquaintances, no friends, or enemies. Everyone can find me to be a sincere friend. I shall never pause or hesitate to aid the Polish laborers in their strife, of whom the Alliance on the most part consists.</p>
   <p>We all, my companions in office and our sincere and loved censor, shall keep vigil upon you in general. With the fundamental aid and security of the Alliance, we shall strive for harmony and intrinsic order.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1444.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I also point out that I shall bring about various new methods in lowering our expenditure and do everything in my power to expand and enlarge the Alliance.</p>
   <p>Not for a moment will I forget about the Alliance's political mission. It is our duty to guard all Polish affairs against all America. What greater result could we achieve than joining with those who strive for the public cause as a united public? We can be assured of the freedom of our nation.</p>
   <p>And so, aid your government in its work, brothers of the Alliance. Strive for the recognition of the Poles. Lend a helping hand to anyone who cares to work for the nation.</p>
   <p>Love and wishes.</p>
   <p>F. H. Jablonski,</p>
   <p>President Z. N. P. Central Gov't.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
