<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-12">Feb. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[Polish] Citizens' Committee Holds Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0940</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0940.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-12">Feb. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[POLISH] CITIZENS' COMMITTEE HOLDS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday evening a plenary meeting of the [Polish] Citizens' Committee, organized to help recruit soldiers in Chicago and vicinity for the Polish Army in France, was held at the Polish Women's Alliance Hall on Ashland Avenue. A great many persons were present who hitherto have shown little or no interest in the Polish Army or in the Polish cause. It could be noticed immediately that an unusual air pervaded the hall. In addition to these persons, there were also present numerous community and recruiting sub-center representatives and many priests from Chicago and out-of-town parishes. Among the priests present, we noticed Reverend [W.] Wojtalewicz of South Chicago; Reverend Pyterek of St. Helen's Parish; Reverend Olszewski of Joliet; Reverend [L.] Grudzinski of St. John of God Parish [Town of Lake]; Reverend Zwierzchowski of Holy Innocents' Parish; Reverend Kowalewski of South Chicago; and Reverend Mazur of Bridgeport. Among the out-of-town representatives were Mr. Sambor of Harbor, Indiana; Mr. Wasilewski of Gary; Mr. Zielinski of Joliet; Messrs. Bloch, Sikorski <pb facs="5423968_8_0941.jpg" n="2"/>and Dudek of South Chicago; Messrs. Strzelecki and Bzdek of Kensington; Mr. Wroblewski of Chicago Heights, and many others whose names we failed to note.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by John Wedda, treasurer of the Citizens' Committee, who explained that the Committee's president, [Casimir] Zychlinski, had gone to New York to meet the Polish military delegation which arrives from France today. He explained also that the Committee's secretary, John J. Chrzanowski is ill, and that he (Wedda) felt it his duty to open the meeting, and to call upon the gathering to elect a chairman. B. Kowalewski of Town of Lake was chosen chairman and W. Brzozowski secretary.</p>
   <p>The secretary read the minutes of the last meeting, held at the Polish National Alliance Building on January 24. The minutes were accepted with a small change. The first treasurer of the Committee, Wedda, then made his report. He read first the treasury report up to January 24, that is, the last meeting, and followed with the report for the period from January 24 to date, which read as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0942.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Income</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>National manifestations</cell>
     <cell>nothing</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Collections</cell>
     <cell>$36.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Donations</cell>
     <cell>388.89</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Disbursements</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Administrative expenses</cell>
     <cell>$ 1.96</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Recruiting expenses</cell>
     <cell>184.44</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Manifestations</cell>
     <cell>30.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>It was decided on the floor that this report must be published in all of the <pb facs="5423968_8_0943.jpg" n="4"/>Polish newspapers. Following the report, Treasurer Wedda opened the question of reorganizing the Committee in accordance with the regulations received from the Military Commission. He said that in view of the fact that the convention of representatives of all the citizens' committees [in the United States] will open in Cleveland on Friday, attended also by the special delegation from Europe, and since important matters are to be discussed at this convention, it is better to postpone reorganization of the committee until after the convention is over. A motion for postponement was carried.</p>
   <p>The next business before the meeting was that of choosing delegates to the convention in Cleveland. A lively and protracted debate arose on this question. Among those who spoke were Reverends Wojtalewicz and Grudzinski, M. J. Perlowski, Mrs. [M.] Milewski, Alderman [S.] Kunz, Mrs. [A.] Neuman, Dr. Balcerzak, Dr. Pietrzykowski, and many others. Treasurer Wedda made a motion that the executive committee choose its own representatives and that each community committee and sub-center also choose its own delegates. Many voices were raised against this motion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0944.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>After a prolonged discussion, the motion was defeated. Szymanski then made a motion that the gathering elect three delegates to the convention in Cleveland. The motion was carried.</p>
   <p>As a result of the voting, the delegates to the convention will be Reverend Wojtalewicz, John Wedda, and Mrs. Milewski.</p>
   <p>Wrzesinski made a motion that the delegates be paid five dollars per day to cover railroad fare and their expenses in Cleveland. The motion was carried.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, the secretary read a proposal made to Recruiting Center II by Charles Wachtel, who offered, if the costs were covered, to make theatrical appearances with the St. John Cantius Parish Choir, with the aid of Mr. n, in all of the parishes in Chicago. These appearances would be made for the benefit of the Polish Army. The matter was referred to a committee. With this, the chairman adjourned the meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
