<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-08-11">Aug. 11, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Fair Judgment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-08-11">Aug. 11, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">FAIR JUDGMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A certain German tailor who lived in New York City almost twenty years and accumulated a small fortune decided to return to his native land that he might enjoy the fruits of his labor and live there comfortably for the remainder of his life.</p>
   <p>He made thorough preparations, packed his belongings, and purchased his passage. Before departing, however, it occurred to him that it might be advisable for him to return to Germany as an American citizen, and since during his stay in America he had not been impressed with the idea of becoming a citizen, he had only his first papers lying somewhere. Therefore, he decided to rectify his negligence at the last moment. Perhaps it occurred to him that he would be safer in Germany as a citizen of the United States. Consequently he took his first papers and went to the proper office for his second, or naturalization papers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0684.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There he was asked the usual questions and the surprised clerk asked him why he had not tried to get his naturalization papers and had neglected his duties as a citizen for so many years. The tailor made a most naive answer; he said that he did not care much about the citizenship, but now he wanted to return to his fatherland and there he would like to pose as an American citizen. Then the clerk told him under such circumstances he could not give him his naturalization papers and dismissed him.</p>
   <p>The clerk is right. Only a person who is interested in the American government, considers it good and desires to live according to its laws should have the right to be an American citizen. Whoever fails to understand this is not worthy to be a United States citizen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
