<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-17">Feb. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Alliance of Polish Falcons</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1026</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1026.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-17">Feb. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ALLIANCE OF POLISH FALCONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last issue of Sokol Polski (the Polish Falcon), official organ of the Alliance of Polish Falcons in America, we read the following appeal addressed to the Falcon members:</p>
   <p>"Due to the possibility of the outbreak of hostilities between the United States and Germany, we wish to call the attention of the departments, circuits, nests and individual members to the fact that no decisions or assertions should be made without the knowledge of the Alliance.</p>
   <p>"Our action at such a difficult and critical time must be united and harmonious in order that our homeland may gain the greatest benefit from it.</p>
   <p>"Let us remember that individually we cannot accomplish much of consequence, <pb facs="5423968_8_1027.jpg" n="2"/>that only a harmonious and united mass can render valuable service to our adopted country here as well as our native land, Poland.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, do not be impatient and do not volunteer individually at recruiting offices, but wait for our united action.</p>
   <p>No individual Pole should namelessly fight our homeland's enemies, but we, as one united, indivisible mass, should set out together to fight them. If we are to show our gratitude, love, and affection for our adopted country, the United States, which hospitably received us wanderers and gathered us under its wing, then let us do it in such a way that all America will know about it and will then be convinced that the Poles represent a valuable asset, which up to the present has been decidedly underrated."</p>
   <p>This is a just and rational appeal, and the Falcons should act in accordance with it. It indicates that in this matter the directors of the Alliance of <pb facs="5423968_8_1028.jpg" n="3"/>Polish Falcons are thinking along the line which the gravity of the moment and the honor of the Falcons demand.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
