<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-11-14">Nov. 14, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Polish League in the United States, Polish National Fund in Rapperschwil, and Jerzmanowski</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-11-14">Nov. 14, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH LEAGUE IN THE UNITED STATES, POLISH NATIONAL FUND IN RAPPERSCHWIL, AND JERZMANOWSKI</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the controversy between the Polish League in the United States and Mr. J. Jerzmanowski, its former president, the most important question is: Who is to blame?</p>
   <p>This is a delicate question because it is personal. In answering it,it is not our desire to pass judgment on anyone; we only desire to explain that neither the Polish League nor its administration is guilty, and that this institution is not and can not be responsible for the outcome of the controversy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jerzmanowski must have been aware of the constitution when he accepted the presidency, for he had a copy of its outline, which had been prepared and printed before the massmeeting, and which contained all the points Mr. <pb facs="5423968_8_1561.jpg" n="2"/>Jerzmanowski wanted to change at the meeting held by the Board of Directors six months after. Practically nothing was added to these points, as only minor changes were made in the constitution. By accepting the presidency of the League unconditionally, Mr. Jerzmanowski accepted its platform also, as adopted at the massmeeting. He must have known that this Fund [Rappersochwil's] existed in America, because he himself had previously contributed toward it, and because it had been widely publicized in our newspapers, to say nothing of the fact that it is written very plainly in the constitution. It seems that at that time, that is, last May, he was of the opinion that, besides the Rapperschwil Fund, there was another fund here in America. This is probable, inasmuch as the Allied Poles in New York and Mr. Jerzmanowski control an eight-thousand-dollar Polish-American fund, which up to now has not been transferred to the Rapperschwil Fund.</p>
   <p>Therefore, sometime between May and October, not the administration of the League, but Mr. Jerzmanowski changed his mind on the matter.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1562.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We will omit the motives of this change, as they undoubtedly are very noble, but, nevertheless, facts are facts. When Mr. Jerzmanowski came to Chicago in October to participate in the meeting of the Central Board of Directors of the League, he demanded, impelled by his changed opinion, immediate revision of certain articles of the constitution which he considered improper and threatened to resign if these changes were not made. Could the administration of the League yield to his demands? No. This is in accordance with the simple rules of logic and common sense. The legislative power of the League is vested in the convention, which makes and abolishes its by-laws. The administration of the League is an executive body whose function is to see that the bylaws are carried out. Abolishing any bylaws incorporated in the constitution of the League would be simply unpardonable licentiousness on the part of the administration.</p>
   <p>The officers of the League are in the right because they have not violated any bylaws of the constitution in their refusal to yield to Mr. Jerzmanowski's demand; on the contrary, they would have committed a wrong had they yielded <pb facs="5423968_8_1563.jpg" n="4"/>to him. But this is not all.</p>
   <p>At the meeting in question, where these views were expressed, it was shown that despite the differences of opinion between the president of the League and the other members of its Board of Directors, a modus vivendi was reached for the good of the cause. As Mr. Jerzmanowski declared that he could not work for the good of the League unless changes in the constitution were made, he was asked to submit these changes in writing, that they might be presented at the next convention for deliberation. This was a concession on the part of the administration, made in the name and for the good of the cause. Mr. Jerzmanowski agreed to this with noble readiness, and the controversy was settled, as the official report proves.</p>
   <p>After making such concession, can it be said that the administration of the League was guilty of the charge made by "an anonymous communication" in Zgoda to the effect that "this matter had been decided at the point of the sword"? Any honest person will admit that it was not. Despite the assertion made by <pb facs="5423968_8_1564.jpg" n="5"/>the author of the "communication," the administration of the League did not precipitate a crisis; on the contrary, it avoided it, for it did not wish to deprive itself of its "thinking and noble head." This was in October. Then came the first days of November. The administration of the League had not changed its attitude toward its president and there had been no official contact between them. Then suddenly came the resignation of the head of the League, with the explanation that it was caused by circumstances beyond his control.</p>
   <p>Evidently, there must have been some change of attitude sometime between October and November. What was this change? Even the author of the "communication" from New York City seems not to understand it, for he keeps mum about it; and if he doesn't know what the change is all about how could we expect the administration of the League to understand it?</p>
   <p>At any rate, the administration of the League is not responsible for this changed attitude and it cannot be blamed for the outcome of this controversy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1565.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Our object has been to elucidate this point. We repeat, we are not looking for guilty persons. Perhaps other complications are responsible. The fact, however, is that the administration of the League acted sensibly, with dignity, and in the interest of the public.</p>
   <p>This fact is established for the purpose of silencing those declared enemies of the League who would like to see it fall, and those false friends who, like the author of the "communication" in Zgoda, annoy the League with hints and insinuations.</p>
   <p>So much for the first question as to who should bear the blame. But there is another question: Will this controversy harm the League? And also, what will be the future of the League?</p>
   <p>That the controversy in question can not harm the League is proved by the controversy itself, which showed that the administration abides faithfully by the bylaws.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1566.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>As to the future of the League, we should not worry about it. What was good in May is good today too. Big national issues remain unchanged. That there is no leader willing to realize our national aspirations is sad, but the aspirations still stand. History is not made by an individual but by the people. The aims of the League are either noble and accomplishable or they are not. In the first case, they will be achieved even without Mr. Jerzmanowksi; in the second, even one hundred men of his type would accomplish nothing.</p>
   <p>It is understood that nothing is perfect in the beginning, and the constitution of the Polish League is no exception. If there are faults and imperfections in it, time will disclose them and the public will make the necessary corrections. If its guiding star is the good of the people and Poland, the Polish League will not perish; on the contrary, it will overcome all obstacles in its way to elevate and unite the people. In other words, it will accomplish its purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
