<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-30">June 30, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Important Notice to Military Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1445</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1445.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-30">June 30, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT NOTICE TO MILITARY SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the many new laws passed by the State legislature is a statute that pertains to all the military societies of Illinois. Certain paragraphs will have to be considered by the Polish military organizations.</p>
   <p>In the future the military societies will not be permitted to carry arms or to held drills or conduct any kind of exercise with them. Only the use of a broadsword will be permitted. No uniforms will be allowed to be worn similar to those of the Army, especially to the regalia of an officer. This will deal a death-blow to many societies, and the remainder will have to reorganize and institute changes. As a "military society" no group will be permitted to exist.</p>
   <p>The paragraphs of the new law dealing with private military societies read as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1446.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"It will not be within the law in this State to belong to any society, except as a volunteer in the regular State militia, United States Army, divisions of the Grand Army of the Republic, or Sons of Veterans, that is of a military nature, or to drill or parade with arms. A reservation is made for students who attend military academies or similar institutions in which training in military tactics is part of the curriculum, provided that they get permission from the Governor to drill and to parade in public with arms under the command of their military instructors. A reservation is also made with the understanding that this order may not be interpreted as forbidding the wearing of a broadsword by members of benevolent organizations.</p>
   <p>"All those guilty of breaking this law by wearing uniforms and arms or parading with them will be fined not more than ton dollars or sentenced to no more than six months in prison, or both.</p>
   <p>"Every person who is not a member of the State militia, the United States <pb facs="5423968_8_1447.jpg" n="3"/>Army, the Grand Army of the Republic, the Sons of Veterans, or the United States Navy, and who wears the uniform or the regalia of an officer used by the nation's defense units will be subject to arrest and a fine of one hundred dollars."</p>
   <p>This law was signed by the Governor and will go into effect July 1, 1887. Our military societies should consider this new law carefully in order that they may not be subject to a fine. According to the first paragraph all these groups will virtually have to disband and cease to exist as military societies. Perhaps some method will be found to reorganize them so that they may continue to exist within the law.</p>
   <p>Such large and excellent organizations as the Chicago Zouaves, the Aurora Zouaves, the clan-na-Gael Guards, etc., will undoubtedly be compelled to disband, and the same will be true of the youths' military groups.</p>
   <p>At the same time it has been stipulated that schools will be permitted to <pb facs="5423968_8_1448.jpg" n="4"/>to include military training in their curricula, and the students will be permitted to drill and parade with arms provided that the schools get written permission from the Governor.</p>
   <p>This law will even affect police officers to this extent, that they will not be allowed to wear badges that are similar to those of the United States Army.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
