<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-07-09">July 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">From the Convention of the Polish National Council</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(A censure.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-07-09">July 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE CONVENTION OF THE POLISH NATIONAL COUNCIL</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(A censure.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note. 1. The Polish National Council (P. N. C.) in Chicago, Polska Rada Narodowa, is an affiliation with the similarly named organization in Poland, founded for the purpose of assisting Poland in her struggle for political independence. The local Polish National Council is sponsored by Dziennik Chicagoski (Chicago Polish Daily News), rival and competitor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy (Polish Alliance Daily), which for different national and political reasons is opposed to the Polish National Council; hence its censuring and sarcastic article that follows.</p>
   <p>2. The title of that article in Dziennik Zwiazkowy does not include the word "Polish" but only the words "National Council" - Rada Narodowa - an abridged name. The word "Polish," officially included in the English title of that organization, is added by the translator to the shortened Polish form of that name. And all these supplements are inserted by the translator in order that the American readers of the following article might perchance not be misled to think that the discussed National Council means some American organization.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1223.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Yesterday's meeting of the so-called Polish National Council has been marked with two troubles: first, from where to get the money needed for the upkeep of the bureaus of the P. N. C., and, second, how to impress the world with the quantity and the quality of regulations and decisions which would become the pointers to the further work of that curious association, called the National Council.</p>
   <p>The first trouble has been quite summarily settled by imposing a one cent tax per month on each member of all Polish organizations that are under the influence of the clergy, and $15. per year on the local committees. Before the particular organizations and committees will approve at their meetings and assemblies the imposed taxes, and until the money from such taxation will start to flow into the treasury of the National Council, the funds of that association will consist of the quarterly donations, contributed by the members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>The special committees have proposed so many regulations and projects that no one of those present at the convention could have grasped the contents of all of them, and it would require an outlay of a tremendous sum of money to put into practice even one half of the projects.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1224.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The delegates resolved that until the next convention, to be held in 1915, the seat of the National Council shall be in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The convention originated four local departments, namely that of information, of press, of scouting, and of citizenship schools. At the head of each department there will stand one of the four vice-presidents, elected by the convention.</p>
   <p>After the reading of the reports of particular commissions, the following officers for the organization were elected: Mr. P. Ligman, president; S. Szwajkart, vice-president; P. Rostenkowski; Medwecki; Reverend F. Landon, and Kolanowski, vice-presidents and chairmen to head the four departments; S. Osada, general secretary; W. Folmer, treasurer; Mrs. P. Zdanowski, Mrs. M. Osuch, and Reverend Wojtalewicz, directors; Bishop Rhode, Archbishop Weber and Bishop Kozlowski, chaplains and honorary presidents.</p>
   <p>After the administering of the oath of allegiance to the newly elected officers and after prayer, which was regularly said also before each session, the convention was adjourned at about midnight.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1225.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We leave it for a later date to talk over further details pertaining to the accomplishments of the convention, and to finish the thrashing of that empty and barren straw, in the hope that perchance we might discover at least one sound kernel therein.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
