<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-06">Feb. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Meeting of the Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-06">Feb. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. K. Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance, called the meeting to order at 2:25 P.M. He devoted a few words to the memory of Anthony Mallek, "one of the pioneers of the Polish emigres, father of Polish song in America, former secretary general of the Polish National Alliance, and a member for many years of this organization, an indefatigable worker in the nationalistic field". He asked those present to pay homage to the memory of Anthony Mallek by rising.</p>
   <p>The secretary general read a resolution [relative to Mallek's funeral,] and the board of directors accepted by rising. The resolution will be published in the papers.</p>
   <p>A motion was passed to the effect that the entire Central Board of Directors will take part in [Mallek's] funeral. The censor of the Polish National Alliance is sending his representative. The body of the deceased, if his <pb facs="5423968_8_1041.jpg" n="2"/>family permits, will rest for a while in the meeting room of the Polish National Alliance building. The administrative board will take care of this.</p>
   <p>In view of the fact that the United States has severed diplomatic relations with Germany, the Central Board of Directors decided to send President Wilson a special telegram, which the secretary general read. This telegram was unanimously accepted, and it was decided to send it at once.</p>
   <p>Further business of the organization was discussed in accordance with the program and rules of the Central Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Mr. K. B. Czarnecki, vice-president, will represent the Polish National Alliance at the Fraternal Congress in Madison, Wisconsin, on February 8.</p>
   <p>The president of the Polish National Alliance received a reply (stereotyped) from the President of the United States to the telegram sent by the Central Board of Directors on his address of January 22 to the Senate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1042.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Five thousand dollars was assigned from the relief fund for the relief of thousands of Poles interned at Irkutsk in Siberia, who are suffering terrible poverty. The clothing committee of the Women's Auxiliary has already sent clothing there valued at more than $3,000. The money will be sent through the American embassy at Petrograd, either together with the contributions of other organizations represented by the Central Polish Relief Committee, or separately.</p>
   <p>The committee on applications recommends the acceptance of 2,049 new members and eight societies as groups of the Polish National Alliance. The last group in order has been given number 1975.</p>
   <p>The insurance committee has recommended the payment of sixty-nine death benefit policies amounting to $45,300.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
