<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-07-21">July 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[Mob Violence Is Condemned]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-07-21">July 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">[MOB VIOLENCE IS CONDEMNED]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In America, a free, civilized, and cultured country, there occasionally erupt, like a volcano, concealed brutality and savagery. Brutality in time of war can be explained, but lynching, the vengeance of offended justice in the hands of people of violent disposition, is abhorent. How can we explain the incident which occurred in Vols, a small village in Illinois, where women neighbors tortured another woman, Mrs. Richardson, living in the same town, in a manner that even the lowest and most savage Africans would be ashamed of?</p>
   <p>The life of this woman might have been immoral, yet nobody is entitled to punish her in such a beastly manner as did these "ladies". All masked, they rushed to the home of the victim, demolished her small grocery store and, in the presence of her invalid husband, dragged her by the hair into the street, beating her mercilessly, and throwing her after some time <pb facs="5423968_8_0063.jpg" n="2"/>into a puddle of mud. Women in their hysterical madness are more brutal than the most bloodthirsty beasts, but this "parade" was witnessed by men, youths, and children without anybody trying to defend, the unhappy woman. This is a very sad example of the degeneracy and savagery of some American women. It is one more evidence of the extremism to which stupid hypocrisy and wrongly understood morality are leading us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
