<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 24,
<date when="1914-06-17">June 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">White Slavery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 24,
<date when="1914-06-17">June 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WHITE SLAVERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago in Chicago there was held an interesting meeting, at which there were raised many important matters.</p>
   <p>A special commission answered to the question, "What are the causes of white slavery?" and in its report we read such details:</p>
   <p>"The vulgar tendency of the new styles in combination with the growing desire to excite lust and indecent entertainment, and chiefly the new dances, are the main causes of the existence and the development of white slavery."</p>
   <p>One of the factors which brings along with it social evil rests in the vulgar tendencies of the present styles.</p>
   <p>Many women today fall into such an extreme in regard to dresses that it turns red with shame even the most shameless man, and places the whole race <pb facs="5423968_8_0168.jpg" n="2"/>of women in America on the pillory of licentious shamelessness.</p>
   <p>The saddest part about this is that even pious women, whose dress should be the mark of modesty, fall likewise into the same mistake.</p>
   <p>So long as Christian women do not become convinced about the ruinous influences of shameless styles, there can be very little hope of bettering moral conditions and the removing of evil.</p>
   <p>The second main factor of the continuous growth of exciting the mind to lust and indecent recreations is the dance.</p>
   <p>Today's dances are not really dances, as they once were.</p>
   <p>Today they represent unlimited nonsense and madness.</p>
   <p>Moving pictures, which are supposedly under control and should moralize, are only spreading corruption, presenting many erratic scenes in such a way that they must spoil the youth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0169.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Present day literature does not know any other theme but the generic problem so that one would imagine that there is nothing else people can be interested in except sexualism and things erotic."</p>
   <p>So much says the report of the commission.</p>
   <p>One must admit the complete justice of this claim and we have to feel sorry that our Polish women, especially the younger generation, are willingly paying tribute to this mad fashion, completing it by painting often beautiful, delicately complexioned faces, which has fatal effects on their complexions, and on the whole has a bad taste, true loathsomeness.</p>
   <p>Remember, young Polish women, that your grandmothers and great grandmothers were known all over the world for their modesty and thriftiness.</p>
   <p>In times past the smart Polish youth sought the modest wife, thrifty, who bakes bread and sours the kraut. He bruised his finger in order to see whether he would quickly find the "cobweb" in the peasant hut or a young miss had to untangle a very much entangled skein of cotton, in order to test her patience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0170.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Times have changed. The above virtues today are only rare, and so rare that very seldom one asks about them, but on that account the marriages today are less fortunate.</p>
   <p>Especially here in America one can often call a marriage a "trial marriage," especially if such a marriage union is deprived of church vows.</p>
   <p>It is true that demoralization is enormous, and many wives often, exceedingly often, forget about their sworn duties. The easy divorce law is the cause.</p>
   <p>A young woman, keenly desirous to make an impression, allows herself easily to be suggested to a man, who knows how to impose her with almost anything. Next comes the breaking of faith, complaints, the court, divorce in the best instant, a new wedding and marriage in court, so that in a short time she can be cast aside by some new husband, and finally suffers complete moral downfall, the street and hospital.</p>
   <p>This the Polish women ought to guard against.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0171.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>They came over here in modest petticoats, bodices and shawls, and now what kind of dresses do you wear.</p>
   <p>At least you Polish women hold on to your modest garb, do not conform to the mad fashions, which will not last long and which place you in the ranks of those who are mentioned in the above quoted report.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
