<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-03-13">Mar. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Resolution Adopted by the Administrations of Fifteen Communes of the Fifteenth Circuit of the Polish National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-03-13">Mar. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE RESOLUTION ADOPTED BY THE ADMINISTRATIONS OF FIFTEEN COMMUNES OF THE FIFTEENTH CIRCUIT OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nearly one fourth of the members of the Polish National Alliance spoke yesterday, March 12, 1915, through the representatives of the fifteen communes of the Fifteenth Circuit of the Polish National Alliance, where Mr. A. Majewski serves in the capacity of commissioner in that organization. The resolution printed in the subsequent paragraphs and adopted by these communes is the best proof of the attitude taken by the members of the Alliance in Chicago and vicinity toward the brawling and dissenting for which the enemies of the Polish National Alliance are responsible. The resolution is as follows:</p>
   <p>"We, the officials of the communes of the Polish National Alliance in Chicago and vicinity, gathered at a special meeting of the communes of <pb facs="5423968_8_1132.jpg" n="2"/>the Fifteenth Circuit of the Polish National Alliance at the Alliance Building, on March 12, 1915, after due and careful consideration of the internal affairs in the Polish National Alliance do hereby adopt the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The purpose of the present struggle, declared against the ideals of the Polish National Alliance by its open and secret enemies, who rally around the "red banner" and the remnants of the former Committee on National Defense, is the bringing about of dissension in the midst of the Polish National Alliance. The sole purpose of these dissenters is to undermine the Alliance's influence and significance among the Polish immigrants and to defame the good name of the organization; and,</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The attacks directed against the highest officials of this Polish National Alliance are secretly intended mortally to wound the whole organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1133.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These fomentors were unsuccessful in their attempt to control the affairs of the Polish National Alliance during the organization's twentieth convention, held at Detroit. It is for this reason that their bitterness and ill will is directed against the present officials, who now benefit from the success of their labor, as a result of the action taken in their behalf by the aforesaid convention; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The Socialists and the red agitatiors of the Committee on National Defense were never interested, and are much less interested today, in the welfare of the Polish National Alliance. Their sole purpose was to gain control of the Alliance and then work for the benefit of their own extremist party. They attempted, under the cover and protection of the ideals developed by the Polish National Alliance, to inculcate their own detrimental doctrines into the members of the Polish National Alliance and thus to kill the real purpose for which the organization was instituted; and, <pb facs="5423968_8_1134.jpg" n="4"/>"Whereas, The present position of the Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance, as well as that of the newspapers of the Alliance and nine tenths of the masses of the Polish National Alliance, relative to matters of great importance now being dealt with in the other hemisphere, matters that greatly interest all Poles, is entirely justifiable and in accord with the will of all the Polish people, with the exception of a handful of political agitators; and,</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Since the honorable position that the Polish National Alliance adopted at the beginning of the present European war, and even before that time, can be ascribed mainly to the highest officials of the Alliance, it is upon these officials that such severe attacks are directed by the opponents of the Alliance; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That a vote of confidence be given to the present Central <pb facs="5423968_8_1135.jpg" n="5"/>Administration of the Polish National Alliance and to its highest officials, for their zealous and sincere work in behalf of the organization. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we, who are congregated at this special meeting, condemn the underhanded and destructive activities of the misled brawlers, who attack officials of the Polish National Alliance, elected by the will of the majority at the twentieth convention of the Alliance, at Detroit. We also condemn all those open and secret enemies of the Polish National Alliance who, by resorting to calumnies and lies, attempt to attain their nefarious goal. At a time so important to the Polish cause, when unity and solidarity is most essential, these dissenters attempt to bring about a rupture in the ranks of the Polish National Alliance. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we implore all our highest officials, chosen by the will <pb facs="5423968_8_1136.jpg" n="6"/>of the twentieth convention, to continue conducting the affairs of the Polish National Alliance, not to be led astray, and to preserve their equanimity in the face of the numerous insults and calumnous articles directed against them by the brawlers and the red fanatics. On the contrary, the officials of the Alliance should proudly forge ahead and proceed in the direction of their intended goal. They should feel that the attacks made by the Socialists are merely an incentive for a more concerted effort to combat the foes of the Polish National Alliance. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we who are here assembled request the Advisory Board of the Polish National Alliance to call a special meeting in the shortest time possible. We also ask the Board to consider carefully all the charges that have been made against the highest officials of the Polish National Alliance, to listen to all the testimony presented by members of the Alliance who make such charges, and, finally, to give a decision which will put an end to all dissension within the organization. This the Board <pb facs="5423968_8_1137.jpg" n="7"/>can do, either by punishing the guilty persons severely, and thus protecting the good name of the innocent, or by removing from office those who are unworthy of the privilege of conducting the affairs of the Polish National Alliance, and by summoning as leaders such people as the members of the Alliance will have faith in.</p>
   <p>"The administrations of the communes of the Fifteenth Circuit of the Polish National Alliance recommend to the commissioner of the Circuit that he not accept the resignation of the censor of the organization, Mr. A. Karabasz.</p>
   <p>"At the same time the administrations recommend the adoption of this resolution by all the individual communes.</p>
   <p>"Joseph Polczynski, president of Commune 41,</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1138.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"S. Lesner, president of Commune Number 2,</p>
   <p>"J. Jablonski, president of Commune Number 55,</p>
   <p>"S. Zielinski, president of Commune Number 80,</p>
   <p>"J. Dydek, president of Commune Number 75,</p>
   <p>"S. J. Dudek, president of Commune Number 23,</p>
   <p>"W. Krzewinski, president of Commune Number 87,</p>
   <p>"S. Kleehammer, president of Commune Number 39,</p>
   <p>"J. P. Szymanski, president of Commune Number 3,</p>
   <p>"A. Jasinski,vice president of Commune Number 79,</p>
   <p>"J. Szyperski, treasurer of Commune Number 101,</p>
   <p>"M. Skupniewski, secretary of Commune Number 34,</p>
   <p>"Michael Such, treasurer of Commune Number 91,</p>
   <p>"A. T. Mazur, secretary of Commune Number 91,</p>
   <p>"T. Wojciechowski, secretary of Commune Number 75,</p>
   <p>"Joseph Rogalski, secretary of Commune Number 101,</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1139.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"Adam Majewski, commissioner of the Fifteenth</p>
   <p>Circuit of the Polish National Alliance and chairman of the special meeting,</p>
   <p>"S. Jakiel, secretary of the special meeting."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
