<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-03">Jan. 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Three Hundred Attend Wilno Society Banquet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0872</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0872.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-03">Jan. 3, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THREE HUNDRED ATTEND WILNO SOCIETY BANQUET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>New Year's day was one of gala festivities for the members and friends of the Wilno Young Men's Society at the Oakley Auditorium. Over three hundred persons participated in the affair, which was held Sunday evening. From the opening of the program to the very close, success prevailed. Many outstanding personages from St. Anne's and St. Adalbert's parish added prestige to the festive evening.</p>
   <p>The success of this affair is largely a result of the experience gathered from several of such annual occasions. This year's affair was planned many months in advance. Many of the new members had contributed a great deal of hard work.</p>
   <p>The popularity of these annual affairs has made possible the ever-increasing number of members. Today, there are over five hundred of them, with a treasury fund of about ten thousand dollars. Their activities in the social and national sphere increase with the membership.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0873.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the doors of the Oakley Auditorium were opened at 7 P.M. Sunday, the places at the gaily decorated tables were quickly occupied by early comers. Soon after 8 o'clock, all reservations were filled. From the standpoint of attendance, the banquet was a success alone. But this was not the only feature.</p>
   <p>The dinner--and what a dinner--was prepared by the well-known Polish epicure, Ignac Lenard. The many tasty courses were devoured with zest.</p>
   <p>After the appetizing meal was finished, the chairman of the banquet, Stephen Mojsiejewicz, called upon the toastmaster. Stephen Tyrakowski, prominent banker and P.R.C.U. (Polish Roman Catholic Union), member from St. Anne's parish, to open the program. The toastmaster gave an interesting and humorous discourse on the many activities of the Wilno Society performed in St. Adalbert's and St. Anne's parishes. He complimented the members who were responsible for a large part of the work. Mr. Tyrakowski, from the very beginning, proved to be a capable toastmaster. His reign throughout the evening was one of admiration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0874.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>and his quips between speeches were masterpieces that will remain long with the audience.</p>
   <p>The first speaker to be called upon was Dr. M. Borzec. He gave a short and snappy talk, and concluded by wishing that no one present would need a doctor during the course of the year. (Dr. Matthew Borzec is a true blooded member of the Wilno Society.)</p>
   <p>Musical numbers by Dylag's orchestra followed. A popular Polish hymn was played. "Tesknota Za Ojczyzna" (Yearning for the Fatherland) was played as a violin trio, with orchestral accompaniment. Misses Josephine Ryzewska, Helen and Ann Jarkowicz were the young artists.</p>
   <p>Miss Wanda Kozarzewska sang selections from the opera, "Halka." Piano accompaniment was played by Miss W. Armatys. The operatic renditions were acclaimed by all.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0875.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When the musical numbers were completed, the president of the society, S. Perchorowicz was called. His speech was based primarily on the activities of the organization. The gist of it being to spur the members to bigger and better work. He was followed by Sigismund Stefanowicz.</p>
   <p>"Clou" sung by Miss Mary Gruszczynska, called the Polish songbird by many, was the musical highlight of the evening. She enraptured the guests with Polish and Russian songs. To climax her glorious entrance, she sang in English. The soft, sweet treatment of her numbers won her thunderous applause. Miss Wanda Swierczek played the piano accompaniment.</p>
   <p>Mr. Tyrakowski concluded the festivities at the table by thanking all for their fine co-operation, and wishing them the season's best.</p>
   <p>This entertainment did not terminate the affair. The orchestra began playing, and many a merry polka and waltz were danced before the festivities came to an end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
