<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 2111,
<date when="1922-09-09">Sept. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Special Correspondence Course on Citizenship</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 2111,
<date when="1922-09-09">Sept. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SPECIAL CORRESPONDENCE COURSE ON CITIZENSHIP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The citizenship schools in Chicago are bringing wonderful results and through them a very large number of Poles received their final citizenship papers. The Poles beyond Chicago have found out about the activities of the local schools and about the results they are bringing. Letters come today to the main headquarters of the citizenship schools from all corners of America. All of these letters are in regard to the matter of American citizenship.</p>
   <p>Stephen L. Kolanowski and M. S. Szymczak, in charge of the citizenship schools in Chicago, have resolved to extend their activities all over the United States. They are working at present on a special correspondence course for the Poles beyond the boundaries of the city of Chicago. This course will be very practical and moderately <pb facs="5423968_8_0406.jpg" n="2"/>priced and will cover all phases of naturalization. At the moment we do not know just how soon the course will appear in print, but it is most certain that it will not take over one month.</p>
   <p>This course will be comparatively short and very practical. All letters in this matter should be addressed to Americanization League of Illinois,156 N. La Salle St., Chicago Ill.</p>
   <p>If the necessary funds were available, if there was a Polish organization in America which would care to interest itself in establishing citizenship schools in all Polish settlements throughout the United States, a course of this kind would not be necessary, said Mr. Kolanowski, but unfortunately, there is no such organization. We hope, however, that several thousand Poles will benefit from this course. This correspondence course is not at all figured for profit - nevertheless, the cost of printing, mailing and office personnel will have to be paid for.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
