<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-08">May 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Podhalan Society Holds Social to Obtain New Members</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0997</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0997.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-08">May 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PODHALAN SOCIETY HOLDS SOCIAL TO OBTAIN NEW MEMBERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday, May 5, the Podhalan Society, Group 1850 of the Polish National Alliance, held a social at A. Zembal's Hall for the purpose of attracting new members, and it was unusually successful.</p>
   <p>Mr. S. Bobrzecki, president of the Podhalan Society, opened the exercises, and called upon Mr. Leon Nowak, president of Commune III of Holy Trinity parish, to act as chairman, and on Miss A. Skierczynski to act as secretary. The president ardently besought those present to arrange such socials more frequently, because such gatherings enlighten the people; and as examples he showed how the Americans, English, French, and even the Czechs unite and work for their nations. Mr. Bobrzecki asked the audience to be quiet during the program, which was as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0998.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>1. Vocal solo by little Victoria Myrda, "Bracia do boju" (Brothers to battle), which was sung very well. The audience rewarded her with enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>2. A Recitation, "Dwaj Ranni" (The Two Wounded Men), by Miss Frances Czuj. Miss Czuj recited with enthusiasm and deserves recognition for her performance.</p>
   <p>3. A Piano solo by Mr. Francis Zembal.</p>
   <p>4. A Recitation, "Polka" (The Polish Woman), by Miss Josephine Lukasik.</p>
   <p>5. A Speech by Mr. Michael Bal, advising the young people to join the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>6. Vocal solo, "O Wolnosc Polski" (For Poland's Freedom), by Miss Sophie <pb facs="5423968_8_0999.jpg" n="3"/>Lukasik.</p>
   <p>7. Piano solo, Krakowiak (Cracovienne), by Mr. F. Zembal.</p>
   <p>8. Recitation, "Bohater" (The Hero), by little Victoria Myrda.</p>
   <p>Mr. Leon Nowak, president of the Commune, then made a speech in which he besought us to become better acquainted with ourselves, to become better acquainted with our national memorials. He also reminded us of how the early Polish immigrants to this country suffered persecution in America on the part of people of other nationalities; and today, thanks to the labor of those who always work in the national field for the good of all, we can be proud of being Poles and of being able also to love our adopted country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1000.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In conclusion, the speaker exhorted us to support one another, so that our nation could be regarded as the equal of others. He also invited those present to the celebration of the anniversary of the Constitution of the Third of May, which will be held on May 6, at the Polish Roman Catholic Union Hall.</p>
   <p>This speech was followed by a monologue by Miss J. Lukasik, which delighted the audience.</p>
   <p>The entire program was a success, for which we sincerely thank all those who participated.</p>
   <p>The entertainment was concluded with the singing of "Boze cos Polske" (God Save Poland), and everyone went home contented.</p>
   <p>A. Skierczynski, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
