<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-09">Jan. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Anti-Immigration Bill and the Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-09">Jan. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE ANTI-IMMIGRATION BILL AND THE DZIENNIK ZWIAZKOWY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Once again in the lower house of Congress an anti-immigration bill, called the Burnett-Dillingham Bill, has been introduced. These two law-makers have introduced this bill in order to curtail the flow of illiterate immigrants. Only those at least able to read and write in their native language will be permitted to enter our borders.</p>
   <p>The contents of this bill are well known to our people. The greatest degree of illiteracy is to be found in the ranks of the people from the Southern and Eastern parts of Europe. This bill is primarily aimed at them. Since a large preportion of our people, who do not know how to read or write, are found in these parts, it also affects them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1141.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The condition of our country can be explained in the following manner: Many years ago Poland was torn apart into three sections. We were deprived of our personal wants and of our personal desires. Our language, religion, and property were lost to us. Those of us that were ambitious were put in the military ranks and later killed on the field of battle. Because of this unjust treatment, we have unwillingly fallen under a shroud of ignorance and illiteracy.</p>
   <p>The fact that not all of us are able to read or write is not our fault. It is the fault of those who took all our privileges and with them, our right to the culture of the world. This knowledge and this culture are today an important requirement among Americans, which will prevent the already starving Europeans from coming to this country to seek salvation and decrease the ranks of the hungry.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1142.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is now no need to explain the reason for this bill. The anti-immigration monster has awakened again. The time has come for our Polish gentry to voice their protest. Polish voters with power to help elect representatives to Congress should also follow suit. It will not be wise to overlook this matter. If we do not send any protests, it will be evident to the congressmen that we are in favor of the anti-immigration movement.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance, our largest and most important Polish organization, is not overlooking this issue. The forces of the P.N.A. are doing everything within their power to show that the members of this organization, who are spread out all over the United States, are not in favor of this bill and protest against its passage. They feel that this country should open its gates to the European people and <pb facs="5423968_8_1143.jpg" n="4"/>give shelter to the oppressed. This will afford the vast masses of people starving for bread and freedom an opportunity to seek shelter on neutral soil. They will be able to earn their piece of bread, although through hard toil, and in time be in a position to rehabilitate their standing in this world of democracy. Here they will be able to have their own home, their own family, amidst freedom and peace.</p>
   <p>The Alliance is joining hands with the other Polish groups and organizations in a mass protest against the Burnett-Dillingham Bill. All these groups are sending invitations to their members to assist in fighting this bill. They ask all to send in their objection to the Senators and Representatives. The more the protests pour in, the greater the possibility that the bill will be defeated.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1144.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Polish people alone have a representation of 4,000,000 in America. Surely, they hold at least a small part in the controlling hand in America. A wholehearted response from adult groups will have a marked influence against the passage of this anti-immigration bill.</p>
   <p>Let us hurry, for the time is passing quickly. Although the possibilities of this bill's passage in Congress may be slight, it is of importance that we present our opinion. It may be up to the President to give his signature for the passing of this bill, but if our protests keep pouring in we will be more certain that this movement will be killed.</p>
   <p>Let us all act today!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
