<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-05">Dec. 5, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Americanization</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0538</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0538.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-05">Dec. 5, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICANIZATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>He who supposes that we Poles here in America are not threatened with the loss of our national identity is gravely mistaken and shortsighted. It is true that loss of national identity does not threaten those Poles who were already in their middle age when they came from Poland and settled here. But loss of national identity threatens our children, born here or brought here in their childhood by their parents. We will not lose all our young people in the foreign sea, but we are losing a large percentage of them, and if we do not pay more attention to this fact, in a few score years we will lose half our young people, who will cling to foreigners and will be forever lost to the Polish cause.</p>
   <p>Americanism penetrates into Polish homes through doors and windows. It does not appear in so brutal a form as Germanization and Russification in Europe, but because of this it is all the more dangerous. Americanism soothes us, <pb facs="5423968_8_0539.jpg" n="2"/>lulls us to sleep, tempts us with various little tricks, but it is systematically trying to pour all races, all nationalities, into one mass.</p>
   <p>There are innumerable proofs at every step that this is so. All sorts of settlements, buildings for supposed Christian youth, and innumerable clubs snatch our children and systematically take away their national identity.</p>
   <p>American chauvinists look askance at the various nationalistic organizations, at their exclusive clubs, alliances, gymnastic societies, choral societies, etc., because they would want to catch all of this in their nets; in their talons.</p>
   <p>They need our blood, our energy, our strength.</p>
   <p>An attempt was made through the church to deprive the Poles of their national identity by having catechism taught in English in the schools, but the Polish people and their national press opposed this energetically. So, for the present, this plan of action has been abandoned in favor of something less drastic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0540.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The American schools try to make our children lose their national identity by inculcating American patriotism upon them and keeping silent about our history or presenting it in an unfavorable light. We counteract these influences by teaching Polish in our schools, but before all our neighborhoods may be benefited by this action many of our young people will be lost to the Polish cause forever.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, all sorts of American sports, clubs, and youth organizations attract our young people, thus exposing them to loss of national identity. It is true that here, too, we try to counteract by establishing turner societies, choral societies, young people's alliances, etc., but this is not enough, since it is difficult for us to compete with the Americans, who, wealthier than we, spend hundreds of thousands and millions of dollars on building clubs and forming all sorts of societies, whose purpose is to pour all the nationalities into one body, in order to create one great American nation.</p>
   <p>Americans are heading in this direction slowly and patiently, but systematically.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0541.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is not, however, enough for them to entrap our young people in their nets, but they cast them also at the older folks. We read in one of the American papers that an American missionary society has set apart certain funds for propagandizing Americanism among specific national groups. This is concealed under a sectarian cloak, and religious matters are supposedly adduced as the chief aim, but this subterfuge is betrayed by a sentence in the announcement of this missionary society, which states: "Our aim is that every person redeemed by us should be, in the first place, a good American, and that he should forget all the ties which bind him to his native land."</p>
   <p>Clearly and plainly stated, what? This society has set aside funds for the "redemption of various nationalities," and, therefore, for propagandizing its purposes among the Poles, it has set aside five thousand dollars. A modest sum, naturally, for which it will be difficult for them to purchase even five good Poles, but this fact proves conclusively that certain American spheres want very badly to assimilate other nationalities, doing everything they can in this direction.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0542.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Other American religious sects and "educational" societies, with the aid of the press and books, are trying to penetrate into the Polish community in order to engulf it. They issue pamphlets printed in Polish, urging the reading of English papers, the sending of children to English schools, and the organizing of American societies. Besides this, they shower the Poles with Bibles and all sorts of pamphlets, from which the spirit of Americanism and Protestantism emanates, which, although not contagious to the older people, can ensnare the younger ones.</p>
   <p>This danger, then, exists and threatens us from many directions. Therefore, we should be on guard if we want to preserve our nationality in America in all its strength.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, the duty of the older people to unite themselves in Polish organizations, especially national ones, to strengthen our turners and to draw our young people to them. This will be our strongest shield against Americanism.</p>
   <p>We live here physically, but our spirit must be Polish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
