<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-10-03">Oct. 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Central Committee in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-10-03">Oct. 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH CENTRAL COMMITTEE IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After long negotiations and deliberations lasting for several weeks, finally, we have accomplished what all of our people in America have been demanding and what the Polish cause required: namely, the consolidation of all the larger Polish organizations in the United States, including the clergy.</p>
   <p>A pact has been signed uniting the following organizations: Polish National Alliance, Polish Roman Catholic Union, Alliance of Polish Falcons in America, Alliance of Polish Women in America, Alliance of Polish Clergy, Polish National Council and several smaller organizations, which, although they have already joined the Central Committee, did not have enough time to send their representatives to the meeting.</p>
   <p>A united representative body has been created. Its purposes are to consider as a whole all of the preparations necessary to the liberation of our homeland from its age-old servitude and to turn the two important watchwords of the <pb facs="5423968_8_1165.jpg" n="2"/>nation into realities--a treasury and an army.</p>
   <p>From today on this body will be known as the Polish Central Committee in America. Its members will be representatives of the above-mentioned organizations and of those Polish societies which want to join in this work and the most prominent Poles among the emigrants who wish to participate in this united action.</p>
   <p>We do not want to go into the organizational details of this Polish Central Committee in America today, because we shall have to return to this matter frequently in the future. We merely want to point out that this action which has been taken has strong support and will not be rescinded. Nothing now can destroy the unanimity of thought and aims of all of those who have founded the Polish Central Committee.</p>
   <p>Each organization retains complete freedom of action. No attempt has been made to change the external differences of these organizations. All of them have already begun to collect funds within their own ranks and a joint treasury has <pb facs="5423968_8_1166.jpg" n="3"/>been created for those who are still standing on the sidelines, who, for various reasons, do not trust any of these societies. All contributors will have a voice in the control of this treasury and any organization committee, or private individual can become a contributor.</p>
   <p>In view of this fact there is nothing left for us to do but appeal to everyone again not to be lazy in his work. Let everyone begin energetic action now, with enthusiasm and faith in the sacredness of the cause, certain that his efforts aim at only one goal. His work will be one of the millions of bricks which are now being made throughout Poland to build a single structure--the deliverance of our country from subjection.</p>
   <p>Poor Galicia, completely impoverished by the last few years, has contributed millions for her most sacred cause, in little more than a day. The generosity of the peasant in Galicia and throughout all of Poland can bring tears of joy to our eyes. The sacred enthusiasm for serving our country at a time of such <pb facs="5423968_8_1167.jpg" n="4"/>stress has affected all Polish people. Then we emigrants here cannot be degenerate sons of Poland. We cannot permit ourselves to be outstripped in enthusiasm. Realizing the desperate situation of our brethren across the sea, we must hasten to bring them the greatest possible aid.</p>
   <p>We have all been waiting for the past week, for this moment of reconciliation, for the end of disputes and fratricidal battles. This moment has arrived. Today we stand together again at the same plow. Today, again in harmony and with an understanding of our needs, we begin co-operative work. This work must describe the widest circles and must include everyone within it. It must be taken up with all of the energy and enthusiasm of which we are capable.</p>
   <p>At this time may we be permitted to add one more thing. The unanimous election of Mr. A. Karabasz, censor of the Polish National Alliance, as president of this Committee is a sort of compensation to him for the grave wrongs which people of ill will have perpetrated against him. This gives him complete satisfaction <pb facs="5423968_8_1168.jpg" n="5"/>for the accusations and lies hurled at him and at the Polish National Alliance by bandit editors, who have not discriminated between good and bad means when they were taking personal revenge, and who have hurled relentless and horrible accusations at the censor of the Polish National Alliance and its other high officers.</p>
   <p>It is not vanity or pride in the fact that the highest officer of our organization was elected to head the committee that prompts us to write these words, but the realization of the horrible wrong which has been done to the people, who wanted leaders whose first concern was love of the homeland, and found only leaders who used the popular enthusiasm of two years ago to further their party interests.</p>
   <p>Now, no one can accuse us or the organizations united in the Polish Central Committee of doing this most sacred work for profit; the people as a whole would shout traitor and robber at such a one. Now all of our people, through their representatives and by the very fact of uniting in co-operative work have expressed their judgment of those who still want to foment and continue <pb facs="5423968_8_1169.jpg" n="6"/>their activities to destroy national unity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
