<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-19">Dec. 19, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Military Society Observes Twenty-Fifth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-19">Dec. 19, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MILITARY SOCIETY OBSERVES TWENTY-FIFTH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A beautiful ceremony was held last Sunday in celebration of the twenty-fifth anniversary of the Second Company of Polish [Cracovians] Krakusy [Translator's note: "Krakusy" was the name given a division of soldiers from the city of Cracow during the Kosciusko Insurrection in 1794.], of St. Hedwig's Parish, Twenty-sixth Division, Alliance of Polish Military Societies. The jubilee included the consecration of the society's new American flag: (a Polish flag had been purchased some time ago.)</p>
   <p>The celebration began with vesper services at St. Hedwig's Church, during which Reverend Obyrtacz, pastor of the Church, consecrated the new flag. Following vespers, the military societies that had gathered for the celebration formed into ranks, paraded down the main streets to the strains of a military band, arriving finally at St. Hedwig's Parish Hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1081.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The large, beautiful hall was soon filled with soldiers [military society members] and other guests. The venerable Captain Victor Woloszkiewicz mounted the platform and after a few words of greeting, named as chairman Titus Jachimowski, president of the Alliance of Polish Military Societies, who, in turn, called upon the editor of the Polish National Alliance publications, S. Orpiszewski, to act as secretary of the proceedings. He then invited the officers of organizations and societies to the platform and formally opened the celebration with a beautiful and moving address.</p>
   <p>The Program</p>
   <p>1. The first number on the program, a rendition by the St. Hedwig Choir I under the direction of the talented Wiedemann, produced a storm of applause that did not cease until the choir returned for an encore. It is an excellently trained mixed choir, a credit to the parish and to its director.</p>
   <p>2. John Prymorski, commander in chief of the Alliance of Polish Military Societies, <pb facs="5423968_8_1082.jpg" n="3"/>unfurled the new flag. He took this occasion to deliver a long and beautiful address that flowed straight from the heart. The flag's sponsors were also upon the platform at the unfurling, and presented gifts.</p>
   <p>3. After Professor Ostrowski's orchestra had played a medley of Polish songs, the secretary of the society [Second Company of Polish Krakusy], read the society's history....</p>
   <p>4. In place of W. J. Andrzejewski, secretary of the Alliance of Polish Military Societies, who was unable to be present because of illness, S. Orpiszewski delivered an address suitable to the occasion.</p>
   <p>5. The local Falcon society next presented some gymnastic exercises (pyramids), which were warmly received. This number was followed by an orchestral selection, during which Mrs. Woloszkiewicz, Mrs. Wojtyla, and Mrs. Guzikowski took up a collection for the benefit of the war victims in Poland. The collection <pb facs="5423968_8_1083.jpg" n="4"/>netted $21.54.</p>
   <p>6. The St. Hedwig Choir sang....and was compelled by the applause to return for an encore. At the close of this number, the Reverend J. B. Obyrtacz, pastor of St. Hedwig's Parish, delivered an address in which he lauded the Krakus Society. After expressing his best wishes for the Society's continued work in its particular field of endeavor, he made a personal contribution to the Polish Relief Fund.</p>
   <p>7. The Kosciusko Guard, Ninetieth Division, Alliance of Polish Military Societies, then presented a rifle and marching drill, to the great enthusiasm of the audience.</p>
   <p>In behalf of the 115th Division of the Alliance of Polish Military Societies, Stanislaus Matyklasinski expressed his best wishes to the Krakus Society, following which the audience sang the Polish national anthem, "God Save Poland", <pb facs="5423968_8_1084.jpg" n="5"/>bringing the celebration to a close.</p>
   <p>The celebration in the hall was followed by a banquet during which Reverend Obyrtacz, as toastmaster, entertained the guests with his witty remarks. Speeches appropriate to the occasion were made by Kaszubowski, Jachimowicz, Janusz, Porzuczek, and many others. A cordiality entirely worthy of our warriors prevailed throughout.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
