<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-07">Aug. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Americanization Temptations</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Contributed Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-07">Aug. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICANIZATION TEMPTATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Contributed Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From various parts of the country there comes disturbing news of a mysteriously rising movement which has as its aim an intensive Americanization of "foreign elements".</p>
   <p>Where this movement is coming from, what is its source and inspiration, what is its principle, and through what means it is acting, cannot yet be judged. Is it an adding of fuel under the famed "melting pot," or is it the action of some unknown and shady force intending to divert the strength and energy of the nation into other useless and impossible directions, creating dissension, discontent, and protest from various national groups?</p>
   <p>That this movement has in it not the smallest particle of the true American spirit, the spirit of freedom, the brightest virtue of which is the broadest <pb facs="5423968_8_0459.jpg" n="2"/>possible tolerance, no one can deny.</p>
   <p>And when did this movement begin? It is, as a matter of fact, beginning now, at the moment when America is sealing the brotherhood of nations with its heroic blood, when it is tying unbreakable knots of friendship, when it is fighting for principles of world citizenship. The present war shows that the American "melting pot" is entirely superfluous. No language or "melting pot" can change or make into one the individual and anatomical virtues of temperament and blood. But the love of liberty, the love of ideals, the love of a great country of freedom and honor for its traditions and past have united the spirits of many nationalities, of which America can be proud. And America is proud of its brave citizen-sons who,although of various descents, are fighting on the fields of France as one under the spirit of Americanism, even those who were not originally born here. What more does America need, what more can it desire?</p>
   <p>If the concern of the new movement is bringing these "foreigners" closer <pb facs="5423968_8_0460.jpg" n="3"/>together, becoming better acquainted with their souls and their needs, making it easier for them to learn the language, spreading enlightenment, teaching them the history of the United States, then such Americanization should be warmly applauded and earnestly co-operated with; such Americanization should be the concern of every person and organization here. For nothing brings and holds people together so closely as love, a mutual understanding, a broad-mindedness and tolerance, a conviction that, on the opposite side, there is friendliness and a real concern for the welfare of one's fellow man.</p>
   <p>But, unfortunately, we see here and there, in the Americanization movement, impulses and purposes that are not very noble. Here we see strong currents that are unfavorable to Catholicism, a tendency toward the elimination of foreign languages from nationalist schools, a tendency to limit the freedom of organization. Nationalist-Catholic schools have two enemies: Catholic bishops of other nationalities and a strong anti-Catholic current originating with other religious groups.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0461.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Can such Americanization reach its goal even if it abandons the American spirit, the spirit of tolerance, and adopts the Prussian system and methods, that is, violence? No, definitely not! Such Americanization must foil; it will create unrest and race hatred, and it will spoil the possibilities of mutual understanding and ideal Americanization.</p>
   <p>The American government should leave unchanged the present freedom of organization of the nationalist schools, and only assume a general control over them; it should watch over that ideal system of Americanization, watch over the scholastic standards of the schools, insist that the teachers be properly trained professionally--but the questions of conscience and of religion should be left to the will and needs of a given race or nationality.</p>
   <p>If the idea is to give us a better opportunity to learn the English language, then everything should be done to facilitate it, without violence and without ridicule of other languages, for all languages, since they exist, are equally good. But it must be taken for granted that, with a great mass of elderly <pb facs="5423968_8_0462.jpg" n="5"/>people who have no education, this plan will not "take," and will be but a dream. Such changes must be made slowly, over a long period of time.</p>
   <p>Everyone understands that a knowledge of the language of the country one lives in is necessary; daily life teaches this. An American going to Poland would try to learn the Polish language for his own good; he would hate the language, however, if he were forced to learn it.</p>
   <p>Americans should not be against other languages. Knowledge of all the languages of the earth can only bring great benefit in the future. If we all have the spirit of true Americanism, there can be no fear for the future of the nation. Let the nation and the government turn their attention to ideal Americanization, to education, to raising and ennobling those neglected, unknown, often hated or scorned "foreigners," and the rest will take care of itself. They will be Americans, body and soul, although perhaps with varied characteristics and temperaments, but (in addition to other, foreign languages) <pb facs="5423968_8_0463.jpg" n="6"/>speaking one national language of their own [English], which will probably some day become the language of the world.</p>
   <p>But all violent, intolerant attempts upon religio-nationalist schools, upon the freedom of organization, upon the souls and traditions of those who were born elsewhere, will only spoil the really noble work of true Americanization, and we will stand as one man against them.</p>
   <p>S. Z.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
