<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-14">Apr. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To Rescue the National Museum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1009</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1009.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-14">Apr. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO RESCUE THE NATIONAL MUSEUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have some good news to share with our readers. Yesterday the treasurer of the Polish National Alliance sent one thousand dollars to Professor Laskowski, president of the [Polish] National Museum Council at Rapperschwil, Switzerland. The money was sent by wire, in accordance with the resolution passed unanimously day before yesterday by the Central Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance in order to rescue from ruin the temple of Polish memorials on Swiss soil.</p>
   <p>This first remittance of one thousand dollars comes almost entirely from voluntary contributions sent to the treasurer of the Polish National Alliance and to our paper in answer to appeals made from time to time. The rest of the amount absolutely necessary to save the museum--which Professor Laskowski figured would be five thousand dollars--will be sent just as soon as the Polish National Alliance receives a reply from the National Museum Council explaining the financial state of this institution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1010.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are taking the liberty of publishing here a copy of the letter sent yesterday to Professor Laskowski. From the contents of this letter we can easily gather the reasons which have prompted the Polish National Alliance to withhold temporarily the sending of the requested five thousand dollars. This letter reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Chicago, April 13, 1917.</p>
   <p>"Professor Z. Laskowski,</p>
   <p>110 Rue Carouge,</p>
   <p>Geneva, Switzerland.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir: We hereby have the honor of informing you that, in accordance with the decree of the Controlling Commission over the National Fund of the Polish National Alliance, we are sending by wire one thousand dollars to your address for the needs of the Polish National Museum at Rapperschwil.</p>
   <p>"In addition, we are happy to inform you that the Controlling Commission over <pb facs="5423968_8_1011.jpg" n="3"/>the National Fund has decided on principle to rescue the Museum at Rapperschwil from ruin, but we must have specific details of the total amount needed to pay the interest on the Museum's debts and all other bills, and the cost of remodeling and restoring the palace.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, we ask you kindly to send us an itemized statement of the financial obligations and state of the building housing the National Museum, so that we may understand thoroughly what expenses these changes will entail.</p>
   <p>"The Controlling Commission over the National Fund would like to have the following data:</p>
   <p>1.) What debts does the Museum have? When and how payable?</p>
   <p>2.) What is the minimum amount necessary for the maintenance of the Museum, and the restoration of the palace? Give the time limits.</p>
   <p>3.) How could the necessary sum be guaranteed if the Controlling Commission <pb facs="5423968_8_1012.jpg" n="4"/>of the National Fund of the Polish National Alliance were to supply the requested amount?</p>
   <p>"All further information which you may consider necessary for a complete understanding of the plight in which the Museum finds itself, we ask you kindly to enclose in your reply.</p>
   <p>"Awaiting your early reply, we are</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours</p>
   <p>Polish National Alliance:</p>
   <p>K. Zychlinski, president</p>
   <p>J. S. Zawilinski, secretary general</p>
   <p>J. Magdziarz, treasurer."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1013.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>From this letter we can deduce that the Central Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance has taken the matter of rescuing the National Museum at Rapperschwil to heart, and that the Controlling Commission over the National Fund, composed of M. Blenski, censor of the Polish National Alliance, Dr. I. Drobinski, Dr. F. F. Fronczak, and Attorney K. Sypniewski, has shown a willingness to lend the necessary amounts for this purpose out of the National Fund, believing that the members of the Alliance will quickly collect the necessary amount through voluntary contributions.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Museum at Rapperschwil will be rescued from ruin, for, when the Polish immigrants in the United States really get to work, they will restore the building at their own expense before the war is over, in order to give it to Poland as a permanent memorial, and as an expression of the work accomplished abroad by her wandering sons.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
