<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, n. IV,
<date when="1890-09-24">September 24, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">For the People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0705</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0705.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, n. IV,
<date when="1890-09-24">September 24, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish language is as important to us Poles as hands to a tailor; which roughly speaking is how can we enjoy our play games or write without hands? Then how can you Poles consider yourselves good Polish citizens if you don't improve your native tongue?</p>
   <p>To learn the English language so we can read books and be able to write it is very essential to all of us of foreign extraction, but to deny your own nationality and native tongue before people of other nationalities is a disgrace to the people of that nationality and their country.</p>
   <p>We Poles should not do as people of other nationalities do; they do not use their native tongue and soon forget it, but eventually pick up some other foreign language, depending largely on the number of people of a certain nationality living in that locality.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0706.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The mothers are the backbone of any language. Who is the judge in our childhood days and teaches us to know right from wrong, makes our meals, sits among us in the dining room, grows dearer to us, is with us at all parties and gatherings, attends to us when we are sick? Everyone respects her, we all bow to her, without a doubt in our minds we know it is our mother.</p>
   <p>Who among the Poles, besides speaking his native tongue is not seeking more knowledge? Don't send your children to work, school is the place for them; that is the foundation of all prosperous business men. Polish parents do not deny your children the right to learn to speak and write the Polish language.</p>
   <p>Eugeniusz K. Pociej.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
