<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-04">June 4, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">From Polish Falcoms Group Number 7</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-06-04">June 4, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">FROM POLISH FALCOMS GROUP NUMBER 7</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sincere thanks are extended to all Polish societies for taking part in [the ceremony of] raising the banners of the Polish Falcons, Group Number 7, held Sunday May 31, at Pulaski Hall. Thanks are especially extended to the officers of the Polish National Alliance, for their presents, particularly the gold pin; to the Polish Women's Central Society of America, for the gold pin; to the King Stephen Batory Society, for the ribbons; to the King Casimir the Great Society, for the gold pin; to the Crown of Poland Society and the Henry Dabrowski Society, for the ribbons.</p>
   <p>The following groups donated their services: Bartosz Glowacki Society, Polish Mechanics Industrial Society Number 1, Krakus Society, St. Michael Society Number 1, and the singing societies Halka, Moniuszke, Bell of Freedom, Morning Star, Lute, and Cracewites.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1450.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Donations also came from the Polish Alliance Falcons and other Falcon groups of Town of Lake and South Chicago. Telegrams came from Buffalo, New York, and Philadelphia. Thanks are also extended to E. A. Jablonski, editor of Zgoda (Harmony); Casimir Zychlinski, president of the Polish Falcons of America; S. A. Osada, Dr. S. Barszczewski, and Mrs. T. Samolinska, for their speeches, recitations, and verses.</p>
   <p>The financial results of the program are as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Income</cell>
     <cell>$199.90</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses</cell>
     <cell>139.28</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Net</cell>
     <cell>$60.62</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Dear Friends: Sunday's performance and attendance will always remain with us as a fond memory. Tears of happiness rolled down our checks as the new banners were unfolded on the stage, for they will awaken our youth to further work for Poland and our people. The goal of the society will be reached through your <pb facs="5423968_8_1451.jpg" n="3"/>support.</p>
   <p>Once again we wish to thank everyone for taking part in this event.</p>
   <p>The Committee of The Polish Falcons.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
