<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-04-17">Apr. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[P.N.A. Membership Drive a Success]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1358</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1358.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiaztowy</title>,
<date when="1909-04-17">Apr. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[P.N.A. MEMBERSHIP DRIVE A SUCCESS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past four months the Polish National Alliance has been increasing its recruiting ranks. Every month over one-thousand new members join. This has broken all previous records. It was not anticipated that the appointed agents could find such a large number of new members.</p>
   <p>The normal growth was from six hundred to eight hundred members, according to statistics. It was not considered that this powerful Alliance should point out that the normal growth could be increased greatly by going beyond the present boundary lines for new members.</p>
   <p>It should not be surprising to anyone that one thousand or twelve hundred new members are being enrolled monthly, or that this or that unusual growth arose to new laurels. If the Alliance would look after this body of new members it would not be necessary to concern itself with new membership, but look after its own course. At present, conditions are different. It was pointed out in <pb facs="5423968_8_1359.jpg" n="2"/>Remarks that the Polish National Alliance is not progressing as rapidly as it should. This cannot be denied nor padded with instantaneous work. In reality, the growth of the Alliance does not reach its normal expectations. It also was pointed out recently, that the Polish National Alliance should have at least 2,000 new members monthly.</p>
   <p>There are about 1,000 groups in this organization. If each group could only bring in two new members a month, then this could be considered as the normal growth. But this is not the case. At present there is only about one new recruit to a group. This is decidedly too small.</p>
   <p>Such poor increases in ranks are mostly due to idleness. What is needed is an effort of superhuman quality in order, not only to fill the gaps caused by natural death and other causes, but to exceed the normal growth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1360.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This requires every member to work with great effort in order to stay on the road that leads towards the betterment of the organization.</p>
   <p>One thousand or twelve hundred new members today in the Polish National Alliance is not enough. Each member should take great steps forward. In this work of development and increasing greatness, each member should compete for new members without question. But there are those allowing others to do their work. It is because of this lack of workers that the Alliance is not increasing in greatness but is actually retarding.</p>
   <p>It should be remembered always and everywhere, that work for the Alliance is work for the Polish Fatherland. The more work for the beloved Alliance, the greater are the merits for the fatherland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1361.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Alliance and Poland are one, like every important deed of its people is synonymous, so whenever anything is done from the love of Poland, it is equally done for Poland.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance is primarily for the personification of the Polish people. It was born for her, lives for her and works and organizes for her. It is for the betterment of the Poles in America; it is her exponent and her borer. In the Alliance there flows Polish thought; enriches it in power and spreads it in all directions. Without this organization the Polish people in America would be like a body without a soul. It tries to rescue its people and protect them from ruin.</p>
   <p>Every member should try his best to heighten the organization and honor it by wearing its emblem. But the end does not lie here. From empty efforts there is no gain. Before us all there remains work and it is work of a difficult calibre.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1362.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We must promote the meritorious ideals of our people. We must increase our ranks despite the hardships encountered. Not one, or two, or ten, but everyone regardless should get together for this work. The Alliance must remain and maintain its accelerating tempo. We must use every effort in order to reach this goal.</p>
   <p>It was pointed out that if each group of the Alliance would have signed two new members each month, the organization could have increased its ranks by almost twelve thousand beginning today. In reality, is this difficult? Is not a group of thirty or fifty members in a position to get two members, even if only among the ranks of relatives or friends? It would be a shame to deny this, for one member with consciencious effort could get that number if not more.</p>
   <p>Effortless power! At present when from all directions flow upon us jealous blows from our enemies who use every means to break up our Alliance, effort-less <pb facs="5423968_8_1363.jpg" n="6"/>force is needed. Let everyone of us become an organizing worker. Let us not have within our ranks those who look upon others to help the cause. Let every member be a promoter without question, whether he is an officer, or whether he holds office in some establishment. Today there is no time for delay, no time to put off our work for the gain of others. We must double our efforts, we mast increase our ranks as never before, because there lies in this our salvation. He who is well and able and has the ambition and does not desire to be dubbed a slacker, should start energetically to aid the cause. The field is very large. Within it lies fertile possibilities. One must put in hope and initiative in order to fuse together the scattered fields, so they could feel that they too belong to the same family. Let us all get to work then, who like and love the Alliance. Let us overcome the barriers. After all, the Polish National Alliance is the essence of our Fatherland and is like a mother that looks after her son during life, and after <pb facs="5423968_8_1364.jpg" n="7"/>death, keeps him in remembrance, and looks after his offspring. Onward for our cause today. Increase our ranks! Let the Polish National Alliance grow and become famous.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
