<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol, VI, No. 18,
<date when="1902-04-30">April 30, 1902</date><title level="a">"Local News."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol, VI, No. 18,
<date when="1902-04-30">April 30, 1902</date><title level="a">"LOCAL NEWS."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of all denials, one may safely say that some persecuting fate has invaded the Sixteenth Ward and it is so much more surprising because all this ill-luck and misfortune seems to date from the last aldermanic elections. Robberies in the ward are a daily occurrence. Mere children are shooting each other or cutting each other up with knives. Not so long age the General Secretary of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, returning home at night after the bank meeting, was held up and dangerously wounded, a few other citizens were robbed. Mr. Golinski was shot to death, Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> died from wounds after being stabbed with a knife by his own son and only last week Mr. Folinski and his son were murdered. It all happened on Noble St. between Blackhawk and Bradley Streets. These sad very shameful occurrences prove most eloquently the bestially of morals of our young people that commit such crimes.</p>
   <p>Mostly to blame for this state of affairs are the parents who permit their children to roam the streets at all hours of the night.</p>
   <p>But the carelessness and laxity of the police must also be blamed, for one never sees a police officer in our ward. We must also mention <pb facs="5423968_8_0096.jpg" n="2"/>our local politicians who defend and protect the wrong-doers, especially when the crime was "the settling of some political accounts." The political hooligans and gangsters are brazen in violating all rules of decency and law, knowing that they will not be punished and most of the time not even brought to court.</p>
   <p>The victims are all innocent and defenseless people.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately our very big parish cannot exert a better influence in spite of the best efforts and intentions of our pastor it is impossible for him to have proper control over this immense mass of our young people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
