<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 200,
<date when="1908-08-26">Aug. 26, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Results of Enlightenment; Effects of Clerical Teachings</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. II, No. 200,
<date when="1908-08-26">Aug. 26, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE RESULTS OF ENLIGHTENMENT; EFFECTS OF CLERICAL TEACHINGS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 'clericals' are reaping an abundant harvest from their teachings. On the 22nd day of this month, at midnight, a tragedy took place among the 'foster children' of the 'clericals,' on 25th Street near Rockwell, resulting in a very abundant harvest. One of the fighters, John Okraska, residing at 319 W. 25th Street, was stabbed with a knife near his heart. He is in a very critical condition - perhaps he is dead now. He was wounded by Jacob Czarnecki, residing on 24th Street. Two other men, who tried to stop the fight, received wounds in their hands by the same hero of clerical ignorance.</p>
   <p>The place where the fight occurred represents a terrible sight today. So much blood was shed that I was horrified at the sight of it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0091.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such scenes of life in our Polish settlements, where drinking and fighting is an every day occurrence, are very bad.</p>
   <p>During the six-week stay in Chicago, in the vicinity of St. Casimir's Parish, I have not seen a peaceful Saturday - a Saturday without a fight .... and in the same place.</p>
   <p>Whose fault is it?</p>
   <p>Of course, all will say that it is their own fault.</p>
   <p>The fault lies with our dear priests and the 'patriotic' saloon keepers. The first - that is, the priests - keep our poor people in stupidity from the very cradle; they keep them in the worst kind of ignorance. The second - that is, the saloon keepers - demoralize our younger generation to such a low degree that it is hard to believe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When such a saloon keeper, with a big belly and the emblem (a button) of the Polish National Alliance, or the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, finds himself behind a bar, he coaxes the young people to drink with the sweetest phrases that his base soul can afford. This is how the clergy and patriotism bring up our new generation.</p>
   <p>The time is approaching when the working man will find out that he is being terribly cheated and kept in ignorance. He will reject today's teachings of the 'Black Ravens' and saloon patriots, and will join the ranks of the Socialists, where there is light and truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
