<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-15">Jan. 15, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Chairman, Mr. Romaszkiewicz, to the Polish National Alliance Brotherhood. a Letter of Appreciation</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0838</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0838.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-15">Jan. 15, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">CHAIRMAN, MR. ROMASZKIEWICZ, TO THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE BROTHERHOOD. A LETTER OF APPRECIATION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor's note. We have received from Mr. Romaszkiewicz, Chairman of the Polish National Alliance's Central Board, the following communication to be published in the Alliance's newspapers, and we deem it appropriate to have it reproduced in the columns of Zgoda.</p>
   <p>Dear Brothers and Sisters of the Alliance:</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance's Jubilee year is ended. Throughout the United States we have celebrated nobly and with great dignity the time - centennial jubilee of our organization. The Jubilee contest arranged for the purpose of soliciting to our ranks 50,000 new members is also concluded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0839.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, while taking a short respite after that laborious and wearisome contest let us cast a look at the past and observe the results of all these efforts of ours. Let us count the fruits of our full year's labor and make a general review of our accomplishments, in order that we might be so much the better prepared for our new efforts. Thus imbued with new strength, we shall be able to take up the further and never ending tilling of the Alliance's soil, which after the harvest is again to be ploughed and has to get new seed, so that we may gather a new crop, never letting our Alliance's soil to lay barren and unproductive.</p>
   <p>While looking behind and observing the results of our labors in the Jubilee Year, we notice that that year has been well spent; that the Alliance's Brotherhood has not been idle; that the crops harvested are actually splendid and of such a kind that we really can be proud of a duty well done and, a task well performed.</p>
   <p>The fifty jubilee festivals, celebrated in as many Alliance's major branches throughout this vast country, from the Atlantic ocean to the <pb facs="5423968_8_0840.jpg" n="3"/>Pacific, with over forty thousand new members and sixty seven new groups added to our organization constitute a great and truly jubileean acquisition, moral, numerical and material. In the last month of the contest 4,885 adults and 1,781 children, making a total of 6,666 new members, joined the Alliance, and the number of groups was increased by sixteen. All these successes have been realized in a period of general and prolonged economical stagnation and unemployment, heavily oppressing our community; that is in a season least favorable for the soliciting of new members. Yet, in spite of the unfavorable economical conditions, last year we have attracted into the Alliance 40,000 new members and sixty-seven new groups. This is a splendid testimony to the zeal of our Alliance's brave Brothers and Sisters, who have earnestly responded to the appeal and have labored for the good of their organization to the best of their abilities.</p>
   <p>Honor to you, Brothers and Sisters of the Alliance! I wish to convey to you a cordial thanks in my name and in that of my Colleagues, male and female, of the Alliance's Central Board. We thank you for your endeavors and the hardships undergone by you while trying to replenish the ranks of your splendid organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0841.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Thanking you, distinguished and beloved Brothers and Sisters, from the depth of my grateful heart for your work given to the Polish National Alliance, I warmly and cordially ask you to continue your work, unceasingly soliciting new members and preaching its national and educational gospel.</p>
   <p>We start this year by writing a new page in the history of the Polish National Alliance. At the Golden Jubilee festivals you became acquainted with its past history and you have heard the plans which are to safeguard its much broader future development and growth, under new conditions and circumstances. Before those plans are reviewed and approved by our next Sejm, (convention), and before they are put into effect by the authorization of the Sejm, let us all in the meanwhile work for the greater development of the Alliance, teaching and preparing our sons and daughters withal so that some day thay may ably take up and further carry that great and splendid endowment, the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Such is my request to you in this new year With best wishes</p>
   <p>Your President,</p>
   <p>Jan Romaszkiewicz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
