<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-12">Dec. 12, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Socialists and the Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-12">Dec. 12, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALISTS AND THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish newspaper Dziennik Zwiazkowy has frequently mentioned that a bitter fight is in progress between the Polish National Alliance and two extreme and completely dissimilar factions of society, the clericals and the socialists.</p>
   <p>It would seem that some extraordinary agreement existed, between these relentless foes, to fight the Alliance together. The organization is already too large and too strong to make it worth while for anyone to attack it singly. It is useless, in fact, for two factions to attack the Alliance because this organization is far stronger than the coalition. Our enemies know that, but they must somehow give vent to their emotions of hatred--the former's hatred <pb facs="5423968_8_1272.jpg" n="2"/>of progress, the latter's hatred of patriotism. And so, although socialists are avowed enemies of faith and the church, and the clergy are equally strong opponents of socialism, that does not bother them in the least when the question of the Alliance comes before them.</p>
   <p>At the same time that this issue is coming out in print, that is, on December 12, 1910, another Polish newspaper, the Dziennik Chicagoski, an organ of the Resurrection Fathers, is hurling an entirely impossible attack upon the Polish National Alliance. Its charges are directed particularly against the administration, whom it calls unbelievers. It unleashes its "court poet" to rebuke us with the terrible weapon of his poetry. The socialists are calling a meeting for tomorrow, so that they can rave and thus give vent to their overflowing emotions.</p>
   <p>An attempt is made to tie up the two extremes and make their coalition appear <pb facs="5423968_8_1273.jpg" n="3"/>in a better light. And so we see a priest, not a Roman Catholic but a so-called Independent Catholic, coming to the aid of the socialists. He faithfully supports them at meetings, makes clericals of the people whom the clericals call atheists. This really is a comedy!</p>
   <p>The people laugh at these exhibitions which are like a free show to them. Both groups of the Alliance's enemies become more and more embarrassed and discredited, while the organization grows and continues toward its goal. The greatest noise is made when people of the Alliance become bored with the attacks and lies and occasionally request a few words of truth from the attacking newspapers.</p>
   <p>Then far more is written than is necessary, and the circus really begins. Sometimes they write, sometimes they call small conventions, and in every instance they rave and declare that an injustice is done them, that the <pb facs="5423968_8_1274.jpg" n="4"/>Alliance newspapers attack them, that these newspapers do not recognize religion or socialism, that they do harm to one or the other, and God knows what else.</p>
   <p>All this is nothing more than one big falsehood, The Alliance newspapers respect religion and good priests. Our newspapers look upon socialism as an economic theory that at present is in a formative stage. They would permit people to profess, advocate, and develop it as long as they do not abuse or attack those who do not believe in it. If tolerance is to exist, then let it. As it is improper for one to attack another because he is a socialist, so too is it bad taste to denounce a third because he chooses [not] to profess socialism.</p>
   <p>In former years the socialists did not attack the Polish National Alliance. They did not denounce in their newspapers people who failed to agree with <pb facs="5423968_8_1275.jpg" n="5"/>them. Because of that, the Alliance's newspapers had no need even to mention the socialists existence. This, however, has not been the situation for the past few years, and at present things are growing worse.</p>
   <p>Because the theory of socialism for some reason fails to win over the human mind sufficiently fast to satisfy its advocates, new tactics have been resorted to. It is, therefore, necessary for the socialists to falsify, to make abominable in the eyes of people that which they consider best and most dear--in a word, to ruin a man's heart and soul--and then, perhaps, something new can be sown on this barren land.</p>
   <p>In the last analysis it is far easier to snap at people and institutions than to instruct and educate the public in matters difficult to understand. The socialists, therefore, attack the Polish National Alliance, on one side, and religion and priests, on the other. These gentlemen figure that when <pb facs="5423968_8_1276.jpg" n="6"/>they kill religion and patriotism in our people, the people will gather by millions to socialism. But the people will not; men devoid of faith in God and love of their motherland will accept nothing in their stead, no matter what is offered them. They will turn against their instructors and thank them for the lesson in a way that is least expected.</p>
   <p>Fortunately, our people in general are not so extremely gullible as one might think. Our people are patient and indifferent, but they are also wise and just. They listen to and read what is presented to them, but they think and act in their own way. The people reason, for example, that if two enemies standing at opposite extremes at all times and conducting a natural battle with each other, suddenly call a truce and together hurl themselves against a third party, then the third must certainly be in the right.</p>
   <p>This is true of the present campaign of the clergy and the socialists against <pb facs="5423968_8_1277.jpg" n="7"/>the Polish National Alliance. The people, under the influence of this campaign, begin to become more interested in the Alliance, to think about it, to take into consideration everything they hear and see, and, as a result, to enroll more willingly and in larger numbers in the Polish National Alliance. The opposition meets with greater resistance and a more intense attachment to the institution among members of the Alliance, that part of the people who have already found the proper way. Certain individuals will allow themselves to be misled, it is true, but even these come to an equilibrium after a short time and return to the lines better members of the Alliance than they were. Those who do not return are small loss, and the general public can easily do without them. The best strategem to be used by friends of the Alliance in the presence of the present-day destructive campaign is to strengthen the Alliance. No consideration should be given to the attacks. Those who would harm us through their lies should not be believed. The assailants should be avoided, their papers remain unread, their meetings unattended, their organizations and activities unsupported. Every right-thinking Pole should exert all efforts and his complete <pb facs="5423968_8_1278.jpg" n="8"/>mental resources to build a truly Polish organization, the Polish National Alliance. It is certain that by so doing our people will nullify the attacks of our enemies and will retain that for which our forefathers fought and which they endeavored to preserve--a true religious and patriotic spirit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
