<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 7,
<date when="1902-02-12">Feb. 12, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Home Should Replace the State</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0608</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0608.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 7,
<date when="1902-02-12">Feb. 12, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">HOME SHOULD REPLACE THE STATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Knowing our sad condition and the duties we have towards God and country, we quite often appeal to you that you should not neglect your duties towards the children. Our future depends on the bringing up of our children; therefore, we owe them our tender care. We spared no bitter words to negligent mothers and weak-minded youths. It was not our intention to offend them, but only a duty placed upon an editor of a paper.</p>
   <p>As our enemy is attacking us from every side and spends millions of dollars for the destruction of our spirit and faith, we must try to replace our native country with our homes. And who can do that better than the mother? Besides the sense of beauty and harmony with which nature gifted her, only a woman can spread around her lost ideals; revive patriotic spirit, disappearing under hard conditions, by the warmth of her heart. A woman, like a faithful guardian of treasures, not only keeps in immaculate purity all characteristic patterns of patriotic love and devotion, but like an open book of songs, traditions <pb facs="5423968_8_0609.jpg" n="2"/>and fables, like a priestess of the sacred fire, preserves it in her mind and hands it down to her children. As a mother and mistress of the house, she should instill in her children the fear of God, all the old virtues of the nation, as well as love and respect towards our neighbor. On you, noble Polish women, falls the sacred duty of preserving our most precious treasures and handing them down to our generation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
