<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 11,
<date when="1916-03-15">March 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Women Section Metamorphosis of a Polish Emigrant Girl</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 11,
<date when="1916-03-15">March 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WOMEN SECTION METAMORPHOSIS OF A POLISH EMIGRANT GIRL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Just like a flower with a lovely scent and allure, a Polish girl was growing and blooming among her native fields.</p>
   <p>As soon as she was taught to put letters together, her mother kept her at home, to help with the housework. Then, when the scent of spring came and the geese hatched, she drove them out in the fields.</p>
   <p>She used to watch them, play with them and loved them. How happy those moments were, and how fast they passed.</p>
   <p>Today she is among strange people, whenever she thinks about those moments, her heart starts bleeding and holds her in a marvellous strange pain, longing for home.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0500.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If only once again she could go back over there, to chase the butterflies, pick flowers and make miracle wreaths to adorn the feet of her immaculate mother, standing at the wayside!</p>
   <p>Oh! For that country,</p>
   <p>Just like a paradise,</p>
   <p>Every day she sighs and cries</p>
   <p>And she will be unhappy,</p>
   <p>Till those miracles and wonders</p>
   <p>She sees once more before she dies.</p>
   <p>They sent her far away into a world, strange and unknown to her, to earn a living.</p>
   <p>Misfortune drove her away from her parental home. To help those she loved she devoted herself and everything that was dearest to her, she left what she had loved with all her little soul.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0501.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All this for bread... for bread!</p>
   <p>Who will not admire that Polish girl? She did not fear that long journey and that danger of travel; she traveled through the mountains, valleys, rivers and the ocean.</p>
   <p>Without any friendly advice and any care, she was among strangers and did not understand the conditions, among thousands of perils and menaces to herself.</p>
   <p>Everything seemed to be against her.</p>
   <p>But she slowly removed the obstacles in the way with a hard fight, and she rapidly accustomed herself to the conditions, and after a little time she was master of the situation.</p>
   <p>And from that soil farmer, the Polish girl became a real American girl.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0502.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>At first comes to her refined outward manners. She is trying to walk just like the real American girls, then she mimics the personal examples, she dresses herself more and more fashionably.</p>
   <p>But she is a deeply religious girl, she needs the spiritual comfort, and for this reason she belongs to the church, she is devoted and always moderate.</p>
   <p>In work she is easily exploited. When she came to this country, at first she was not particular, she accepted work of any kind, in the factory or home work.</p>
   <p>Money she did not spend, if she did not have to. Then when she gets used to this life, and this very often soon follows, she buys herself a dress and a hat, which is very often out of fashion.</p>
   <p>That kind of Polish girl also has her faults.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0503.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If she once becomes fond of dresses, then afterwards she continually goes beyond her limits.</p>
   <p>She only earns a miserably four or five dollars per week, but she pays for dresses the same as millionaires and she has to have the same things.</p>
   <p>This is the great fault in the common life of our Polish girls in this country.</p>
   <p>They forget themselves, their standing and try to be on the same level, she will not part with one iota of all the freaks of this country's fashions.</p>
   <p>The wife of a millionaire or capitalist might do this, they have plenty of money for that purpose and luxury, but the poor Polish girl, with bloody sweat and who works like an ox, if she does not save the few dollars she makes, the sin is unforgivable, spending bloody money only for dresses.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0504.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>A soul of a Polish girl has a most excellent constitution and is noble; but if she comes in contact with drunkards and boarders, she is material to be spoiled under such conditions.</p>
   <p>This is why we hear very often such sad stories.</p>
   <p>A married boarder, who has a wife in the old country, and is looking for a good chance, when he finds a credulous girl, is worse than the devil. He cheats her under the promise of marriage, and coaxes her out of her hard earned money, then after all that he disappears, leaving his credulous unlucky girl unhappy for the rest of her wrecked life.</p>
   <p>Single men are not better, and of them we do hear and read such stories.</p>
   <p>And you, poor credulous and sacrificed girl, you cry and suffer and pray to God, He is the only one who will listen to you and avenge you and punish the guilty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0505.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Credulity is the great defect of our girls, in spite of every day conduct, it is hard to cure them from this defect.</p>
   <p>Another defect of our immigrant girls is their thoughtlessness in choosing husbands.</p>
   <p>Every girl comes to this country with the aim of getting married at the first opportunity. She is ready to give her heart at once to any young man and go with him to the altar. Blindly she believes in him, then, after the wedding, the mask comes off the face of her lover-husband.</p>
   <p>Drunkenness and abuse has no end, and she becomes the slave of her husband, living with out faith and customs. She cries, complains, moans, and that grief drives her to drink.</p>
   <p>To get married is not like drinking a cup of coffee, this is the aim of your whole life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0506.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Only once you can make such a mistake in your life. So you should be careful before you marry a man, investigate the life of your future husband, his bad and good habits, get information from those who know him for a long time, but this you can't do in a week or two.</p>
   <p>Those girls will be mothers of our future generation. As they are so will be our next generation.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to protect them from such a beast and brute in the human flesh.</p>
   <p>Our immigration accomplished good things for any of the category, notwithstanding the fact that they have done almost nothing for our immigrant girls.</p>
   <p>For the protection of our girls, from exploitation of the dishonest Americans and Jews, there should be organized an association to protect <pb facs="5423968_8_0507.jpg" n="9"/>the girls, by each Polish parish.</p>
   <p>For this reason we should get for them homes, so they will live together and there will be no male boarders.</p>
   <p>For illiterates and girls with a lower education there should be given to them private lessons, evenings or Sundays, then they will not be treated so indifferently by others.</p>
   <p>The Polish maid, is the Angel of Purity,</p>
   <p>Her heart is Fondness and Bravery;</p>
   <p>Her soul prevails over the beauty of her flesh,</p>
   <p>Her virtue is crowned with Glory.</p>
   <p>Chester Lulinski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
