<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-18">July 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Pole for Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0742</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0742.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-07-18">July 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A POLE FOR CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday evening, a gathering of Polish political leaders of the Eighth Congressional District was held at the rectory of the Reverend Francis Gordon for the purpose of discussing the possibility of electing a Pole from this district to the House of Representatives. The Reverend Gordon presided, with H. Lokanski acting as secretary. Earnest speeches for conducting as energetic a campaign as possible for the election of a Pole to this office were made by Father Gordon, J. F. Smulski, Alderman [S.] Kunz, Alderman S. Walkowiak, Committeeman [J.] Ruszkiewicz, the Reverend J. Obyrtacz, Casimir Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance, the Reverend Zwierzchowski, Editor K. Wachtel, Attorney Koralewski, Editor J. J. Chrzanowski, Attorney [S.] Jankowski, H. Lokanski, and [P.] Rostenkowski, former president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>All of the addresses reflected anxiety for unity of action. This critical period also was emphasized as a time which we need a Congressional representative in Washington who would not only have influence in American circles, <pb facs="5423968_8_0743.jpg" n="2"/>but who would understand the Polish cause and would present and defend it in Congress.</p>
   <p>Although the exhaustive discussion continued until midnight, it brought no definite result. However, a temporary decision was reached to propose Koralewski for the post before a political mass meeting. A committee to call the mass meeting was not chosen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
