<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-29">May 29, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">St. Adalbert Parish and the Polish League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-29">May 29, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">ST. ADALBERT PARISH AND THE POLISH LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are requested to publish the following communication in Dziennik Chicagoski.</p>
   <p>"The members of St. Adalbert Parish held a meeting on May 27 in behalf of the Polish League. Reverend John Radziejwski, pastor of the parish, opened the meeting; Joseph Napieralski was chosen chairman of the meeting, and W. Zwierzynski secretary.</p>
   <p>"Methods for arousing the interest of the parishioners in the Polish League were discussed. It was decided to organize a unit of the Polish League in the parish. The following persons were chosen officers of the unit for one year: K. J. Bielinski, president; Francis Czerwinski, John Frazyna assistants; Lucian Jastrzebski, secretary. Moreover, it was decided to choose five collectors. Joseph Napieralski was made chief collector. W. Zwierzynski, Anthony Pelenz, John Lewandowski, and Skarupa were also selected for this task.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1616.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The collectors are authorized to collect the penny assessment for the League. They will turn over the collected money to the chief collector, and will then be given a receipt. A person may also join the League at the rectory.</p>
   <p>"It was decided to hold meetings in behalf of the League every two weeks. In these meetings girls, women, and even children will be allowed to participate. The following members paid their dues after the meeting [names omitted in translation].....</p>
   <p>"The entire Holy Family Society has joined the League and has paid its twelve-cents assessment for all forty members, a total of four dollars and eighty cents.</p>
   <p>"Towarzystwo Najsw. Serca Matki Boskiej Bolesnej (The Most Sacred Heart of our Lady of Sorrow) has promised to join the League and pay the assessments after the next meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1617.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Eleven dollars and fifteen cents was collected for the League at this meeting.</p>
   <p>"W. Zwierynski, secretary,</p>
   <p>"715 West 17th Street."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
