<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-02-18">Feb. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Bloody Riot at the Illinois Steel Company in South Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II E 2 (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>II A 2 (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>II E 2 (Slovak)</item>
     <item>II A 2 (Slovak)</item>
     <item>I C (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-02-18">Feb. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">BLOODY RIOT AT THE ILLINOIS STEEL COMPANY IN SOUTH CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon a bloody riot occurred at the South Chicago mills of the Illinois Steel Company between Poles on one side and Slovaks and Czechs on the other. Six of the participants were gravely injured, three of them probably fatally. All of the injured men live in South Chicago and, judging from their names, are Slovaks, Czechs, and Germans.</p>
   <p>Bad blood between the Poles and the Slovaks working in the factory has existed for some time. After the payment of wages, which lasted until noon, many of the workers went to a nearby tavern. The disturbance occurred when they returned to the factory after lunch. Two Slovaks, And a and Sozin, accosted a Pole, P.A. Walkowski, and proceeded to rail against him. When Walkowski advanced toward them, one of the men struck him with a stone. Thereupon Walkowski attacked his assailants. Workers <pb facs="5423968_8_0140.jpg" n="2"/>collected from all points of the yard and a free-for-all developed. Knives, clubs, and crowbars came into play and blood flowed copiously. The intervention of the foremen and some company officials brought the riot to a close. When the men had withdrawn from the field of battle, Sozin lay on the ground severely injured. Beside him lay a bloody knife, with which he had evidently been attacked. No one admitted ownership of the weapon. Two other men lay on the ground in pools of blood. Many others suffered minor injuries. Walkowski, around whom the riot had centered, appeared to have suffered the least of all. The police arrived presently, and many arrests were made.</p>
   <p>As a result of this riot, a score of men will lose their jobs in the factory, and three men may die. Such are the consequences of anger and violence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
