<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-06">Oct. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Is it True That We Are Denationalizing Ourselves</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0398</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0398.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-06">Oct. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">IS IT TRUE THAT WE ARE DENATIONALIZING OURSELVES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular publication of the Alliance of Polish Falcons Sokol-Polski writes about denationalization of the Poles in America as follows:</p>
   <p>No one is to blame, but ourselves, for our denationalization, we can prove this in many ways, for instance; the parishioners of a certain church, consisting of 150 families, requested that the pastor, discontinue-the use and teaching of the Polish language in the parish school. The pastor protested, and demanded that the teaching of both, Polish and English be continued. The question was finally brought to a vote. There were 57 votes against the teaching of the Polish language in the school, and 74 votes in favor of its continuation. Not everyone, however, voted. The decision was for the continuation of the Polish language in the parish school. The pastor also made it known, that so long as he is the pastor of that parish, he will retain the teaching of the Polish language in its school, and that he would resign rather than discontinue the teaching thereof.</p>
   <p>In Stevens Point, Wis. the Poles of St. Peters parish, petitioned the pastor to preach in the American language. The pastor was compelled to preach as the people demanded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0399.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In another locality, various Polish organizations that were unable to increase their membership, promoted the reading of Polish papers, but failed in their efforts, no one wanted to read them; which goes to prove that the Poles themselves are responsible for their denationalization. It is true that we are denationalizing ourselves? Are the rank and file responsible for this? No! It is not a natural trend to neglect the Polish speech or to completely annihilate the Polish spirit. It is not characteristic of our people. The reason is, they are not encouraged to keep the Polish spirit and language alive. They do not see Poles, that are holding some of the highest public offices; they do not look up to our leadership, because, they really have no leadership or organization to guide and lead them. They mingle with the others without discomination, and finally other nationalities use them, to attain their selfish end.</p>
   <p>We wonder, how some of our people, here and there, expect enlightenment, by eliminating their native tongue from their church. And do we know how it came about, that we are so neglectful? We simply don't care, we are disappearing in the ocean of all other peoples. We are denationalizing ourselves, without representation of Polish leadership, lack of a national program, and by our don't care attitude. Therefore, let us hope that in the future, we will be strong enough, to keep alive, the cause of our people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
