<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 30,
<date when="1914-07-29">July 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Songs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0523</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0523.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 30,
<date when="1914-07-29">July 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SONGS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish mothers, teach your children to sing Polish songs.</p>
   <p>There is nothing more splendid and nothing that speaks more to the soul than a song, the more so a native song, since it honors every nation, develops it, lifts it up and exalts it at every opportunity. Every nation has its national songs. The song is the outpouring of inward feelings, the more so folk songs, since they grasp directly at the heart.</p>
   <p>The Slavs love very much to sing, and of all the Slavic people the Poles sing the prettiest. The power of our songs exceeds anything that any song can give. The tones of Polish songs once roar with thunder, then again they sob with the cry of a little child, and sometimes they are grieving with a complaint of the innocent harmed one. In the Polish song is everything; there is power, beauty, verve, feeling of the whole nation! So, the, justly says our poet Adam Mickiewicz, that the Polish song is the "Ark of the Covenant between older and younger years."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0524.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Because even if destiny is cruelly persecuting us today, the song which we sing ties us with our bright past, disperses the despair and despondency within our hearts; it is our solace and tells us to believe in a better future.</p>
   <p>Without song there is no nation! Without song there is no future!</p>
   <p>Mothers, sing with the children as often as you can our beautiful Polish songs and ditties.</p>
   <p>Singing our songs we give proof to the entire world that we are a nation, that we are living and the future belongs to us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
