<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title> VOL. V. No. 30.
<date when="1901-07-24">July 24, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Court Record of Injunction</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>NAROD POLSKI</title> VOL. V. No. 30.
<date when="1901-07-24">July 24, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">COURT RECORD OF INJUNCTION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Thursday Attorney Piotrowski appeared before Judge Hanecy to void the injunction against Klemons J. Belinski, former president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union who was removed from office the twenty-third of last month for falsifying his age.</p>
   <p>This being vacation time for Judges, Judge Hanecy did not wish to go into the matter, saying it was not urgent, and does not require immediate settlement. Upon statements of Mr. Piotrowski that in spite of the injunction, Mr. Belinski threatens to attend the Polish Roman Catholic Union convention as a delegate. Judge Hanecy said, that the injunction does not pertain to the convention and the convention and the officers of the convention can ignore it.</p>
   <p>The Judge added "that if Mr. Belinski should go to the convention they need not let him in the hall, and that if he came in thru <pb facs="5423968_8_1407.jpg" n="2"/>the door he could be thrown out of the window." The convention can fire him out of the window." These are the words the Judge used in his decision.</p>
   <p>Mr. Belinski did not wish to step back without some ceremony, so he will with great ceremonies. The old proverb that "He who digs pits under another falls in to them himself." It would be better for Mr. Bolinski to, stay at home peacefully and not run to courts. That is not a credit to him because everyone knows what favors Mr. Bolinski showered upon his clients and upon the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
