<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVII, No. 134,
<date when="1923-06-08">June 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Fathers and Mothers, as Well as the Polish-American Youth!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0895</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0895.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVII, No. 134,
<date when="1923-06-08">June 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FATHERS AND MOTHERS, AS WELL AS THE POLISH-AMERICAN YOUTH!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Read this ever to your sons and daughters: tell them what joy they would bring you, if you were to see them among a company of singers upon the stage, on when hundreds of eyes were set listening intently to our national songs and bestewing their praises by calling for repeated encores. Also explain to them how this will encourage the Polish-American youth to sing our songs more frequently.</p>
   <p>Polish work has taken the lead in Washington as well as in other loading cities of the United States. Poles are known throughout the world as a great nation, free and independent, and not ashamed of their extraction. Proud also of the fact that they were given able assistance by our former President, Woodrew Wilson, and all United States in winning their freedom and independence.</p>
   <p>Toll them that today the most prominent men in America are trying to learn our Polish language - manufacturers, commissioners, and even diplomats; because it is an asset to them. Tell them that many Americans would be willing to give thousands of dollars if they were able to speak Polish like our Polish-American youth: because the Polish language is very necessary to them in business.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0896.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>You, Polish-American youths, are given the opportunity to improve your speech and increase your vocabulary; but you can not find this opportunity upon the streets. However, the Singing Circles can do this, because instructors there give particular attention to pronunciation.</p>
   <p>You young folks have an excellent opportunity to occupy better and higher paying positions, whether it be in business or in public affairs. We mean to encourage you to cultivate your Polish language in the various Polish Singing Circles; this aid is furnished at your command.</p>
   <p>You, young ones, should be proud that you possess another language beside the American; because it can not harm anyone to know even the Chinese language. Unquestionably the Polish-American youth should first know and perfect his own Polish language, which can be achieved in Polish Singing Societies; therefore, come to us.</p>
   <p>The Polish Singers Alliance in America has choirs in nearly every Polish section and everyone of the young ladies or men will be agreeably looked after in our midst.</p>
   <p>Many of our youths with high school education could occupy better positions if <pb facs="5423968_8_0897.jpg" n="3"/>they could speak the Polish language just as well as their American language. While you are improving your Polish speech, we also wish to inform you that it is not sufficient just to sing, but it also is necessary to read books written by our famous Polish authors, such as - Sienkiewicz's "Quo Vadis", "Without Dogma", "Trilogy", and many others.</p>
   <p>We wish to have you in our ranks for the simple reason that you could teach us the American language, which is very necessary for us. In other words, the elders together with the Polish-American youth, will reap benefits in this country and equally so for their native land - Poland.</p>
   <p>Polish youth! Join with us; step into the ranks of the singers and let Polish song ennoble us; let mutual work in Polish song place us everywhere on the same plane with other nations here in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
