<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-11">Nov. 11, 1914</date><title level="a">We and the Americans</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-11">Nov. 11, 1914</date><title level="a">WE AND THE AMERICANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the outbreak of the European War, erudite and profound articles have frequently appeared in the American press on the subject of Poland's future. These articles indicate such sincerity, such a sympathetic and honest evaluation of our situation, that we could not expect a more favorable attitude even from the Polish-American press.</p>
   <p>"A miracle has happened," one of our "authorities" on American conditions writes, "that the cold Yankees, these notorious exploiters of the Polish immigrant, should write about Poland with such sincerity!"</p>
   <p>"A miracle has occurred," another cries, "that these ignorant people, who have only a vague idea of the geography of the politically existing countries, <pb facs="5423968_8_0517.jpg" n="2"/>should be so well acquainted with the geography and history of politically nonexistent Poland!"</p>
   <p>Many such remarks are being voiced at the present critical moment within the ranks of those Poles who are ceaselessly discussing America--all of them empty and unfounded chatter, dictated by European rather than Polish patriotism,</p>
   <p>In the United States one can criticize certain faults in the social conditions, in the police system, and in captialism, which is running riot; but an intelligent person cannot accuse those whom he does not know, and to whom he is not even allowed access, of ignorance and lack of good will.</p>
   <p>It is exactly these unapproachable Americans--who jealously guard the circle of their most intimate friends--that we intend to write a few words about today.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0518.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is they who are responsible for the favorable remarks about our homeland, not the millionaires, the ward politicians, the factory forman, or the propagandist of American chauvinism.</p>
   <p>It is no miracle that we find favorable comments on Poland in the American press, nor is it a miracle that the authors of these articles are acquainted with the history of the martyr of nations. But it is a "miracle," an unpleasant and shameful miracle, that these Americans show themselves better disposed toward Poland than many of her own sons.</p>
   <p>While American publications print discussions of Poland written from a general humanitarian standpoint, we so not even want to recognize her as a firmly united nation, but, divided into parties, each of us wants to reconstruct this poor Poland according to his own plan.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0519.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Americans assert the historical necessity of Poland's resurrection, and although they are divided in their opinions regarding the Germans, they are unanimous in declaring that Poland can benefit only by the victory of the Allies. Yet, we blunder like a flock of lost sheep, unable to accept even the one clear and simple idea. "Poland is a great thing--greater even than this or that party."</p>
   <p>While Americans appreciate Polish self-sufficiency and peculiar nationalism, and unanimously declare themselves against depriving us of our rights to freedom and independence for Poland, we are becoming Americanized in spirit, denying our language, becoming ashamed of belonging to the Polish group, licking the boots of the American mob, and tossing nickels for the cause of Poland.</p>
   <p>Instead of lifting our heads with pride, giving the chauvinist a lesson, pointing to the favorable articles on Poland in the American press, and leaning on that <pb facs="5423968_8_0520.jpg" n="5"/>honest and noble strata of American society which without our pleading will take Poland's side at a critical moment,we are ashamed of the sound of Polish names and are willing to perform the most menial service to gain a dollar.</p>
   <p>Where do we think this sort of politics will get us? Will denying our homeland, which even Americans recognize, gain us the recognition and respect of these Americans?</p>
   <p>No! These Americans who write about Poland and deliberate over Poland's lot are apt to hurl in the teeth of the renegades the words "For the others we have respect--for you contempt."</p>
   <p>An American loves his Star-Spangled Banner. He demands absolute respect for this flag. He wants to increase the numbers of its venerators on American soil--but at the same time he is able to understand that the flag with the white eagle on a red field can be equally dear and worthy of respect to the Pole. He knows <pb facs="5423968_8_0521.jpg" n="6"/>that this flag has been torn, stamped upon, and profaned. For this reason he wants it to be put together again and to come to the fore of this nation which suffering could not crush, whose soul despite the Styx-like mire, was able to emerge pure, free, and independent.</p>
   <p>Let us learn from the Americans how to love our flag. Let us learn how to respect the White Eagle. Let us not deny our languate and our names. Then we shall deserve not only the favorable articles that are being published in this country, but the respect and support of the Americans.</p>
   <p>Today one must not be two-faced. One must not be a Pole at the meeting of a Polish society and a German, an American, or a Swede (depending on the nationality of one's customer or elector) at a political rally or in business. One must definitely decide to be on one side or the other. One must, finally, decide to give active support to resurrecting Poland.</p>
   <p>A Pole who is an American Citizen should respect the laws and customs here and should work for the good of the country which gives him political freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0522.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>But he must not forget that the country of his origin was Poland and that he owes it everything.</p>
   <p>He who does not regard Poland as his homeland should not force his way into Polish society. Let him be whatever he wants to be for "business" reasons,but do not let him be a Pole because such people at present are revolting even to Americans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
