<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-02-26">Feb. 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish National Alliance Youth Excursion to Poland</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0826</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0826.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-02-26">Feb. 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE YOUTH EXCURSION TO POLAND</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This year's excursion to Poland, though predominantly for the Alliance youth and members, is opened, like all other Alliance public enterprises, also for all other Poles who would like to join that great educational undertaking.</p>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that America is famous throughout the world for her practical learning, which is more useful than all theories. Emulating this example shown by the Americans, the Allianoe's educational department wants to give the native Polish youth the opportunity to learn all about Poland in the best, that is the most practical, way.</p>
   <p>The visiting of Poland, the country of our ancestors, and the two months' sojourn in a typical Polish atmosphere since the moment of embarking on board of a Polish ship until the time of landing again on the American soil, is truly the most practical way of learning everything about the Polish ways of life. It is a greater, deeper and more effective way than many years' study of books about Poland. Beautiful as these books may be, they necessarily can give only a cold, theoretical knowledge of our native country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0827.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is superfluous to write extensively of the nationalistic influence, derived from such an excursion, because that influence is known and acknowledged by all immigration groups, which want to keep up the spiritual tie with their native countries. For that reason they travel with their youth to their home hearths. Such excursions are undertaken by the American-Germans, the French, the Italians, the Scandinavians, the Belgians, the Czechs and others. And our Poland, in the geographical radius of her possibilities, extends every year her hospitality to crowds of such vacational excursionists, who with every year are becoming more and more numerous. These young people are taken to Poland from Bohemia, Germany and France, because the contact of a foreign born Polish child with the holy land of its ancestors brings about in its soul a miraculous transformation. Like that mythical Greek, Antheus, who by only touching the earth was regaining his strength in a mortal combat, so also the emigrant child, by visiting Poland, by beholding her ancient memorials and monuments of fame, and by breathing the air of the million-peopled Polish center, inhales and imbibes into itself that miraculous national power, which will remain in the child and some day will develop into something immortal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0828.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Alliance's educational department knows it and, therefore, it works indefatigably in that direction, and expects that with the cooperation of the parents and of the youth the excursion will be a complete success.</p>
   <p>The departure from New York on the Polish steamship Polonia will be on July 2, and the return to New York on the same ship will be on September 2. The entire time of the excursion will last, therefore, two months. The sea voyage from New York to Gdynia and return will take twenty-four days, while thirty-nine days will be spent on visiting Poland - on seeing, understanding and learning everything whatever in Poland is most beautiful and best.</p>
   <p>On the diligently worked out program for the travel in Poland there are placed among other cities the following: Poznan, Zakopane, Krakow, Wieliczka, Lwow, Wilno, Warszawa and Gdynia; at this last repose there will be spent seven days in the camp on the seashore belonging to Poland.</p>
   <p>From this can be seen that the approaching excursion to the land of our ancestors is far-reaching in importance for Poland, for the future of Polish immigrants and for the prestige of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
