<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-07-01">July 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Citizenship</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0534</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0534.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-07-01">July 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CITIZENSHIP</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of our countrymen came to our editor and complained that a judge refused him citizenship, because he did not have qualified witnesses. Upon examination by the clerk of these witnesses, it was found that they could not answer the questions correctly. At first the witnesses stated that they have known the applicant for a period of five years; however by further questioning it was revealed that it was less than two years. These discrepancies caused the refusal of citizenship. In order to secure citizenship, our countrymen must bring new witnesses who have known him for at least a period of five years.</p>
   <p>For the benefit of protecting others, we point to the above facts, in order that anyone applying for citizenship, whether it be the first or second papers, should have witnesses who have known him for many years, and who at the same time would give honest replies to questions asked by the judge or clerk. At <pb facs="5423968_8_0535.jpg" n="2"/>the present time it is very difficult to obtain citizenship papers, especially in the state of Illinois, where an applicant is examined very thoroughly by the court clerk and the federal clerk at the post-office and finally before a judge. Therefore, it is necessary to give identical answers; do not withhold anything and speak the truth, because a lie will be found out, and liars cannot become citizens of this country.</p>
   <p>Any foreigner who has been residing in this country for a full period of five years, and who has had his first citizenship papers for two years, can become a citizen, if he is capable of answering questions asked by the clerk or judge. If you want to apply for citizenship, you must observe the following rules:</p>
   <p>1... Bring along two witnesses, preferably American born; if your witnesses are naturalized citizens, they must bring along their final citizenship papers.</p>
   <p>2... Give your name, date of birth, the ages of all your children, and the names of the places where they were born.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0536.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>3... Give the name of your wife, and the place and date of her birth.</p>
   <p>4... Tell from which port in Europe you had sailed.</p>
   <p>5... Tell the name of the ship on which you arrived in America.</p>
   <p>6... Give the year, month and day of your departure from your native land.</p>
   <p>7... Give the year, month and day of your arrival in the United States.</p>
   <p>8... You must know, that an anarchist is a person dis-owned by every nation and he cannot become a citizen of this country.</p>
   <p>9... You must know that a polygamist is a person who has more than one wife or husband at one time and that this is prohibited in the United States by law.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0537.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>10... You must know, that the United States has an organized government with laws and office holders, who govern and enforce these laws, and to be a good citizen you must help the United States in upholding these laws and must not break them.</p>
   <p>Our press is issuing a special pamphlet, in which you will find all these laws and regulations; it contains in the English language, questions which are asked by the judge and the answers to these questions. If you desire to become a citizen of this country, you may have this pamphlet for the asking.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
