<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-29">Jan. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">To P. N. A. Groups, Communes and Districts Regarding the Membership Contest</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0835</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0835.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-01-29">Jan. 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">TO P. N. A. GROUPS, COMMUNES AND DISTRICTS REGARDING THE MEMBERSHIP CONTEST</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Brothers and Sisters:-</p>
   <p>The Golden Jubilee membership contest of 1930 has splendidly fulfilled its purpose not only by adding to the ranks of the Polish National Alliance (P. N. A.) over 40,000 new members, but also by giving rise to numerous improvements in our organization, which since the year 1931 enters into the period of its second semi-centennial. It does so under conditions and circumstances much more favorable than were those fifty years ago, when the pioneers of the Polish National Alliance were inaugurating their great work among the early Polish immigrants, numbering then scarcely 50,000.</p>
   <p>While in the first semi-centennial our chief purpose was to help Poland regain her independence, in the just opened period of the second semi-centennial of the existence of our organization we will endeavor mostly to guard and to preserve the national spirit among Polish immigrants. This our new national policy will be more concretely shaped by our next Sejm, <pb facs="5423968_8_0836.jpg" n="2"/>or National Convention, to be held in the second half of this year, at Scranton, Pa. We extend, until that time, the jubilee membership contest in order not only to attain the originally desired 50,000 jubilee new membership quota by the time the next Sejm convenes, but also to give new workers an opportunity to be honorably cited before the convention Forum as the pioneers of the second semi-centennial in the history of our organization. Those who will enlist at least fifty new members will be thus cited. This pre-convention membership contest gives some facilities and opportunities also for those who want to send their children or go themselves with this year's Youth excursion to Poland under the auspices of the P. N. A. educational department.</p>
   <p>Brothers and Sisters! In this important moment of inaugurating a new semi-centennial may there fully be realized that heart's desire of our chairman, Mr. Jan Romaszkiewicz, to attain for our organization 50,000 new members before the time of our next national convention (Sejm).</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance Central Board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
