<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-19">May 19, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Erasmus Jerzmanowski Makes a Donation to Polish League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-19">May 19, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">ERASMUS JERZMANOWSKI MAKES A DONATION TO POLISH LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That Erasmus Jerzmanowski will be a capable and energetic president of the newly founded Polish League in Chicago, that he sees in it a future for the Polish people in America, and that he is willing to work for it ardently and sincerely may be proved by a beautifully worded letter which he sent to Peter Kiolbassa, the treasurer of the League.</p>
   <p>The letter reads as follows.</p>
   <p>"New York City, May 18, 1894.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Peter Kiolbassa,</p>
   <p>"Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>"Leaving American shores, I am bidding you and all my countrymen farewell. I accepted the office of president of the Polish League because I was convinced that the League would promote unity and harmony among the Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1622.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Those who did not join the League also love their motherland as we do; they differ from us only in their viewpoint, and they also desire to liberate our unfortunate country, only by a different means. The aim is the same. Time will unite us all. I beg you gentlemen to be indulgent, to respect the opinions of others, and patriotism will do the rest.</p>
   <p>"Upon my return I will plunge into the work of the League with enthusiasm, and with the co-operation of my colleagues, will see to it that the Polish League has a prominent place in our society.</p>
   <p>"I am sending twelve cents as my yearly assessment for the Polish National Fund, and an additional five hundred dollars as a contribution to the Fund. I also enclose two hundred and fifty dollars for administrative expenses of the Polish League. Thus the sum enclosed is $750.12.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1623.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I wish you and my countrymen success.</p>
   <p>"Yours very truly,</p>
   <p>"E. J. Jerzmanowski."</p>
   <p>A check for $750.12 was pinned to this letter.</p>
   <p>The letter speaks for itself. It shows the attitude of Erasmus Jerzmanowski toward the League and the attitude that every true Pole should have. We do not wish to interfere with anyone's mode of life, but we believe in working honestly for our motherland in the way we think is best.</p>
   <p>The only proper way to close this article is to write:</p>
   <p>Long live the Polish League and the Polish National Fund! Long live Jerzmanowski!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
