<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-14">Nov. 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Erroneous Conception of Organization Work</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-14">Nov. 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ERRONEOUS CONCEPTION OF ORGANIZATION WORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. W. Koniuszewski, a member of the so-called "Clean Press", sent an article to the Polish dailies and weeklies in America that belong to his faction. In this article, bearing the caption "Work Within Organizations", the author displays utter ignorance of the actual internal workings of the Polish organizations in America, and leads us to suspect that he does not belong to any of these organizations, and has never taken part in their work, internal or external; if he does belong to any organization, it is probably one in which nothing is done for the Polish masses in America or for the mother country.</p>
   <p>We would not have paid much attention to this article had it been published in only one publication, but since many papers have printed it, and many readers may thus have been misled, we wish to utter here a few words of explanation as to what actually goes on in such organizations as, for instance, the Polish <pb facs="5423968_8_1250.jpg" n="2"/>National Alliance. We wish to explain what can be done, and what cannot be done in spite of the very best of intentions....</p>
   <p>The author of the article "Work Within Organizations", makes in one section this remark: "Every organization, should be, first of all, a bulwark of Polish nationalism, a temple of the national spirit, a school of civic sentiments. Other matters should be relegated to a secondary position--must be so relegated, if the work of the organization is to produce any actual results."</p>
   <p>What is the Polish National Alliance, if not that which Mr. Koniuszewski wishes Polish organizations to be? After thirty years of hard work, in the face of storms and obstacles which testify to its vitality, the Polish National Alliance here in America is exactly a bulwark of Polish nationalism, a temple of the national spirit, and a school of civic sentiments. Today its radiant motto, "Love of country and brotherly love", reaches everywhere that our brothers are, kindling <pb facs="5423968_8_1251.jpg" n="3"/>the noble flame of nationalistic effort. But one must be in the Alliance, must take part in its work, and in the efforts that it makes to improve the position of our immigrants; one should look through the pages of its history to see why, in the past, it has sometimes been unable to do this or that, and only now is able to convert its ideals into deeds; then one will be convinced that it is really solving its great problems.</p>
   <p>Nationalistic matters always have been and always will be the first concern of the Alliance, and matters of insurance merely serve to draw the masses of our people under the national banner, in order to develop them into good Poles and good citizens. After all, even the insurance department of the Alliance represents, in a way, work for Polish nationalism, because it prevents thousands of our brothers and sisters from joining the ranks of other nationalities, where they would lose their national identity and might even see their hard-earned money go to the tills of our enemies.</p>
   <p>On his article, Mr. Koniuszewski made another ill-advised statement: "The <pb facs="5423968_8_1252.jpg" n="4"/>assembling of fifty thousand members in good standing around an insurance company is not particularly praiseworthy, although one frequently hears about this at all sorts of conventions! How much more deserving is the education of thousands of sincere and enlightened Poles, marching earnestly forward shoulder to shoulder!"</p>
   <p>In our opinion it is not only praiseworthy, but greatly praiseworthy, to assemble not fifty thousand but eighty thousand Polish men and women under one banner, as the Polish National Alliance has done; and its merit will be even greater when it assembles about three million, and inspires them with one thought and one spirit--love for the homeland and its sacred national ideals.</p>
   <p>Today the Alliance is erecting from the foundations a strong and noble edifice; when the structure is completed adornments will gradually be added. We should all, without exception, lend our efforts to the construction of it, we should <pb facs="5423968_8_1253.jpg" n="5"/>stand in the same rank regardless of sex, wealth, opinions, or convictions; then we can strengthen and perfect this only great Polish organization among the immigrants.</p>
   <p>It is not difficult to criticize from the side lines, when one does not feel it his duty to roll up his sleeves and get to work in the building of this structure and the embellishing of it from within and without. Nothing is perfect in this world, and the Alliance may be lacking in this or that. But, since in its purposes it is the best and most noble Polish organization under the sun, all true Poles, men and women, should join it and should march ahead together. The Alliance is not shut up in a shell of partisanship or denominationalism, but is universal and will go along with the current of the times. But it needs people--it must first unite all of us under the banner on which is inscribed, in letters of gold, "Love of country and brotherly love".</p>
   <p>That the Alliance does not perform miracles, because no one can perform them, is not the fault of its purposes or its aims. Great things are accomplished <pb facs="5423968_8_1254.jpg" n="6"/>only after years of experiences, battles, and efforts, and this organization is still young and heading toward a great future. It is progressing with youthful enthusiasm, in the belief that its ideals will embrace all our immigrants, and cement them with unity and brotherhood; then it will perform the great things of which we dream today.</p>
   <p>For its membership of eighty thousand, the Alliance already is doing great and splendid things, of which no other Polish organization in America can boast; and when it takes under its wing all the wanderers in this strange land, then its work, uninterrupted by battles, jealousy, and envy, will be more productive.</p>
   <p>Go, then, all of you, to the Alliance--all of you who today criticize it, but who remain on the sidelines and do not even know what is happening within it, and what sort of work it has undertaken. We need all the strength of numbers and intelligence that we can get, if we are to turn our projects and aims into realities. We must concentrate on achieving numerical strength, because, <pb facs="5423968_8_1255.jpg" n="7"/>through quantity, quality will develop, and because only a large mass numerically will be strong enough to accomplish its aims. The quality of the members of the Alliance today, in contrast with other organizations, speaks to the advantage of our organization, and will be ever more perfect when more of us stand in the same rank, because a crowd is a mighty individual.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
