<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Gen. Joseph Haller in Chicago</title>," <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. II, No. 3,
<date when="1923-11">November 1923</date>,p. 4
<title level="a">[General Haller Visits United States]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0400</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0400.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Gen. Joseph Haller in Chicago</title>," <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. II, No. 3,
<date when="1923-11">November 1923</date>,p. 4
<title level="a">[GENERAL HALLER VISITS UNITED STATES]</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In keeping with the custom inaugaurated by the American Legion, each year at its convention it has some distinguished soldier who helped make history in the World War. The guest of the American Legion this year was the Polish hero, idolized by the people of his country, Poland, General Joseph Haller. This distinction is greatly appreciated by the Americans of Polish blood and ancestry, and has made a great stride in the Legion's Americanization program.</p>
   <p>General Haller's visit to the United States is bound to cement the ties of friendship more closely, for it brings out the similarities of the character of the two peoples, their love of liberty and fair dealing. The general, according to Lt. Commander Savage of the American Legion, urgest his compatriots in the United States to learn the language and customs of this country, and become an integral part of it as good and loyal citizens, professing and maintaining a single, whole and undivided allegiance to this their adopted country.</p>
   <p>He stated in one of his speeches that the United States when it entered the war made the independence of Poland possible, and Poland will ever be grateful to this country <pb facs="5423968_8_0401.jpg" n="2"/>for its espousal of the cause of the New Poland. We, who have been born here, are appreciative of the friendship of our country towards the land of our parents and ancestors, many of whom were denied the privilege of realizing their dream of a free and unshackled Poland.</p>
   <p>General Haller's conception of the duty of his compatriots in America squares with our continually expressed principles of undivided allegiance to these United States We are interested in Poland and her success, but our first duty is here, as it has always been, and we applaud General Haller for his approval of our Americanization policy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
