<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 110,
<date when="1921-12-18">Dec. 18, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Commercial Club in St. Casimir's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0430</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0430.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 110,
<date when="1921-12-18">Dec. 18, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH COMMERCIAL CLUB IN ST. CASIMIR'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>--What is the news in St. Casimir's parish?</p>
   <p>-- All is well, my dear sir. We have organized a Polish commercial club in our parish and we are getting along much better.</p>
   <p>-- What did you do?</p>
   <p>-- We placed at the head of our organization very energetic and educated young men who know their business, and they conduct it for us properly.</p>
   <p>-- This is nice - very nice! I have visited many of our settlements and observed what is going on among us, but I have not seen such solidarity as in your parish.</p>
   <p>-- See? Even politicians bow to us and ask for our support. However, we shall be careful and will not support our enemies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0431.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>-- If only other settlements would follow your example!</p>
   <p>-- They will, my dear sir, they will. Let them wait a short time and see how we will thrash the outsiders and patronize ourselves reciprocally.</p>
   <p>-- How many belong to your club?</p>
   <p>-- Almost all Polish merchants. What do you think? That this is Avondale, where they have three clubs, do nothing and work against their own interests? We go together and I believe that our brothers from Avondale will follow us and elect young men who are more energetic, quicker and not so easily offended, for the managers of their clubs.</p>
   <p>-- Who belongs to the management of the Commercial Club in St. Casimir's parish?</p>
   <p>-- Here they are: Attorney Leon Wachowski, president; Jan Fruzyna, undertaker, vice-president; Ksawery Czastka, banker, secretary; John Paprocki, <pb facs="5423968_8_0432.jpg" n="3"/>druggist, treasurer; also John Klimer, John Dygdon, and Dr. John Luczar, trustees.</p>
   <p>-- Have you many Jewish stores as yet?</p>
   <p>-- There are only five Jewish stores between the boulevard and Kedzie Avenue, and a few Bohemian stores: altogether about 10% of the outsiders.</p>
   <p>-- And now, if you will pardon me, I will ask you an indiscreet question. The Bohemians live on the other side of Kedzie Avenue. Are there five Jewish and a few Polish shops in their settlement?</p>
   <p>-- Hm! Indeed, that is an indiscreet question. As far as I can remember they never had any Jewish or Polish stores. But please do not fret, for we will have the same thing. Rome was not built in a day. But why are you asking such queer questions?</p>
   <p>-- Because I was there and saw their nice stores. I even tried to get some <pb facs="5423968_8_0433.jpg" n="4"/>information but in vain. I am not from "our country." They stick together and that is their good quality. There was among them one Pole who kept a grocery store and prospered. The Bohemians, noticing it, called a meeting and decided not to patronize him. The result was that he was obliged to sell the store for half of its worth.</p>
   <p>We also must adopt their system whether we desire it or not. If that is good for them it must also be good for us. If they will not patronize us we will not patronize them.</p>
   <p>-- It is easy to say but hard to do. You would be surprised how many people frequent the Bohemian stores and the Bohemians laugh at them; they do not ask them if they come from their country.</p>
   <p>-- Our people should patronize each other. If we will do this, the money will stay with us, we will be prosperous and we will be able to employ thousands of people.</p>
   <p>-- And how is the building loan business?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0434.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>-- Our five building loans are progressing wonderfully, but they would progress much better if our people would not go to Bohemians.</p>
   <p>If a Bohemian deposits his money in a Polish bank by mistake, he will draw it out next day. We must learn from the Jews and the Bohemians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
