<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-06">Dec. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Falcons' Resolution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1088</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1088.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-06">Dec. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH FALCONS' RESOLUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Falcons of Chicago, gathered at the Polish Women's Alliance Hall on December 5, at the Council of Nest II, unanimously approved the following:</p>
   <p>1. Considering the heavy, irreparable loss which the Polish nation suffered at the death of its greatest son, Henryk Sienkiewicz, and this at a time when it most needed his great mind and warm heart to shield it from doubt and to guide it toward a brighter future, we have decided, in order to honor the memory of this great Pole, to bend ourselves most earnestly to the spread of Falconry, of which the fundamental aim is to produce in our community exactly those civic virtues for which the late Henryk Sienkiewicz set the highest example.</p>
   <p>2. Faithful to the requirements of our organization, we will obey our rightful authority, for we ourselves have placed it at the helm, believing firmly that it will lead us in these days of terror, chaos, and internal dissension along <pb facs="5423968_8_1089.jpg" n="2"/>the path of duty and honor, under a banner, unsoiled by any faithlessness, of honest love for our motherland.</p>
   <p>3. Recognizing the establishment of a "School for Ensigns" [Szkola Podchorazych] as one of the most certain means of accomplishing the Falcon organization's aims, we appeal to all of our members to work earnestly at collecting contributions toward this fund; at the same time, we must tighten our ranks in order to repel more effectively all attempts to destroy Falcon unity and discipline.</p>
   <p>Long live the united and independent Poland! Long live the one authorized Polish Falcons' Alliance of America!</p>
   <p>Resolution Committee: Henry Setmajer, Henry Lokanski, and Agnes Wisla.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
