<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-10">Jan. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To Command or to Obey</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1074</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1074.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-01-10">Jan. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO COMMAND OR TO OBEY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We were greatly astonished on reading in one of the last issues of the Polish Falcon, organ of the Alliance of Polish Falcons, that the board of directors had decided to call a special convention in Pittsburgh.</p>
   <p>We understand, in a measure, the reasons which prompted the board of directors to issue the decree calling for a special convention. The board of directors evidently wants to put an end once and for all to the disagreements, and to finish with this mania for petty politics exhibited not only by the circuit presidents and group presidents but even by individuals. Action of this sort is unheard of in military societies, and the Falcons consider themselves a military society. If this were the reason for calling a special convention, we might be apt to applaud the idea, although we remember well the decrees of the Buffalo convention, which clearly left <pb facs="5423968_8_1075.jpg" n="2"/>the matter of the policies of the organization to the discretion of the board of directors.</p>
   <p>We are struck, however, as must everyone be who looks upon the Falcon organization in true Falcon spirit, by the note of disharmony in the appeal of the board of directors with the aims and principles of our brother organization.</p>
   <p>The board of directors of the Alliance of Polish Falcons summons delegates of the Alliance groups to a special convention in order to define the political policies which the Falcons should pursue.</p>
   <p>We therefore ask, by what authority can this be done? We have considered and continue to consider that when the Falcons serve the country as ordinary citizens, they cannot issue orders to the people in general nor seek any special authority for themselves, but should and must place themselves under the orders of those who are authorized to make decisions for the people in general. If, on the other hand, the Falcons were to take up arms in order to defend those who formerly <pb facs="5423968_8_1076.jpg" n="3"/>deliberated over the good of this nation, in that case the positions would be reversed and every citizen would place himself completely under the will and command of the military leaders, obeying not only their orders but also their intelligent directions.</p>
   <p>An army does not play politics in peace time, but trains and prepares for war. That is how things are and should be with the Alliance of Polish Falcons. We today want to look upon the Falcons as the peace-time mobilization of our forces here among the emigres, as our advance guard, which does not play at politics but sees to the training and development of its forces. In accordance with the suggestions of the board of directors, it should develop these forces to their maximum efficiency, and prepare them for the time when the nation will need them.</p>
   <p>The board of directors, and it alone, is responsible for the work of the entire organization, and it alone can decide on matters of this type. Therefore, if in some of the groups there are some individuals who joined <pb facs="5423968_8_1077.jpg" n="4"/>the organization merely for the purpose of playing politics and causing confusion within the ranks of the Falcons, and if these individuals persist in being deaf to all admonitions, they ought to be dropped from the organization. "It is better that we number only a thousand men, but good ones."</p>
   <p>In addition we would like to ask the board of directors who, even at the special convention, will have the authority to decide the proper direction the Falcons should follow, since at present it is difficult to obtain true information and directions from the homeland. Even those who have access to the sources cannot orient themselves in the situation, and although in their opinion they proceed along the right road, according to the opinions of others they are making grave mistakes. Can the ordinary delegate to the convention, who usually is uninformed, uncritical, and without a proper background for and acquaintance with national problems, be a good judge in matters which befuddle the minds of trained and experienced politicians?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1078.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>You will reply that a majority decides these matters, that one person may be wrong but that a majority will always find the right road. This answer is quite right. If, however, we are to follow this axiom, why call a special convention, since a majority of the nation and our own emigrants here have already decided the direction which the work of the Falcons should take? The majority still persists in the same stand which the Falcons had taken at the very beginning, the stand which the Buffalo convention had also taken. This convention clearly defined in its decrees and resolutions the policies which it wished the board of directors to pursue.</p>
   <p>It seems to us, however, that the board of directors itself is vacillating and cannot or does not know how to adhere to this stand because it allows itself to be provoked by a handful of trouble-makers, and gives them the greatest satisfaction by calling a special convention.</p>
   <p>Perhaps we are mistaken in the conclusions which we have drawn, but we are <pb facs="5423968_8_1079.jpg" n="6"/>not mistaken in declaring that a soldier should always obey the orders of the people he serves and not dictate to the people. Our paper has always considered the Polish Falcons soldiers, and wants to continue to look upon them as such.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
