<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-09">Nov. 9, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Publisher of Djabel Found Guilty of Libel--Jailed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0116</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0116.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-09">Nov. 9, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLISHER OF DJABEL FOUND GUILTY OF LIBEL--JAILED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the case against Stanislaus Segers, publisher of the former Djabel (Devil) and the present Kropidlo (Sprinkler), was finally brought to trial before Judge Payne in the Criminal Court.</p>
   <p>Mr. Segers was accused of criminally slandering Andrew Kwasigroch, organist of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish.</p>
   <p>As we know, this case was started last year immediately after Mr. Segers announced in his scandalous organ a sensational story about Mr. Kwasigroch. The article stated that Mr. Kwasigroch had murdered his maid and had been sentenced to three years imprisonment; that through the influence of Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, he had been given a lenient sentence. Naturally, the entire contents of the article was a lie.</p>
   <p>Consequently, A. Kwasigroch, desiring to put an end to the scandalous Djabel, <pb facs="5423968_8_0117.jpg" n="2"/>now Kropidlo, entered suit against Mr. Segers for libel. The case went from one court to another until it reached the Criminal Court.</p>
   <p>The charges were brought forth before Judge Payne by Assistant District Attorney Todd.</p>
   <p>Attorneys for Mr. Kwasigroch were Max Drzemala [also Drezmal] and Davis. Mr. Seegers' attorneys were Max Kaczmarek and Geeting.</p>
   <p>To prove the charges in the case several witnesses, namely, Kwasniewski, Schultz, Klarkowski and Czekala, were questioned, and a copy of the Kropidlo [sic] was also introduced as evidence. The proceedings lasted two days.</p>
   <p>Attornies for the defense contended that the article in the paper was not libelous, that it was directed against some other person, etc. But these arguments were of no avail.</p>
   <p>Yesterday at 4 P.M. the jury, after hearing the speech of the prosecuting attorney <pb facs="5423968_8_0118.jpg" n="3"/>and after receiving instructions from the judge, came to the conclusion that Segers was guilty of criminal libel.</p>
   <p>The fine was set at five hundred dollars or one year in jail, and sentence will be imposed by the judge next week.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, after the verdict was reached, Mr. Segers was arrested. When no one put up bail for him he was taken to prison.</p>
   <p>Mr. Segers' attorneys will ask for a new trial.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
