<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-02-19">Feb. 19, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">People Are Known by Their Deeds (Women's Auxiliary, Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0833</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0833.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Weekly Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1931-02-19">Feb. 19, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLE ARE KNOWN BY THEIR DEEDS (Women's Auxiliary, Editorial.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A proverb says that "A friend in need is a friend indeed."</p>
   <p>The Polish Alliance College has recently become afflicted with painful loss, when the museum and the library of the Alliance College were completely destroyed by a fire.</p>
   <p>The news of that conflagration has evoked in the hearts of true Alliance members a deep sorrow, but at the same time it has awakened in them the consciousness that there should be hastened help to erect as soon as possible a new school edifice.</p>
   <p>To rebuild the Alliance school - that palpable proof of our culture, that institution which keeps watch over our national feelings - has now become the slogan that resounds in the hearts of all those who truly love their organization. And that watchword has already been turned into deed by liberal donations for the restoring of the Alliance school.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0834.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That deed will be sustained and enlarged by all Alliance groups and communes, and by individual men and women members who understand that we are not allowed to retreat, for we would give thereby a very sad testimony to our mental maturity.</p>
   <p>In spite of the present economic crisis, there will be found many in our community, who will be able to place larger or smaller sums on the altar of education. All, without exception, should participate in the work of restoration.</p>
   <p>Guided by good will we may give the matter such a turn that there will be no need for the future Sejm to resolve upon funds to be assigned for the rebuilding of the school and the museum; we may stand before that Sejm with a cordial gift in our hands.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
