<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-08-07">Aug. 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">First Quarterly Report of the Polish League in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1581</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1581.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-08-07">Aug. 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST QUARTERLY REPORT OF THE POLISH LEAGUE IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The secretary of the Polish League in America has submitted his first report on the activities and development of the Polish League for the first two and a half months. The report was road at a meeting of directors, hold on August 1, 1894. It reads as follows.</p>
   <p>As this report will also be published in the newspapers, I have decided to add to the dry figures a few explanatory remarks, because I think they will interest the friends of the League and explain to the members and the public the functions of the League, and activities of its central board of directors; this in my opinion, is necessary for and understanding of the report.</p>
   <p>This is the first quarterly report. It is quite true that this first quarter does not contain three full months, but this does not matter, where mathematical exactness is not necessary, for there are four quarters in a year, and four reports may be prepared, if necessary. The object of this report is to acquaint <pb facs="5423968_8_1582.jpg" n="2"/>the public with the activities of the League and the task that lies before its administration.</p>
   <p>The Polish League's first quarter marks its struggle for existence, and the circumstances made it so that it was a true fight for existence, for we all know that we were not without enemies from the very beginning. It was, at the same time, a period of preliminary work or, may I say, a period of formation. It is true that a Polish mass meeting has outlined the object and functions of the League and the duties of the central board and its respective members, but the working out of the details was left to the central board of directors. There were also great difficulties to evercome, which hindered progress.</p>
   <p>To these difficulties belonged, besides the bitter and tiring fight with the opponents of the League who fought it stubbornly at every opportunity, the further circumstance that the central beard could not meet for frequent consultations. I am taking this matter up in order that the next mass meeting, <pb facs="5423968_8_1583.jpg" n="3"/>or the next convention of the Polish League, may take it under consideration and make necessary adjustments. The members of the central board of the Polish League perform their duties gratuitously, and as every official usually has his own occupation, and must work hard for his daily bread, he can not devote so much time to public matters as is required by such a large organization as the Polish League. And the circumstance that almost every member of the control beard lives in a different locality or in a different city--quite often at a great distance--makes it so much the harder. Holding conferences under these circumstances therefore entails great expense and loss of time, and for the board members to act independently without mutual understanding is an impassibility; correspondence as a means of handling business affairs, is not satisfactory. The League has no funds for traveling expenses, because the mass meeting did not provide for this item; under such circumstances, holding frequent meeting is an impossibility. Another contributing factor is the absence of the president of the League, who is still in Europe, and the unfortunate circumstance that a few members of the League were unable to fulfill their duties on account of sickness or business.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1584.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Despite these and other difficulties, the League has made good progress during this first quarter.</p>
   <p>The League has with great enthusiasm throughout the United States in spite of the loud noise and quiet (but dangerous) intrigues of its enemies.</p>
   <p>During the first few weeks, many persons from different localities, and a number of societies, applied to the secretary for membership; donations also were sent This first (pardon my expression!) impetuous movement was rather dangerous, because necessary order could not be established, and it might have caused misunderstanding. Misunderstanding was possible because, at the mass meeting, the meaning of the Polish National Fund, guarded by the League, was defined, but the public, filled with enthusiasm for the League and not realizing that it had not yet begun to function, flocked to it as if it were am ideal organization for which we had beam longing for some time. The secretary of the League dared not chock this movement; on the contrary, he encouraged it by frequent <pb facs="5423968_8_1585.jpg" n="5"/>appeals until it was possible for the members of the board of directors to held a conference, on June 6, at which the rules and regulations for organizing agencies, and other important bylaws which will regulate all functions of the organization, were adopted.</p>
   <p>After loud manifestations, which were a benefit to the League, and after the first meeting of the members of the central board of directors, a quiet but effective work began.</p>
   <p>The work began, not publicly in the newspapers, but by correspondence. The clamors of the opponents quieted down a little, which enabled us to work in peace. From that time, the secretary sent out more than seven hundred circulars containing instructions for the agencies and appeals to the public; he also sent sixty-two official letters containing matter relative to administration, and two hundred and forty-one letters, concerning the League's problems, to persons who either worked part time for the League or whom we wish to win to the cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1586.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Our work brought the following result:</p>
   <p>The League has members in twelve states: California, Illinois, Indiana, Maryland, Wisconsin, Nebraska, New Jersey, New York, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Texas, and Missouri. There are applications for membership from the State of Michigan, but so far there are no agencies or members there. Activities will begin there in a short time.</p>
   <p>In these twelve states there are thirty localities in which the League has individual members and societies. The League has only six agencies, but many more are being organized.</p>
   <p>From those thirty localities, thirty societies joined the League. However, I cannot submit the exact number of members of those societies or agencies, because the secretaries have not sent complete reports, but the reports on hand indicate that fourteen of these societies have seven hundred and seventeen members.</p>
   <p>There are seven hundred and eighty-seven independent members who do not belong <pb facs="5423968_8_1587.jpg" n="7"/>to any society. These members joined the League themselves, and promised to pay the regular dues to the League, and to the Polish National Fund in America.</p>
   <p>According to the reports, three thousand persons are paying regular special assessments to the Polish National Fund in America.</p>
   <p>The following agencies of the Polish League have been organized and are active:</p>
   <p>Agency No. 1, at St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish in Chicago: L. Szopinski, president; Thomas Krolik, collector; Boleslaus Klarkowski, secretary.</p>
   <p>Agency No. 2, at St. Adalbert's Parish in Chicago: K. J. Bielnski, president; Joseph Napieralski, chief collector; Lucian Jastrzebski, secretary.</p>
   <p>Agency No. 3, in Mill Creek, Wisconsin: Reverend Jachinski, president; [?] Szczesny, collector; Slowinski, secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1588.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Agency No. 4, at St. Hyacinth Parish in Milwaukee, Wisconsin: Ignace Gorski, president; Theedore Sebolewski, secretary; John Demagalski, collector.</p>
   <p>Agency No. 5, in Toledo, Ohio: Anthony Szyperski, president; Stanislaus Schlesser, collector; August Kasprzak, secretary.</p>
   <p>Agency No. 6, in Posen, Wisconsin: J. Bogumil, president; J. Samolowski, collector; F. Jasinski, secretary.</p>
   <p>I am submitting a financial report. However, I wish to remark that this report is not complete, because most of the societies and agencies have not sent their reports. The "common fund," or the money sent to the League without a designation, will be apportioned between the Polish National Fund and the League by the trustees of the Fund, because the donors did not specify to which fund their gifts should be credited.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1589.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Here is the financial statement:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Polish National Fund</cell>
     <cell>$ 689.61</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Polish League</cell>
     <cell>444.42</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the common fund</cell>
     <cell>18.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$1,152.43</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Expenses to date:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Miscellaneous expenses</cell>
     <cell>$ 64.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Drawing of bonds</cell>
     <cell>23.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Office [rent]</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Smulski's Printing Shop</cell>
     <cell>43.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. J. Migdalski's Printing Shop</cell>
     <cell>21.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Badges for the Polish mass meeting</cell>
     <cell>60.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Charter for the Polish League</cell>
     <cell>6.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$242.75</cell>
    </row>
    <pb facs="5423968_8_1590.jpg" n="10"/>
   </table>
   <p>The miscellaneous expenses are as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Paper for temporary record books</cell>
     <cell>$ 2.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Postage, telegrams, etc</cell>
     <cell>16.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Office expense for the month of June</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Polish Publishing Company</cell>
     <cell>20.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$ 64.25</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Printing jobs were divided among three printing shops, namely: Gazeta Katolicka, J. J. Migdalski Printing Shop, and the Polish Publishing Company. The first printed ten thousand copies of the constitution of the Polish League in America ($43.00); the second printed the stationary ($21.00); the third printed one thousand copies of instruction for the agencies, one thousand appeals to the Poles, one thousand letters to citizens asking for co-operation in organizing agencies, and five thousand five hundred receipt blanks ($20.00).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1591.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>After paying these bills, for which checks have been drawn, the books will show the following balance:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>The Polish National Fund</cell>
     <cell>$ 689.61</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>The Polish League in America</cell>
     <cell>201.67</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Common Fund</cell>
     <cell>18.40</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$909.68</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>In reality, this sum is the property of the Polish League, as are the funds held by collectors of agencies and treasurers of societies.</p>
   <p>This report will be concluded next week, when I will present the plan of the central board of directors for the next quarter.</p>
   <p>Newspapers favorable toward the League are asked very kindly to reprint this report.</p>
   <p>Stanislaus Szwajkart,</p>
   <p>Secretary of the Polish League in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
