<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-10-13">Oct. 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Judge [Thomas] F. Scully's Opinion on the Registration of Poles</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0495</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0495.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-10-13">Oct. 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE [THOMAS] F. SCULLY'S OPINION ON THE REGISTRATION OF POLES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As some of our people know from past experience, the election judges and clerks in some of the Chicago precincts have made matters difficult for the Polish people who have come to register. This has been especially true in precincts presided over by Irish, Jewish, and German election officials. These officials refused to register our people as Poles, insisting that Poles were to be registered as Germans, Austrians, or Russians, according to the part of occupied Poland where they were born.</p>
   <p>Some of the Polish voters have complained to Judge Scully about this abuse on the part of politicians and chauvinists. The judge, who became very indignant after hearing the complaints, ordered these officials to register the Poles as Poles. One of Judge Scully's letters reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"October 11, 1916</p>
   <p>"Henry Schulenberg,</p>
   <p>1501 Milwaukee Avenue,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0496.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Dear Sir: My attention has been called to the fact that in your registration precinct, when people applied for registration and gave Poland as their birthplace, you subjected them to examination as to what part of Poland they were born in. This is unnecessary--when they said they were born in Poland that was sufficient. Enter in your register 'Poland.'</p>
   <p>Very truly yours,</p>
   <p>Thomas F. Scully,</p>
   <p>County Judge"</p>
   <p>It seems that the chauvinists and enemies of our people have been taught a little lesson. It is hoped that they will follow the Judge's orders or else be punished in a more drastic manner--by imprisonment.</p>
   <p>Polish-American citizens are urged to register as Poles, without specifying the part of Poland they came from. The election clerks have to register our people as natives of Poland, and the word "Poland" should appear in their records. We have recourse to the courts here in America, and will not allow people of any other nationality to push us around.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
