<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-03-21">March 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">A New Polish Settlement in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0582</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0582.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-03-21">March 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW POLISH SETTLEMENT IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the south side, in a section called Town of Lake, a new Polish settlement is forming. This settlement is growing so rapidly that in a short time it will equal any large Polish community in number of inhabitants, dwellings and commercial enterprises. This development is uniting in a circle of Polish element around the foul smelling Chicago stock yards. In this part of Town of Lake the Poles have crossed So. Ashland Ave. and are moving east toward Halsted St. To the north they have expanded to St. Peter and Paul Polish Parish, which centers at 38th and So. Paulina Sts. This group of Polish settlers, surrounds the largest meat industry in the world.</p>
   <p>The stock yards district embraces four Polish parishes and is inhabited by about 75,000, people, of Polish extraction. The stock yards district is dirtier than any other part of Chicago, and the stench is terrible, but because there is plenty of work and food, the people do not mind that. Many recreational activities are also in evidence, in spite of the fact that the sun's rays seldom penetrate the heavy atmosphere, and the fresh breezes from distant fields and meadows are rare in that locality. The new Saint Peter and Paul school is almost complete and will be ready for service in a short time. Business is very good in this community. New stores are being opened daily. However, here as elsewhere, saloons are too numerous.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
