<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-05">Oct. 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">High Tariff in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0783</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0783.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-05">Oct. 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">HIGH TARIFF IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Russia and other European countries suffer from a plague which has already taken a heavy toll in human lives. [Translator's note: Reference here is made to the then rampant cholera, typhoid, small pox, etc.] The people in America have also been touched by a plague, which, although not as lethal as that of Europe, is equally paralyzing to economic conditions. The pestilences referred to in this instance are the dishonest trusts, their self-centered management, and the previously unheard-of high cost of living caused by them. Every working man yields eventually under its unbearable weight; he is unable to purchase necessities for his family. The protective tariff rate, the Payne-Aldrich tariff, adopted last year by the Congress of the United States, is one of the reasons, if not the sole reason, for the high cost of living--of acquiring even the immediate necessities of life. It was termed "protective" because it supposedly protects national trade and <pb facs="5423968_8_0784.jpg" n="2"/>commerce. Actually, it is protective in the sense that it safeguards the interests of the few individuals, who, through their political influence, caused the adoption of this measure.</p>
   <p>It has been proved conclusively, by concrete examples, that the Payne-Aldrich tariff imposes a rate as high as 105 per cent of the actual value on imported articles. These are not articles of luxury, such as furs, diamonds, and other items of like nature; the high tariff is placed upon such items as sugar, glassware, tinware, metalware, stockings, blankets, flannel, wool, and the like.</p>
   <p>Should not the tariff rate therefore be blamed for this postilential high cost of living, which affects each of us? We have enumerated but a few of the items of almost daily use. But how many articles are there without which we cannot dispense and for which we are compelled to overpay because of this high tariff? What about meat and other consumable items! The figures presented as illustrations have been extracted from official reports and there cannot be the slightest doubt as to their authenticity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0785.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We believe it because we feel it upon our own hides, to use the vernacular. "But," some will say, "what can we do about it?" It is exactly here that this newspaper replies to our fellow citizens of this republic, to those who have the right of suffrage. Thus we know that the elections for various offices are in the offing. We shall find candidates aspiring for positions as representatives to Congress. These aspirants, like others, will, in the near future, conduct energetic campaigns in their behalf. Let our compatriot citizens interrogate these candidates as to their views on the Payne-Aldrich Tariff Act. Let them make recommendations to the candidates, if any of them are opposed to this act in principle, and endeavor to bring about a congressional revision of this tariff in behalf of the demands made by the working people. Only those should be elected representatives to Congress who, besides possessing other qualifications, are confirmed opponents of the present high tariff rate. It is hoped that through such measures the high cost of living can be controlled, which now continues to increase with each day and is becoming a veritable plague to the less wealthy people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
