<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-11-09">Nov. 9, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Officials Hold Conference</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-11-09">Nov. 9, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">OFFICIALS HOLD CONFERENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of the Central Board of the Polish League in the United States held a monthly meeting last Wednesday, at 7 P.M., in Dziennik Chicagoski's office. At this meeting several important problems were settled. The secretary read the resignation of the president of the League, Mr. Erasmus J. Jerzmanowski, which was addressed to him. It reads: "New York, October 30, 1894.</p>
   <p>"To the Central Board of the Polish League in Chicago.</p>
   <p>"Because of reasons beyond my control, I hereby tender my resignation as president of the Polish League.</p>
   <p>"Wishing you success, I remain,</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>E. J. Jerzmanowski"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1568.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The resignation was accepted, and thereupon it was decided that Mr. Joseph Napieralski, first vice-president of the League, be the president until the next convention Mr. Michael Kruszka, second vice-president, became first vice-president.</p>
   <p>Subsequently, committees were appointed to organize educational and welfare departments and prepare plans for their functioning, the latter to be submitted at the next convention for deliberation.</p>
   <p>As to the committees, it was decided that they should consist of nine members appointed by the president. It was agreed, for practical purposes, that all members of the League's Educational Department Committee be chosen from League members residing in Chicago, and that all or most of the members of the Welfare Department Committee be chosen from residents of Milwaukee, Wisconsin.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1569.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Pursuant to these decisions, the president made the following appointments:</p>
   <p>Educational Department Committee: Reverend E. Siedlaczek, chairman; Reverend John Kasprzycki; also, S. Zahajkiewicz, Ignace Kowalski, Leon Szopinski, Henry Nagiel, N. L. Piotrowski, Andrew Kwasigroch, and Peter Ligman.</p>
   <p>Welfare Department Committee: Dr. Julian Czapka, chairman; Peter Kiolbassa; and Clement Belinski of Chicago. The other seven members are residents of Milwaukee.</p>
   <p>Both the Educational Department and the Welfare Department committees will hold their meetings in Chicago on the dates and at the locations designated by their chairmen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
