<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Oases</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. Kmieciak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-01-15">Jan. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR OASES</title><title level="a" type="sub">by M. Kmieciak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Deprived of our liberty, driven from our ancestral land, we took a bit of the soil of our homeland as a talisman and went out into the world in search of bread and freedom; here, under the Star-Spangled Banner, we found both. But bread and freedom of speech is not all that a man needs for life.</p>
   <p>Surrounded by foreign and, often, not very friendly elements in the factories and in the Pennsylvania coal mines, we felt like pilgrims in a sandstorm, searching for an oasis at which to quench our burning thirst and to draw strength for continuance of the journey, for further struggle with the elements, in order that we should not fall victims to their fury.</p>
   <p>No one worried about us, no one understood us, no one tried to become better <pb facs="5423968_8_0471.jpg" n="2"/>acquainted with us and lend us a helping hand when we needed it.</p>
   <p>In the midst of other, well-organized national groups, we felt that, unless we had some source of spiritual comfort, we must disintegrate; we felt that we could not survive against our false friends, the Irish and the Germans, who sought to trip us up at every step, lest the more patriotic American society come to know us better and lend us a fraternal hand in our struggle.</p>
   <p>Amid such difficult conditions, we banded together, we organized, and we considered ways and means of preserving the ideals for which we struggled, of preserving our race here, that it might one day help to burst the bonds of slavery in which our homeland languished.</p>
   <p>We organized, and our organizations were real oases scattered throughout this vast country; but there was still a lack. We lacked literature, we lacked newspapers, and these we had to create in order that, with their help, the scattered groups might be tied together by the thread of brotherly <pb facs="5423968_8_0472.jpg" n="3"/>love, and in order that they might be urged to co-operate in a definite program of work.</p>
   <p>All honor to those--living and dead--who formulated that program. All honor to the editors and publishers, living and dead, who gave us the first Polish newspapers--the newspapers that gave this program to their readers and thus contributed to a great accomplishment--the founding of the Polish National Alliance and its publications.</p>
   <p>What trials the Alliance and its publications passed through, need no longer be discussed; let us draw the curtain on the past and on all that we suffered in defense of our program; for today that program has triumphed, having won the support of the entire Polish element in the United States. The [Polish] National Committee, consisting of representatives of all Polish organizations, the patriotic clergy, and all of our patriotic newspapers, stands as a symbol of brotherhood, unity, and harmony to the Poles in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0473.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On the tenth anniversary of the founding of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, we should be happy; for thirty years ago, whenever two or three Alliance members met, their desire for Poland's freedom formed a natural bond between them; today, as a result of perseverance, not only the Poles, but all the Allies have raised the cry: "Drive the Germans from Polish soil!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
