<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1921-09-07">September 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Whose Fault Is It?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1921-09-07">September 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WHOSE FAULT IS IT?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A young girl was caught stealing, in a large department store. She stole an article worth only a few cents. She stood with bowed head and shamed face, answering questions demurely</p>
   <p>Ques. - Did you steal? Ans. - Yes.</p>
   <p>Ques. - Do you know what you did? Ans. - Yes.</p>
   <p>Ques. - Do you know what is awaiting you? Ans.-Yes.</p>
   <p>Ques. - Why did you do it? Ans. - Silence.</p>
   <p>Ques. - How old are you? Ans. - Thirteen years.</p>
   <p>Ques. - Have you any younger brothers or sister? Ans. - I have.</p>
   <p>Ques. - Will it be pleasant to have your younger brother and sister visit with you in a house of correction? Ans. - Silence. The questioner thought for a moment. "Go and don't do it any more." The young girl thanked him with expressive eyes, and went slowly toward her home. Who is at fault in this particular case?</p>
   <p>The parents are to blame. They do not question their children when they bring home things for which they cannot account, or which, they claim to have acquired without cost. Parent do not protest against such behavior, nor do they investigate the source of the money which children are spending for sweets and tid-bits.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0046.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They do not admonish children not to stay out late at night nor to keep bad company. Therefore, parents should be held to account for all such behavior, not the children.</p>
   <p>When tears and sorrow have taken hold, it is too late. I reiterate, "Parents are responsible for their children's behavior, no one else."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
