<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-25">Jan. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter from the Polish Patriotic Educational Youth Society of St. Adalbert's</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0663</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0663.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-25">Jan. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER FROM THE POLISH PATRIOTIC EDUCATIONAL YOUTH SOCIETY OF ST. ADALBERT'S</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We received the following letter with a request that it be published:</p>
   <p>"Living here in a foreign land amidst foreign customs, our youth is in constant danger of losing interest in their mother tongue. The spread of Americanism engulfs tens, perhaps hundreds of our young people, who become lost to Polish society forever. We have no quarrel with Americanism, as in our opinion it is possible to be both a good American citizen and a good Pole. However, to forget one's mother tongue and to be ashamed of one's descent, simply because one lives in a foreign land, is not at all proper. With the purpose of awakening the Polish youth to a love of their language and a realization of the Polish spirit, the Polish Patriotic Educational Youth Society was founded eight months ago. As with all good things, this had its enemies, but in spite of opposition it is developing successfully. The Society possesses a number of Polish books on various subjects, dictionaries <pb facs="5423968_8_0664.jpg" n="2"/>maps, and newspapers.</p>
   <p>"Honorable Polish Youths! Here you have a good opportunity to join a purely Polish society at a very low expense. Do not delay, but come to the next meeting and we shall welcome you with open arms. Remember that here you will learn to respect your mother tongue. You will become acquainted with the history of our once great nation; you will be convinced that the descendants of Sobieski, Pulaski, Kosciuszko, Mickiewicz, and others have no cause to be ashamed of their heritage.</p>
   <p>"Parents! if you desire that your children do not forget the Polish language; that instead of frequenting saloons and street corners they spend their time in reading worthwhile books and in acquiring an education, send them to the Polish Patriotic Educational Youth Society."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
