<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I No. 41,
<date when="1897-10-06">Oct. 6, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">United Efforts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1440</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1440.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I No. 41,
<date when="1897-10-06">Oct. 6, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED EFFORTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special committee of convention delegates of the POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION has started to work in earnest. Two groups have turned in a sworn statement of the state of the treasury of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, a third group worked on the system of past dues of members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, another group is being formed for the purpose of organizing young Poles in the Catholic organization. Members of societies belonging to our organization are helping steadfastly our officers in the hard work of organizing the Polish-American public in a strong organization which would be a strong bulwark against atheism, gather under its care those of wavering faith and tempted by enemies, the weak countryman in a strange land. We will not go in detail as our opponents are doing, we will not fight with sword, remembering the words of Our Lord "He who fights with a sword dies by it."</p>
   <p>We will fight with confidence in God, with words of truth and faith on our lips, under the care of that Patron of ours, who so many times saved our country in her difficulties and in Her mercy is interceding to God to send to the blinded the Holy Ghost to enlighten the hardened stragglers.</p>
   <p>We believe in the intercession of the Heavenly Queen of Poland, we feel the moment is near when light will overcome darkness, when rebellious groups will be converted or disappear.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1441.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polish Roman Catholic Union will work to hasten that blessed moment, to gather the scattered groups all over North America not with an artificial and short lived flame but with a powerful knot of brotherly love, our common Catholic faith, and national arms.</p>
   <p>We will not build castles on ice and try to convince the people that the ice is granite, but will slowly and steadily raise a Polish Catholic building of faith on the mount of Jesus built by true patriotism. The ice will melt, the castles will tumble in ruins, but our building will endure through ages, to testify to the power of God, to work with faith. The Jewish-Socialist agitation armed to destroy everything that is holy, to remove "judges with a code" and "priests with mass" has increased greatly in these times, and we need a strong Polish-Catholic organization. This organization is the Polish Roman Catholic Union and its brave members, who stand steadfastly by their organization and work towards its growth.</p>
   <p>In this work other Catholic organizations will undoubtedly help us. We must unite and work together, as one Catholic newspaper says "either in one spirit and one thought and defend together, our faith of our forefathers, spread the glory of God among people, awaken the spirit of patriotism, but not with sharp words but with calm, quiet work, spread morality, education, inspiring <pb facs="5423968_8_1442.jpg" n="3"/>love of country, which we should love all the more now that she is suppressed and in slavery. We turn a pleading eye to God in whose hand rests the fats of all nations. We hope that other Catholic organizations will help us, laying aside small issues and offering our work on the altar of the general good of Polish public. We must all join hands forgetting all misunderstandings in face of that terrible illness that attacks the Polish American public, this doubt and it's consequences-the schism.</p>
   <p>Our members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union well know the material help in case of death is not our main reason of existence nor our main aim. That is Christian duty, which we rightfully perform.</p>
   <p>Our main aim is to invite Polish-Catholics into one large family, defend our members from false prophets, who having no faith in their hearts, tear it away from others. Sectionists and demagogues having on their lips the word of God even when they are arousing the people to wreck the works of God, that is His Church and her priests, to approach God without intercession, to free from revealed commandants the hearts and thoughts of our people - these are the greatest enemies of our Polish people in America, betraying everyone, God, our people and our country. Against these we must arm ourselves by joining forces, not to attack and fight them, but to defend the teachings of Christ, our Holy Faith and the ideals of our country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
