<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 137,
<date when="1905-06-13">June 13, 1905</date><title level="a">Curiosity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0599</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0599.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 137,
<date when="1905-06-13">June 13, 1905</date><title level="a">CURIOSITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We received one of the original circulars of a certain firm selling farms, with offices located near Milwaukee avenue. This circular was printed in Polish, but it so ignominiously mutilated the Polish language that every Pole who read it was shocked. This proves that it was not printed in one of our Polish print shops, because so many words were misspelled and sentences were miscontrued. Here are a few of the lines taken from this circular:-</p>
   <p>"Lots in the city given bygone for free. Get one lots. In the neighborhood are multitude small lakes and rivulets, overflowing with fish - there are wells with crystallized water.</p>
   <p>"Everyone, whether you are man, woman or child, for yourself is easy to make a living. Come to visit us, it will pay you."</p>
   <p>We are not mentioning the name of this firm because we do not want to expose them, but we think that every Pole that has received one of these circulars will refrain from doing business with a firm that does not do business with Polish printing firms.</p>
   <p>If a firm of such high standing does not support any of the many Polish printers in our city, how can they expect the Polish people to support it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0600.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Polish people should consider this matter that confronts us; it is not a matter of small importance but one that reflects badly on a Polish enterprise for our dealing with and supporting a non-Polish print shop. How can Polish business men exist if we Poles do not support our fellow countrymen?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
