<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-02">Nov. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Welcoming the New Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1262</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1262.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-02">Nov. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">WELCOMING THE NEW CENTRAL ADMINISTRATION OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance, elected by the Eighteenth Convention held at Milwaukee, Wisconsin, became inoperative today, November 2, 1911. The old Administration has just been replaced by a new one, elected at the Nineteenth Convention of the Alliance, held in St. Louis, Missouri. The changes in the personnel of the Central Administration are slight; perhaps there are fewer changes this time than there were at the Milwaukee Convention two years ago. Of the thirteen members who composed the retiring Administration, eight were elected again to the new, namely: A.Schreiber, censor; M.B.Steczynski, president; F.Ksycki, vice-president; S.J.Czechowicz, general-secretary; M.Majewski, treasurer; and M.Sakowska, M.Kmieciak, and N.Zlotnicki, directors. The editor of Zgoda, although re-elected by the Convention to fill this post, is not considered a member of the new Administration.</p>
   <p>The Nineteenth Convention separated this post from the Central Administration. None of the retiring officials and directors--former Vice-censor R.S.Abczynski <pb facs="5423968_8_1263.jpg" n="2"/>and Directors J. Hetmanowicz, M.Wojtecki, and J.Wleklinski--ran for re-election at the Nineteenth Convention.</p>
   <p>Such a large representation of the old Central Administration in the ranks of the new is the best indication that the Nineteenth Convention justly evaluated the work and the abilities of the Administration elected two years ago at Milwaukee. The two years of attacks against these people in all kinds of newspapers opposed to the Alliance were of no avail; the truly maddening propaganda that certain Alliance politicians directed against them at the St. Louis Convention did not help either, since these politicians, together with a mob of their agents, had gone to the Convention, not for the purpose of working for the good of the Alliance, but to strike down the candidacy of certain people disliked by them but respected by the Alliance and the people. Nor was the decision of the delegates affected by the fact that, before the Convention, some self-appointed guardians of the Alliance--who themselves could not run for any office--mentioned by name the officers who, according to them, should be removed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1264.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Convention, as the expression of the will of the members of the Alliance, disregarded all this and passed to the order of the day, electing whom it wanted and whom it considered useful to the organization. By this action, the Convention itself gave its vote of confidence to the old Central Administration, which, as a result, should consider itself completely vindicated. The new Central Administration begins its work with a strengthened organization. The Convention, mindful of the fact that the increased membership of the Alliance requires more work on the part of its directors, increased the number of the latter from thirteen to fifteen. Another reason for this is that the censor and vice-censor live in outlying districts and cannot take part in the meetings and work of the committees. Having two more members, the new Administration, therefore, will be more active than the former, which should have a beneficial effect on the activities of the Alliance.</p>
   <p>The new Administration will certainly be just as busy as the old. Granting that the tasks of building a monument and of reconstructing the Immigration <pb facs="5423968_8_1265.jpg" n="4"/>Home [in New York] are completed--tasks which required so much work and took up so much time in the last two years--yet there are other tasks, neither less difficult nor less important, which require attention. One of them is the building and opening of a home for the aged and the crippled; another is the election of an organizer, whose task will be to get new members for the Alliance. Then there will be the matter of the branches, as decreed by the Nineteenth Convention, which will cause at first no little work. And finally, the new Administration is faced with two problems recommended by the Nineteenth Convention, namely, to work out a plan for a future colonization society and to select a site, in the State of Pennsylvania, which would be best suited for the future school of the Alliance.</p>
   <p>Besides these specific problems, the continual and ever-increasing growth of the Alliance will bring its usual share of work to the Central Administration.</p>
   <p>Among the new people, in the Central Administration, who have not yet worked for the Alliance in the capacity of directors, are Vice-censor H.Niedzwiecki, <pb facs="5423968_8_1266.jpg" n="5"/>of Cleveland, Ohio; Mrs. W. Chodzinska, already well known to the members of the Alliance for her work in the Women's Auxiliary; L. Mallek, a young attorney (son of Anthony Mallek, well known both here and in Poland as a musician and composer, formerly secretary-general of the Polish National Alliance); K. Zychlinski, also widely known both in America and Europe, organizer of the Falcons and an excellent speaker; W. Kuflewski, who has already served three terms in the capacity of director and who has gained for himself the reputation of an honorable man, well versed in matters concerning the Alliance; J. Szymanski, delegate to several conventions and well known for his work primarily among the singers; and S. Mermel, former clerk in the office of the secretary-general and a zealous organizer of Alliance groups, for which activity he was distinguished by the Seventeenth Convention in Baltimore with a medal of honor.</p>
   <p>The Nineteenth Convention, therefore, has placed the administration of the Alliance in capable hands for the next two years.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1267.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Dziennik Zwiazkowy extends its sincere greetings to the new leaders of our organization and wishes them luck, health, and the co-operation of all their brothers in the responsible and homorable task that awaits them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
