<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-12">Dec. 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Capital Punishment or Imprisonment</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Anna Wyczolkowska</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-12">Dec. 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CAPITAL PUNISHMENT OR IMPRISONMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Anna Wyczolkowska</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because certain people from among my acquaintances, as well as complete strangers, have criticized me for defending criminals and murderers, I consider it my duty to clarify my stand in this matter for the benefit of both of these groups.</p>
   <p>Capital punishment itself is a vestige of barbarism, a vestige of the times when people believed in free will, believed that they alone were responsible for their deeds. Today we know that man's behavior is dependent first upon his natural inclinations, and next upon the environment in which he grew up, upon the upbringing which he received, upon the amount of education which gave him the means of developing his own ego, etc. He who possesses all of these means for character development, but has bad, evil instincts by nature, <pb facs="5423968_8_0179.jpg" n="2"/>will, despite these advantages, do a great deal of harm to his family, and to society. However he who has bad instincts and is also deprived of the influence of a great or even average culture, is also deprived of the aura of family warmth and understanding which simple and badly brought up people do not know how to create around themselves. That person easily becomes so degenerate that saying first, "I don't care", he then begins actually not to care about what he is and what he does. When a person of limited experience once begins to slip on the road leading away from true morality, a fall leading to crime is not far off.</p>
   <p>When you consider capital punishment on the one hand, and the cause of crime on the other, I know that the former will not eradicate the latter, and that in order to elevate people morally, it is necessary first to elevate them by educational and social means.</p>
   <p>For this reason, at the time that I began to agitate to change the death <pb facs="5423968_8_0180.jpg" n="3"/>penalty of our Polish (unfortunately) criminals, to life imprisonment, I also began to agitate for an increase of the social and educational advantages of our community.</p>
   <p>Therefore, I called upon the superintendent of schools and asked her to incorporate into the curriculum a more specific, more comprehensive course than the present one in moral education. Miss Young promised me that she would set about at once to do all that she could. She said however, that very few Polish children go to American schools, by which statement of course, she tactfully gave me to understand that I would have to go to the directors of the Polish schools with this same proposal.</p>
   <p>But although improvements in the schools can do a great deal in the future, they cannot redeem the evil to which those criminals have already fallen prey. One of these uttered a characteristic sentence. "Mother, don't say <pb facs="5423968_8_0181.jpg" n="4"/>good bye to me....because you could have brought me up better, and then I would not have to ascend the scaffold." The boy uttered a relative truth; a truth because he was entitled to a better upbringing, relative, because he did not understand that his mother as well as he was probably not endowed with a good upbringing. So much for theoretical opinions.</p>
   <p>And now let us ask what benefit does society receive, from a practical standpoint, from capital punishment, other than the fact that it becomes gradually used to the idea of killing a man. None. Thousands of our most worthy people are annoyed by this, barbaric custom considering it an insult to their finer sensibilities, in other words capital punishment in its manifestations and results becomes to a certain degree punishment for our finest citizens, which fact itself speaks for its abolition. Besides, the death penalty has become a question of miles, not morals, since Wisconsin, which is only a few miles away has abolished capital punishment. Why, therefore should we desire it so earnestly in Illinois? On the other hand <pb facs="5423968_8_0182.jpg" n="5"/>by substituting life imprisonment for the death penalty, and condemning the criminals to hard labor, we could gain appreciable benefits. For instance, supposing that these same criminals at hard labor were to earn three hundred dollars a year besides their keep, and this for an average period of thirty years. The proceeds from this labor for this period of time would amount to $38,000, with which money, having added to this sum the proceeds from the labors of others condemned to life imprisonment in the state of Illinois, the government could give financial aid to widowed mothers, or it could support orphanages, from which minor children could not be adopted by people, who want them merely for the purpose of cruelly exploiting them, as is frequently practiced now.</p>
   <p>I believe therefore, that those who reproach me would admit,if they went into this matter a little deeper, that capital punishment is only a legal necessity in a society of low culture, to which category America must therefore be relegated. This fact should be a stimulus to us, making us <pb facs="5423968_8_0183.jpg" n="6"/>eager to bring about better educational conditions, and making us believe once and for all in the fact that "knowledge is power" which nothing can destroy, even the greatest reverses in life. Ignorance, on the other hand, is the road to evil, if not actually to crime.</p>
   <p>After all I talked on this subject for an hour and a half at the meeting for equal suffrage on the fourth of this month, but our cultural level is still such that whenever there is a lecture on a more serious topic the hall is empty. However, little theaters where one can see crimes performed are unusually popular.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
