<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-07">July 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Will of the Majority</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0970</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0970.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-07-07">July 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE WILL OF THE MAJORITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>And again the people of the [Polish National] Alliance [Lud Zwiazkowy] have spoken, making plain their will. The official report from the office of the censor of the Polish National Alliance on the referendum submitted to the groups concerning the calling of a convention this year shows that only eighty out of every thousand Alliance members are in favor of calling that convention this year, while the rest have voted to uphold the decision of the convention in Schenectady to hold conventions every three years.</p>
   <p>It would be well to describe here the events that led up to the Alliance referendum on this matter. The controversey is an old one. It involves the same people who ever since the Detroit convention have been striving for leadership in the Alliance in order that they may dominate our organization. They could not gain control of the Alliance in Detroit; they could not cause <pb facs="5423968_8_0971.jpg" n="2"/>a split at the time of the struggle with K. O. N. [Komitet Obrony Narodowej: Polish National Defense Committee]; they could not gain a majority at the Schenectady convention and thus force through their own candidates; and from this point on they tried to undermine the Alliance in secret, creating a ferment that threatened to paralyze its development.</p>
   <p>At the last convention in Schenectady it was decided that conventions of the Polish National Alliance should hereafter be held every three years instead of every two years as stipulated in its charter. The convention has a right to change any basic laws of the organization as long as the changes are in agreement with the insurance laws of the State of Illinois. However, that principle is not recognized by those in the Alliance who in their blindness and opposition to certain officials now at the head of the organization have allowed themselves to be the tools of evil people, selfish people who have only their own interests at heart ever and always--sly, treacherous Pharisees who give the impression of being the best members of the Alliance, but who in reality desire its downfall because they could not, at the most significant <pb facs="5423968_8_0972.jpg" n="3"/>moments, use the name of that organization for the traitorous plots and allegiances that bring harm to the entire [Polish] nation.</p>
   <p>It is such people who attempted to prove the unconstitutionality of the Schenectady convention's decision and shielding themselves behind the alleged good of the Alliance began a widespread agitation to hasten the calling of the next convention in order that they might immediately renew, in the present year, their attempts to seize control of the Alliance and begin their destructive work.</p>
   <p>Since the members of K. O. N. are too much discredited in the Alliance to conduct a struggle of this sort themselves, they have found suitable tools with which to create dissension within the Alliance's ranks. However, the majority of the Alliance's members, who today understand well enough where lie truth and justice, and where lie ill will and private ambition and (let us speak plainly) the betrayal of the Alliance's aims and interests, has passed judgment on those who are ready for the fratricidal destruction <pb facs="5423968_8_0973.jpg" n="4"/>of the Alliance's interests merely that their victim, the Alliance, may become subject to their party or faction--that is, to our enemies and their sympathizers.</p>
   <p>It was not just a simple majority but a vote of nine to one, that is, 920 out of every thousand, which spoke against further disturbances of this kind in the Alliance and calls upon those in its midst who have gone astray or who are unenlightened as to the aims and purposes of their false instructors to think and to recollect themselves. It is a great voice with which every one must reckon.</p>
   <p>But will the incorrigibles reckon with it? Will they finally comprehend, now that they have suffered so disgraceful a defeat, that this is no time for private ambition or for avenging disappointed hopes, since greater tasks and aims demand the attention of us all,.....for which we must concentrate our strength, not dissipate it? And will they comprehend that "great things arise from harmony, while dissension brings about the destruction of even <pb facs="5423968_8_0974.jpg" n="5"/>the greatest," and that therefore we need unity and harmony and greater co-ordination in our ranks, not quarrels and bickerings and traitorous plotting, if we are to realize the most sacred precepts embodied in our constitution, those precepts which we have inscribed upon the banners of the Polish National Alliance?</p>
   <p>Today, whoever works against these precepts, whoever works destructively, whoever tends to split our ranks, works in reality not only the destruction of the Polish National Alliance but that of the entire Polish element in the United States, as well as that of the one and only cause, the Polish cause. For such attempts the nation will one day condemn those who deserve it; and with the mark of disgrace upon their foreheads they will be unable to lift their faces toward truth and light when the hour of triumph comes. For they will be constantly tortured by the memory of the evil which they consciously wrought, with the full understanding that they were working this evil solely to gratify some one--if not for money, then to earn adulation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
