<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 44,
<date when="1921-09-30">Sept. 30, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The P.N.A. President Forwards Thanks to the President of the U.S.A. and Senator McCormick</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item><item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 44,
<date when="1921-09-30">Sept. 30, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE P.N.A. PRESIDENT FORWARDS THANKS TO THE PRESIDENT OF THE U.S.A. AND SENATOR McCORMICK</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Kind Sir and Honored Guests of the 23rd Convention of the Polish National Alliance of America:-</p>
   <p>Permit me, the chairman of this Convention, to assure you that we, the Delegates of this Alliance, are exceedingly happy and feel honored at the message of our President which you bring to us.</p>
   <p>Your mission is the greatest event of this Convention.</p>
   <p>The alliance is a body of American citizens of Polish descent and extraction, who are gathered here to deliberate upon the good of our organization and the problems which confront our race in this, our adopted country, and the land of our birth.</p>
   <p>We are striving to retain the valuable traits of our ancestry because they are <pb facs="5423968_8_0447.jpg" n="2"/>an asset; we are trying to adopt the good that is in the Anglo-Saxon race and mold both qualities into a whole that will make good men and women, loyal citizens, worthy of a great inheritance.</p>
   <p>Kindly assure our President that this gathering of American citizens has the welfare of our country at heart and does its duty, second to none, by training and developing the highest type of citizenship, loyal to our adopted country, although mindful of its undying love for our mother country-Poland.</p>
   <p>The duty cast upon me in asking you to bear this message from the 23rd Convention of the Polish National Alliance of America, I consider a great privilege. I beg you to deliver this message to our noble President and assure him of our love and affection.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
