<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 123,
<date when="1922-05-26">May 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Kosciuszko Manifestation; Committee Invites H. Hoover as Speaker</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0900</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0900.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 123,
<date when="1922-05-26">May 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">KOSCIUSZKO MANIFESTATION; COMMITTEE INVITES H. HOOVER AS SPEAKER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Who of the Polish men and women did not hear of Herbert Hoover?</p>
   <p>It seems to us there are none amongst us who did not hear of him. There, beyond the sea, the name of Herbert Hoover evokes a smile of happiness from mothers and children -- in men of great diplomacy, expressions of recognition for Herbert Hoover.</p>
   <p>Hoover, during the war, did whatever he could in order to bring food relief to countries devastated by war. When the terrible sight of war, destruction and conflagration abated, Hoover did not stop working.</p>
   <p>He visited countries devastated by war, organized relief committees, sent food and made an effort toward its equal distribution.</p>
   <p>The name of Herbert Hoover became the name of charity for the oppressed and the hungry; the unclothed and the homeless.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0901.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today he is blessed in the countries of the Allies,and in Poland his name is surrounded by the halo of a great man, at a great moment.</p>
   <p>Herbert Hoover is at present head of the Department of Commerce. It is he who the committee of the Kosciuszko manifestation invited as speaker in Humboldt Park, where we will gather in a great throng to honor the memory of the hero of two worlds, Thaddeus Kosciuszko, whose monument stands so proudly there.</p>
   <p>As every year, so next Sunday we will go to the monument in order to demonstrate by our presence that we value the memory of the immortal Thaddeus, because he did not pay homage to gold and power but recognized freedom as the greatest treasure.</p>
   <p>We will not march to the park, but we will all be there, so as to listen to the speeches of the great friends of Poland, Minister Herbert Hoover and Brigadier-General Magnus McCloskey, who will speak with our own prominent Polish speakers on the theme of the past and present, and about <pb facs="5423968_8_0902.jpg" n="3"/>the future of the emigration and of Poland.</p>
   <p>We will come to the monument in throngs so as to honor the memory of the immortal Kosciuszko, and to make a revision of our strength, the strength of workers, who always and everywhere were active in collective appearances.</p>
   <p>On to the monument of Kosciuszko in the aim of honoring a hero, to take on fresh strength for further work, in the direction of elevating the influence of emigration!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
