<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-17">Sept. 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[Anniversary of Polish National Alliance]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1344</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1344.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-17">Sept. 17, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[ANNIVERSARY OF POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many societies as well as groups of the Polish National Alliance celebrate this year the twenty-fifth or thirtieth anniversary of their existence. These festivities occur in various cities where the given societies or groups are located, and they are conducted in an elevated mood, joyfully and with decorum. Truly there is something to be elated about when we hear that one group or another of the Alliance has successfully warded off attacks, dissension, underhandedness and slander. These groups, having become hardened in their battles, have come forth victorious, and today they can gladly celebrate the triumph of their wholesome national ideals. Twenty-five years. It is really a period of time in infinity, but how fruitful in the various transitions, in the changes and progress in the lives of individual nations, organizations and individuals making up the population. Just as every nation adds pages to its written history, so also does every large congregation, every organization, or even the most insignificant society possess its history--it has its bright and dark moments, which it <pb facs="5423968_8_1345.jpg" n="2"/>recollects either with joy or with sorrow. Let us ask each of the older champions of the Alliance about the past of the Polish National Alliance, its transitions and development, its battles and sacrifices, and each of them will present a picture before our eyes--everyone will have something to say on how the work was done for this organization, what it has produced, and how the brave champions defended the good cause--how they did not allow the national standard to be besmirched.</p>
   <p>Every group of the Polish National Alliance is likened to a strong pillar upon which our entire national structure rests. Remove these pillars or only undermine them, and we will find that the whole edifice will fall. The duty, therefore, of every group, of every society belonging to the Polish National Alliance is to endeavor to have his pillar strong, that it may not be weakened, or become fragile, but become more massive, that it may acquire durability, which even time and various elements cannot weaken. These pillars can be strengthened only by organizing ourselves, by gaining new champions that they may replace those leaving the field, fill the breaches brought by death to the ranks of the older fighters for these principles. Each year tears many of our workers from our lines.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1346.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many did not even have the fortune to live long enough to witness the silver anniversary of the fruitful work done in the national organization in behalf of Poland and our people. These gaps must be filled by new recruits whom the elders should encourage to join the ranks. Let us found as many pillars in this national structure as possible, that it may be more firm, more powerful and more secure. Where there are no groups of the Alliance, but where Poles are found, there let our bright idealism east its light, let it enlighten the hearts, awaken the spirit, develop the minds and--let it build our future. Let us build this structure higher and wider that it may exceed all others with its vastness, that it may find room in its confines for all Polish immigrants, as among one loving family.</p>
   <p>We hereby thank all our societies and groups, celebrating their jubilees, for their work done thus far for the national ideals which are higher than all other ideals. Moreover we sincerely wish that they may live long enough to witness their golden jubilee, when the Polish National Alliance will number, not tens of thousands, but millions of workers for the Polish cause and her sacred mottos. You have passed through many difficulties, dear members; you have suffered many</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1347.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>abuses from vicious people during these thirty years. Your joy is therefore the greater that you are not observing a sad anniversary of defeat and failure, but of a complete victory, and that, to you, worthy workers, is perhaps the dearest of all remuneration. Continue to follow the road which you have taken for so many years, and let the love of the Motherland lead you, and the star of hope and of a better tomorrow brighten your path. Continue to work in behalf of the Polish National Alliance because that is a work for all of Poland. Build the Alliance, increase its ranks, spread the true knowledge and principles which refreshen you that others may partake of them, and God and the Motherland will repay you for your efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
