<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-19">Dec. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Useful New Polish Institution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0162</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0162.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-19">Dec. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">USEFUL NEW POLISH INSTITUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Tuesday at 8 P. M., a meeting was held to organize the newly created society for the following purposes:</p>
   <p>1. To exert a moral influence on the Polish men and women who are leading immoral lives and setting their children bad examples, and through this influence to lead them back to the good and honest way of life.</p>
   <p>2. To give all possible care and attention to the children of immoral parents.</p>
   <p>3. To prevent, whenever possible, young Poles from being taken to court for moral offenses.</p>
   <p>These are the main purposes of the new institution, of which the Poles here are so greatly in need. Naturally these three points, as has been stated above, constitute only the main aims and program of activity. The institution <pb facs="5423968_8_0163.jpg" n="2"/>however, will not step there but will continue to develop its scope with time and to undertake more activities for the benefit of our Polish people.</p>
   <p>Those present at the organizational meeting held at the Polish Raman Catholic Union building were: Mrs. M. Geshkiewicz, a clerk of the probate court; Miss Anna Neuman, a clerk of this court; Miss Antoinette Behnke of Cook County Hospital; Mr. Albert Newak, County Commissioner; Mr. Thaddeus Sleszynski and Mr. Stephen Napieralski, clerks of the juvenile court; Mr. Stephen Lewenthal editor of Dziennik Narodewy, and Mr. A. Basinski, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Thaddeus Sleszynski explained to those present the immediate need for establishing such a Polish institution in our city. To justify his assertion he produced a list of statistics taken out of the records of the juvenile court.</p>
   <p>From these statistics we learned that from December 1, 1912, to December 1, 1913, the juvenile court handled 4,695 cases, of which 785, or 17 per cent, were Polish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0164.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From December 1, 1913, to November 1, of the present year [1914], this same court handled 5,788 cases, of which 1,069, that is, 18 per cent, were Polish.</p>
   <p>It is obvious from the above data that offenses among the Poles are greatly on the increase. This is due to the fact that the Poles do not provide their compatriots with proper care--although they need it more than members of other nationalities. Here are some other statistics dealing with offenders--both boys and girls--between the ages of fourteen and seventeen:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1913</cell>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>Poles</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Boys</cell>
     <cell>1363</cell>
     <cell>318</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Girls</cell>
     <cell>592</cell>
     <cell>84</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1914</cell>
     <cell>
</cell>
     <cell>
</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Boys</cell>
     <cell>2258</cell>
     <cell>464</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Girls</cell>
     <cell>659</cell>
     <cell>95</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0165.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Boys whose parents cannot support them:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1913</cell>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>Poles</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Boys</cell>
     <cell>1089</cell>
     <cell>160</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1914</cell>
     <cell>
</cell>
     <cell>
</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Boys</cell>
     <cell>1227</cell>
     <cell>233</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>This data also points to the obvious fact of the lack of care of our young people. Mrs. Geshkiewicz presented a series of facts indicating the great need for an institution to care for, and bring up, minors.</p>
   <p>Mr. Napieralski suggested that an institution be founded which would deal especially with children from fourteen to sixteen years of age--that is, from the time they leave school until the time when they can legally work. The speaker mentioned that some time ago Reverend Piechowski suggested founding such an institution but received no co-operation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0166.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>After further debating, Miss Behnke suggested that a special committee be appointed ad hoc to call on the more influential Poles and clergy and invite them to come to the next meeting and take an active interest in this important matter. This suggestion was accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Napieralski, Mr. Nowak, and Mrs. Geshkiewicz were appointed to this committee and Mr. Napieralski was elected temporary president of this committee and Mr. T. Sleszynski temporary secretary.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held on Thursday, December 17, at 8 P. M., at the Polish Roman Catholic Union building, and all willing and clear-thinking Poles are invited.</p>
   <p>Committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
