<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. V, No. 33,
<date when="1901-08-14">Aug. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Remember Our Young People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-13">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. V, No. 33,
<date when="1901-08-14">Aug. 14, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">REMEMBER OUR YOUNG PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Gazette in this manner addresses the people in Upper Silesia: "How is it with the Czechs? There cities and farms were already Germanized and now everything is changed because the Czechs considered: "In what lies our future?' and the answer rang throughout the whole country, 'In our younger generation, in our youth.'"</p>
   <p>Let us only study the brave spirit of that gallant nation. A few years ago we attended an ethnographic exposition in Prague. At this exposition, each day was dedicated to some special branch, one day to the bakers, another to tailors, then shoemakers, butchers, etc. We were present on the day dedicated to maids and cooks.</p>
   <p>They came in a large automobile, with music. Do you think they came empty-handed? Not at all, they brought as a gift 600 zloty, gold coins, gathered among themselves penny by penny, for the school children.</p>
   <p>No wonder that they got a great ovation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0611.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The crowds burst into shouts and the orchestra played to a thunder of applause for these maids and cooks, as other spheres of public had done in giving daily gifts of money for the schools.</p>
   <p>Where among us will anyone do as these cooks and maids? We are still far away from that. There is not even any understanding of the matter among most of our people; to attend national anniversaries and ceremonies, amateur theatricals, etc., at least by our presence so that we can show we are alive.</p>
   <p>Therefore it is sad for us, and we should bend all our efforts to the benefit of our mutual interest.</p>
   <p>Man is not on earth to live alone and for himself, but among the important duties to his soul is to remember his Christianity which links him with his neighbors and his nation, because a nation is a great soul whose beauty and goodness, or ugliness and evil we, as members of a nation all reflect. So much for the Polish Gazette.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0612.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We should mark these words, they suit us also on a foreign soil. Our young people have no great longing for books nor for matters of general public interest, and as for generosity, there is much to be desired and we need not count on it in the future.</p>
   <p>The older people, who left their native country, have given generously for monuments, churches, schools, hospitals, orphanages, etc., but the younger generation born here is less generous.</p>
   <p>There is very little feeling of unity, even among themselves, in our young people. Numerous societies and clubs with foreign names, organized by young Poles, testify to this.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we must, with all our strength, draw our youth to us, help their organizations, bring to their attention duties which they have in regard to their fatherland. Unless we awaken this soul, our youth, or at least the larger number, will be lost. The home, school and church have much to work for in this field.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0613.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If parents will care for their children more, if they will associate with them more and instill into their souls Polish patriotism, if the schools will meet their needs and if the church will gather abundantly the fruit of their labors, then our fatherland will not lose any sons.</p>
   <p>Youth, that flower of our nation, is our future and only with careful attention to its needs, will this youth and its future generations remain Polish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
