<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-07-18">July 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Past Presidents of the Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-07-18">July 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">PAST PRESIDENTS OF THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The longest record as president of the Polish National Alliance is held by M. B. Steczynski, who was president for about nine years; and the shortest record is held by F. M. Ksycki, who was president for nineteen days. But both will be equally mentioned in the history of the Polish National Alliance as former presidents. The services of both are well known to the members of the organization; therefore, though both these ex-presidents are holding now other offices, the work done by them will bring further benefits to the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1237.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The members of the Polish National Alliance did not remove either one of these presidents, but they themselves resigned, because the members of the Polish National Alliance continues to function regularly under the changes brought about.</p>
   <p>During the life time of the Polish National Alliance three presidents have resigned voluntarily. They were M. B. Steczynski, F. M. Ksycki and the late Francis Jerome Jablonski; the latter resigned because he could not support his family on the five hundred dollars annual salary he received as president. He, therefore, was compelled to seek employment in other fields, where he could earn a higher salary. Explaining this <pb facs="5423968_8_1238.jpg" n="3"/>matter in his farewell article, he wrote that "earning a salary which is too high to die of starvation, and too small to support my family, it is with sorrow that I must hand in my resignation as president, to seek employment elsewhere for a salary which would meet the demands."</p>
   <p>At the present time, the Polish National Alliance pays its president a salary, which allows him to easily support his family; but it is none too high if he wants to represent our organization worthily. The fact is that very often he has to meet expenses, for which he does not make any account to the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1239.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Some time ago, when the Polish National Alliance numbered but two or three thousand members, a person could be president without remuneration, and carry on a business or be employed; But today we are nearing one hundred thousand in membership. Therefore, the president must give his entire time to the organization; he must worthily represent it at each step, and he has very much work, supervising the various departments and carrying on a large correspondence.</p>
   <p>Today the president of the Polish National Alliance receives more mail from all parts of the United States in one day, then years ago in one year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1240.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The voting commission will vote to elect a vice-president and one director, out of the three candidates nominated by the administration, to fill the two vacancies resulting from resignations. For vice-president the administration nominated: F. M. Ksycki, former president and vice-president; directors, Mrs. Mary Sakowski, and Joseph Szymanski. For the vacancy of one director, the following were nominated: Chester Hibner, a former director; Dr. Ladislaus Statkiewicz, and Mr. Adam Majewski, a former director.</p>
   <p>We cannot endorse or praise any of the candidates, as it is against our rules, but we have confidence in our voting commission, and trust that it will elect the proper candidates, because the commission is familiar with each candidate from the past convention, where they acted as delegates. The election should be easy and just.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
