<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-06-07">June 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Central Board of the Polish League in the United States Meets for the First Time</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-06-07">June 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">CENTRAL BOARD OF THE POLISH LEAGUE IN THE UNITED STATES MEETS FOR THE FIRST TIME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The central board of the newly established Polish League in America held its first meeting yesterday at the office of this newspaper.</p>
   <p>The following members of the central board were present: M. Kruszka and Ignace Czerwinski from Milwaukee, Wisconsin; Stein, from Shamokin, Pennsylvania; J. Napieralski, Peter Kiolbassa, S. Szwajkart, and N. L. Piotrowski, from Chicago, and F. X. Rydzewski, from South Chicago.</p>
   <p>Many problems were settled.</p>
   <p>It was decided to incorporate the League in the State of Illinois under the title, "Liga Polska w Stanach Zjednoczonych Polnocnej Ameryki" (The Polish League of the United States of North America). The task of incorporating the League <pb facs="5423968_8_1602.jpg" n="2"/>was entrusted to J. Napieralski, Peter Kiolbassa, and N. L. Piotrowski.</p>
   <p>It was voted that all officials of the League, including the trustees of the Polish National Fund, must furnish bonds without delay. The bonds of the officials will be kept by the treasurer, but the bond of the treasurer will be kept by the president of the League.</p>
   <p>It was decided that the central board should meet once a month; quarterly meetings will be held every three months. The necessary quorum for making decisions at monthly meetings will be five members, and at quarterly meetings eight. Monthly meetings will be held every first Wednesday; at these meetings regular routine problems will be taken up.</p>
   <p>The organization of the Polish League will begin creating branches without alleting them to districts for the time being. With this in view, a suitable announcement will be published in all newspapers, and copies will be sent to the Polish clergy, societies, prominent Poles, etc. To this announcement will <pb facs="5423968_8_1603.jpg" n="3"/>be attached the statutes of the League, instructions for branches, and bulletins in behalf of the petition for abolishing the Russian-American Treaty.</p>
   <p>It was received to print ten thousand copies of the statutes of the League, one thousand copies of instructions for branches, and a suitable quantity of office stationery and forms.</p>
   <p>The problem of printing and sending the resolution adopted at the Kozeiuske Demonstration to all European governments, and of preparing suitable bulletins, was entrusted to a special committee consisting of Dr. Casimir Midowiez, H. Nagiel, and L. Szopanski, who are not members of the central board of the League.</p>
   <p>It was voted to purchase suitable office books and supplies, for which twenty-five dollars was appropriated. The headquarters of the League will be temporarily located at the office of the Polish Publishing Company, 141-143 West Division Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1604.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The matter of the bulletin to Europe, explaining the Polish League, was entrusted to Dr. Casimir Midowicz, M. Kruszka, and Ignace Czerwinski.</p>
   <p>The secretary and the treasurer announced that, so far $828.31 has been received by the treasurer; the secretary has received $82.17; and $65.28 has been received by other persons. The total received so far is $976.71. Out of this sum, $528.68 belongs to the Polish National Fund: The balance belongs to the League, and will be used to defray the expenses of the League.</p>
   <p>The meeting was then adjourned; unfinished business will be taken up at the next meeting.</p>
   <p>Announcements will be made in a few days, and the organization will soon begin to function.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
