<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-23">Sept. 23, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Falcons Fete Europman Guests at Pulaski Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1511</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1511.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-23">Sept. 23, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH FALCONS FETE EUROPMAN GUESTS AT PULASKI HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two distinguished European guests, Dr. C. Lewakowski and S. Balicki, were feted last night by the Polish Falcons of Chicago at Pulaski Hall. The guests were welcomed by fifty young ladies and seventy young men, a company of thirty trained Falcons and the entire Falcon staff.</p>
   <p>Casimir Zychlinski opened the festivities with a short address appropriate for the occasion. Dr. Lewakowski also spoke, and he told the audience that he came to America with the idea of awakening the Polish spirit but that he was surprised to see it unfolding before his eyes. The Polish doctor voiced his satisfaction at the work which is being done here to foster Polish culture.</p>
   <p>Greetings were extended to fellow Falcons by Mr. Balicki, a veteran Falcon from Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1512.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The short addresses were followed by drills executed by the Polish youth.</p>
   <p>Mr. Balicki was made an honorary member of the Polish Falcons Alliance (Dr. Lewakowski had been previously so honored). Then A. Mieczynski, an official of both the Polish Falcons Alliance and the Polish Sokols Alliance, gave a speech. He was followed by Dr. Lewakowski, who imparted the idea of uniting this group of Falcons with those of Galicia, an Austrian-occupied Polish province.</p>
   <p>After the exercises thirty persons attended a banquet. Many toasts were given; among them a toast in honor of the Polish League of America was given by Dr. Lewakowski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
