<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 18,
<date when="1919-04-30">April 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The President of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union to Lloyd George and Woodrow Wilson</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Cablegram in the Matter of Gdansk (Danzig)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_0910</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>9:ww
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0910.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 18,
<date when="1919-04-30">April 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESIDENT OF THE POLISH ROMAN-CATHOLIC UNION TO LLOYD GEORGE AND WOODROW WILSON</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Cablegram in the Matter of Gdansk (Danzig)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few weeks ago the president of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, sent, in the name of the Union and the Polish National Council, a cablegram to the English premier, Lloyd George, and President Woodrow Wilson. The text of the cablegram was as follows:</p>
   <p>Hon. Lloyd George</p>
   <p>Prime Minister of England</p>
   <p>Peace Congress</p>
   <p>Paris, France</p>
   <p>Poles in America are distressed at your attitude as reported in the press as to disposition of Danzig. Simple justice demands that stolen property be restored to its rightful owner. Danzig, which was stolen <pb facs="5423968_8_0911.jpg" n="2"/>from Poland by the perfidious king of Prussia, should now be restored to Poland without any quibbling.</p>
   <p>To prevent Germany from again becoming a menace to the peace of the world, there should stand between Germany and Russia a strong nation completely independent and capable of taking care of itself. That nation is Poland. She must be the great constructive democracy of Eastern Europe, a barrier to German pressure eastward. To cope with this situation, the frontiers of Poland must correspond with geographical requirements.</p>
   <p>The restoration to Poland of West Prussia, besides the province of Posen, which embraces in its territory the mouth of the Vistula with a part of the Danzig, is absolutely essential to the economic independence of Poland and for her free intercourse with the outer world. Upper Silesia, which is essential for the industrial development of Poland, must also be restored to her.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0912.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is a subject worthy of much attention of the great statesmen sitting at the peace table. Had the statesmen of Europe, one hundred forty-seven years ago, been more foresighted and had they not permitted the partition of Poland, at whose expense Prussia had grown strong, perhaps this great war would have never taken place.</p>
   <p>We trust that England will not make the same mistake as she did one hundred and four years ago at the Congress of Vienna.</p>
   <p>It is an admitted historical fact that the reason why the Poles did not obtain even what Tsar Alexander was willing to give them, was due mainly to the unpardonable short-sightedness of England's Prime Minister, Liverpool, and of Lord Castlereagh, her representatives at the Vienna Congress.</p>
   <p>If the Peace Congress will not award Danzig to Poland, Prussia's crime in the partition of Poland shall have been confirmed and Germany's commercial and industrial supremacy over the East will be established.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_0913.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If Danzig is not awarded to Poland the war has been fought in vain and there can be no permanent peace in Europe.</p>
   <p>In the name of justice, we, American citizens of Polish extraction, appeal to you, Mr. Prime Minister, to award Danzig to Poland.</p>
   <p>Polish R. C. U. and Polish National Council of America.</p>
   <p>by N. L. Piotrowski, President.</p>
   <p>A cablegram of the same contents, with only small technical changes, was sent by Mr. N. L. Piotrowski to the President of the United States, Woodrow Wilson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
