<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-09">Feb. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Anthony Mallek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1034</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1034.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-09">Feb. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ANTHONY MALLEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the death of Anthony Mallek we have lost a man who played one of the most important roles in the history of our organization. Since I worked with him and frequently had the opportunity of seeing his work at close range, I am writing these few words in order to give him a credit which he so justly earned.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance was passing through a terribly difficult phase when the late Anthony Mallek took over the office of secretary general, which at that time was the most responsible position in our organization.</p>
   <p>The powerful clerical camp was constantly striking blows at the young and weak Alliance with all its might. At the convention in Buffalo, the clergymen who were members of the Alliance came out in a body. In addition the preceding secretary general defrauded the treasury and absconded. The Alliance was left abandoned, threadbare, and poor. It seemed that it had reached its end and that <pb facs="5423968_8_1035.jpg" n="2"/>nothing could ever get it back on its feet again. Even its enemies became silent for a while, as if they wanted the ailing Alliance at least to have a quiet death.</p>
   <p>But they were mistaken. I remember as though it had happened yesterday when Mr. Mallek came into the office. His first words were: "To work!" and appeals, explanations, and encouragements began being sent out to the groups, that they might not just give up. Soon the battered members of the Alliance realized that this was a person who knew how to guide them. Courage entered the doubting hearts, and the people began to rally around the flag of the Alliance. They got "to work" with all their might and kept at it until the Alliance was again on solid ground.</p>
   <p>It should be emphasized here that at that time Holy Trinity Parish played no small part in the history of our organization. The same people who wanted the Alliance's downfall also wanted to take over the government of this church--and, coming upon opposition, they succeeded in having the church closed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1036.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is not strange then that these two groups--the Alliance and the Parish--should unite in the battle against their adversary. Holy Trinity was looked upon as a fortress of the Alliance, and the link between the Alliance and the "fortress" was, of course, the late Anthony Mallek. It was absolutely natural that anyone who wanted to be considered as a one-hundred-per cent member of the Alliance considered it his duty to be a member of the parish, and vice versa every good parishioner was at the same time a member of the Alliance.</p>
   <p>One of Mr. Mallek's greatest accomplishments was his instrumentality in the founding of the library and museum of the Polish National Alliance. At one time the late Mr. H. Kalusowski suggested the establishment of this institution. Mr. Mallek got to work energetically and realized the idea.</p>
   <p>"This is a matter of greater weight than one would think," he said to me one day, "because if patriots of the measure of Kalusowski, feeling their end approaching, want to offer their invaluable keepsakes for the use of the <pb facs="5423968_8_1037.jpg" n="4"/>public, and turn to the Alliance with this offer, that means that they look upon the Alliance as representing the people. Those over there," he added, pointing in the direction of the Alliance's antagonists, "will be greatly angered by this recognition."</p>
   <p>In 1892 Anthony Katski, Polish composer and pianist of world-wide fame, visited Chicago. Mr. Mallek--it must be explained--loved music and song more than life. It was even said of him that he had notes instead of brains in his head. Therefore he soon struck up an acquaintance with the composer which, based on the similarity of interests, blossomed into a lifelong friendship.</p>
   <p>One time, while a storm was raging with thunder and lightning, Mallek burst into the print shop crying: "Boys, hurry and get dressed and go to Tomek (Thomas) Nalepinski's Hall. You'll see something there the like of which you may never see or hear again in your life; it is the birth of the 'March of the Polish National Alliance.'" The order had to be obeyed, because at that time the secretary general was also the boss of the printing shop. At that time the <pb facs="5423968_8_1038.jpg" n="5"/>whole bookkeeping department of the Alliance and the administration of the printing shop were in the hands of the secretary general.</p>
   <p>When we arrived at the hall, there were already quite a few Alliance members there. Katski was bent over a table writing music. Every now and then he would get up and play a few bars. Finally he stopped writing, and sat down at the piano and played, for the first time, the "March of the Polish National Alliance," as only he could play it.</p>
   <p>You should have seen Mallek. His eyes darted from person to person, and when the playing was over, his enthusiasm burst forth--he was ready to hug everybody. In the evening when I was returning from work, Mallek, still under the impression of the March, stopped me.</p>
   <p>"Did you hear the March? Good, isn't it? Now we wont be strung out like a mass of stalks, but will march in ranks like an army; we have a march." And having said that he went on in order to stop some other passer-by to tell him <pb facs="5423968_8_1039.jpg" n="6"/>the good news.</p>
   <p>Not long afterward, when the Polish, or rather the Alliance division, took part in the parade celebrating the four-hundredth anniversary of Columbus' discovery of America, an orchestra composed of a few score people played the "March of the Polish National Alliance" before the reviewing stand of Mr. Morton, vice-president of the United States. Mr. Mallek just beamed as he did when the March was born; he threw out his deep chest, and nailed his flashing eyes right into the vice-president as though he were trying to tell him, "Listen, that's the 'March of the Polish National Alliance,'composed by my friend Anthony Katski.....Listen!"</p>
   <p>(Signed) Ed. B.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
