<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Develop the Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">DEVELOP THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of the war raging in Europe and its accompanying industrial stagnation in this country, our organizations suffer: their numerical increase is not as great as it was a few months ago during normal times.</p>
   <p>At present many of our brothers are not working and those who have jobs are not working full time. Therefore the laborer is complaining, the industrialist is complaining, the merchant is complaining, about "the hard times" and the Polish organizations must also complain about the smaller increase of membership.</p>
   <p>Many of our brothers belonging to battalions of enemy armies have deserted, the sea being not yet closed to sailing. On the other hand, immigrants are not coming in from Europe because the various governments will not let them leave. Therefore the influx of people from Europe has almost ceased. This <pb facs="5423968_8_1200.jpg" n="2"/>affects disadvantageously our organizations, which were formerly supplied with new members from abroad. The Polish National Alliance feels this, the Polish Roman Catholic Union feels it, other Polish organizations which base their existence on the influx of new members feel it.</p>
   <p>It is true that the large organizations can more easily survive this crisis than the smaller ones, for which the influx of new members is the only means of postponing bankruptcy.</p>
   <p>The influx of members to the Polish National Alliance is greater proportionately than that of any other Polish organization. Nevertheless it is not as large as it should be. The circumstances which we have named above are the cause of this. Nevertheless if each member of the Alliance were to make a greater effort, if he were to campaign among his friends, relatives, and acquaintances, then, in spite of outside circumstances, the growth of the organization would be normal. There is-still no lack of material here for building the Alliance, but there are too few builders who know how to get this material together to build the Alliance. We have too few organizers and workers in the Alliance, <pb facs="5423968_8_1201.jpg" n="3"/>though the field is very large, though hundreds of thousands of our brothers and sisters do not belong to any organization.</p>
   <p>We should all be organized, because the great moment for our nation is drawing near. Over there in the homeland all of the people are organizing today, all parties are strengthening their numbers and then all joining into one body, in order to form a power which both our enemies and our friends will have to take into consideration. A nationally united, well-organized mass is evolving there. We emigrants should follow the example of our brothers across the sea. It is true that we cannot pour all of our organizations here into one body. The reason, easily understood, is that there are purely technical barriers. Nevertheless, at least in nationalistic matters these organizations should advance together toward one aim, because Poland's cause is not just the cause of the Alliance, the Falcons, the Union, or the societies of the clergy, but the cause of the entire nation.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, Alliance members, during this period of organizational stagnation, should exert all of their efforts and energy to get those under <pb facs="5423968_8_1202.jpg" n="4"/>the banner of the Alliance who do not yet belong to us or to any other Polish organization. Do not let them wander about, do not let them remain unattached, when the whole nation is arising and joining in co-operative work for the homeland. It is a national sin to forget about those who, either through ignorance or negligence or for some other reason, do not belong to us or anyone else and from whom our homeland therefore gets no benefit.</p>
   <p>The gaining of one member for the Alliance, and by the same token for the Polish cause, means more than talking about Poland and patriotism for a whole year.</p>
   <p>Therefore,members of the Alliance, rouse yourselves from your lethargy! Do not rest on your laurels, but work to extend our organization, because the Polish cause needs this from you.</p>
   <p>If there were not a hundred thousand of us, but a million, concentrated under the banner of the P. N. A. [Polish National Alliance], then we could contribute <pb facs="5423968_8_1203.jpg" n="5"/>not thousands, but hundreds of thousands and even millions of dollars to the needs of the homeland; because every Alliance member is nationally more enlightened than the man who is unattached and does not know about anything.</p>
   <p>Therefore, let us build up the Polish National Alliance!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
