<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-11-22">Nov. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Twentieth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-11-22">Nov. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTIETH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On November 22, 1916, the Polish National Alliance celebrated the twentieth anniversary of the date when the organization for the first time acquired its own headquarters. On that day the first Polish National Alliance Building was dedicated. It was intended to contain the offices of the Alliance's Central Administration, collections for the museum, the library, and the printing press of the organization's official organ, the weekly Zgoda. No one even dreamed at that early date that the Polish National Alliance would some day have a daily newspaper. The total number of members of the Polish National Alliance was then estimated at ten thousand.</p>
   <p>The matter of erecting a Polish National Alliance Building was raised at the organization's eleventh convention, held at Cleveland, Ohio, in 1895. After a heated argument with the opponents of the project, it was decided to erect the organization's own building at a cost of thirty thousand dollars. This amount was considered to be sufficient to construct a <pb facs="5423968_8_1098.jpg" n="2"/>magnificent edifice.</p>
   <p>In the spring of 1896 the actual construction of the building was begun. The Reverend Casimer Sztuczko officiated at the ceremonies of dedicating the cornerstone. Father Sztuczko is pastor of Holy Trinity Church, the parish which has the largest number of members of the Polish National Alliance. The opening of an already completed building occured on Sunday, November 22, of the same year. The official organ of the organization, the weekly Zgoda, described this celebration in the following words:</p>
   <p>"The day of the opening of the first Polish National Alliance Building was a memorable one for the Alliance and its ideals. The organization was finally succeeded in establishing itself in its own headquarters. Houses on the Northwest Side were decked with garlands. American and Polish flags, and appropriate inscriptions. Above all the others the Polish National Alliance Building stood magnificently decorated.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1099.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"For nearly the entire week the skies had been covered with clouds, and even on Sunday rain was threatened. But when the people began to gather before the new Alliance Building, the clouds disappeared, and the sun cast upon the world floods of autumn light. And so the sky favored us, and God looked kindly down upon His children who had gathered in the name of Poland, a nation whose sufferings are sufficient to expiate the sins of the whole world.</p>
   <p>"At the given command the procession moved. The lead was taken by a division of Polish policemen with Lieutenant Joseph Palczynski at its head. Next came the band under the leadership of Mr. Reibetn, followed by the Polish cavalry under the command of Mr. Andrew Szulc. These were followed by the Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance, flanked by the Polish Falcons' Alliance, which acted as honorary guard. Close to them were the delegates of the various societies, Polish lancers, cadets, and representatives of the numerous Polish Alliance groups as well as societies not affiliated with the Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1100.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"The parade was impressive; more than four thousand Poles participated in it. It was a solemn and serious demonstration of the Polish National Alliance which will long remain in the minds of those who witnessed it. When the parade returned and stopped before the new Polish National Alliance Building, and the Administration entered first, the ladies of the Polish Central Society, according to a typical Polish custom, presented the Administration with bread and salt. Within a short time both halls were filled with the public, and thousands of people were forced to remain outside, since they could not enter for lack of space. The censor of the Polish National Alliance, Mr. Helinski, and the president, Mr. C. Zychlinski, spoke from the balcony to those who were compelled to remain outside."</p>
   <p>Twenty years have elapsed since those inspiring moments. What colossal changes have occurred since then! These changes can best be appreciated by noticing the changes within the building itself. At that time the Alliance Building was too large and was exceedingly spacious; today it is overcrowded. The congestion is so great that the people working there, of whom there are more <pb facs="5423968_8_1101.jpg" n="5"/>than a hundred, trample on one another's feet in passing through the corridors, which also have been transformed into offices. Every department suffers for lack of space. Today the quarters of the board of directors, the offices of the officials, the publication's administrative offices, the editorial rooms, the local print shops of the hand press and the power press, the mailing department, etc., even the library itself, are so badly congested that in spite of moving the museum elsewhere and adding a wing to the building the quarters will soon be completely inadequate.</p>
   <p>The remark, therefore, has been made by the Zgoda that if twenty years ago a mere handful of Alliance members were able to erect a building so impressive for that time, the present large number of Alliance members can erect one which will adequately answer our needs.</p>
   <p>We believe that this will be done. However, before the convention--perhaps the next one--makes the proper enactment, may we be permitted to remind you of former times and to rejoice in the fact that the Alliance Building after <pb facs="5423968_8_1102.jpg" n="6"/>twenty years of existence has become too small? This is the best indication that twenty years hence the new building which we are now thinking of erecting may also be found too small.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
