<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 14,
<date when="1902-04-03">April 3, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">In the Affairs of Women's Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_8_1395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 14,
<date when="1902-04-03">April 3, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE AFFAIRS OF WOMEN'S ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thanks to the newly established constitution, the Alliance lists over 12,000 female members. This vast number of Polish women should partake more frequently in the affairs of the Alliance. We know from facts that the women of the Alliance, belonging to groups with their husbands, are not in the least interested in the affairs of the Alliance.</p>
   <p>They do not attend the group meetings with the expectations of having their husbands fulfill their duties in everything; they know nothing of the administration in their groups; they don't send any of their delegates to be represented at conferences (at the last conference meeting we had the presence of only one woman delegate); in one word, they treat their rights and duties carelessly, negligently, as members of the Alliance. This should not be the case. The Polish women who have joined the Polish National Alliance should not take the attitude with regard only to the benefit from the insurance point of view. The Alliance, classifying a great difference between the males and the females, has <pb facs="5423968_8_1396.jpg" n="2"/>called upon and requested the Polish females to work jointly, and through that, the Alliance says, we can be certain of success in our national politics.</p>
   <p>To achieve this sort of recognition we must stand up, go to work and fulfill our duties as citizens.</p>
   <p>It shall not be long when in all civilized countries the women shall receive the same equality and recognition as that of man in political affairs. Already our generation of women may go to the polls, take part in the parliament and in Congress, and then create with man the laws for the nation, and guide its future.</p>
   <p>The true friends of the people long awaited patiently for this moment, from which they foresaw that we shall derive a great deal of benefit. From their point of view, the women mingling in politics will bring with themselves a great deal of good, smoothness, greater care, and a cleaner slate in the line of politics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1397.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>With the admission of women to the parliament, the women shall advance our schools and institutional budgets, and curtail the costs for war, police department, etc.</p>
   <p>Before we undertake this big job, the good and right thing to do is to prepare ourselves for this task by accomplishing smaller things first. Our Alliance with its finances, its national politics, its activity, is already a small empire, a metropolis on a small scale. It is not only worth to work for it, but to work and prepare yourself for greater and bigger things in the future, the things we predict that shall come soon to us.</p>
   <p>If the men disturb the women of the Alliance in their groups in any way, they are at liberty to establish their own groups, special groups for the women. In this sort of groups the women would have their own government, their treasury, their own politics. This sort of groups could then send out one of their own delegates to the conference and the conference would benefit a great deal by this.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_8_1398.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Well, let us forget for the present about those women who belong to these various groups. We would not care to lose any good member of our organization. A more important factor that confronts us, that is, the Polish women who still don't belong to our society, the ones who still don't belong to any of our groups.</p>
   <p>If there are so many ladies' church societies, why can't there exist Polish national societies and be combined with the brotherly groups of the Z.N.P. (P. N. A).</p>
   <p>The Alliance is waiting and calling out: "Do not go and join any other organization unless it is a strictly national institution, prominent and strong; those organizations which you fellow men and brothers respect as the best."</p>
   <p>We care not to hinder any existing Polish women's organization. But we are free to say, as anyone else is, and to choose the best for ourselves. We are free to grasp anything for our organization that would bring <pb facs="5423968_8_1399.jpg" n="5"/>benefit to our nation. It is the admitted truth even by our enemies that the Polish woman is the treasure of our nation. We would like to see a lot of this treasure in our Alliance.</p>
   <p>It is a known fact that in inviting all of the Polish women to join our Alliance, we would collide with the existing alliance of women. We respect this organization, admit the duties and patriotism of its members and their capability of governing, but that's the way it goes. Everyone strives for his own.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
