<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-06-05">June 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Chicago's "Living Orphans"]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0569</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0569.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-06-05">June 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[CHICAGO'S "LIVING ORPHANS"]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are four thousand Jewish orphans in the city of Poltava [Russia]. There are, perhaps, fifteen thousand Jews in the whole province of Poltava. The four thousand Jewish orphans in Poltava lack either one or both of their parents and their only comfort lies in the thought that the Jewish people will educate them and will take care of them.</p>
   <p>There are about four hundred thousand Jews and forty thousand Jewish orphans in Chicago. The Jewish orphans of Chicago are not orphaned--God forbid--from their parents, but from their people; they are estranged, torn away from their people, and, in a certain sense, from their parents as well. What is sacred to the parents, is a common thing to the children; what the parents hold dear--the children hold cheap; what the parents consider worthy of attainment, the children deem of no importance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0570.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The children are neglected, estranged, torn away from their people. When a child is neglected, we say that he is a "living orphan" even if he has parents. In Chicago we have about forty thousand such living Jewish orphans, forty thousand Jewish children who do not receive any Jewish education and who thus become estranged from and neglected by their people. Forty thousand Jewish orphans in Chicago! Tear your clothes, cover your head with ashes, and lament this terrible calamity!</p>
   <p>The synagogue presidents are busy with the affairs of their synagogues--a new cantor, a new building, a mortgage payment, synagogue decoration, organization of a new choir, increase of dues, etc. In short, they are very busy. What are the one hundred synagogue presidents of Chicago doing for the forty thousand Jewish orphans in the city? For whom are they building the Synagogues? You see only grown-up or elderly Jews in the Synagogues. Where are the children? Haven't the Chicago Jews any children? They have. But the children are orphans, they do not have guardians. From the point of view of Judaism, Chicago Jews are stepparents to their children; they give their <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0571.jpg" n="3"/>children everything but Judaism. They do not do anything, as Jews, for their children and the children grow up as Gentiles. At present, the older Jews are building synagogues--for their own use and not for the children's use because the children, who know nothing about Judaism, grow up like Gentiles and Gentiles do not go to synagogues.</p>
   <p>You, synagogue presidents of Chicago, supervisors prominent citizens, leaders of society--tear your clothes, cover your head with ashes, and weep over this terrible catastrophe! Forty thousand living orphans in the city and nobody cares, nobody does anything to help those Forty thousand orphans!</p>
   <p>You believe that you will succeed in perpetuating Judaism without the school children. You are fools! Jerusalem was destroyed because of the school children and you want to build Judaism in Chicago without the school children--and Chicago is not Jerusalem, even with the school children.</p>
   <p>What shall be done with the forty-thousand Jewish orphans in Chicago? You <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0572.jpg" n="4"/>are all ready to help the orphans in Poltava; why don't you want to help your own orphans?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
