<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-01">Apr. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Mayor Dever Will Help</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0985</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0985.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-01">Apr. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">MAYOR DEVER WILL HELP</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reader will find on another page of today's Courier a report about the interview which a committee of prominent Jewish public workers had with Mayor Dever about the plan of founding a colony by the name of Chicago in Palestine. The Mayor declared himself in sympathy with the plan and promised to extend a helping hand toward its realization. He will appear at one of the many functions which will be arranged during the Keren Hayesod drive and will appeal, as the Mayor of Chicago, to the Jews of Chicago to help found a colony by the name of Chicago in Palestine, to perpetuate in that country the name of a city where the Jews have found so much happiness and prosperity.</p>
   <p>We have no doubt that the idea of founding a colony named Chicago will be realized, not only because it appeals to the pride of Chicago's Jews but <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0986.jpg" n="2"/>because it is an idea which promises many great economic and political possibilities. Just as the Chicago [Jewry] set a good example for other communities to follow when its Jewish representatives headed by Mr. Horwich founded here the first Zionist organization, so will it set now a good example by initiating a movement that will revolutionize our entire colonization work in Palestine. The Chicago Jewry will not be the only group to do this. Jewish groups in other cities in America will do the same. There is such a thing as imitation in the political and social life of a people. This is particularly true when the new venture of a community is successful. It is not only possible but quite probable that Palestine will be covered by a network of Jewish colonies during the next five years, all bearing the names of American cities densely populated by Jews. Within a short time the American-Jewish communities can build in Palestine not less than thirty big Jewish colonies. They can establish these colonies upon such a solid financial foundation that during the next twenty years the many millions which they will cost will be returned to the treasury of the Keren Hayesod, which will enable it to go on with its work without making any <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0987.jpg" n="3"/>further appeals for help.</p>
   <p>This year's drive of the Keren Hayesod, in which Mayor Dever will participate, and which aims to establish in Palestine a colony named Chicago, will be a lively one and indications are that it will be very successful. Many forces which did not take part in previous drives will take part in this one. Mayor Dever is one of the most respected and beloved Mayors Chicago has ever had. His appeal will be of a twofold nature: for a Jewish Palestine and for perpetuation of the name of Chicago in Palestine. There are Jews in Chicago who stand afar from Jewish problems, particularly the Palestine problem, but they are all proud of their Chicago citizenship. They are proud of their city, of its progressive institutions, its progressive spirit, and they will not remain indifferent to an appeal which seeks the perpetuation of the name of this city in Palestine, the fatherland of the Jews and the motherland of human culture. They will surely respond to this appeal. The Keren Hayesod will gain thereby and the plan of founding a Jewish colony by the name of Chicago in Palestine will be realized sooner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0988.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Chicago Keren Hayesod workers, knowing that now they have the support of our esteemed Mayor in their work, will throw themselves into their work with their hearts and souls and will work with greater enthusiasm than they did last year. The campaign this year will really bear a community character. It will not be limited to one part of Chicago. Not only the synagogue Jews, not only the West Side and Northwest Side Jews, but also Jews who belong to different groups, who have other interests, will be absorbed this year in Keren Hayesod work. The old friends of the Keren Hayesod, the synagogue Jews, who up to now have borne the heavier burden and have done most of the work, will now have more energy, a greater desire to work, because they know that they are working for a great plan which has the sympathy of the esteemed, duty-conscious Mayor of this great and booming city.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Jewry is now standing in front of a great historical undertaking. If it should be successful in it--as we hope it will be--then, we have no doubt, Palestine will become a Jewish country much sooner than many people <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0989.jpg" n="5"/>imagine. Many speak of fifty years building activity in Palestine. The truth of the matter is that Palestine can be built up in ten years by intensive work. Of course, the task of building it up will not be fully completed. Is America completely built up? There is plenty of building work to be done in the great and prosperous America. Many generations to come will still be busy in building up this country. A country is never completely built up. Palestine, too, will not be completely built up within ten or fifteen years, but the main work will have been done, and that is what is important. We cannot provide for the next ten coming generations. Every Jewish generation must be the master of its own fortune. We are duty bound to provide for ourselves and for the next coming generation. We can do it during the next ten or fifteen years. [Translator's note: There are five or six more printed lines to this article. They cannot, however, be translated because many words are missing, torn out from the text.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
