<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1918-03-29">Mar. 29, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Holidays and a National Jewish Education</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0646</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0646.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-03-29">Mar. 29, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH HOLIDAYS AND A NATIONAL JEWISH EDUCATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several say: Go back! Return to the ancient customs and ways--to the ancient superstitions! Dig up from the grave that which is already dead long ago! Dress up the skeleton in new clothing and seat him at the head of the family! [The revival of these old customs at home] is what these people call national Jewish education!</p>
   <p>They forget at once, however, one general law of pedagogy (I shall not speak of humanity): namely, not to be false to the children--not to create two religions, one for the adults and one for the youngsters. The truth can be seen through such an hypocritical cloak. Jesuitical relentlessness will be bound to grow there, where one believes that the pure seed of legend is planted.</p>
   <p>No! Not the traditional, religious conduct of the old Jewish generation will help us bring up our children. I cannot go into the synagogue and pray if I do not believe; I cannot wake my child and take him to Slihoth (prayers of forgiveness recited before Rosh Hashanah very early in the morning) if the Slihoth <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0647.jpg" n="2"/>service is of no importance to me; I cannot fast on the Day of Atonement; and I cannot observe the special dietary food laws on Passover. If I inculcated in my children religious precepts and practices I would only fool them. That would implant within them a hatred toward me for my hypocrisy. I want to be true to the younger generation and true to myself, and I also want to implant within their hearts the beauty of a legend--the sentiment of the old poetry--which will shine in their soul throughout the rest of their lives.</p>
   <p>Aren't there any means?</p>
   <p>If we would only think more about the way we live and do more for our future--if only that our practical acts were saturated and penetrated with our idealism--then we would already find a way to give our children an harmonious education. But this would require a permanent control over our acts.</p>
   <p>For everybody's sake we must become Jews--that means we must become in practice what we are in theory. To be Jewish, however, means that one should speak <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0648.jpg" n="3"/>Yiddish, conduct himself in a Jewish manner, and feel that he is bound to the Jewish past. My words should not be taken in the usual way. I demand sincerity from our national, democratic, intelligent Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
