<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-13">June 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Can Yiddish and Hebrew Be Assimilated?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-13">June 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CAN YIDDISH AND HEBREW BE ASSIMILATED?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Cultural history tells us of racial and national assimilation. From this we understand also that language assimilation exists. Furthermore the intermingling of languages often leads to the development of national self-respect and independence.</p>
   <p>We do not have to go far to find an example. The English language is a mixture fundamentally of two languages, German and French - and yet English is one of the richest languages while the English nation is one the most independent.</p>
   <p>But the problem before us is, can Yiddish and Hebrew be assimilated? Has not the assimilation process of both our national languages already begun even without our conscious participation? It seems to me that Yiddish and Hebrew have long since begun to mingle and are still being assimilated.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0633.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is noteworthy. The "in-laws" so to speak, the Hebrewists and the Yiddishists, fight among themselves and are at swords' points while before their very eyes occurs this romantic and necessary union.</p>
   <p>If we [were not blinded] by party affiliation, either Yiddishist or Hebrewist, but permitted ourselves to investigate the new literary productions we would observe the conspicuous assimilation tendency of the two languages.</p>
   <p>A few examples: Read Mendele's [translators note: Mendele Mocher Seforim (pen name) - Shalom Abromowitch - called the grandfather of Yiddish literature] Yiddish works and Mendele's Hebrew works and you will feel their relationship. The charm of our "Grandfather's" Yiddish flows through his Hebrew writings and the delightful quality of his Hebrew works shines throughout his Yiddish.</p>
   <p>It is quite clear that both his languages spring from one source, from one poetic soul, and that is mainly from our national folklore which is largely a mixture of Yiddish and Hebrew, a synthesis of past and present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0634.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Another illustration. Before me lies the story book of Rab Nachman Braslaver. These stories are the greatest treasures our new literature possesses. In the same volume we find the stories printed both in Hebrew and in Yiddish.</p>
   <p>As I read these wonderful stories in both versions I am frequently apt to forget which is written in Hebrew and which in Yiddish.</p>
   <p>One overlaps the other. One borrows words, expressions and descriptions from the other. The Hebrew is a kind of Yiddish and the Yiddish - a sort of Hebrew.</p>
   <p>Numerous such illustrations can be found in our literature.</p>
   <p>I believe for example that Peretz's Chasidishe tales [Translators note: written in Yiddish] are more Hebrew than Shpoman's or Brener's Hebrew works.</p>
   <p>At times the works of the last two mentioned appear to be translations from the Yiddish or Russian, while Peretz's best prose stems from original sources.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0635.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Unfortunately Hebrew at the present time is more of a dead rather than a living language.</p>
   <p>The Biblical style is the Hebrew style. However there also can be found several Yiddish works which appear to be more Hebrew than most works written in the Holy Language (Hebrew) which themselves smack of the jargon (Yiddish) in both character and form.</p>
   <p>We should and must Hebrewize the Yiddish (simply from a purely artistic motive). Instead of Yiddishizing English or Russian words we should rather Yiddishize the Hebrew. Yiddish as a result will become more colorful and more brilliant.</p>
   <p>Hebrew writers on the other hand, will themselves unconsciously jargonize their writings. Life itself will force them to do it. The contents, the gist of their books, songs and articles will compel them, even against their will, to depart from mechanical rhetoric.</p>
   <p>Therefore there is no need to worry much when we see and hear the "in-laws"</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0636.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>(Yiddishists and Hebrewists) wrangling over the question, which language is our national one?</p>
   <p>Life itself will straighten matters and reconcile the two. They are "in-laws" and their fate has been determined in Heaven. Just as we cannot and must not ignore the past so we cannot and must not set aside the present.</p>
   <p>A healthy national life is a synthesis, a sum total of all the folk epics of all the generations.</p>
   <p>And we so ardently hope to build a healthy national home life in Palestine</p>
   <p>Leo Kenig.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
