<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
Volume 5. Week of <date when="1925-01-02">January 2, 1925</date>. Page 4.
<title level="a">A Jewish Press Club.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorials (1)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0939</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0939.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
Volume 5. Week of <date when="1925-01-02">January 2, 1925</date>. Page 4.
<title level="a">A JEWISH PRESS CLUB.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIALS (1)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some years ago a Jewish press club was organized in Chicago. Though the organization was short-lived, owing to personal antagonisms peculiar to the time.</p>
   <p>Now comes the suggestion (from the Chronicle, be it said) for another Jewish club of the same kind. The time is over-ripe for such a project. The Jewish population of the city is several times greater than it was at the time of the first attempt. The number of Jewish writers and those interested in the written word is incomparably greater. But as yet we have no center, no organized facilities for fostering interest in literature and art in general.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0940.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We need such a center, such a group, to encourage writers, to bring out the talent that often is stifled for lack of a little moral assistance, to speak and act coherently for the community. When a great son of our people comes to this city, someone who has done something worth while in any field of knowledge, such a group could "do the honors" efficiently, economically and enjoyably; whereas, now, there is no one to take the lead in such matters.</p>
   <p>But with a Jewish press club, arts club, the situation would be marvelously changed for the better. True, there is the Peretz Schreiberverein, but this is merely a union of Yiddish scribes, for professional purposes. What we have in mind is an organization of literati, professional and amateur, and of those interested in other arts, whether as workers or as patrons; an organization operated on a broad scale for the benefit of the community as a whole.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
