<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-06">Feb. 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Jews Will Gather Tonight in the Synagogues to Honor the Friend of the Jews Who Has Died</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-06">Feb. 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO JEWS WILL GATHER TONIGHT IN THE SYNAGOGUES TO HONOR THE FRIEND OF THE JEWS WHO HAS DIED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Memorial meetings will be held tonight at seven-thirty in many synagogues of the city to honor the memory of the late ex-President Woodrow Wilson, whose body will be laid in eternal rest today. Chicago Jews will thus have the opportunity to express openly their sorrow at the death of one of the best friends they ever had in the non-Jewish world. It is expected that every synagogue will be crowded and that many people, as Americans and as Jews, will attend the memorial meetings.</p>
   <p>The memorial meetings will be held at the following synagogues:</p>
   <p>West Side: Congregation Anshe Kneseth Israel, 3411 Douglas Boulevard; Congregation Kehilath Jacob, Douglas Boulevard and Hamlin Avenue; Congregation Anshe Sholom, Ashland Avenue and Polk Street; Congregation Beth <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1368.jpg" n="2"/>Hakne-Seth Anshe Vilno, 508 South Springfield Avenue.</p>
   <p>Northwest Side: Congregation Tiphereth Zion, 1243 North Lincoln Street.</p>
   <p>South Side: Congregation Beth Hamidrosh Hagodol Anshe Dorom, 5129 Indiana Avenue; Congregation Beth Abraham, 3019 South Wabash Avenue. The meeting there will begin at seven o'clock. At the Congregation Rodfei Zedek, 54th Street and Greenwood Avenue, the meeting will begin at three-thirty in the afternoon.</p>
   <p>All the meetings will follow the same program. The chairman will open the meeting and give the floor to the rabbi of the synagogue. The Cantor will chant a prayer. A speaker will deliver a speech in English. Chapter forty-nine of the Psalms will be sung. A speaker will deliver a speech in Yiddish. An appropriate resolution will be passed. The Cantor will chant the "Prayer for the Dead".</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1369.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The more Jews there are present at the memorial meetings in the synagogues, the more credit will be reflected on the local Jewish community--the greater will be the respect expressed for the friend of the Jews.</p>
   <p>Woodrow Wilson has done us many favors. He has shown us true friendship, in behalf not only of the American Jews, but of the Jews of the entire world. Let us, therefore, crowd the synagogues, and take part in the holy memorial meetings.</p>
   <p>These are the important things which the ex-President Wilson did for the Jews: The first time ex-President Wilson showed his friendly feeling toward Jews was when he appointed Louis D. Brandeis as justice of the Supreme Court, in spite of the great opposition that arose against that appointment.</p>
   <p>Woodrow Wilson vetoed anti-immigration bills three times because they were <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1370.jpg" n="4"/>aimed against the Jews. Woodrow Wilson wrote a letter to Dr. Stephen S. Wise, in which he declared himself in favor of Palestine as a homeland for the Jewish people. This letter later made it possible for the English government to issue the well-known Balfour declaration.</p>
   <p>Woodrow Wilson appointed Morgenthau and then Elkus as ambassador to Turkey, Felix Warburg as chairman of the Federal Reserve Board, Bernard Baruch, Julius Rosenwald, and other great Jews to posts of honor, which appointments helped win the great war. During the war, Woodrow Wilson prevented a pogrom by the Russian Army.</p>
   <p>Before he left for France, Wilson had a conference with Stephen S. Wise, Louis Marshall, and Judge Julian W. Mack. He discussed the Jewish problem with them. Woodrow Wilson did a great deal to help the Jewish delegates at the Paris conference win [recognition of the] rights of minorities. Keep all these things in your mind; remember them!</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1371.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The public is asked to come on time to the above-mentioned synagogues because the services will begin promptly at seven-thirty. Jews are expected to behave with dignity at these meetings. It is expected that the memorial meetings will be conducted in a respectful, and impressive manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
