<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-22">Feb. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Volunteers Needed for Keren Hayesod]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-22">Feb. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[VOLUNTEERS NEEDED FOR KEREN HAYESOD]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The wheels of the Keren Hayesod are turning rapidly, but the ten thousand Zionists are sleeping as sweetly as though they had just had a heavy meal. Many faces can be seen in the offices of the Keren Hayesod in Chicago, but not the faces of the Chicago Zionists.</p>
   <p>It seems as if the work of the Keren Hayesod does not enter the thoughts of the Chicago Zionists. As long as there is an administrative committee and an executive committee, why should the Zionists think about the work? How, when, and by what means is the work going to be accomplished? Well, let Messrs. B. Horwich, Judge Shulman, Max Shulman, P. Lubin, Isidor Liederman and Samuel Phillipson worry about it.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Zionists have slept throughout the year, they are snoring loudly <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1094.jpg" n="2"/>now, and God alone knows when they will awake from their slumber. If they awake too late, they will find the ruins of Chicago Zionism and of the Chicago Keren Hayesod, and the blame for it will fall upon their heads. It will be their fault if Chicago Zionism becomes a thing of scorn and derision.</p>
   <p>If the Chicago Zionists were not tobacco-snuffing grandpas, but earnest, energetic Jews, they would organize five hundred volunteers for the Keren Hayesod campaign in Chicago. The campaign cannot be a success without volunteers. The money must come from the masses, and volunteers are needed to collect the money.</p>
   <p>The Zionists of Chicago did not work too hard last year, and it would not do them any harm to devote a week's time for the Keren Hayesod work. Every Chicago Zionist has friends and acquaintances to whom he may turn for the Keren Hayesod. Everyone can do something about collecting money.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1095.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That is why I say to you: Gentlemen, Zionists! Stop yawning if you are awake, and stop snoring if you are asleep; get busy with Keren Hayesod work and help make the campaign a success. Do not depend upon individuals or committees. Either we will build Zion with our united forces, or Zion will not be built.</p>
   <p>Chicago Zionists! Do not take a nap, do not yawn--get to work; otherwise, we will be disgraced; it is better to be busy than to be disgraced.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
