<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-01">Sept. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish National Workers Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joshua Shtulman</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-01">Sept. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH NATIONAL WORKERS ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Joshua Shtulman</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Shortly after the Poale Zion party was officially organized in this country, a few individual members began to think about organizing a workers order, which would satisfy the material needs of Jewish workers, and, at the same time, would not be in contradiction with their national sentiments and inclinations. This idea soon began to awaken interest among the Poale Zion members throughout the country. The question of creating such an order became a point on the agenda of the Buffalo Party Council at the close of 1908.</p>
   <p>In 1908 Comrades [Translator's note: The word "comrade" here does not refer to a communist or socialist in which sense it is commonly used today.] Wexler, Miller and Meyer Brown of Philadelphia started the practical work necessary to realize this plan and launched a benevolent verein in Philadelphia <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1267.jpg" n="2"/>under the name "National Workers Alliance".</p>
   <p>Shortly afterwards Poale Zion Benevolent Vereins were organized in New York, Pittsburgh, Chicago and in other cities. Despite the fact that these vereins were in contact with each other, they all expressed the same purpose: "to remove the Jewish worker from the atmosphere of assimilation which asphyxiates him and to bring him into a purely Jewish atmosphere where he can move about freely."</p>
   <p>This plan answered the demand of the time and satisfied the need of Jewish workers who were pursuing nationalist ideals. This proves to us that the intelligent Jewish workers of that period were vitally interested in such an organization and participated in heated discussions regarding it. It also indicates that they joyfully welcomed the proposal to establish an independent order which would give the necessary material assurance and benefits to workers, and would simultaneously satisfy their national aims.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1268.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The idea spread throughout cities and states. Group after group began to organize. They soon wanted to hold a convention for the purpose of clarifying this movement and of creating a common bond among the various groups.</p>
   <p>The conference was held in June, 1910. This conference voiced the common opinion that the National Workers Alliance should strive to unite all nationalistically inclined Jewish workers on the grounds of common economic and national interests. The New York Poale Zion Benevolent Verein is self-sufficient and independent of the Philadelphia verein. The former distributed literature to a few vereins and groups urging them to join the New York verein.</p>
   <p>The discussion in several vereins of the party [Poale Zion] forced the Central Committee of the Poale Zion to take an official stand on an important question. The Central Committee decided to put this question on the agenda of the fourth Poale Zion Convention in Chicago. The fourth convention, which was held in Chicago, had to clarify this point: viz, the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1269.jpg" n="4"/>solution to the territorial problem of the Jewish people. This convention also urged the delegates to organize Alliance branches in their cities.</p>
   <p>The individual vereins and groups gradually grew weak and temporarily broke away [from the central organization], the first Philadelphia verein included. The work in the verein came to a standstill for a few months. Together with the General Executive which was independently formed by the Pittsburgh verein, with Comrade Seigel as secretary, the Central Committee of the Poale Zion took the initiative in organizing one verein after another with the aim of holding a general convention in order to evolve a general platform and to formulate the principles of the Alliance. Later the committee decided to call an organizational conference of the Alliance in Rochester.</p>
   <p>An appeal was sent to the comrades throughout the country to organize more vereins in order to have a large representation of delegates who would familiarize themselves with all questions, and would then consider them carefully.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1270.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This conference had to establish not only the principles of the verein and to draw up a constitution, but it also had to decide on a specific insurance system and to begin work to legalize the organization. Twenty-five delegates representing eleven vereins attended this conference, which lasted four days.</p>
   <p>One of the basic points that the conference had to clarify was: The solution to the territorial problem of the Jewish people. The radical Poale Zion delegates demanded that the position be a positive one, i.e., the Alliance should clearly explain that the complete national revival and liberation of the Jewish people is only possible in their own land--Palestine. The majority argued, however, that the National Workers Alliance should become the central body of a large number of Jewish workers, and the Alliance could be that only if every nationalistically inclined Jewish worker joins, but as soon as it embraces the Poale Zion program, it limits its possibilities of growth and development.</p>
   <p>A second important question with which the convention had to cope was the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1271.jpg" n="6"/>question of legalization. This was tied up with the question of determining the insurance system for the verein.</p>
   <p>Through the decision to adopt the most modern and safest insurance system, known as the "American Experience Table", which is based on a legal reserve of four percent, the convention laid the foundation for a solid and strong National Workers Alliance.</p>
   <p>The following basic principles were adopted:</p>
   <p>A. The National Workers Alliance endeavors to organize all Jewish workers on the following bases:</p>
   <p>1. Mutual aid in case of need, sickness and death.</p>
   <p>2. Education of Jewish workers in full consciousness of their national and social interests.</p>
   <p>B. The National Workers Alliance supports all workers who seek the national liberation and revival of the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>C. The National Workers Alliance supports those trades which will lead to <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1272.jpg" n="7"/>the strengthening and emancipation of the working class.</p>
   <p>By establishing in the Alliance such an insurance system and inculcating a spirit of nationalism and liberalism, which will lead to the liberation of the Jewish people and to the strengthening and fortifying of the working-class position, it became possible for the Alliance to become one of the most important and necessary workers' institutions in the country. The rapid development of the Alliance throughout the country is attributed to the two above-mentioned factors.</p>
   <p>The general sentiment for organizing all nationalistically inclined Jewish groups into a huge Alliance which would admit and support all workers who seek the liberation of our people and the emancipation of the working class resounded among the Chicago-Poale Zion comrades in 1908.</p>
   <p>On January 15, 1909 there was an appeal in the Yiddishe Arbeiter Stimme (Jewish Workers' Voice) by M. Melamed, urging all nationalistically minded <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1273.jpg" n="8"/>and liberal Jewish workers to help organize the National Workers Alliance. This appeal impressed the small group in Chicago. It encouraged them to begin intensive work to organize an Alliance branch. Greater numbers of Jewish workers became interested in the new organization. The small group increased, and on Monday, June 4, 1909 the foundation was laid in Chicago. The first branch, with Mr. Harry Resnick as secretary, was organized in the Hebrew Institute. The verein, however, did not exist long. It disintegrated rapidly. Later a few futile attempts were made to revive it.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Poale Zion Convention primarily clarified the position of the Alliance. And with marked success the comrades again undertook the organizational work until they finally laid the foundation for the organization of the first branch. The branch was officially installed on May 15, 1910. The Verein participated in formulating the agenda of the organizational conference which was held in Rochester in June 1910. It sent A. Molin as a delegate and instructed him to vote for an unrestricted platform which would give the Alliance the opportunity of admitting all nationalistically <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1274.jpg" n="9"/>inclined Jewish workers as members.</p>
   <p>The organizational conference united all groups and vereins into one Alliance with a unified program. It also encouraged the comrades to swing energetically into the organizational work in order to strengthen the Alliance in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The first convention in Albany shaped the Alliance's spiritual character by approving the principles adopted at the organizational conference in Rochester. The legalization of the Alliance was greeted with great celebration on January 6, 1913.</p>
   <p>Conscious of the fact that the financial side of the Alliance was absolutely secure, the comrades began, with greater animation and interest, to develop the Alliance's activities, making the idealistic, as well as the practical functions of the Alliance more popular among Jewish workers in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Alliance in Chicago became active in various aspects of social work, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1275.jpg" n="10"/>carried on agitation among Jewish workers for nationalist and radical thought, became interested in educational work and organized the first daily Jewish Peoples School, in the John Smythe School, after 5000 signatures were secured. The Alliance also prevailed on the Chicago Public Library Board to open a library branch and reading rooms in the Lawndale district (the present Douglas Park Library Branch on Twelfth Street between Central Park and St. Louis Avenues). It is now active in organizing Young Macabee Clubs, supporting Jewish unions, participating in strike conferences held by Jewish workers and in all social and labor activities. It has become an all important factor in Chicago-Jewish life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
