<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-08">Jan. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Hadassah</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1655</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1655.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-08">Jan. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">HADASSAH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regional conference of the Hadassah, held on Monday, January 1, at the Hotel La Salle, was one of "high lights" and the out of town delegates, as well as Chicago Hadassahs who attended, were richly repaid for the entire day spent in the interests of Hadassah work.</p>
   <p>The morning session, presided over by Miss Pearl Franklin, president of the Chicago Hadassah, was devoted to discussion of the different phases of the work on part of the local members of the organization and the many out of town delegates. Short talks were given by the following:</p>
   <p>The Medical Unit, Mrs. Benjamin Davis; Parlor Meetings as a Means of Obtaining Members, Mrs. Isidore Natkin; Formation of New Chapters, Mrs. Abe Simon; The Tithe Campaign, Mrs. Bertha Read.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1656.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss Rebecca Blumenthal, a Hadassah who has just returned from Palestine, spoke vividly of her impressions, not so much of the land itself, as of the idealism of the men and women settled there, and their determination at whatever sacrifice to rehabilitate the ancient Home Land.</p>
   <p>The luncheon, presided over by Miss Anna Levin, outdid even Hadassah luncheons of the past in its spontaniety, its moments of inspirational fervor, generously seasoned with hearty laughter evoked when the entire assemblage sang the songs, to the tune of popular airs, composed by Hadassah's own poetess, Miss Jennie Pearstein. In addition was a dramatic reading of "Die Freiheit" by Maurice Rosenfeld, rendered by Evelyn Hattis Fox and Jewish songs, sung by Miss Florence Bernstein. Both Miss Bernstein's singing and Mrs. Fox's readings roused the audience to intense enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The afternoon meeting, also presided over by Miss Franklin, was given over to discussion of Hadassah's work, in talks by Dr. Arthur Ruppin, Shmarya Levin, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1657.jpg" n="3"/>and Mr. Louis Lipsky, given to a very large audience. The musical program of the afternoon was rendered by David Schonthal, violinist, and Miss Ethel Ohrenstein in vocal selections accompanied by Miss Hadassah Delson.</p>
   <p>The Hadassahs in Chicago, in a city abounding with clubs, stand unique in the quality of their members, their wholehearted devotion to a sacred cause. No organization can boast of more women who work with less thought of self in a desire to be of service. It is this quality among its leaders which has so rapidly increased its membership until it embraces the finest women in Chicago, and it is this quality, this singleness of purpose, which stamps so indelibly on the minds of all who attend every function they give.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
