<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-22">Feb. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Washington's Birthday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1411</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1411.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-22">Feb. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WASHINGTON'S BIRTHDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago immigrants of all nationalities who have become citizens of the United States will assemble today in the Auditorium to pay homage to the memory of the first President of the United States, the Field-Marshal of the Revolutionary Army who freed this country and made it a home of freedom for all people, regardless of race, religion, sex, or color: George Washington.</p>
   <p>And it is seldom that the observance of this day does not affect the immigrant. The noblest people from all parts of the world have sympathized with the revolting farmer of the New World. On one side stood the well-trained armies of the British despots, and on the other the free citizens who fought for their independence with the aid of liberty-loving enthusiasts who came from remote lands in order to join the fight for justice.</p>
   <p>From then on this vast country, from the Atlantic to the Pacific, has succeeded in being a Land of Liberty for those who abandoned the countries in which they <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1412.jpg" n="2"/>were born and reared because they coveted a land where all men would be equal and where everyone would have the opportunity to develop his ability without any restrictions by the rich and the powerful.</p>
   <p>But since that time--since the great general signed his name to the Declaration of Independence which was dictated by the noblest human sentiments of truth and justice--many waters have run over the millrace. The people who inhabit this great free country think that the population is too large; that equal rights should not be granted to the foreigners; that the poor immigrant is only useful when he does all the hard work and lives in submission and servitude. But should he protest against conditions, should he become active in social movements and voice his opinion, the older children of Washington become full of wrath and speak ill of the foreigners who dictate to the natives.</p>
   <p>Washington's birthday, like every other holiday that reminds us of lofty ideals, is therefore chiefly a holiday for the immigrants who still believe in those ideals and are ready to fight for them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
