<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-21">Mar. 21, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">16th Street Bank Closed; President and Cashier Held</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-21">Mar. 21, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">16th STREET BANK CLOSED; PRESIDENT AND CASHIER HELD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Andrew Russell, the state auditor, declared yesterday that there is a strong possibility that the depositors of the 16th Street Bank will receive one hundred per cent of their deposits. In any event, they will receive no less than eighty per cent of their money. The doors of the 16th Street Bank, 3500 West 16th Street, were closed yesterday morning upon the order of the state bank examiner Mr. H. M. Sevedge, who, together with his assistant, proceeded immediately to examine the books of the bank. According to the present estimate, the bank has a shortage of approximately $150,000.</p>
   <p>Samuel W. Maltz, former president of the bank, and Jacob Kalish [cashier] are being held until the investigation of the state examiner is completed. A criminal charge will be brought against those who are responsible for the bank's condition. States Attorney Crow instructed his assistants to begin a grand jury investigation of the bank.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0107.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The exact number of depositors of the 16th Street Bank, most of whom are small Jewish businessmen and workers, who stand a chance to lose [their deposits] will not be known until after the investigation of the books is completed. Mr. Kalish, cashier of the bank, asserts that the depositors will receive no less than eighty per cent of their money.</p>
   <p>The news that the bank closed caused a great deal of excitement in the vicinity of 16th Street. A large crowd of depositors congregated around the closed bank. Police were there, ready to quell a riot. The crowd, however, was calm. Apparently, the condition of the 16th Street Bank has been weak since last summer, when the state bank examiner, Mr. Sevedge compelled Mr. Maltz to resign as president. J. M. Austin was elected in his place.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sevedge issued the following statement yesterday: "Three weeks ago, a committee, consisting of Herman Elenbogen, Louis J. Robin, S. B. Komaiko, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0108.jpg" n="3"/>Samuel Ginsberg, Edward Berkson, and Rolling M. Coleman, was requested to make an investigation of the assets and liabilities of the 16th Street Bank, with a view to take over the management of the bank for the purpose of protecting depositors, as well as stockholders.</p>
   <p>"Ten days ago they were elected as directors and immediately began to examine the bank's condition. The investigation disclosed a condition that made it impossible for these men to remain as directors and officers of the bank. They reported this situation to the office of the state auditor. The committee had discovered that certain liabilities, of which the amount is not known, were not entered into the books. Entanglements in real-estate transactions and in the issuance of gold bonds were also discovered. In short, the bank had to be closed and its books examined. It will take a week to complete the examination."</p>
   <p>Jesse M. Austin is now president of the bank. B. J. Swetta is vice-president and secretary, and Jacob Kalish is cashier. The capital assets of the bank are <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0109.jpg" n="4"/>$100,000 and when it closed last night, the resources and liabilities were estimated at $725,000. The bank, it is said, had a sum total of $700,000 in deposits, and of that sum $150,000 is missing.</p>
   <p>Officials of the state bank examiner's office said yesterday that from the books it is obvious that the officers of the bank had violated state banking laws, and are, therefore, liable to criminal prosecution.</p>
   <p>Samuel W. Maltz, former president of the bank, was taken into the States Attorney's office yesterday to give an account of his transactions and manipulations during the period that he was president. Detectives had raided simultaneously the offices of the Real-Estate Securities and the Modern Realty Company, two firms organized and run by Samuel Maltz. Evidently, he carried on the business of these two offices with money from the bank.</p>
   <p>At the hearing in the States Attorney's office, Maltz admitted that he had <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0110.jpg" n="5"/>borrowed one hundred thousand dollars from the bank for investments in two buildings of which he is the owner. He borrowed the money from the bank for a first mortgage, although the buildings already had first mortgages. Maltz is thirty-five years old. Before he became a bank president, he worked as a brakeman on the railroad. Austin, the present president of the bank, was a former conductor.</p>
   <p>Jacob Kalish, cashier of the 16th Street Bank, lays the entire blame of the bank crash on Maltz, whose dubious speculations led to the crash, he claims. Mr. Herman Elenbogen, who was a member of the new Board of Directors that was authorized to reorganize the bank, and who was forced to resign because the bank was too far entangled, stated yesterday that he believed that the depositors would sustain only a small loss. Mr. Elenbogen also said that Mr. Maltz is chiefly responsible for the crash.</p>
   <p>"After Mr. Maltz resigned, at the request of the state bank examiner, Mr. <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0111.jpg" n="6"/>Austin was elected president," said Mr. Elenbogen. "I believe that Mr. Maltz also controlled the bank afterwards and his resignation did not improve the bank's condition. Our investigation proved that the bank is loaded with mortgages and several first mortgages turned out to be second mortgages. In two cases, we compelled Maltz to return the money on such mortgages.</p>
   <p>"The bank had $700,000 in deposits. I first become aware of the bank's condition a few weeks ago, when I was asked to do something for the bank. I invited a few other bankers and directors to assist me in the work. We finally became convinced that nothing could be done and became disassociated from the bank on Monday evening."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
