<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-09-01">Sept. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Rabbi Meyer Berlin in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1162</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1162.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-09-01">Sept. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">RABBI MEYER BERLIN IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The visit of Rabbi Meyer Berlin to Chicago and the conferences which he has held here with various Jewish personalities will surely lead to a clarification of certain misunderstandings about the Mizrachi [Orthodox wing within Zionist group] and its relationship to the Zionist organization.</p>
   <p>It is highly regrettable that at this historical moment, all the Zionist forces cannot work in unison despite certain basic differences which have developed in the past few years and which are difficult to eliminate at the present time. Up until now, we always heard the Zionists' side of the argument and had the opportunity to hear only the arguments advanced by the Zionist organization. All Zionist supporters were convinced that the Mizrachi did not work in unison with the Zionist organization because it demanded vast financial resources; the Zionists felt that the differences were more of a financial character than one of principle.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1163.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But if we listened for a moment to the arguments of the Mizrachi leadership, then we would look at the matter differently. We do not, as yet, wish to come to any conclusion, but we do maintain that the Mizrachi should not be condemned before we hear its side of the controversy.</p>
   <p>The readers of the Courier will soon have the opportunity to acquaint themselves with the facts about the Mizrachi. They will soon have an official statement issued by the Mizrachi leader, Rabbi Meyer Berlin himself. In the light of that statement it will be seen that first, the Mizrachi was ready to co-operate in a peaceful manner with the Zionist organization. Second, the Mizrachi asks only that which it has been promised, and third, the Mizrachi has sufficient ground for dissatisfaction with the general Zionist policies and administration. If the Zionist headquarters in New York are unable to deny the charges advanced by the Mizrachi leader, then every impartial Zionist will have to revise his previous views as to the relationship between the Mizrachi and American Zionism.</p>
   <p>It seems that at the New York headquarters of the Zionist organization a <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1164.jpg" n="3"/>policy is being pursued which has for its purpose the destruction of the legitimate factions within Zionism, viz., the Mizrachi and the Poale Zion [Socialist wing in Zionist group]. Naturally, if such a purpose exists, then one can understand why the New York headquarters belittle the Mizrachi. Yet, we wish to remind our leaders in New York that they cannot carry out this policy without the sanction of the Zionist Congress because the latter recognized the legitimacy of both factions. We doubt very much whether the Congress would sanction the policy of the American Zionist organization.</p>
   <p>It is, nevertheless, very regrettable and deplorable that the two Zionist groups, the [regular] Zionists and the Mizrachi, cannot work in harmony and as a result, Zionism itself suffers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
