<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-15">Apr. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Men and Money Needed for the Rebuilding of Palestine</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0968</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0968.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-15">Apr. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">MEN AND MONEY NEEDED FOR THE REBUILDING OF PALESTINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Balfour Declaration gave our people a homeland in Palestine. The responsibility of rebuilding and bringing life to Palestine rests upon all Jews.</p>
   <p>Much has been accomplished in the past years. Still more remains to be done in the coming years.</p>
   <p>Jews in all parts of the world, particularly in the countries where they are oppressed and persecuted, strive to settle in Palestine.</p>
   <p>They are ready to go there knowing beforehand the difficulties which are connected with pioneering work in a country that has been neglected and [left to] waste for hundreds of years.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0969.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Idealism and love of the nation force them to return to their ancestral land, to help build the land culturally, religiously, economically, and agriculturally, so that Palestine may once more lift her voice among the nations and be again as strong and beautiful as she was in the past.</p>
   <p>The rebuilding of Palestine demands men and money--men to work for the success of the Keren Hayesod campaign and money to enable the Keren Hayesod to go on with its rebuilding of Palestine.</p>
   <p>This is an appeal made by Jews to Jews, particularly to the Jews who live in blessed America and whom the circumstances enable to be the driving force in this movement.</p>
   <p>Three hundred thousand dollars is the sum that the great Jewish community of Chicago is asked to contribute this year.</p>
   <p>The Keren Hayesod campaign begins now! You are urged to give to the Keren</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0970.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Hayesod! Give with an open hand, give freely, give in proportion to your means!</p>
   <p>Build Palestine!</p>
   <p>Keren Hayesod</p>
   <p>118 North LaSalle Street, Chicago.</p>
   <p>(This advertisement was paid by the Community State Bank, Roosevelt Road and Central Park Avenue. Max Shulman, president.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
