<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-30">Aug. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Growth of Jewish Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-30">Aug. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE GROWTH OF JEWISH CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jewish Chicago is growing very rapidly. A great deal of progress has been made during the last few years in all fields of Jewish life in our city. This progress has been particularly noticeable in the field of institutional life. Many new institutions have arisen. The most important of them are: the Hebrew Theological College, the two infant homes, the home at Lake Forest for Jews who are incurables or cripples, and the establishment of a Jewish kosher hospital on the West Side.</p>
   <p>The growth of the Jewish press in Chicago has kept pace during the last few years with the growth of institutional life. Chicago now has more Jewish newspapers proportionally, than any other city in America. This is particularly <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0561.jpg" n="2"/>true of the Jewish press in the English language. New York has two Jewish weeklies in English, Chicago has six. Just as Chicago has been for many years the center of Jewish philanthropy in America, so it is now the center of Jewish journalism in America.</p>
   <p>This rapid growth of Jewish life in Chicago must lead to a unity of forces. Life itself demands a concentration of our forces because growth of activity and division of forces do not harmonize. This struggle to unite our forces has already expressed itself in the philanthropic field. The so-called German Jews are ready to accede to the demands of the Orthodox Jews, in order to make possible the merger of both institutions. We understand that all the necessary spiritual and administrative preparations have already been made for the merger of these two great charity organizations of our city.</p>
   <p>The Orthodox Jews in Chicago, however, are still unable to understand the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0562.jpg" n="3"/>importance of uniting our forces. Neither the Chicago Orthodox rabbis nor the Chicago Orthodox congregations are properly organized. The Reform rabbis are organized; they have their Rabbinical Association. The congregations of the United Synagogues are also organized in one body, but the Orthodox congregations are not yet united. We now have every opportunity of creating an official judicial council in Chicago, which could become an ornament to Chicago Orthodox Jewry. We can do it at the present time because one of the great men of our age is now living in Chicago. He is a genius of the Torah and of wisdom, a man any judicial council would be proud to have at its head. However, Chicago Orthodoxy moves very slowly; it is slower than any other Jewish group in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We believe that it is high time for the Chicago Orthodoxy to attempt to unite its forces, because later it may be too late. The Orthodox Jews must be united, now that the entire philanthropic life in our community is regulated by one management, now that the Amalgamated Jewish Charities have included an <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0563.jpg" n="4"/>educational program in their activities. Furthermore, there is soon going to be founded an educational council, which will represent various groups.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Orthodoxy should utilize the presence of such a great man as the rabbi from Lomza in the work of uniting our forces. We understand that Rabbi [Judah] Gordon, although he is nearly seventy years old, is ready to put his great authority and his great influence at the service of the Orthodox Jews of Chicago, to help unite the forces of the Chicago Orthodoxy.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the Association of Orthodox Synagogues of Chicago, with the approval of Rabbi Gordon, have called a meeting for this evening at the Grenshaw Street Talmud Torah. Problems relating to the unification of the Orthodox forces in Chicago will be considered, we are told, at this meeting of rabbis and synagogue presidents. We hope that no rabbi or <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0564.jpg" n="5"/>synagogue president will fail to attend this meeting. The rabbi of Lomza will address the meeting and plans of great importance to Chicago Orthodox Jewry will be discussed.</p>
   <p>This meeting may become an historic one if the rabbis and prominent citizens who represent Chicago Orthodoxy, should begin to work seriously, conscientiously, and with a firm will.</p>
   <p>We expect a great deal from this meeting because the Orthodox Jews of Chicago now have a great rabbinical authority upon which they can lean.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
