<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1880-10-08">Oct. 8, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">How to Raise Funds for the United Hebrew Relief Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0054</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0054.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1880-10-08">Oct. 8, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">HOW TO RAISE FUNDS FOR THE UNITED HEBREW RELIEF ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not necessary to go back to the early history of Chicago to trace the orgin of our Jewish charities. Those who have lived here over a quarter of a century know full well that a spitit of unselfishness and self-sacrifice called them into life. As long as communities are small this spitit is less apt to die out. The moment strange elements begin to mingle with the first settlers the stream of sentiment flows in a different direction. And when, after a lapse of many years, the new population vastly outnumbers the old, we must not be surprised that, as in matters pertaining to societies, congregations, clubs, etc., Israelites have become estranged from one another, so have they separated with respect to the problem of public charities.</p>
   <p>Chicago is often called a bee hive of business. The city is young and its businessmen are too much engrossed with their affairs to devote much time to art, charity, etc. There are too many hunters in the arena, and each one <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0055.jpg" n="2"/>is eager to carry off the highest prize. Business in the morning, business at noon, and business in the evening, plus an occasional business nightmare. Add to our local history the ever-memorable fire of nine years ago, and you have a plausible excuse why sauve qui peut is the motto of every businessman. The losses were immense, and each propietor of a store in the burnt-down district had to build up his store again. Hence, why demand of him time to devote to others when his own existence is at stake? Yes, the Fire, instead of teaching us common brotherhood of man by reason of the munificent gifts the whole civilized world poured in upon us, seems to have intensified the spirit of indifference of our Chicago Israelites. To retrieve their losses was the goal of their ambition.</p>
   <p>Another reason for the gross indifference displayed by the Israelites in charitable matters is to be found in the fact that the city population is scattered over a wide area. The large area, the steady influx of newcomers, and the consequent incongruous elements made any united action impossible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
