<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-06">Sept. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Stormy Congress</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1709</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1709.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-06">Sept. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">STORMY CONGRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is very lively in Carlsbad, and the discussions are very stormy. The criticism against the administration is very sharp, and the tone of the general debate points to a certain deep-rooted bitterness. The administration which had labored for the last eight years under great difficulties is being criticized and attacked from all sides, and yet, the congress will again re-elect the same administration.</p>
   <p>What is going on in Carlsbad? Dr. Weizmann is in a position similar to that of a liberal prime minister, who has no majority of his own, but is dependent upon the good will of conservatives and radicals. Neither the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1710.jpg" n="2"/>conservatives nor the radicals are able to direct the governmental work and both must compromise. In this instance, Dr. Weizmann is the compromise, not because he is an influential and wise man, but because he is conservative in many matters and radical in others, yet he cannot be considered entirely as a conservative or as a radical statesman and, therefore, is always exposed to a cross fire.</p>
   <p>If he does something that does not please the radical element, then he is attacked by them, and if he does something that does not please the conservatives, then he is attacked by the conservative element. Every statesman pursuing a middle-of-the-road policy finds himself in such a situation and, therefore, it is no wonder why it is so stormy now in Carlsbad.</p>
   <p>Like every successful leader, Dr. Weizmann also has many outspoken opponents and enemies. The opposition is often based on pure psychology. The personal <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1711.jpg" n="3"/>and political opponents of Dr. Weizmann utilize the latest events in America for their own personal gain, and therein lies the reason for the stormy session. Also, the general embittered opinion of many delegates as a result of the war should not be forgotten. The troubles of the Jews in all Eastern European countries, and the political complexities in Palestine, create among all a vehement mood. This is the reason for the turbulent atmosphere at each session of the congress, and finds expression in heated discussions.</p>
   <p>As already stated, very little positive action will result from this turmoil: many delegates will give vent to their depressed spirits and unburden themselves, and the old administration, with slight modifications, will be re-elected. The World Zionist Organization cannot afford to let either Dr. Weizmann or Nahum Sokolow go. It may be that Ussishkin will be eliminated as president of the Zionist Commission in Palestine. Also, this appears to us only as a possibility, but not as a probability. Several new men like George Halpern, the famous <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1712.jpg" n="4"/>economist, and Sir Alfred Mond will enter into the administration, but otherwise everything must remain as before, because we haven't many Weizmanns, nor many Sokolows.</p>
   <p>As to the question of the American Zionist administration, the congress cannot make any changes. All attempts which are being made in Carlsbad by people with good intentions, like Mr. B. Horwitch of Chicago and others, to establish peace between Weizmann and Brandeis, i. e. between the Zionist rank and file in America and Brandeis-[Judge Julian W.] Mack-De Haas-Frankfurter faction will not lead to anything, because the American Zionists have a right to select their own leaders and conduct their own business. At the last Zionist convention in Cleveland, the American Zionists broke away from the Brandeis-Mack group, and it is improbable that they will change their minds so soon. Weizmann cannot compel the American Zionists to recognize Brandeis and Mack as their leaders.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1713.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Of what value is a peace between Weizmann and Brandeis, when Brandeis is not and cannot be the leader of American Zionism?</p>
   <p>Until now, many Zionists in America thought that Brandeis was instrumental in securing the Balfour Declaration, but from the official report presented by the administration to the congress, it is clearly seen that Brandeis had no part in the Balfour Declaration. This was just as well, as he did not obtain any funds from the Reformed Jews for Zionistic purposes.</p>
   <p>The business of the congress will somewhat calm the tempers, but will effect great changes in the internal political situation. We do not have leaders more capable than Weizmann and Sokolow, and they will solve the great problems which are now facing Zionism if we aid them financially to carry out these plans.</p>
   <p>The storm in Carlsbad appears like a storm in a glass of water.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
