<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-15">Feb. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Second Jewish Congress</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1638</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1638.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-15">Feb. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE SECOND JEWISH CONGRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of the executive committee of the American Jewish Congress, it was decided to convene the Congress, May 27. The location of this Congress is not yet known. The Jews of America evidence relatively little enthusiasm for the idea of a Jewish Congress. No Congress movement has been heard of since the first Congress adjourned--three years ago--and we are suddenly surprised by the news that the American [Jewish] Congress will soon be convened.</p>
   <p>The convening of a congress is purely a political action--and every political action, unless it is child's play, must be politically motivated; it must be a necessity; it must arise from certain events and conditions, and it must also arise from a practical need.</p>
   <p>Is the Jewish Congress today a political necessity and a political possibility?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1639.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Can it exist and can it serve a practical purpose?</p>
   <p>An American Jewish Congress must be what its name implies. The majority of the Jews in America must be represented in a Jewish Congress, and at present there is small likelihood that more than a small fraction of the Jews in America will participate in, and send delegates to a Congress.</p>
   <p>The American Jews are divided into four large groups--Orthodox Jews, i.e., Jews who do not belong to the Reform Temple; Reform Jews, radical Jews, and indifferent Jews. The Orthodox Jews are not organized, and a large portion of them belong to the class of the indifferent Jews. They will participate in a Jewish Congress to the extent that they are organized. They will not do so consciously nor deliberately--but they will be represented in the Congress through their leaders, viz., synagogue presidents, grand masters of fraternal organizations, and rabbis.</p>
   <p>The Reform Jews, who are the most powerful economically and the most <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1640.jpg" n="3"/>influential socially, will not participate in a Congress. They are opposed to [the idea of] a Congress.</p>
   <p>The radicals of all shades, with the possible exception of the Poale Zionists [Labor wing of Zionist organization], who are quite a small group, will not participate in a Congress because they are against an American Jewish Congress, lest it gain control over the working masses and thereby cause the pseudo-socialist comrades to lose their feed bags.</p>
   <p>The indifferent Jews who constitute at least one third [of all the Jews], will not participate in a Congress because they do not participate in any Jewish movement. They are interested only in their businesses and pleasures and do not care about the Jewish community. They do not even know anything about the existence of a Congress. The Congress will, therefore, consist of representatives of the Orthodoxy and of a few other small groups like the Poale Zionists, the nationalistically inclined intelligentsia, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1641.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The first American Jewish Congress spoke in behalf of three hundred and fifty thousand Jews--of one third of the American Jewish voters. The first Congress was, however, the product of a strong and developed Congress movement. Today, there is no Congress movement; one or two hundred thousand Jews, at the most, will participate in the elections--possibly only fifty or seventy-five thousand. Of what value can the American Jewish Congress be? Upon whom can it make an impression? The opponents of the Congress, the Reform Jews and the radical Jews, will lose no time in informing the American public that this American Jewish Congress is neither American, nor Jewish; nor is it a congress, but rather a meeting of naturalized Jews from Eastern Europe, who are interested only in themselves, and care nothing about the American Jews.</p>
   <p>Is the Congress a necessity? If it is called for the same reasons as the first Congress--to assist in the liberation of Eastern European Jews--it is not a necessity. On the contrary, it is quite superfluous. If the first Congress was unable to do anything when conditions were much more favorable, this <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1642.jpg" n="5"/>Congress will certainly be able to do nothing.</p>
   <p>If the Congress is being called to take up problems concerning the American Jewish, it is not timely because the American Jews are not adequately united for a Congress. The American Jews are still enormously dominated by the spirit of countrymen's societies and are not yet ripe for a Congress.</p>
   <p>First of all, we must have Kehiloths [Hebrew name for organized Jewish community] in America. Then--when there are Kehiloths, when the foundation has been laid--then we will be able to think of a roof.</p>
   <p>The background of the present Congress "movement" is a mirage. The Congress does not have a definite practical or political aim. It does not answer a political necessity and we cannot imagine what it will, and can, accomplish.</p>
   <p>Therefore, what is the reason for an American Jewish Congress? This question can only be answered by a counter question: What would the army of mediators, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1643.jpg" n="6"/>synagogue chiefs, "leaders," and politicians in New York do, if they didn't have an issue to discuss? If there is none, they must raise one.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
