<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1878-11-08">November 8, 1878</date><title level="a">Chicago Sketches by - Ben Golan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0823</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0823.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1878-11-08">November 8, 1878</date><title level="a">Chicago Sketches By - Ben Golan</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jews of Chicago - Population.</p>
   <p>It is very difficult to ascertain the exact number of Israelites living in this great City. There are no means to obtain a strict census, for a very great number of our co-religionists have severed all connection with their brethren, and are either ashamed to be known as Jews, or have grown lamentably indifferent to Judaism, and do not frequent its institutions.</p>
   <p>Judging from the many Jewish countenances which are met daily in the throngs on the public thoroughfares there must be a considerable number of Israelites, perhaps over 15,000, in this City. There is, perhaps, not much of importance in the history of the feast worth mentioning now, except the facts that differentiate congregations, as well as many individuals. Israelites have suffered severely by the tremendous conflagrations which have visited this City repeatedly in but very short succession. Only the destroyed Jewish Hospital did not rise after it had fallen, and the pride of the Israelites of Chicago is still a mass of ruins, waiting for the generous philanthropist <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0824.jpg" n="2"/>who will provide for it the means of a renewed existence. In consequence of said conflagration, the Israelites were scattered to the different ends of this eminent city, which has done great harm to the progress of our institutions, increasing the obstacles in the way of concentration.</p>
   <p>Congregations and Ministers:</p>
   <p>We have here at present twelve Jewish congregations, with a total membership of from five to six hundred. The majority of these congregations have their own synagogues and temples located in the different parts of the city, from the hyper-orthodox Beth-Hamedrash standing in one of the most filthy, dark and disreputable streets, to the stately and costly, radiant reform temple, situated on one of the aristocratic avenues, where it was in massive grandeur with the elegant and substantial structures of the fashionable churches. Only few of these congregations have their rabbis and preachers. Rev. Leibman Adler of the Anshe Yaariv; Dr. B. Felsenthal, of the Zion; Dr. K. Kohler of the Sinai, and Rev. A. Norden, of the North Side H.C. Drs. Felber and Felsenthal are the two <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0825.jpg" n="3"/>oldest rabbis in our midst. Dr. Felsenthal had, about twelve years ago, established the Sinai Congregation, where the Rabbis now fill the pulpit.</p>
   <p>Rev. A. Norden is a self-made man of talent. He is an excellent choice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
