<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
Vol. 21, p. 288. <date when="1895-05">May - Oct., 1895</date>.
<title level="a">The First Jewish Settlers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Vol. 21, p. 288. <date when="1895-05">May - Oct., 1895</date>.
<title level="a">The First Jewish Settlers</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first Jewish settlement in Illinois was in the City of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The first Jew who settled here was J. Gottlieb, in 1838. He was followed in 1840 by Isaac Ziegler, the brothers Benedict and Jacob Schubert, and Phillip Newberg. The following settled in Chicago between the years 1840 and 1844: H. Fuller, Jacob Fuller, Marx D. Mayer, Rosbach, Isaac Engle, B. Stern, A. Frank, Marcus Peisser, Levi Rosenfeld, Jacob Rosenberg, Morris Einstein; the brothers Julius, Abraham and Moses Kohn, James Marks, the brothers Benjamin and H. Meyer, and Mayer Klein. The following arrived here in 1845 and 1846: Morris Kohn, B. Weigselbaum, Samuel Cole, M. Braunschield, M. Leopold, Louis Leopold, Martin Clayburg, Henry Leopold, Michael Greenbaum, Louis Mayer, Ben Schlossman, and wife; Joseph Schlossman and wife; Simon Schlossman, Samuel Schlossman and wife; Levi Cline and wife; Hirsch Kohn, Mrs. Dilah Kohn, and her daughter Miss Clara Kohn. In 1847 the followed arrived here: Joseph Kohn, Elias Greenebaum, Isaac Luckey and wife, Isaac Wolf and sisters; Henry Horner, Louis and Samuel Haas; Jacob Friedman; Isaac, Louis and Simon Wormser; Mr. Greenebaum and his sons, Leon, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1349.jpg" n="2"/>Abraham, Herman, Jacob and Moses, with three sisters. In 1848 M.M. Gerstley, E. Frankenthal, and Max Weineman. Of the very first settlers, only six are still living in Chicago. They are Marx L. Mayer, Isaac Wolf, Mayer Klein, Morris Kohn, Elias and Henry Greenebaum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
