<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-29">Jan. 29, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Voice of the People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-29">Jan. 29, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">VOICE OF THE PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of the Jewish Courier: Permit me to express my opinion on the question of Jewish centers for the youth, which you have recommended. It grieves me to think that we need even debate this question. From the very first day that I took the pulpit of Congregation Rodfei Zedek, up to this very day, I have always endeavored to attract the young people to Judaism and even to bring back those who have alienated themselves.</p>
   <p>I have set down before me the ideals of Moses--not only to be contented with being the shepherd of my own flock, but to endeavor to bring back to the flock of Israel, those sheep that have wandered far off to drink from foreign waters, and if necessary, to carry them back on my shoulders, because the midrash (books containing old Jewish sayings and Jewish folklore) tells us that only when Moses became interested in the lost sheep, did the Lord select him to be the leader of Israel.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0540.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the five years that I have been connected with this congregation, I have, with the aid of God, realized this ideal to a large extent. On Friday evenings and Saturday mornings, we have had an attendance of young people that would put to shame every accusation hurled at the American-born Jews--accuse yourself and not them--but by beating your breasts, you will never achieve that which you wish--centers for the youth. The synagogues, however, must not work separately. Let us gather all the pebbles to form a large stone. Then the abandoned youth will begin to visualize higher ideals, and then, heaven and earth--the older generation with its celestial spirituality and the younger generation with its earthly materialism--will be combined in the symbol of building--the erection of a center for the youth.</p>
   <p>Rabbi [Benjamin] Daskal</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
