<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-02">Oct. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Children Celebrate the Holidays in School</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Z. Leibmer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-02">Oct. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH CHILDREN CELEBRATE THE HOLIDAYS IN SCHOOL</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Z. Leibmer</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The classes of the public and high schools that are attended almost wholly by Jewish children are nearly empty on Rosh Hashonoh and Yom Kippur. The Board of Education does not recognize these days as legal holidays, but the principals and the teachers count the children as "absent," the same as if the "absence" was due to sickness or other justifiable cause. As previously stated, the classes are empty on the holidays but the playrooms, the corridors, gymnasium halls, and the auditoriums of the school building are crowded with Jewish children. This arouses hatred and envy among the Christian children who do attend school on these days, gives extra work to the employees there and is a profanation of the holiday. We ask what kind of holidays are these two days, Rosh Hashonoh and Yom Kippur among the Jews, when their boys and girls, instead of going to the synagogue or temple, or taking a walk with their parents, go <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1466.jpg" n="2"/>to the schools for a rendezvous to serenade, promenade in the corridors, dance in the auditoriums, play ball and athletics in the gymnasium, roller skate on the sidewalks near the school? The Gentiles also ask this question and grown-up Jews bow their heads and don't know what to answer.</p>
   <p>To make an end to this situation, Mr. Block, principal of the Marshall High School called a meeting of the following persons: Mrs. Benjamin Davis, Mrs. Jacob Malkes, Rabbi Prom, H. Zeligman, Max Bot and Harry Lipsky. At this meeting the following high schools were represented: Medill, Crane, Carter Harrison, Lane, Tuley, Senn, Hyde Park, and Englewood. It was decided to bring this matter before [the bar of] Jewish public opinion; Jewish parents should realize that it is a profanation of the holidays when their children go to school to have "fun".</p>
   <p>It is also the duty of the rabbis and the representatives of the synagogues and temples to speak about this situation tomorrow from their pulpits. It <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1467.jpg" n="3"/>will thus add emphasis to the problem.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
