<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-27">Apr. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Weitzman Arrives This Morning in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0956</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0956.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-27">Apr. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">DR. WEITZMAN ARRIVES THIS MORNING IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Chaim Weitzman will arrive this morning, at nine thirty, from Kansas City. As soon as he arrives in town, he will have a conference with the Keren Hayesod workers, will receive information about the status of the campaign, and will give directions regarding its further course. The offices of the Keren Hayesod, which are now in the Ashland Block, will be open all day. Last minute preparations are being made there for the banquet which will be given by the synagogues on Tuesday night in honor of Dr. Weitzman. The Rabbinical Council has appointed Rabbis Goldstein and Sfirsky to supervise the kosher food that will be served at the banquet. The caterer will serve the food from new dishes. Everything will be absolutely kosher. The synagogues, if they want to have a place at the banquets, must make their reservations today at the Keren Hayesod office. Sixty five synagogues will be represented at the banquet. This is the first time that representatives from so many synagogues come together for the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0957.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Chaim Weitzman will address the Keren Hayesod volunteers at a confidential meeting, which will take place on Monday evening, at eight o'clock, at the Club Room of the Sherman Hotel. At this meeting, the Keren Hayesod workers will receive interesting information about the latest political and diplomatic developments in as far as they affect Palestine, and they will learn about the Keren Hayesod work all over the country. Three hundred and twenty-five volunteers , among them presidents of many synagogues, are expected to attend this conference.</p>
   <p>The Hadassah [Women's Zionist Organization of America] Chicago Chapter will give a tea party on Tuesday in honor of Mrs. Weitzman at the Morrison Hotel. Six hundred Hadassah members are expected.</p>
   <p>All Orthodox rabbis and most of the conservative rabbis have made appeals this year in their synagogues for the Keren Hayesod. Thousands of new Keren Hayesod subscribers have responded to the appeal. The representatives of <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0958.jpg" n="3"/>synagogues, rabbis, and citizens who do the Keren Hayesod work will go out today, tomorrow, and Tuesday to collect the pledges made in the synagogues during the holidays. They expect to collect not less than eighty thousand dollars. It is expected that by May 14, the last day of the campaign, the synagogues will raise a total of one hundred thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Meetings will be held today in many Orthodox synagogues by synagogue leaders, in order to work out plans for collecting within the next few days the pledges made during the holidays. The synagogues want to get through with the Keren Hayesod work as soon as possible, so that they may be free to begin the great Keren Hatorah [Fund of the Torah] drive. The Keren Hayesod drive should, therefore, be a quick and intensive one.</p>
   <p>An appeal made by Alderman Jacob M. Arvey yesterday at the Anshe Emet Synagogue, before the Reading of the Torah, brought nine thousand dollars in pledges. Rabbi Lang says that the pledges are as good as cash.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0959.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>An appeal by Dr. S. M. Melamed at the B'nai Moses Synagogue brought five hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>Leonard [J.] Grossman appealed at the South Side Hebrew Congregation. The result was fifteen hundred dollars. Rabbi [A.] Margolin, I. T. Feingold, and S. J. Wolffson undertook to raise five hundred dollars more, to complete the quota of two thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Three hundred dollars was pledged by the B'nai Sholom Synagogue, 1231 South Union Avenue, after an appeal made by Rabbi Robinson and president Isaac Rabinowich.</p>
   <p>One thousand dollars was pledged by the B'nai Bezaleel Synagogue after an appeal by Judge [Philip E.] Bregstone.</p>
   <p>Five hundred dollars was pledged at the Persian Synagogue, Washburne [Avenue] and Throop [Street], upon an appeal made by Joseph Weisman. Mr. Weisman also <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0960.jpg" n="5"/>made an appeal at the Beth Israel Synagogue, on Robey Street. This appeal brought three hundred dollars in pledges. Messrs. Miller, [Morris] Kurzon, and [Rabbi A.R.] Mushkin promised to collect the pledges from the members right after the holidays.</p>
   <p>The banquet arranged by the Association of Synagogues in honor of Dr. Weitzman will take place on Tuesday evening, April 29, in the Grill Room of the Capitol Building, State and Randolph Streets. Eight hundred people are expected to attend this affair. Cost per plate is two dollars and fifty cents. Reservations should be made at the Zionist office. Telephone Dearborn 3120.</p>
   <p>The Zionist office has been moved from 118 North La Salle Street and is now at rooms 408-409 Ashland Block, Clark and Randolph Streets. Dr. Abramowich can be found there all day long. Max Shulman, chairman of the Keren Hayesod, and other Zionist leaders can be found there during part of the day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
