<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-15">Feb. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Do Not Forget Your Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-15">Feb. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">DO NOT FORGET YOUR DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Keren Hayesod committee of one hundred members will meet tomorrow evening to work out plans for the coming Keren Hayesod drive, which will begin about March first and will last until after Passover. The committee of one hundred has not met since last summer--that is, the chairman of the administrative committee of the Keren Hayesod has called meetings, but the members did not come. At none of the Keren Hayesod meetings held since July, 1921, has there appeared more than twenty-five members. This is the best explanation of the failure of the Keren Hayesod work in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The work for the last six months has been neglected so much that we have to marvel at the results--fifty thousand dollars collected. In proportion to the number of Chicago Jews, it is a niggardly sum. Milwaukee gave more than <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1100.jpg" n="2"/>fifty thousand dollars, and Philadelphia, which has fewer Jews than Chicago, gave four times as much. It is a big sum if we consider the minimum amount of work that has been done.</p>
   <p>The truth of the matter is that in relation to its large Jewish population, Chicago has not done anything for the Keren Hayesod. With the exception of the few regular contributors, such as Mr. Samuel Phillipson, Mr. Platt, and Mr. Bomash, none of the rich Chicago Jews has given a large sum to the Keren Hayesod. We claim that even most of the Zionists have not given as much as they could and should have given. Of course, we cannot tell anyone how much he should give for the Keren Hayesod, but when we see ardent Zionists, who are active in the movement, give no more for Keren Hayesod than they gave for local charities, we are not impressed, and we feel that the Zionists are not doing their duty to that which is very dear to them.</p>
   <p>But ninety-five per cent of Chicago Jews have not given anything for the Keren Hayesod up to now. Nobody has ever come to them with a request that they should <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1101.jpg" n="3"/>give. This is not the fault of the chairman of the Keren Hayesod committee, Mr. Max Shulman; it is mainly the fault of the committee of one hundred which has simply forgotten its duty.</p>
   <p>It is high time for the committee to remember that it has a duty to perform, unless it wants to bring shame and humiliation to the Jewish community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Chicago is the second largest Jewish community in the world (sic). It is expected that Chicago should give more than a provincial city because Chicago is known all over the world for its great heart and its generosity. In the field of relief, Chicago is doing more than any other city in America. It is, therefore, quite natural to expect extraordinary achievements from Chicago in the field of Keren Hayesod work. When we see that in that field Chicago is not doing anything, we are disappointed even more.</p>
   <p>Those Chicago Jews who have local pride, to whom Chicago is a great philanthropic center, are grieved and insulted by this situation; they are simply ashamed of the sad results of the Keren Hayesod work in their city. The Jews of Chicago <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1102.jpg" n="4"/>whose sense of local pride is not developed, but who know what Chicago can and does achieve in all fields of Jewish philanthropy, simply cannot understand why Chicago is not doing anything for the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <p>Both groups of Chicago Jews ought to know that the blame and responsibility for this miserable condition falls not upon Chicago Jews, but on the committee of one hundred that has undertaken to do great work, in a great moment, for a great purpose, and has failed miserably.</p>
   <p>The committee of one hundred meets tomorrow night, and we do not doubt that a majority of the committee will appear at the meeting. The chairman will read a report to the committee about its activity. This report will not be satisfactory, and some members will get up and deliver long speeches in which they will try to discover the guilty person who has caused this lamentable condition.</p>
   <p>We cannot correct the past--that which we have failed to do in the last few months cannot be made good again--and from long speeches and personal criticism, no good can come. What we can do now is to take care of the future: prepare <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1103.jpg" n="5"/>good, practical plans for the coming drive, and carry out those plans immediately.</p>
   <p>The committee of one hundred will not do its duty if it wastes time with fruitless criticism and long speeches. If its past mistakes can be made good at all, they can be made good only through positive, energetic work, or Chicago will remain an abandoned city as far as the Keren Hayesod is concerned.</p>
   <p>We can only appeal to the committee of one hundred to do its duty. Sokolow is coming to Chicago soon, and the committee will have to render an accounting of its work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
