<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-27">Oct. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Jewish Will.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0773</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0773.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-27">Oct. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A JEWISH WILL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last edition of the Outlook much space is devoted to the will of the Jewish millionaire, the late Benjamen Altman. The deceased is highly lauded and set forth as an example for others to follow.</p>
   <p>Mr. Altman, who left a fortune of tens of millions of dollars, not only provided for his relatives, but also for the employees of the large Altman industrial firm. Besides the sums of money willed to the workmen according to the amount of years in the firm's service, he has also provided that each employee shall get a share of the profits.</p>
   <p>This is very humane, a becoming Jewishness. The eulogy given in the Outlook is truly well earned.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0774.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is another item in the will. The Outlook strongly calls this to our attention. The deceased was an art lover who had gathered a costly collection of art works and antiques valued at millions of dollars. This rare collection he bequeathed to the Metropolitan Museum so that the public might have access thereof to help develop artistic appreciation.</p>
   <p>All this is good and noteworthy. It points to the gentle nature of the man, his loving heart, his artistic tastes, his humanity and generosity to society.</p>
   <p>Yet one thing was missing. The broader view in relation to his own home, to the extensive activities carried on by his fellow Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0775.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He left money to charitable and educational institutions with which he was associated. But concerning Jewish affairs he remained within the narrow local limits of his community. Broader activities of a general national Jewish character were strange and unknown to him.</p>
   <p>Consider Jacob Moser, the Jewish Lord Mayor of Bradford, England, who is far from possessing the riches of Altman, but participates in all the activities of his country and spends large sums of money for Hebrew schools in Jafa; then we can see the difference in the two personalities.</p>
   <p>Of course, Altman's gift to the Metropolitan Museum will bring useful results. But, America is rich enough. She possesses many millionaires, much richer than Altman, who donate, to America great works of art.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0776.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But the poor Jewish people who own nothing nationally, deserve more consideration in gifts extended by her children. The Morgans, the Vanderbilts, and even Carnegie have thus far failed to give any money for national Jewish institutions. And when the Schifs, the Altmans and the rest of them devote their means, their art, and antique collections for Harvard University and the Metropolitan Museum, that is, putting it mildly, not deserving of a too great consideration. No one will concern himself with our dark corner when a friendly glance is not even bestowed upon us by our own brothers.</p>
   <p>To the strangers who laud their worthy deeds they are Benjamin or Jacobs; to us they are brothers and the sting smarts sharply that the Diaspora should have separated and estranged them from us to the extent that they do not feel the national needs for which we aim and strive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
