<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-25">August 25, 1913</date><title level="a">Just a Reminder</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-25">August 25, 1913</date><title level="a">JUST A REMINDER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the finest customs established by Chicago Jews within the last few years is that of pasting Zion stamps on synagogue tickets sold for the holidays. On festive occasions the Jewish spirit seemed to be lacking in this method of selling all seats to worshipers who come to enlighten their souls on Rosh Hashana and Yom Kippur, and to pray to God for health and a good year. The conditions in America, and especially in so large a city as Chicago, are such that it is impossible for it to be otherwise, since without the sale of tickets for the holidays it would be almost impossible to support the synagogues, and worse yet, there would be no particular order.</p>
   <p>To give the ticket a holiday meaning, however, it can be labelled with a Jewish stamp, the Zion stamp. This would indicate that the buyer has paid for his seat as well as supported his nationality and his religion. Thus he has a clear conscience and an understanding with his fellow Jews that he prays not only for himself, his health, and his business, but also for his fellow Jews.</p>
   <p>The Zion stamp is very cheap, only one cent. The cheapest synagogue ticket usually costs $1.00, and we are certain the buyer will not refuse to buy a <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1505.jpg" n="2"/>ticket because of the stamp. Although it has been the custom of the synagogues to buy a set amount of Zion stamps and to give them, so to speak, as a premium to the ticket buyers, we do not believe this method was a good one. The intake for Zion stamps go to the National Fund to which every Jew ought to contribute. Therefore, it would be more appropriate that each ticket should carry the Zion stamp with the penny added to the cost of the ticket.</p>
   <p>Let every synagogue see to it that its tickets are truly of a Jewish nature. The superintendent of the National Fund in Chicago should cooperate with the presidents and committees of synagogues and permit rabbis and lecturers to make the people stamp conscious so that no holiday ticket will be complete without one. Thus as soon as the tickets come from the press the Zion stamp should be immediately attached to them. Thus it becomes the true symbol of a national Jewish people.</p>
   <p>It would be a good idea, if the people who print these tickets would leave a special blank space for the stamp, thus making the ticket appear to lack this important item, so that the empty space will cause those people who must worship in rented flats or halls to feel this ommission and thus get the Zion stamps.</p>
   <p>We write this article merely to remind the public of this. Most of the larger <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1506.jpg" n="3"/>synagogues will continue to sell these stamps as they have previously done. But there are many small synagogues which in the rush of the holiday activities may forget and it is to them that we wish to send this reminder.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
