<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-18">Jan. 18, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[Jewish Slackers in Chicago]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-18">Jan. 18, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[JEWISH SLACKERS IN CHICAGO]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Switzerland is the worst country in the world for Jewish slackers, that is for Jews who do not belong to any synagogue, who do not send their children to a Talmud Torah, and who do not donate to charity. In the little Swiss republic, Jews enjoy the freedom of not belonging to any synagogue, of not sending their children to a Talmud Torah, of not giving to charity, but they must do all those things because if they do not, they are notified officially that the Jewish community will not take care of them after their death; that it will refuse them a burial place on the cemetery. Every Jewish community in Switzerland has only one burial society and only one cemetery. Even Jewish slackers are afraid of a cemetery. That is why they do what the community tells them to do. Just imagine what would happen if the Chicago Jewish community, as a unit, controlled the burials, and if there were only one cemetery--. The <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0466.jpg" n="2"/>Talmud Torahs would be crowded, every Chicago Jew would belong to a synagogue, and everyone would contribute his share to charity.</p>
   <p>Only eight thousand Jews, of the two hundred thousand Orthodox Jews in Chicago, belong to a synagogue. Only three or four thousand, of the twenty thousand Jewish children in Chicago, attend a Talmud Torah. The biggest Jewish organization in Chicago, the United Charities, has barely ten thousand members, whereas it should have fifty thousand. Why do such conditions prevail in Chicago? These conditions exist because the Jews have all sorts of freedom, because the community has no means of compelling the individual to do his duty. Everything that is done by the Chicago Jewish community for religion, charity, or education, is done by a small minority which bears upon its shoulders the financial burden that should be borne by the majority. Jews do not abuse their political freedom as citizens, but they abuse their freedom as Jews shamefully.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
