<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-17">Apr. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate News</title><title level="a" type="sub">North and Northwest Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-17">Apr. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE NEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">North and Northwest Side</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>N. Elkin, Robert and Yuri Levin bought the sixteen-apartment building on St. Louis Avenue and 18th Street for $66,000.</p>
   <p>Simon Dlat and Benjamin Bartz bought the property on the northeast corner of Jackson Boulevard and Central Avenue for $40,000. The buyers plan to erect an apartment building on the site to cost approximately $225,000.</p>
   <p>Max Drucker bought the apartment building on Washington Boulevard and Leclaire Avenue, from J. Tapf, M. Feldman, and A. P. Jacobs for $90,000.</p>
   <p>Max Drucker sold the forty-two apartment building at 5072 Washington [Boulevard] to William Zanz for $289,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Goland and others bought the property on Avers Avenue, near 15th Street, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0232.jpg" n="2"/>from Isaac Levin for $22,000.</p>
   <p>Morris Brener bought the property on Central Park Avenue, near 16th Street from Otto Glickman for $13,800.</p>
   <p>Sam Rosenthal and Morris Zevin bought the property on the southwest corner of Cicero and Gladys Avenues, from Nathan Plyer for $210,000.</p>
   <p>Jennie Meyerson bought the property on the northwest corner of Fifth and Spaulding Avenues, from J. Schneider for $10,000.</p>
   <p>Ida Weinstein bought the property at 1310 South Halsted Street for $58,000.</p>
   <p>Becky Goldberg bought the property on the northeast corner of Huron Street and Maplewood Avenue for $62,200.</p>
   <p>Abe Horwitz bought the property on Lawndale Avenue, near 16th Street, for $21,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0233.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Rose Shapiro bought the property on the northeast corner of Logan Boulevard and California Avenue from N. Batzman for $20,000.</p>
   <p>Solomon Graff bought the property on the southwest corner of Madison Street and Waller Avenue for $84,500.</p>
   <p>Jacob Kaplan bought the property on Millard Avenue, near 13th Street, from Morris Levin and others for $31,500.</p>
   <p>Jacob Albert bought the property on the southeast corner of Division Street and Menard Avenue for $13,000.</p>
   <p>Paul Ginsburg bought the property at 2524-28 Milwaukee Avenue from B. Morris and others for $45,000.</p>
   <p>Ben Zion Rappaport bought the property on Ogden Avenue, near Randolph Street for $12,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0234.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>K. Weiner bought the property on the southwest corner of Roosevelt Road and Keeler Avenue from Harry Cohen for $38,500.</p>
   <p>Morris Rosen bought the property on Springfield Avenue, near 14th Street, from David Erenstein for $27,000.</p>
   <p>Abe Feldman bought the property on the northwest corner of Trumbull Avenue, near 15th Street, from Philip Steinberg for $50,000.</p>
   <p>The Garfield Park Hospital bought the property on Washington Boulevard, near Hamlin Avenue, 27 by 158 feet, from David Warso for $12,000.</p>
   <p>Albany Park and North Side</p>
   <p>M. L. Goldber sold the property on the southeast corner of Hamlin and Milwaukee Avenues, 100 by 125 feet, for $50,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0235.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>M. Louis Goldberg bought the eighteen-apartment building at 1443 Victoria Avenue from Lillian Silverman for $84,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Alper and Bertha Cohen bought the apartment building on the southwest corner of Potomac Avenue and Rockwell Street from M. Sherman and J. Siegel for $11,000.</p>
   <p>Anna Cohen and Mary Bernstein bought the property on the southeast corner of Chase Avenue and Paulina Street for $50,000. The buyers plan to erect a thirty-apartment building on the site.</p>
   <p>Benjamin Morris bought the property on the northwest corner of Berteau and Kedzie Avenues, 47 by 125 feet, for $8,975.</p>
   <p>David Grinshpan bought the property on the southeast corner of Lawndale and Ainslie Avenues for $22,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0236.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Sarah Eisenberg bought the property on Lawndale Avenue, near Ainslee Avenue, from Rose Cooperman for $11,500.</p>
   <p>Herman Greenbaum and Ida Fisher bought the property on the northeast corner of St. Louis and Ainslee Avenues for $95,000.</p>
   <p>Morris Gitlin bought the property on the northeast corner of Ravenswood Park and Ainslie Avenue for $12,000.</p>
   <p>In Other Neighborhoods</p>
   <p>Alexander Weiss, Z. Dicker, and George Lurie bought the Commercial building on the northeast corner of Cottage Grove Avenue and 64th Street for $375,000.</p>
   <p>Joseph Gold bought the nineteen-apartment building on the southwest corner of Ingleside Avenue and 54th Street for $110,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0237.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Benjamin Hetner bought the thirty-apartment building on the southeast corner of Everett Avenue and 54th Street from M. Rosenberg, H. Glick, H. Zisak, and A. Levinson for $277,500.</p>
   <p>Herman Goldberg bought the commercial building at 1315-19 East 63rd Street for $101,500.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
