<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-27">Nov. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Thanksgiving Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-27">Nov. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THANKSGIVING DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of all the holidays that are commemorated during the year in this land, Thanksgiving is the only one that must and should be celebrated by everyone in this great country.</p>
   <p>Thanksgiving is not a religious holiday, since its derivation is in no way connected with any specific religion, nor does it ally itself with any religious beliefs, but simply a day of thankfulness in which the entire nation unite to thank God for the bounty they enjoy in this land. Just like Independence Day, - the 4th of July, in which everyone participates regardless of religion, race, or political opinion, - Thanksgiving is everyone's holiday from the standpoint of general well being.</p>
   <p>We will here relate the story of Thanksgiving, according to various historical writings:</p>
   <p>The first general Thanksgiving celebrated throughout the entire country occurred on the 18th of November in the year of 1777. It was enacted by the Continental Congress, and its proclaimation was issued by President <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1414.jpg" n="2"/>George Washington. The day was fixed, in the wording of the resolution, to express thankfulness because "God was merciful and favored us, during our oppression in a rightful and necessary war for the defense and establishment of our rights, to have freedom for all men alike."</p>
   <p>The Constitution had just been accepted, and before the president designated the day, many debates took place in Congress regarding his power to enforce gratefulness on an entire nation for a Constitution that many people were not at all thankful for.</p>
   <p>That Thanksgiving be the last Thursday in November is an acceptance of a later date.</p>
   <p>It occurred at first, when the nation, united under the constitution, expressed its thankfulness on November 26, 1789. From that day, the last Thursday in November is set aside for Thanksgiving. The custom has never been changed, although during the Civil War, Thanksgiving was not celebrated regularly, except in the New England states, where it has always been an annual holiday.</p>
   <p>It was after the Civil War, which brought new sentiment to the American <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1415.jpg" n="3"/>Nation, a feeling of National unity, and since 1863, that every president of the United States proclaims each year the last Thursday in November as Thanksgiving Day. But, what president, or prophet, could have then dreamed that in the span of a quarter of a century the call of this proclaimation would extend over such vast territories, - in the islands of the South Sea and the islands of the Pacific Ocean, all in unison with the American Nation, giving thanks on this same day?</p>
   <p>When governor Wm. Bradford, soon after the first harvest of the grains in the New World in 1621, sent four men to shoot birds for the new colony of Massachusetts, he wanted the people to rejoice in a special manner. But little did he know that this natural deed would in time assume such width and proportions as the present day of thanks.</p>
   <p>Regarding that moment, Edward Wilson, one of the immigrants who came to America on the Mayflower, and later governor of Massachusetts, wrote:</p>
   <p>"When our grain was harvested, our governor sent four men to shoot fowls so that we might set aside a day for rejoicing for everyone after we had gathered the fruit of our labor."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1416.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Governor Bradford was noted for his kindness to the Indians. In his honor the Indians and white men lived in peace, the latter having no complaints.</p>
   <p>Thanksgiving Day, a day when the entire people of a land are asked to give thanks, is found nowhere in any European country. Every nationality has its day of thanks, and every ruler fabricates a new one. The only nation that had a day of thanks for a bountiful harvest were the Jews, the Chag Haosif (Harvest Festival), much like the day used by the fathers of this large republic.</p>
   <p>The Greeks, too, had a similar holiday, which lasted nine days, but it was in honor of the Goddess of the Fields. Her sacrifices consisted primarily of the fruit that came from the earth.</p>
   <p>The Romans, too, had a holiday, the Saturnalia, also occurring in the beginning of the winter. But these holidays, both by Greeks and Romans, were devoted to the licentiousness of their idol worshippers, who were hardly acquainted with the fact that these days were of thanks for the bounty of the earth.</p>
   <p>America is a religious country. The first settlers, as well as the fathers <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1417.jpg" n="5"/>of this republic, were religious people. Even the freethinkers, among them Thomas Payne, and etc., were not outspoken opposers of religion.</p>
   <p>Being from England, from a nation that derives its spiritual benefits from the Tonach, it is little wonder that they decided on a day of thanks similar to that mentioned in the Jewish Torah.</p>
   <p>Thanksgiving is, therefore, a holiday which Jews may, must, and should participate in.</p>
   <p>In closing, it is noteworthy to mention that the American name "Turkey," as applied to the large fowl so customarily eaten on this day, is also strongly related to the Jew. The turkey does not come from India or Turkey, but is a true American bird eaten on the first Thanksgiving Day, when Govenor Bradford, in 1621, sent his four men to shoot birds for the new colony. The first birds sent from America to Europe went with the expedition of Enrico Cortez to Spain. The Jews were the first and only ones to spread these fowls in other European countries. Jews named them "TuKee," the Hebrew word for Peacock. In 1541 the Spanish Jews exported "TuKee" to England, the Jewish name followed. The Englishman erroneously called it Turkey, since they did not understand the Jewish expressions of <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1418.jpg" n="6"/>the Spanish Jew very well and the English "R" is not a strongly prounounced sound.</p>
   <p>Thus it is that Jews have a large part in our Thanksgiving Day and in the name of "turkey." We should therefore celebrate this day together with the entire American Nation.</p>
   <p>E. M. Walfsohn</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
