<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-23">Feb. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Are You a Piker?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1087</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1087.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-23">Feb. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ARE YOU A PIKER?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The leaders of the World Zionist Organization are anxious to find out whether you are a piker or not, and if you are not, how is it that you did not do your duty toward Palestine?</p>
   <p>The leaders of the World Zionist Organization are anxious to see you corroborate the statement made by the leaders of our relief organizations that Chicago is the philanthropic capitol of American Jewry and of the Jewry at large. You can corroborate the statement by doing your duty toward Palestine and by giving at least as much for Palestine as you have given for relief purposes, and by giving as much for Palestine as you give for local philanthropic purposes.</p>
   <p>The leaders of our relief organizations are very proud of Chicago's accomplishments <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1088.jpg" n="2"/>in this field of work. Only the other day, the chairman of the Chicago relief drive, Mr. Jacob Loeb, went down to New York and told a New York crowd about the great things Chicago Jewry has been doing recently, and exhorted them to do the same thing--to give and give and give again. Today we have with us a gentleman from New York, one of the leaders of the Keren Hayesod movement, who came here with the object of telling us what the country at large has been doing recently for the Keren Hayesod and that we should do the same thing.</p>
   <p>To the mind of our relief leaders, you are very charitable, very philanthropic, very generous, and noble. To the mind of our Keren Hayesod workers, you are a miser, you are a piker, you are neglectful of your duty, and everything but a liberal.</p>
   <p>Can you explain how is it that the same Jewish Chicago, so famous for its generosity and liberality when matters of relief are at stake, is so <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1089.jpg" n="3"/>notorious for its miserly attitude towards Palestine and the Keren Hayesod? Are you a piker or aren't you? Are you only moved by the tales of horrors from across the seas and by the vision of the Valley of Death in Eastern and Central Europe, and being moved by these sights of horror and tales of horror, you forget your miserly nature and you give liberally; or are you generous in every respect and do not give for Palestine because you do not understand what is at stake or because there are not enough workers of the Keren Hayesod to approach you in the right spirit and at the right moment?</p>
   <p>We believe that the statement made by our relief workers concerning your philanthropic disposition is a true statement. We believe that you are generous and liberal and always ready to help, and as to your somewhat miserly attitude to the Keren Hayesod, we believe that your lack of vision and a faulty organization are responsible for your attitude towards Palestine. You fail to understand that real constructive relief work can <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1090.jpg" n="4"/>be done in Palestine only, because if you invest money there you invest it in the Jewish land or for the benefit of the present and future Jewish organization, while investing your good money in Poland or in Russia might not be productive of results because one pogrom on a large scale may wipe out your investment. You fail to understand that the only way to solve the question of Eastern European Jews, and the only way to solve the question of Judaism, is to establish in Palestine a Jewish homeland. This homeland cannot be established by miracles. It requires your money, your energy, your labor, and your enthusiasm. But first of all, your money is needed and unless you give, and give liberally the plan of a Jewish [homeland] in Palestine cannot be carried out. If this great plan should not be carried out because of your refusal to help, then you help to perpetuate Jewish suffering and you predetermine the fate of the future generations, in a way that instead of blessing you they will curse you, and you surely do not want to be cursed by your children and grand-children.</p>
   <p>Women and children are moved by tears only. Men are moved by ideas, by <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1091.jpg" n="5"/>thoughts, by possibilities. If you are a manly Jew, a virile Jew, and an energetic Jew, you will give for the Keren Hayesod much more than you have given for relief, because the Keren Hayesod is the treasury of a Jewish Palestine, the treasury of the Jewish people, with the help of which we mean to build Palestine and to prepare the happiness of future Jewish generations, while the relief chest only serves the purpose of the sick and the poor of the moment.</p>
   <p>You have displayed so much generosity during the relief drive. Reveal your true spirit during the coming Keren Hayesod campaign, so that people should not say you are a piker.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
