<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-22">April 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Answer to the Lover of the Hebrew Group</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1336</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1336.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-04-22">April 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWER TO THE LOVER OF THE HEBREW GROUP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Dear Editor:</p>
   <p>I read a letter in the Courier, written by Mr. Seligman regarding the sad plight of the Hebrew Speaking group. With all respect for Mr. Seligman, in particular, and for members of the group, in general, I must say that the members of the Hebrew Speaking group are not facing reality. I once told Mr. Seligman, personally, when the Hebrew group was still in its glory, that the society couldn't exist very long, for it had no definite objectives to follow. Its meetings were too dry and uninteresting. It had club-rooms and a library, but what good did it do when the members came there for no other purpose than to read and speak Hebrew.</p>
   <p>Societies that segregate themselves and live in isolation from the outer-world cannot exist very long. When members become Americanized they immediately lose interest in such organizations. One pulls one way, the next one the other way. It's hard to keep them together, after they have been in America for some years.</p>
   <p>There were two Hebrew-speaking circles in Chicago, and not one could exist, Why? Because of the bitter rivalry and jealousy amongst the two groups. Instead of <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1337.jpg" n="2"/>co-operating and pulling together for one purpose, they have been quarrelling with one another.</p>
   <p>If the Hebrew group is in a coma, well then, it's their own fault. Let that be a lesson to the heated members of the group.</p>
   <p>H. Wilk, Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
