<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-27">August 27, 1913</date><title level="a">Anshe Knesess Isreal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0777</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0777.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-08-27">August 27, 1913</date><title level="a">ANSHE KNESESS ISREAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to information received the new synagogue which is being erected by the congregation Anshe Knesess Isreal on Douglas Boulevard, will be completed and in readiness for the coming holidays. It is not news that in so large a city as Chicago, a new synagogue is being built. It is simply natural that when the Jewish population of a city increases, mor synagogues are built. The building of synagogues is the pioneer work of the Jews in every district.</p>
   <p>The Anshe Knesess Isreal is not a new congregation, it is one of the oldest Jewish communities in Chicago. The newness of this synagogue is due to the migration of the Jewish community further west which created a new center of activity. Thus the old synagogue was sold and a new one built in the new Ghetto.</p>
   <p>Such activities show which way the wind blows in the Chicago Jewish community. The beautiful building being erected on Douglas Boulevard indicates how the common Jewish people have developed both spiritually and materially in the last twenty-five years.</p>
   <p>The new building will be a large and beautiful orthodox Jewish synagogue. It will be richly decorated, roomy, and comfortable. It is built quite strongly.</p>
   <p>The Anshe Knesess Isreal has always been proud of being the center of activities <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0778.jpg" n="2"/>of the community in good or bad times. And now in its new home it means to live up to this fact of serving the people as before.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
