<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-16">Apr. 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Spring of the Jewish People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0961</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0961.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-16">Apr. 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE SPRING OF THE JEWISH PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The long, hard winter of the Jewish people has ended. The spring of our people has begun.</p>
   <p>Spring! That which we hoped for, prayed, dreamed, and believed during the two thousand-year-old Diaspora winter is being realized.</p>
   <p>Our people, our language, our land, our national honor, our historical greatness--they all live anew.</p>
   <p>Spring! What we plant and sow now will later sprout and grow big, rich, multicolored, to our glory.</p>
   <p>But we have to plant more, we need more workers, more means.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0962.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If we neglect now the Jewish spring, then we lose our future, we miss the greatest opportunity in our history.</p>
   <p>The land which our leaders and prophets, kings and lawgivers made holy thousands of years ago with their spirit and their blood for the entire world, for all humanity, has been returned to us by the Balfour Declaration, with the agreement of all great powers.</p>
   <p>The entire civilized humanity is now watching the Jewish people build up their land, their national independence.</p>
   <p>Every Jew is responsible for that. "All Jews are responsible for one another". Every Jew bears a part of the great historical responsibility.</p>
   <p>Plant and sow during the Jewish spring. Respond with a full heart to the present Keren Hayesod campaign.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0963.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is a call from Jews to Jews, particularly to the Jews who live in blessed America, whom the circumstances allow to be the driving force of this movement.</p>
   <p>Three hundred thousand dollars is the sum that is demanded this year from Chicago, the great Jewish Community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Keren Hayesod campaign begins now. You are urged to give for the Keren Hayesod, give with an open hand, give freely, give in proportion to your means.</p>
   <p>Build Palestine!</p>
   <p>Keren Hayesod, 118 North LaSalle Street, Chicago.</p>
   <p>(This advertisement was paid by the Municipal Coal Company, 4201-09 Ogden Avenue. Julius Lilenthal, president.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
