<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-11-12">November 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Shooters.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0208</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0208.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-11-12">November 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH SHOOTERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mournful accident, as that of a young Jewish man shooting Harry Jacobs for a trivial matter, is further evidence that our rabbis have more important work to attend to, than commenting on the sermons of a reformed rabbi in his, or in other, temples.</p>
   <p>Jewish children equiped with revolvers in their pockets are a new phenomenon among Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0209.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A Jewish woman was recently charged, in the Criminal Court, with murder. The fact that she was acquitted did not prove that she did not kill. All this is due to the fact that our youth is to highly Americanized, that is, they inherit all the faults of the Americans and do not adopt a single, good qualification from them.</p>
   <p>The freedom in carrying weapons certainly points to a higher standpoint of civilization. A man of knowledge and decency who can control himself in an orderly manner can be given the responsibility of carrying deadly weapons by society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0210.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A Jew should, more than any other person, be able to hold a weapon without fearing that he might use it in an improper way. The Jew is, more than anyone else, against bloodshed and brutal force.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, very tragic how our youth, pretending to become Americanized in the pool rooms, have rooted from their hearts all Jewish tradition by learning to bear weapons.</p>
   <p>It is, still sadder to note that our teachers and rabbis, while witnessing the manner in which these children are reared, and how the children of their synagogues are found in the pool rooms, can only see what is going on in the South Side (referring to the reformed rabbis and temples).</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0211.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Jewish shooting is a new misfortune and the sooner we shall seek methods to eradicate the desire for bloodshed from our youth the better it will be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
