<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-07-07">July 7, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">District Grand Lodge of the Independent Order of B'nai B'rith in 65Th Convention.</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. F. Baskin.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-07-07">July 7, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">DISTRICT GRAND LODGE OF THE INDEPENDENT ORDER OF B'NAI B'RITH IN 65TH CONVENTION.</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. F. Baskin.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Particular interest in the 65th Annual Convention of District Grand Lodge No. #6, Independent Order B'nai B'rith, held at the Hotel La Salle this week centered on reports of what the Order has done to date in the German crisis and its plans to enlarge the activities of the anti-Defamation League to check the growth of Hitlerism in this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1541.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Delegates from eight Middle-Western states and four Canadian provinces comprising the district were reminded that many Hitler cells are already functioning in the United States, Richard E. Gutstadt, director of the anti-Defamation League, which has moved its headquarters from Cincinnati to Chicago for increased effort, reminded the convention that the B'nai B'rith requires the fullest measure of support from the Jewish community.</p>
   <p>TELLS OF COOPERATION.</p>
   <p>Honorable Alfred M. Cohen, international president, and Dr. I. M. Rubinow, secretary, also told of the persecution of the Jews in Germany.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1542.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Cohen narrated how the B'nai B'rith helped create a council composed of the American Jewish Committee, the American Jewish Congress, and the B'nai B'rith so that in the future there could be joint action on the German situation. Dr. Rubinow urged that the maximum number possible of German Jews be permitted to emigrate here.</p>
   <p>President Sam Beber in his annual report referred to the "fresh out burst of anti-Semitism in one of the otherwise most enlightened nations on the earth."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1543.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Morco Nadler, president of the B'nai B'rith in Alexandria, Egypt, asserted that the boycott in that country was depriving Germany of an annual trade of $2,500,000.</p>
   <p>ELECT GROSSMAN AS HEAD.</p>
   <p>By unanimous vote, First Vice President Joseph F. Grossman, who is assistant corporation counsel of Chicago, was elected president, and Arthur Brin of Minneapolis was advanced from second to first vice president. Omaha will probably be selected for the 1934 gathering, as the convention was originally scheduled there, but was transferred here because of Jewish Day and A Century of Progress.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1544.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Much attention was given by the convention to possible changes in the method of selecting the general committee and other means of providing more efficient operation. The membership report stated that except for Chicago and Milwaukee, the 82 lodges in the district practically held their own. To Winnipeg went both the individual and lodge prizes for the largest membership gain.</p>
   <p>EXTENSIVELY ENTERTAINED.</p>
   <p>The delegates were guests of the Chicago lodges at the Jewish Day "Romance of a People," also at the Century of Progress, at a dinner at the Standard Club, where they were addressed by Mr. Cohen and Dr. Abram L. Sachar, director of B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation, and at many other functions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1545.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The convention heard detailed reports of the Hillel activities as well as those of a wider scope, Aleph Zedek Aleph, the National Jewish Hospital in Denver, the Leo N. Levi Memorial Hospital at Hot Springs, and the Jewish Orphan Home in Cleveland.</p>
   <p>Concurrently with the convention was staged the first annual convention of the B'nai B'rith Women's Grand Lodge, which was organized last year with Miss Lucille D. Zinner of Chicago as president. She was succeeded for the coming year by Mrs. Jacob Beck of East St. Louis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
