<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-03-15">Mar. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">B'nai B'rith Hears from Zion</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-03-15">Mar. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">B'NAI B'RITH HEARS FROM ZION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A huge meeting of B'Nai B'Rith, arranged by the Ramah Lodge, was held last night in the large salon at the Morrison Hotel.</p>
   <p>The audience responded enthusiastically to the detailed explanation of the meaning of Zionism, its aspirations, and its importance.</p>
   <p>Judge Hugo Pam was the principal speaker of the evening.</p>
   <p>Zionist gatherings certainly are not new in Chicago. The Zionist movement has been spoken of and written about so frequently, that it is almost impossible to say something original,something that has not been said <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1288.jpg" n="2"/>before, in one form or another. And yet, at this meeting, it was obvious that an innovation had taken place in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The newness was not to be detected in what the speaker had to say, although he spoke dynamically at the time adhering to facts and logic; nor was it a new accomplishment to hold the interest of a Jewish audience in a Zionist lecture. The newness consisted of the bringing together of such a speaker with such an audience. As is known, Judge Hugo Pam has become interested in the Zionist movement during the last two or three years. But the order B'nai B'rith, as an organization, is still not interested in the great movement. It was therefore a real novelty to witness how a new converted Zionist, a son of American soil, to whom Judaism was only a faint speculation, stood and spoke of the reconstruction of Jewish territory, of the pioneers who helped rebuild Palestine, of the colonies and schools, of <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1289.jpg" n="3"/>the modern language and culture, and of the necessity for Jewish center that will make possible a finer material life for a certain portion of Jews, and that will act as a divine inspiration to all Jews.</p>
   <p>It was still more interesting, to see how the members of the B'nai B'rith, to whom the idea was completely new, received the words of the speaker. They listened with as much attentiveness as they would listen to a lecture on some remarkable discovery.</p>
   <p>This confirms the ideas which we ourselves have in the past so often expressed on this position, namely, that Jewish organizations, whatever their programs may be at their inception, will untimately prove to be of great help to the cause of the Jewish people. Wherever a vast number of Jews assemble, the common Jewish instinct prevails. Very often, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1290.jpg" n="4"/>the individual, who may be far from Jewish problems, is not aware of it. This is now indicated by the position that the largest Jewish orders have taken toward Zionism and the question of the Jewish Congress.</p>
   <p>The Ramah Lodge is worthy of heartfelt praise for last evening's meeting. This was so far as we knew, the first "official" test, where Zionism was discussed before a large attendance of the members of B'nai B'rith. As a Jewish problem, Zionism should have been discussed in the councils of the B'nai B'rith quite some time ago. We do not wish to imply however, that the order as such, should turn Zionistic. Nevertheless, it seems to us that a large Jewish organization, with so many intelligent and wealthy Jews having so much influence, should not pass over any Jewish movement without due consideration.</p>
   <p>Last evening's meeting was a fine beginning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
