<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, 
            <date when="1917-05-20">May 20, 1917</date>.<title level="a">A Day in Chicago (Editorial)</title>
        
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>, 
            <date when="1917-05-20">May 20, 1917</date>.<title level="a">A Day in Chicago (Editorial)</title>
        </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whatever reasons for dissatisfaction this day might bring to the Jews in Chicago, one thing is certain, -the Chicago Jewry have not witnessed a more active day for a long time.</p>
   <p>An ordinary Sunday holds the interest of the Jews who take a hand at Jewish affairs. Hardly a Sunday goes by without a Jew attending a meeting, or lecture, or election, let alone pinochle, which is also a Jewish undertaking. However, to the ordinary Sunday affairs of the Chicago Jewry there are added three great events which attract the attention of the great masses: The Convention to nominate delegates to the Jewish Congress, the Tag Day for the Jewish National Fund, and the mass meeting at Sinai Temple, with Mr. Louis Marshall, of New York, Rabbi Emil. G. Hirsch as principle speakers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1252.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Jew who wants to pass time today will find the opportunity of great benefit, and will be inclined to utter the prayer, when it rains too much: "You have endowed us with too many good things and we are unable to consume everything." On his way to the convention he will be greeted by a Jewish maiden, with American roses, who will pin one on him, explaining that it is for the benefit of the National Fund. At the convention he will encounter various Jewish interests, and ideas concerning leadership which will be disputed by different groups who wish to be represented at the American Jewish Congress. Today's convention is an event that the Jews in Chicago, and probably in America, have never witnessed. There they will hear rhetorical expressions, as well as common ordinary words, and will see all sorts of exciting scenes, which will leave him no time to waste. And as soon as he gets through with the convention, he will have to hurry to the Sinai Temple, to the huge mass-meeting for the 10 million dollar fund, and listen to the appeals by Mr. Marshall and Rabbi Hirsch, and -who knows?- perhaps throw a check or a subscription into the basket when the opportunity presents itself.
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1253.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In short, it is a Sunday in which one cannot afford to waste time. And may the weather man have some consideration and not sprinkle these warm undertakings with cold water.
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
