<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>American Jewish Year Book</title>,
<date when="1913">1913</date>-14, pp. 361-393.
<title level="a">Jewish National Organizations in the United States with Branches in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>American Jewish Year Book</title>,
<date when="1913">1913</date>-14, pp. 361-393.
<title level="a">JEWISH NATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS IN THE UNITED STATES WITH BRANCHES IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Arbeiter Ring (The Workmen's Circle). Baron De Hirsch Fund. Cantors Association of America. Educational League for the Higher Education of Orphans. Federation of Roumanian Jews of America. J. Gartenstein, president of the Chicago branch. Independent Order of B'nai B'rith. Independent Order B'rith Abraham. Independent Order B'rith Sholom. Independent Order Free Sons of Israel. Independent Order Sons of Benjamin. Independent Order of True Sisters (Unabhangiger Order Treue Schwestern). Independent Western Star Order. Industrial Removal Office. Inter collegiate Menorah Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1298.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Jewish Consumptives Relief Society. Jewish National Workers Alliance of America. Jewish Socialist - Territorialist Labor Party of America. National Conference of Jewish Charities in the United States. Constituent Societies, Chicago. Associated Jewish Charities, Bureau of Personal Service, Chicago Women's Aid, Chicago Women's Loan Association, Jewish Consumptive Relief Society. National Federation of Temple Sisterhoods - Affiliated Sisterhoods, Chicago - Emanuel Society, Isaiah Woman's Club, K. A. M. Auxiliary, Ladies' Auxiliary of Temple Sholom National Jewish Fraternal Congress - Orders, Chicago - Independent Order Western Star.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1299.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>National Union of Jewish Sheltering Societies. Order B'rith Abraham. Order Knights of Joseph. Order Knights of Zion. Pi Tau Pi Fraternity. Progressive Order of the West. Union of American Hebrew Congregation. Chicago Congregations, Anshe Maarab, Bene Sholom, Chicago Sinai, Emanuel, Isaiah Temple, North Chicago Hebrew.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
