<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-29">June 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[Community Activity]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-29">June 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[COMMUNITY ACTIVITY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jews living in the Logan Square and Humboldt Park districts will celebrate today. The Hungarian Congregation, Bnai Duvid Auhevi Tzaduk (Sons of David, Lovers of Righteousness), are laying the cornerstone for a new synagogue, Talmud Torah (school), and community center at the corner of Humboldt Boulevard and Armitage Avenue.</p>
   <p>The building will be erected and fashioned in the same manner as the Institute Synagogue in New York. It will cost about ninety thousand dollars, and will cover an area of 55 by 175 feet, with a seating capacity of 1400, a huge auditorium, ten classrooms for the Talmud Torah and Sabbath School, a kindergarten, a library with a large reading room, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1184.jpg" n="2"/>and a social room.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Israel Elfenbein, the spiritual leader of the congregation for the past three years at the old synagogue, will also be the spiritual leader of the new abode. Greater and better things are expected of him which certainly will be fulfilled. Dr. Elfenbein is a learned man from Europe; he went to Shecters Seminary, also to the University, and has written and published in English various articles concerning Jewish lore.</p>
   <p>The synagogue, naturally, will be strictly orthodox. Hungarian Jews, as a rule, are more orthodox than those coming to America from other countries.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that the above-mentioned Jewish community will play as important a role in Jewish life in Chicago as the Hungarian community, Auhav Tzaduk, does in New York.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1185.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We congratulate the Bnai David Auhevi Tzaduk on today's festivities.</p>
   <p>Before America entered the War, a society of young people was established in Chicago, called the "Chicago Zion Advent" with the purpose of rendering to Zionism such personal service as might be required.</p>
   <p>The society had begun to conduct many necessary activities, but the War came along taking every young man into military service. Naturally the society dissolved.</p>
   <p>But now that the War is ended, and a great Zionist convention is to be held in Chicago which demands much personal attention, the Chicago Zion Advent has been reorganized with a membership of one hundred.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1186.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Their purpose will be to help Chicago Zionist districts in all their undertakings which require an increased number of workers.</p>
   <p>Membership dues for the Chicago Zion Advent is not paid in money, but in "services". Each member pledges to devote as much time to Zionist activities as is necessary to accomplish those duties assigned to him.</p>
   <p>The reorganization meeting will be held this coming Tuesday evening in room 312 of the Ashland Block building.</p>
   <p>All former members and those desiring to join are asked to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
