<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-11">Apr. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0979</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0979.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-11">Apr. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Orthodox Jewish community of Chicago, as well as the Keren Hayesod, will benefit from this year's drive of the Keren Hayesod. I have seen for the first time since I am in Chicago nearly all the rabbis, presidents, and committees of all the big synagogues gathered under one roof and interested in the problem of how to build Palestine. I have heard for the first time since I am in Chicago the rabbis and synagogue presidents speak briefly, seriously, and to the point about Palestine and our duties to it. Every speaker--beginning with Rabbi Rabinowitz of Knesses Israel Nusach Sford Synagogue, who, by the way, was in charge of the Kosher food for the banquet, and ending with Dr. Abramowich--spoke seriously, briefly, and to the point. This is a good omen for the growth of this year's drive. It is to be regretted that two big synagogues--the Liebawitch and the Agudas Achim North Shore were not represented. Both synagogues will, of course, fulfill their quotas, Mr. [Leo] Fox is the acting <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0980.jpg" n="2"/>president and Messrs. Zevin and Rosenthal are the assistant managers in the Liebawitch Synagogue. Dr. Sonderling, Hibshman, and Isidor Liederman are the chief workers in the Agudas Achim North Shore Synagogue. Both synagogues will not give less than the Knesses Israel Nusach Sford Synagogue gave--ten thousand dollars. The Liebawitch Synagogue gave last year ten thousand dollars but at that time the energetic Diskin was living and Zevin was very active. Mr. Diskin is now dead and Mr. Zevin is in California. It remains to be seen whether Fox and Rosenthal can do this year as much as Diskin and Zevin did last year. We should keep an eye on the Liebawitch people to see what they are going to do.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
