<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-28">Feb. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Scandalous Situation in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0116</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0116.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-28">Feb. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDALOUS SITUATION IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jewish Chicago is all agog, Jewish Chicago is excited. At meetings, in the synagogue, at the family table, they talk about it. You understand what I mean, don't you? I mean the talk that is going on about the two sluggers who came in to see Mr. T. Piser, a well-known undertaker, and slugged him until he lost consciousness, because he had dared to bury a dead person in Chicago. For a "crime" like that the punishment in Chicago is death and Mr. Piser should be grateful to the sluggers because they didn't kill him.</p>
   <p>A Jewish community like Chicago, with its hundreds of thousands of Jews, has to ask the permission of sluggers in order to bury its dead! This is the great Jewish community of Chicago! The proud Jewish community of Chicago! The Jewish capitol of America! The Chicago Jewish community is a free and independent community, but slaughtering is in the hands of a union, burial <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0117.jpg" n="2"/>is in the hands of strangers, and the Chicago Jews have only one kind of freedom--to give money. And we talk about the free, independent, proud Jewish Chicago!</p>
   <p>But what do the representatives of Chicago Jewry say about this? The presidents of the one hundred Orthodox synagogues, of the hundreds of Jewish lodges, the rabbis, the social workers, the public busybodies--what are they doing? They are silent--ssh-ssh--one must not make a scandal.</p>
   <p>[Editor's note: The reference here is evidently to the Sunday burial of the dead, a custom which the Jews were trying to institute, and to which the liverymen and chauffeurs were opposed.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
