<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-02">Mar. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Young Criminals</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0200</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0200.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-02">Mar. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG CRIMINALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new juvenile court will be opened in Chicago, March 15, for young people between the ages of 17 and 21, because the juvenile court which already exists only deals with crimes committed by children up to 17 years of age, and there is evidence that in the past few years of its existence, the juvenile court has accomplished wonderful work.</p>
   <p>One fact is worthy of mention here in order that everyone should understand that children very often become criminals on account of the ignorance and negligence of their parents. We wish to relate the story of a child who was poor at school in his studies and was not given any special attention by his teacher. He was even looked upon with contempt in his own home. When he became 8 years old, he failed in the second grade, for which he became despondent. His despondency drove him to associate with bad boys who inveigled him to take to thievery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0201.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When this child was brought into the juvenile court and examined by a psychiatrist, it was discovered that he had poor eyesight, that he could not study because he was unable to see any printed letters. His vision was immediately corrected by the aid of glasses, and shortly afterwards he did excellent work in school.</p>
   <p>If, however, the juvenile court had not been in existence, what would have become of him? Until the time for his trial, he undoubtedly would have been locked up in prison with other criminals, where he would have learned everything that is to be learned about theft. Everybody knows that a prison does not reform, does not improve human nature, but that on the contrary it drives one deeper into the marsh of crime. With the inauguration of juvenile courts, hundreds of children are saved from this background.</p>
   <p>Why shouldn't there be such a court for older children? Aren't there enough youngsters between the ages of 17 and 21 who need reformation and correction rather than be sent to prison? With the opening of this court, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0202.jpg" n="3"/>better reforms will actually be introduced. Many young, irresponsible lives will be saved and probably be brought back to their normal condition.</p>
   <p>Chief Justice Olson says that it depends on whether the people are fully grown enough to realize that we should treat those who have not become professional criminals so that they should be given the opportunity to again become good citizens. Only then will such a court be crowned with success.</p>
   <p>It is hoped that everybody will realize that every means to lessen crime is an urgent necessity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
