<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-10">Aug. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-10">Aug. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new Jewish institution has been organized in Chicago, and it has been very successful since the time of its inception. The institution referred to is the Zionist plan of "open-air" meetings.</p>
   <p>This plan was introduced in Chicago by Mr. S. Blitz of New York, who came here to help the membership campaign of the Zionist districts in Chicago. When Mr. Blitz first presented the plan of open-air meetings to the Zionist leaders of Chicago, they were skeptical of its success. Its success in New York meant nothing in Chicago, because in New York, whole areas are populated by Jews alone, whereas such a situation does not exist here.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, the representative from New York was not discouraged when he failed to receive the enthusiastic response he had expected here. With the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1176.jpg" n="2"/>aid of several volunteers, he organized some open-air meetings in various districts, and wherever volunteers signed up new members, the meeting proved to be very successful.</p>
   <p>During an evening, you may pass a corner in some neighborhood, and see a gathering of honorable Jews, older men and women, and young folks. They are listening with interest to the Zionist speakers. Later, when the speakers are gone, you will find groups of Jews still there, discussing what they heard. Nor is this all. Immediately, right on the spot, Jewish men and women will enroll as Zionist members, and will pay the two-dollar [initiation fee]. There are not enough volunteers to enroll the new members.</p>
   <p>The open-air meetings increase the membership of the Zionist Organization, and strengthen the propaganda among the Jews to become a nation like the other nations of the world.</p>
   <p>To date, the following speakers have been heard at the open-air meetings: <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1177.jpg" n="3"/>Blitz, Grossman, Goldberg, Goldstein--all of New York--and Leon Zolotkoff, M. Shulman, N.D. Kaplan, W. Steinberg, Dave Hirsh, S. Ginsberg, B. Jenkin, H. Shapiro, H.L. Meites, and several others from the Chicago districts.</p>
   <p>The open-air meetings are only a small part of the activities of the great Zionist movement in connection with the Zionist convention, which is to be held here, September 14. The meetings bring new life to the Jews in Chicago. The local delegates to the convention are beginning to discuss Zionist problems, so that they can bring definite proposals to the convention regarding the type of work they want to continue, and what they want to change. They will be able to explain what they expect from the American organization, and how they want the problems pertaining to the rebuilding of Palestine to be handled.</p>
   <p>The Zionist bureau in Chicago, headed by Mr. Leon Zolotkoff, has made possible the success of the open-air meetings by its moral support. It is helping to make the coming convention the kind of a convention it should be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
