<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-26">Mar. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Course of Jewish Literature</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0505</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0505.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-26">Mar. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE COURSE OF JEWISH LITERATURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By its literature and art, a people waxes great or perishes. For unless a people transmute its spiritual life experiences into creative form, so that he who runs may read, it has no emotional significance to humanity at large because the history of mankind is, after all, the concrete narrative of the progress of civilization, and civilization is the product or man's spirit, and without this spirit, no real progress may be achieved. The Jewish people is distinguished from all others by the distinction of its contribution to civilization, and this contribution, it need hardly be repeated, is that which has been made in its literature. The Jewish people would never have known persecution in any large sense, if it had been content with a physical life merely. But if the expression of our spirit has caused us some persecution, and in its reaction upon ourselves has given us a taint of melancholy and has made us at times an elegiac people, it has also been our light of hope through <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0506.jpg" n="2"/>the centuries, and only as creators have we been able to sustain our life as a people.</p>
   <p>However, in this respect, it is essential to make clear the fact that it was not only our literature of ancient times, our literature of the Bible and the Talmud, which has perpetuated our life as a people. The Bible and the Talmud have merely served as the foundations of our structure, and the literatures that we have created in the different countries of the Diaspora and in the different ages of our history have been the rivets and the steel girders which have lent strength to our structure and enabled it to bear up its load and even to send its spires into the blue skies of hope.</p>
   <p>No people can nourish itself wholly upon the food of its past. To be consistent to life, to co-ordinate its actions into thoughts, and to create a response that will sustain it further, it requires nourishment all the time. It requires a translation of its current life into literature and art forms. Thus it is enabled to reach a perspective of the life it is leading, as well as <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0507.jpg" n="3"/>to know how to direct its overflowing currents. Life is never stable, of course, and the wisdom that is gleaned from the Past may teach us traditions and forms of our present creative efforts. More than that, as in the case of our own experience as a people, our ancient literature may radiate an ever-illuminating and warming energy to light us and strengthen us in our present tasks, yet every age and place has its conditions and characters of life and unless we give expression to the latter, we are dead to the actual life that we are leading, and thus resemble not the living oaks of the forest, but rather the petrified flora and fauna of bygone ages, which may have a geological, but can have no Spiritual interest of any real sort.</p>
   <p>The Jewish people have sustained its life throughout the revolutionary changes of civilization both in ancient times and modern times, not by a physical adhesion to one group, which our evilly disposed critics think clannish, but rather by the creation of such spiritual forces within us as have welded our people into a spiritual whole.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0508.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Thus at the very beginning of our Diaspora life, Philo, influenced by new currents of life, in a center of civilization hostile to the Jewish spirit, sees in Hellenistic philosophy not what a Greek philosopher could see in it, but a philosophy of life which is in many respects profoundly Jewish. Likewise, Maimonides translates Aristotle into a philosophy of his own which again is Jewish rather than Greek or Arabic. In medieval Spain, Portugal, and Italy, Jewish life, though it ran independently in each of these countries, yet reflected a common spirit and has been continuous in some of its manifestations down to our own day.</p>
   <p>But while the Jewish creative men of letters have always found not only their medium but even their content in the countries of their sojourn, the literary expression which is current in American Jewish life has been grafted from alien soil. As long as we were not native here and lived in the light of our past, there was some justification for our literature to be alien to the soil. But now American Jewry is fast becoming the most organic group of Jewry in the world. We cannot attain an organic character, however, unless there is a <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0509.jpg" n="5"/>spiritual fire to fuse our whole people together in a common aim. This can be achieved only by a full devotion of our creative men and women to an expression of our American life here.</p>
   <p>Most of our Jewish contemporary men of letters in America, it is true, have themselves been born abroad, and having come here at a mature age, it is probably not to be expected of them that they write of a life which is novel to them and the nature of which they do not as yet fully comprehend. However, the new generation of our men and women know American life and should be able to create in the field of American life. Too often many of them who know more about Jewish American life than of non-Jewish American life, employ all their efforts in describing conditions and characters who can be known to a group other than themselves. That is a great error on their part. They should not forget that when they write on subjects that possess no Jewish significance, they will yet betray their spirit, which if it is at all powerful, must be Jewish in its intensity, since they are children of the Jewish people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0510.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>So far American Jewry has produced only a few works of scholarship and translation. This is not enough. Eastern European Jewry is at present disorganized and not in a position to do a great deal of constructive work either in the field of scholarship or creative writing. If we wish to continue the spiritual expression of our people, we must not only help Eastern European Jewry to return to its normal state of life. We need not only to encourage Russian Jewry economically, so that it might reassume its Spiritual life, which we doubt not will shortly come to pass, but we must not break up the continuity of the Jewish spirit. The remarkable achievement of the Jewish people in the Spiritual field lies in the fact that a score of Jewries in different countries of the Diaspora and in different periods and ages of history have produced so many literatures. We have thus entertained many points of view and have gained a greater coordination of the human spirit perhaps than any other people by viewing life in so many forms. What is still more remarkable is that we have succeeded in imbuing all these different phases of our activity with the one spirit common to our genius, the spirit which is present in the Bible and in all our literature since, in greater or lesser forms, the spirit of devotion to a few <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0511.jpg" n="7"/>fundamental ideals, which have been the beacon lights not only of the history of the Jewish people, but the history of the civilized world.</p>
   <p>It is essential, therefore, that the American Jewry reflect its current of life in a literature that shall be both native to the soil and in continuation of Jewish creative traditions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
