<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-01-06">Jan. 6, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Liberation of the Negroes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1419</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1419.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-01-06">Jan. 6, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">LIBERATION OF THE NEGROES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday Chicago celebrated the golden jubilee of the abolition of slavery in America.</p>
   <p>On the 1st of January, 1863, Abraham Lincoln officially proclaimed that "all persons, who are being held as slaves in every state, or part of a state, where the inhabitants have revolted against the United States, are now, and for all times, declared free".</p>
   <p>These simple words freed an entire race from servitude and from the peril of being taken from their homes in Africa to be brought to the southern states to pine away and die under the yoke and whip of the white christians.</p>
   <p>These simple words have cleansed that disgraceful stigma from the American Republic.</p>
   <p>However, it is more significant to remember that these simple and clear <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1420.jpg" n="2"/>words served as a weapon, in the hands of the government, to preserve the unity of the United States and to combat the tendency of the South to separate itself into a separate nation.</p>
   <p>The freedom of the Negro is, at the same time, the uniting of America and the beginning of the powerful growth of our Republic in all branches of social life.</p>
   <p>The states which were loyal to the Washington government have re-affirmed the fire of idealism and the deep devotion of freedom--lovers to the Proclamation of Emancipation by Abraham Lincoln, which brought in a fresh and powerful current of unity and patriotism, which, in turn, over-balanced the sectional, egotistic interests and efforts of the uncultured and backward, but courageous, slave states.</p>
   <p>It is sentiment of patriotism mixed with a sentiment of human love that moved Chicago to celebrate the jubilee of the Negro's liberation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1421.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And who can estimate a holiday of freedom better than we Jews? It is true that we weren't, prior to our exile (before the Jewish state was destroyed) in a state of slavery, but we endured enough persecution, as a race and as individuals, to understand the philosophy of freedom. Our condition today in various countries is exceedingly mournful, and we understand the sighs of the persecuted. We endorse the holiday of the free.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
