<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-09">Apr. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">[An Appeal to Jewish Workers to Join the Jewish National Workers Alliance of America]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-09">Apr. 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">[AN APPEAL TO JEWISH WORKERS TO JOIN THE JEWISH NATIONAL WORKERS ALLIANCE OF AMERICA]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Adv.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jewish workers, join the Jewish National Workers Alliance of America! What is the Jewish National Workers Alliance? This question can best be answered by the following excerpt from our declaration of principles:</p>
   <p>"Recognizing the need for assistance in case of death, want or sickness, and conscious also of the discrimination and injustice which Jews face in our present society, we Jewish workers have found it necessary to create an organization which has set itself to:</p>
   <p>"1. Give its members sick and death benefits.</p>
   <p>"2. Strengthen through education the national and social consciousness of the Jewish masses in order to fight against assimilation; participate in the revival of an international Jewish movement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1285.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"3. Function actively in the labor movement which seeks to improve the condition of the working class and to bring about a new and better social order."</p>
   <p>OUR MATERIAL BENEFITS</p>
   <p>The Alliance gives in benefits to its members: Insurance policies ranging from $100 to $2,000, the premiums of which are paid according to age.</p>
   <p>It also gives ten dollars a week consumptive and sick benefit. Special benefits are provided for accident insurance and "paid up" policies. The Alliance offers the most modern type of insurance policies.</p>
   <p>Men and women of 18 and over are accepted.</p>
   <p>Join with us; let's work together!</p>
   <p>If you are a Jewish worker, you should be interested in the Jewish National Workers Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1286.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As a Jewish radical, you should recognize your obligation and join the organized Jewish workers who are struggling for national and social emancipation. You should join with those who are fighting against discrimination, and for the recognition of Jewish rights--with those who seek Jewish emancipation.</p>
   <p>Jewish workers, do not remain aloof! Through an organization of all nationally conscious Jewish workers, let us build a powerful Jewish workers' order which may act as a model to others.</p>
   <p>Your place is in the Jewish National Workers Alliance! Come, build your own institution. Join one of our four Chicago Branches! For information, apply to the District Committee Secretary, Samuel J. Stulman, 3544 W. 12th Place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
