<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-02">May 2, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Washington and California.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0886</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0886.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-05-02">May 2, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WASHINGTON AND CALIFORNIA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Wilson Administration met with a dilemma, from which it is rather hard to disentangle itself.</p>
   <p>This entanglement started by the State of California demanding that a law be passed to prevent the Japanese from obtaining land in that state.</p>
   <p>If this demand would apply to all "aliens" in general, the national administration would not care, but in this case the phrase is underscored as "foreigners" who are not justified to citizenship. This indication is very insulting to the Japanese, and the Japanese ambassador submitted the usual protest against such treatment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0887.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A protest at random in behalf of justice probably would have no effect, but behind this protest is a country having a powerful army and navy, and some respect should be shown to such a nation.</p>
   <p>The Washington Administration is greatly embarrassed. The embarrassment is two fold: on the one hand, the administration does not want to provoke a powerful enemy, and on the other hand, it doesn't want to lose the sympathy of the California voters who oppose the Japanese.</p>
   <p>The dislike of the Japanese is not a new phenomenon in California, and the other states situated on the Pacific. The movement against these foreigners started many years ago - as far back as the Roosevelt Administration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0888.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The labor unions were among the first to start the campaign against the Japanese. The Japanese captured the jobs in the orchards and packing houses, and also penetrated into small business as fruit stores, restaurants, barber shops, etc. The Independent Labor Party sprung up to fight the Japanese.</p>
   <p>At that time the struggle to exclude the Japanese from the public schools and to establish separate schools for children of the Asiatic countries began.</p>
   <p>Roosevelt temporarily stilled the storm, and the California Jap-baiters threatened his administration by declaring that the entire Pacific coast would turn Democratic if the Republican administration would not create limitation laws against the Japanese.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0889.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There is now an administration in Washington, which was elected on a platform that had promised to give the different states unrestricted rights. The Governor of California, Johnson, found a suitable opportunity to throw a monkey-wrench into the Democratic administration. He began to warn the law-making machine to produce these "alien laws."</p>
   <p>The President's message didn't alter the situation, William Bryan's tour did not bear any weight. The California law-makers remained very persistent in their determination not to erase the insulting clause which was directed at the Japanese.</p>
   <p>The California state administration acted very rashly and did much harm to the principle of state rights. It is true that the states should be free in the management of their own affairs, they should, however, consider the interests of the entire union. America is now closely connected with the whole world and the world should feel safe that the Federal Government can live up to the treaties, which it signs with different nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0890.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We do not think that this dispute will lead to a war with Japan. It will, however, result in a revision in the relationship between the states and the union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
