<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-06">May 6, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0786</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0786.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-06">May 6, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Public Cook Pot. (Local News Column).</p>
   <p>The musical evening for the Maimonides Kosher Hospital - A holiday in West Park No. 1 - Fourth annual banquet for the Marks Nathan Orphan Home - Annual meeting of the Associated Jewish Charities - Adolph Krause of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The musical evening, to take place next Sunday at the Annex Hall of the Chicago Hebrew Institute is being arranged for the Maimonides Kosher Hospital. That this affair will receive the whole-hearted support of our Jewish community is out of question. We all realize and understand what the Hospital stands for, and above all we realize our need for such an institution.</p>
   <p>West Park No. 1 is rapidly becoming as popular among Jews as West Park No. 2. Already large numbers of our people are taking advantage of the fine atmosphere and spiritual uplifting that public parks so readily provide. West Park No. 1 is located at Chicago Ave. and Nobel St. West Park No. 2 is situated in a <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0787.jpg" n="2"/>Polish neighborhood, but there is also a large Jewish element. It would be only fitting and proper for Jews to participate in next Saturday's celebration at the Park. Among the many folk dances to take place will be the old time Chassidischer Folk Dance, the "Karahad." A good time of music and song is assured all who attend.</p>
   <p>Plans for the fourth annual banquet of the Marks Nathan Orphan Home have already been made. Invitations have been sent out. The banquet will take place at the West Chicago Masonic Temple at six o'clock in the evening. Mr. Nikolov Pritzker will be toast master. Others to speak will be Dr. S. Wolfenstein, superintendent of the Cleveland Orphan Home, Samuel Alschuler, Senator Ettelson, Dr. Israel Klein, Rabbi Budzinsky, B. Horwich, S. B. Komoiko, and Mr. Sol Drucker.</p>
   <p>A banquet and annual meeting of the members of the Associated Jewish Charities will take place Monday evening May 16, at the Hotel La Salle. The speakers <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0788.jpg" n="3"/>will be Professor Jacob H. Hollender, president of the National Conference of Jewish Charities, and head professor of Political Economy at John Hopkins University, and Judge Julian V. Mack, prominent New Yorker.</p>
   <p>Mr. Adolph Krause of Chicago was reelected to the presidency of the Order, B'nai B'rith, which no doubt makes the Jews of Chicago very happy. Mr. Krause has long been identified with those progressive forces seeking to unite Jews and Judaism and to strengthen those inherent and potentially powerful forces not lying stagnant in Judaism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
