<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-24">May 24, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1323.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-24">May 24, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Professor Shabsovitz on the Jewish Farmer.</p>
   <p>The manager of the Baron De Hirsch Fund says that Jewish farmers are increasing in the United States. Professor Shabsovitz, in Chicago on a short visit, in an interview with a Courier reporter, stated that already 7,000 Jewish families have settled upon farms in the United States. These farms represent an investment of about seven-million dollars. To settle people on farms is now a business and no longer a charity. The professor predicted an enormous increase in Jewish farmers within the next twenty-five years. Jewish farmers have been settled near large cities throughout the East, West, and Northwest.</p>
   <p>Can Jews be successful farmers? Well! Tobacco grown by Jewish farmers in Connecticut has been proven to be just as good if not better than that grown by non-Jews. The wine produced by Jewish farmers in New Jersey is as good as that produced from California vineyards. Sweet potatoes bring from 35 to 75 cents more per barrel to Jewish farmers.</p>
   <p>There are two Jewish Agricultural schools in the United States today, graduating <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1324.jpg" n="2"/>eighteen students this year who are full fledged farmers.</p>
   <p>Professor Shabsovitz has been interested in Agriculture for the past 28 years. He was graduated from the University of Zurich, Switzerland, and was the first trained Jewish Agriculturalist in Russia, and later in the United States.</p>
   <p>In Russia, he founded an agricultural publication. Professor Shabsovitz has come here from St. Louis where he attended the conference on Jewish Charities. There, he stressed his belief in the future and the necessity of settling Jewish families on farms.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
