<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-07-06">July 6, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.7"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-07-06">July 6, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Naturalization Conference determines to start a systematic campaign to make our masses into citizens.</p>
   <p>The Naturalization Aid League Conference, at the meeting last Friday, approved a number of decisions to broaden the activities of important branches represented by delegates of various organizations. They are as follows: 1. The organizations now being organized by unions, the Workmen's Circle, Socialist branches, and other Jewish organizations, shall be known as the Naturalization Aid League and shall, on a broad systematic plan, introduce the work which the Naturalization Aid League has accomplished in the last few months. 2. The purpose of the Naturalization Aid League shall be - (a) To help make our Jewish masses into citizens. (b) To combat all efforts made to rob our immigrants of their right to naturalize. 3. The League shall have a permanent office with at least one responsible person in charge, as soon as funds will permit. The League shall, as until now, have sub offices in various parts of the city and shall, besides the regular routine work, help people fill applications <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0566.jpg" n="2"/>for first and second papers, write letters to officials, go to court, etc., keep up classes on naturalization and, if possible, classes in Jewish and English history.</p>
   <p>4. The League shall not consider it sufficient to be helping those calling on them, but shall have a steady agitator among the Jewish masses, urging them to become citizens. This shall be done - (a) through the press, (b) through naturalization meetings. A competent committee of the League shall visit the meetings of the organizations belonging to the League and when a request is made, these committees shall declare the necessity of becoming a citizen and provide the necessary information. The League shall not accept any recompense from applicants for its work. In order to be able to carry on the work, each organization belonging to the League shall give a sum of not less than $5.00 a year. Larger organizations shall pay more in proportion, and from time to time run some sort of program.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0567.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>5. The League's money shall be deposited in the Amalgamated Bank.</p>
   <p>6. The Naturalization Aid League belongs to the whole labor movement, in that it must hold its conferences very often, and must have a central body to whom the officials of the League are always responsible. Therefore it became necessary to elect an Executive Board of fifteen who select among themselves a Chairman, Vice-Chairman, Secretary, and a Treasurer. The Executive shall also select a manager, who shall be responsible to the Board. The Board shall appoint an Advisory Committee of lawyers who also shall become members of the Executive Board. The Board shall also select one representative from each of the following bodies: The City Central Workmen's Circle; The United Hebrew Trades City Central Alliance; The International Union and the Amalgamated Unions. The Executive Board shall meet at least once a week. The Naturalization Committee shall meet every three months for the first year.</p>
   <p>The Naturalization Aid Conference finds it necessary that such Naturalization Aid Leagues shall be organized in all large cities of America, and they shall be combined in one National Bureau.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0568.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This Bureau is to be able to speak with authority on questions in general that may involve the whole nation.</p>
   <p>The Conference is thankful to the New York League, which was the example and guide in the work, for its warm greetings and its assistance. Thanks also to the Manager, Comrade Yeshurin, who is assured that as he undertook to organize the East, so shall the West be organized; that a chain of Naturalization Leagues shall cross the nation to make the organizing of a National Bureau possible. There are questions of a general national interest that the New York League, with the Chicago League should take up for discussion; such as hardships being planned against people who want to become citizens and new laws planned against non-citizens, etc. The Conference recommends to the Executive Board that contact be made with the New York Executive Board to take up these questions. The Conference expresses its heartiest thanks to the Forward for its agitation on the naturalization movement, also to the lawyers and all Comrades for their sincere work at the Conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
