<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, 
            <date when="1917-05-10">May 10, 1917</date>.<title level="a">Thousands of Jews Thunder "Yes!"</title>
        
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1254</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1254.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, 
            <date when="1917-05-10">May 10, 1917</date>.<title level="a">Thousands of Jews Thunder "Yes!"</title>
        </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting [Zionist] in Herzel School, last evening, was the most spectacular one ever witnessed by the Chicago Jewry.</p>
   <p>The program was carried through as announced, with the exception that Professor Foster, of the University of Chicago, substituted for Judge Cavanaugh.</p>
   <p>Mas Shulman opened the meeting with a brief introductory speech, after which he introduced Judge Hugo Palm as the first speaker.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zolotkoff followed him in Jewish with an explanation of the significance of the resolution, and the inspiration with which the great mass meeting adopted it.</p>
   <p>Professor Foster gave a brief talk which embraced the philosophical aspects <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1255.jpg" n="2"/> of Zionism, and Mr. Isadore Natkin in a brief talk appealed in behalf of the Hadasah.</p>
   <p>The meeting concluded under the tunes of "Hatikyah," and America."</p>
   <p>The resolution reads:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, reports were received from official sources that various governments are prone to concede official recognition to the Jewish Nation in Palestine, and that such recognition will probably be given to Jews with the full approval and assistance of the United States; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the spirit of the People's Government of which the Russian revolution is an important factor, implants hope and trusts that the Allies will very willingly recognize the justice of the Zionists;</p>
   <p>Therefore, be it resolved that we Jews, at this representative meeting, declare <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1256.jpg" n="3"/>by this resolution our firm position to the fundamental ideal of the Zionist movement, which is that the Jewish people demand the solution of the Jewish question through a guaranteed public assured and legally recognized home in Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
