<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-16">Mar. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Reading and Seeing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-16">Mar. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">READING AND SEEING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Contrary to the belief that some books tend to demoralize the character of children, people of keen perception and having some knowledge concerning children's education, bear witness to the fact that a child is not influenced by the reading of noxcious passages in books. In spite of this fact parents and guardians forbid their children to read books which, as the older people think, deal with subjects that should not reach the child's mind. In this connection, society provides children with special libraries and reading rooms. When reading room facilities are not available, control of children's reading material is accomplished by means of special juvenile cards, on which children are allowed to draw such books as are primarily written for them.</p>
   <p>Ouite different, however, is the attitude of parents and society on matters of "seeing." Parents who are rather cautious as to the selection of their children's reading material, do not show enough interest in the sort of moving pictures their children see. On the other hand, the censors, who have recently put a clamp on moving pictures, overdid their job by compelling adults to share <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0188.jpg" n="2"/>the lot of the children.</p>
   <p>What the child sees influences him more than what he reads. Such is the opinion of those who study child psychology. Moving pictures make the strongest impression on the child's mind. When seeing moving pictures, the child lives through their plots, and becomes impregnated with such thoughts and emotions as he cannot get from reading story or pictorial books. Without a Board of Censors for moving pictures shown to children, humanity would sink to abysmal depths; without a Board of Censors, the spirit of the new generation would become corrupt, poisoned, and mutilated.</p>
   <p>Be what it may, the question is that adults should not be obliged to suffer on account of small children. If they are not barred at public libraries from reading books that are unfit for children, we do not see why they should be forbidden the same privilege in theatres.</p>
   <p>Society can force the moving picture companies to arrange special pictures <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0189.jpg" n="3"/>for children, but under no circumstances should it deprive adults of the right to see whatever picture they like, just because they are unfit for children. Let the moving pictures be organized on the same basis as are the libraries, with a special division for children. The film companies will then be able to carry on their work without needing to fear censors, who look upon the matter from the children's standpoint, and without harming the children who shall then have their own special kind of pictures.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
