<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-04">Jan. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Women's Organization for Palestine Work</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1000</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1000.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-04">Jan. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AN IMPORTANT WOMEN'S ORGANIZATION FOR PALESTINE WORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What is the Women's Esrat Halutzim Society? It is a women's organization that has undertaken to raise money through various affairs; the money will be sent to Palestine for welfare work among the Halutzim. The money is raised among the membership and there is no public appeal for funds. The meetings are held in the homes of the members and they do not incur any expenses. Every dollar raised goes to the Jewish pioneers in the Holy Land.</p>
   <p>The members of the Esrat Halutzim Society are, at the same time, members of the Hadassah. The women contribute to every Zionist undertaking. They are Zionists in the full sense of the word. Their work is sanctioned by the Zionist Organization of America. When they have some money in their treasury, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1001.jpg" n="2"/>they send it directly to Jerusalem, to the financial department of the Palestine Zionist Executive Committee. They trust to the discretion of the Zionist Executive Committee because its people, being right there on the spot, know better than we do what kind of welfare work should be done among the Halutzim. We have on our desk copies of letters from the Palestine Zionist Executive Committee, which letters prove that the money sent from here by the Women's Esrat Halutzim Society, has been spent wisely. The letters say, among other things, that the Halutzim are being taught trades.</p>
   <p>The Women's Esrat Halutzim Society in Chicago has four hundred members; they are well-known Jewish women and girls who are an honor to themselves and to the community. We would like to see the Women's Esrat Halutzim Society increase its membership because a larger membership means more money, and more money means greater achievements in Palestine. Palestine will be built only by men and money--not through politics. Let our Zionists, once and for all, get this into their heads.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
