<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-19">Feb. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1096</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1096.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-19">Feb. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All Chicago Jews should greet with great enthusiasm the decision of the committee of one hundred [members] of the Keren Hayesod to begin at once the campaign for two hundred thousand dollars, the goal to be reached by the time Mr. Nahum Sokolow visits Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Keren Hayesod is today the most important fund of the Jewish people. All other funds have the task of helping the Jews temporarily, of easing their suffering as much as possible. Though this is, undoubtedly, our most sacred duty, it does not, however, radically solve the Jewish problem; the Keren Hayesod faces a much broader and a much more important task. The Keren Hayesod has the task of rebuilding the Jewish homeland, and of establishing a place there for our brothers, where they can live peacefully as other people live in other countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1097.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It has been known for a long time that the only way of curing a sickness is not by easing the pain and suffering, but by removing the cause of the sickness. The Jewish nation is sick. All of its sufferings, no matter in which land they occur, arise from the fact that the Jews are Diaspora people and do not have solid ground under their feet.</p>
   <p>We now have the opportunity of eliminating the reason for the Diaspora if--if we only want to. Palestine will become a Jewish homeland only when we exert our greatest efforts to provide the means needed today to build up our country.</p>
   <p>Chicago is one of the greatest Jewish centers in the world. Chicago has always fulfilled its duty to all local and national Jewish undertakings, and it must and it will do its duty for the future of the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>A city like Chicago should not find it difficult to raise two hundred thousand dollars by the time Mr. Sokolow arrives. This sum must be raised.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1098.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As you have read in the Courier, the Keren Hayesod committee has decided to organize two clubs: a club for two-hundred dollar members and a club for one-hundred dollar members. Anyone who wants to become a member of a club pays the required sum, and thereby becomes a member of the club. Only five hundred members for the first club and a thousand members for the second club--and the two hundred thousand dollars is raised.</p>
   <p>Chicago Jews! Enroll at once as a member of one of the clubs and help build the Jewish future in our own land.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
