<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[Chicago News]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[CHICAGO NEWS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Monday evening a meeting was held of all Chicago Zionist districts, presided over by Mr. Samuel Blitz, the New York campaign director.</p>
   <p>Reports of activities from each district were given, after which they set to work to formulate various plans for making the Zionist campaign in Chicago successful. Mr. Blitz suggested some plans which were accepted unanimously.</p>
   <p>The following tasks were accepted: first, that letters be sent to all officials of lodges and societies to [urge them] to support the Zionist cause. Also that meetings of these lodges and societies be attended for that purpose.</p>
   <p>Second, that Mr. Meyer Goldberg of New York should contact rabbis and presidents of synagogues in order to bring them into this organization. Many <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1188.jpg" n="2"/>other plans were formulated to make this campaign, which begins next Sunday, successful.</p>
   <p>The following are active in this work: S. Adelman, F. Berenson, Mr. Komsky, Dr. J. K. Rosenzweig, M. Abrams, Mr. Gefen, Miss Shapiro, Miss Zimring, Mrs. Yebitz, William Mack, William Weinstein, etc. etc.</p>
   <p>The children's congregation, composed of children from the Rachel Leah Talmud Torah (school), 1536 So. St. Louis Avenue, accepted last Saturday, at the appeal of Mr. Weil and Mr. Polock, a resolution in which for one whole week each member shall contribute his or her candy money for World War sufferers. They have already contributed twenty-five dollars in cash. Children from other schools should follow their example.</p>
   <p>The drive for twenty-five thousand dollars for the Mt. Sinai Hospital, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1189.jpg" n="3"/>sponsored by the Ladies Auxiliary, has already received fourteen thousand dollars in cash and pledges. The public is asked to respond and to send donations to Mrs. Edwin Romberg, 1244 Congress Hotel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
