<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-23">Mar. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Depositors Plan to Reorganize 16th Street Bank</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-23">Mar. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">DEPOSITORS PLAN TO REORGANIZE 16th STREET BANK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, a depositors' committee, with Samuel S. Horwich as chairman, discussed plans to reorganize the [16th Street] Bank. Mr. Horwich said that if the depositors were willing to purchase $50,000 worth of shares from the reorganized bank, he would ask Mr. Herman Elenboben, vice-president of the West Side National Bank, to take over the management of the bank. With this money and a capital stock of $110,000, the bank could be reopened. The plan was brought to the attention of the chief bank examiner, Mr. Sevedge.</p>
   <p>Attorneys Micon and Savitsky, together with a committee of depositors, appeared before Judge Foell yesterday and proposed that the court appoint a receiver for the closed bank. Judge Foell accepted the suggestion and said that he was willing to listen to proposals and would see that the receivership was as economical as possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0105.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Samuel Maltz, president of the closed bank, will be indicted by the grand jury and will face a criminal trial for his speculations, which led to the bank's failure.</p>
   <p>In the State's Attorney's office yesterday, Mrs. Sanford, a widow, denied that she had ever borrowed money from the 16th Street Bank. She said that Maltz induced her to sign a deed on property which she had allegedly purchased. Afterwards, Maltz took possession of the deed and the property remained his own. Mrs. Sanford claimed that on the aforementioned property, Maltz had borrowed money from the bank under her name.</p>
   <p>The State's Attorney will also investigate a charge that the 16th Street Bank accepted deposits last Monday--the day prior to its failure--when the officers knew that the crash was inevitable. Dr. Louis Zeidenberg informed the State's Attorney that he deposited $115 in the 16th Street Bank on Monday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
