<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-15">June 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Chaos in Our Philanthropy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-15">June 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CHAOS IN OUR PHILANTHROPY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It took years before we finally decided to systematize and centralize our various philanthropic activities in order to end the old charity system which was so costly and yet could not meet many of the philanthropic needs. But now many Jewish charities are centralized, not only in large Jewish centers but also in small Jewish communities in America. Our present philanthropic activities are now conducted according to a definite method and system. However, he who thinks that this has eliminated the chaotic condition is mistaken.</p>
   <p>The orthodox community in Chicago has its Federated Charities, a body which earns all the credit given its work. But this does not prevent the existence of many private charities which are responsible to no one and are not controlled by anyone. At present there are different tag days almost every day on the West Side. It has also happened that five different societies have <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1197.jpg" n="2"/>tagged on one and the same day for various purposes. Even last Sunday when the National Fund's annual tag day, known as "Flower Day," was held, a small local charity had the audacity to send out their own tag girls, thus setting up competition to the National Fund and confusing the public. It so happened that [the local group was collecting for relief purposes]. But so far as we know, the Joint Relief Committee, the only body controlling all relief activities in Chicago, had not given permission to this small local group to make its own tag day. How can the Joint Relief Committee control the relief activities, if every small local group works independently? How can the Federated control philanthropic work in Chicago if every small local group sets its own stage, makes its own tag day, keeps its own "money-purse" outside the jurisdiction of a central authority?</p>
   <p>Next Sunday, Chicago Jews will experience another example of this chaos and anarchy which reigns in our philanthropic life. The City Hall has issued a permit for a tag day to the "Ezreth Evlleem Viunkeem" (Aid for Nursing Babies), <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1198.jpg" n="3"/>formerly the "Bonuth Zion Jewish Day Nursery" and the "Motherless Infants Club". This organization, with a membership of four thousand, has a great and noble cause; it cares for the unfortunate Jewish infants under six years of age who are either orphans, or who cannot be cared for by their parents. Hundreds of such unfortunate Jewish infants live in Chicago. If a Jewish organization does not offer these babies a haven, Christian institutions will take them and rear them as Christians. It is unnecessary to discuss further the significance of this organization. For weeks its leaders worked for this tag day which was set for tomorrow. Everything seemed to indicate a successful day until last month some private charity, not a community organization as is the above-mentioned, but merely a small local group, announced a tag day for the same date. We do not know if they have a permit, but it seems to suit them to send out their volunteers on the same day which was so hopefully chosen by the Ezreth Evlleem Viunkeem. Such proceedings are scandalous in [their reflection on the activities of these] small groups and societies which are competing with the infant welfare organization. Further, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1199.jpg" n="4"/>such proceedings cast a shadow on the Federated since they show that the Federated has no control whatever over the philanthropic activities on the West Side. Rightly no small group should set its own tag day without the permission and approval of the Federated. We believe that the Federated is in a position to exercise its authority in this respect, to halt chaos and anarchy in our philanthropic life. If the City Hall continues to issue permits for tag days we must come to an agreement with them not to issue permits for Jewish tag days without the permission of the Federated.</p>
   <p>In the same manner must the Joint Relief Committee control all Jewish relief work in Chicago. The Pinsk, Minsk, Brisk, and similar "landsmen" groups must not work independently without the consent and approval of the Joint Relief Committee. When they do so, they endanger all Chicago relief work as has been done for the past few years. If each "landsmen" group had its own relief circles the Central Relief Organization could not exist. Of course there is want in Pinsk, Lemberg, Proskirov, and other cities where Polish pogroms occurred.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1200.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Their needs are great and heart-rending. But this does not justify [the work being done by the "landsmen" groups of these cities in Chicago]. They do no one any good thereby.</p>
   <p>We ask, why does the Joint Relief Committee permit such chaos? It has enough authority to force these small groups to co-operate and work harmoniously with it. The Joint Relief and the Federated must end the existent chaos in our Chicago philanthropy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
