<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-06-22">June 22, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Eucharistic Congress in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Johah Spivak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1576</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1576.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-06-22">June 22, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE EUCHARISTIC CONGRESS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Johah Spivak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eyes of the entire Christian world are now centered on Chicago, as are the eyes of the Mohammedans on Mecca and those of the Jews on Jerusalem because the Eucharistic Congress [of the Roman Catholics] is being held here this week under the presidency of Cardinal Banzona, the special messenger of the Pope.</p>
   <p>The Eucharistic Congresses have been observed since 1880. They differ with each session, and serve as a means of demonstrating the dogmas, ceremonies, and processions of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>Since the Roman Catholic Church lost its political power and limited itself to religious activities only, it has changed its attitude toward other faiths. Instead of commanding, ruling, and suppressing other faiths, as it formerly <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1577.jpg" n="2"/>did, it now speaks of tolerance and democracy. It is now in the same condition as the Jewish church.</p>
   <p>We shall now consider the social aspect of religion pointing out in passing that with regard to the question of tolerance Jews join hands with Catholics--especially in our country, the United States of America. First of all we shall consider the matter of teaching the Bible in the public schools of America. For the last two decades the Protestants have been fighting for compulsory teaching of the Bible in the public schools. They say that the study of the Bible, which is sacred, will have a great moral influence upon the children. The Bible is, however, interpreted in many ways, and the Protestants would naturally desire that it should be taught as they understand it. The Jews and the Catholics, who interpret the Bible according to their own commentaries, agree in their attitudes toward this matter: both believe that the Bible should not be taught in the public schools because one group has no right to force its religious beliefs upon another. The Catholics and <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1578.jpg" n="3"/>the Jews have constantly fought together, through the courts and the State legislatures in various sections of the country, against the Protestants whenever they introduced the Bible bill. It is understood that the Catholics did not do this because of their great love for the Jews; they desired to prevent the Protestants from attaining religious power.</p>
   <p>There are also a number of minor religious, social, and political problems facing the Catholics in America which also confront the Jews--since both the Jews and the Catholics are minority groups. We shall stop here to point out only one great problem, or to use a better phrase, one American social evil--the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
   <p>As is well known, the Ku Klux Klan is a rotten product of the Protestant Church and of moldy chauvinism. We do not mean to accuse the Protestants of America since the more progressive elements of America, who are still the majority, combat the Klan and do not let its arrogant head rise in social and political <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1579.jpg" n="4"/>life. The Eucharistic Congress was greeted by President Coolidge, who is a Protestant, in the name of the United States and of American tolerance. This was a great blow to the Klan. And even though Chicago is now less religious than it was, yet it accepts the Eucharistic Congress favorably, and extends the hand of friendship to all the delegates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
