<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-08">May 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-08">May 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jewish welfare workers of New York, who are interested in the Jewish Congress, are strongly set against Chicago. How is it that Chicago does nothing nor does it want to do anything for the Congress? Unfortunately, or fortunately, Chicago is not the only Jewish community in America which takes such little interest in the Congress, because the Jews of the Middle West cannot understand the purpose of a Jewish Congress that does not have the approval of all classes of American Jews. It is a hundred per cent certain that the working class and the extremely rich class will not participate in the forthcoming Congress, and what the Jewish middle class in America thinks is well known from the resolutions which the various Jewish fraternal orders adopt from time to time. The Zionists' <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1637.jpg" n="2"/>opinions on various Jewish questions are also well known, and if the Congress shall only be an expression of opinions, then it isn't at all necessary. If the Congress, however, has special tasks; if it wishes to accomplish a certain thing, then let the Congress leaders declare what they wish to do and what can be expected of it. Then, we shall hear, as well as be able to express, an opinion about the possibility of a special congress. But as long as the Congress has no definite aims, and has only the support of a small group of New York leaders, I cannot conceive of how the Jews in Chicago and in other cities of the Middle West can take an interest in it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
