<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-07-15">July 15, 1923</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1923-07-15">July 15, 1923</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Medical Conference of the Workmen's Circle was held in the Labor Lyceum, with Friend Lewin, Branch 176, Chairman, and Friend Folkson, Branch 306, Secretary; Stern, Branch 178; Finegold, Branch 377; and Berkovitz, Branch 65, were appointed as Credential Committee.</p>
   <p>The committee reported that 21 Branches were represented and all delegates were admitted.</p>
   <p>A report was given by a committee of seven, stating that they have contacted the New York Workmen's Circle Medical Department, which sent them all necessary information concerning management. This gives us the opportunity to absorb their experience, so that we may carry through everything with fewer mistakes and greater success.</p>
   <p>It was reported that several physicians were interviewed, and the matter was thoroughly discussed with them.</p>
   <p>The physicians said that a medical department would be one of the greatest things the Workmen's Circle could achieve for its members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1619.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee of seven came to the conclusion that, in order to carry through the plan with success, they must know, above all, how many members will join the medical department. The greater the number of members, the better conditions and more competent doctors.</p>
   <p>When we organize we will engage prominent specialists, at low rates, and also install private dental and medical clinics for various examinations.</p>
   <p>The report was thoroughly discussed by all delegates, with much interest and spirit.</p>
   <p>1. The conference unanimously decided that a medical department should be established in Chicago.</p>
   <p>2. It was resolved that anyone would be eligible for membership.</p>
   <p>3. The dues shall amount to five ($5.00) dollars a year; $1.50 quarterly for a family of three; or $.75 quarterly for a single man.</p>
   <p>4. The dues shall be collected by the branches.</p>
   <p>5. Every member of the Workmen's Circle shall receive application cards and a <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1620.jpg" n="3"/>letter informing him as to the medical department.</p>
   <p>6. A committee of nine was appointed to promote the work.</p>
   <p>7. It was determined that the committee should carry through as it sees fit, make all arrangements with the doctors, and then call a conference.</p>
   <p>8. A question was presented about financing the work,and it was decided that all Branches should contribute two dollars or more.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
