<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-15">May 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1634</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1634.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-15">May 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On October 14, the Jewish Congress will convene either in Washington or in New York. The Congress elections will take place June 24. This is good news, but what will be the consequences? Will the Congress earn the name of American Jewish Congress? Dr. Motzkin and Nathan Straus claim that the Congress is important for the struggle for Jewish rights in Europe. This is purely an opinion and I don't believe in opinions. In Europe not only the governments but also the people are anti-Semitic, and if something is to be done for the oppressed and persecuted Jews there, it has to be done through diplomacy and back stair policies, not through massmeetings. If the American Jewish Congress devotes itself to Jewish work in America, it will exist and be justified. As a Jewish foreign office or as a Jewish diplomatic agency, it is, to my mind, useless. If you think otherwise, I shall not hold it against you. And if you will convince me that I am <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1635.jpg" n="2"/>wrong, I shall not be ashamed to admit it openly. I would like to know what the Chicago Jews think about the American Jewish Congress.</p>
   <p>At least fifty delegates from America will depart for this year's Zionist Congress in Carlsbad, [Germany]. Five or six delegates active in Zionist work, such as Max Shulman and B. Brenner, will leave from Chicago. If the American delegation consists of good human material, Dr. Weizmann will be able to carry out all of his plans, and all troubles will vanish, because the entire work in the organization will be centralized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
