<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-12">Jan. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Center for the Youth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0547</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0547.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-12">Jan. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A CENTER FOR THE YOUTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rabbis and welfare workers are both complaining, and with good reason, about the religious and spiritual abandonment of our youth. They seldom see the youth in the synagogues or at Jewish affairs and they cannot conceive of the Jewish youth constituting a factor in Jewish life. Should a person attend the synagogue, he would meet only elderly people. Should he frequent Jewish lodges, he, likewise, would meet only elderly Jews. It is obvious that if such a condition continues, Judaism in Chicago will not endure.</p>
   <p>The question is often asked: who can be blamed for this sad and deplorable condition? Some blame the deficiency in Jewish education; others argue that the old-fashioned methods of the rabbis are to blame; and still others, who <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0548.jpg" n="2"/>can see farther than their noses, understand that the new American atmosphere is basically at fault, because it creates its own relationship between Jewish parents and Jewish children, a relationship which affects disastrously the elderly Jew who has given his child a practical Jewish education.</p>
   <p>We wish to ask those who hold the old-fashioned methods of the rabbis responsible: Have the modern rabbis accomplished more than the old-fashioned rabbis? Are the Reform temples full? It seems that the Reform temples are also empty; that the Jewish youth does not enter them. How can we say, therefore, that the old-fashioned methods of the [Orthodox] rabbis are responsible for the spiritual and religious abandonment of the Jewish youth generally in America, and particularly in Chicago? The Reform rabbi makes it so easy for the youth. He does not impose upon them any arduous tasks. Nor does he impose difficult precepts upon them. On the contrary, he offers them things which should attract them, viz., a trained choir, shortened prayers, sermons on topics of <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0549.jpg" n="3"/>the day--and yet, only elderly people can be seen in the Reform temples.</p>
   <p>Consequently, we cannot say that the old-fashioned methods of the rabbis have caused the spiritual and religious abandonment of our youth.</p>
   <p>As far as the other accusation is concerned--the deficiency in Jewish education--we admit that this is a more reasonable explanation. Had the Jewish youth in America been reared in a Jewish manner--at home, and received his theoretical training in the Hebrew school--he would have been more interested in Jewish matters. But in America he got neither a practical Jewish upbringing at home nor a Jewish theoretical education in [Hebrew] school; and the result is deplorable. There is no Jewish youth in America. There are plenty of young Jewish people, but there is no Jewish youth, which could be a driving force in the Jewish life of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0550.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>American Jewry now faces the great problem of bringing the Jewish youth back to Judaism. This is a very difficult problem, which cannot easily be solved.</p>
   <p>The American way of life has destroyed the old Jewish home with its old Jewish atmosphere, and the Hebrew schools here can only accommodate ten per cent of our children. But we can still build Hebrew schools. That is a matter of money. However, we cannot so easily re-establish the old Jewish home with its typically Jewish atmosphere. Therefore, we must seek to establish the next best, viz., a Jewish center for the Jewish youth.</p>
   <p>This Jewish center may take the place of the Jewish home and the Jewish school. In this center the Jewish youth must find [the atmosphere of] a Jewish home; in this center the spirit of the Jewish youth must develop; in this center there must be Hebrew classes for adults; in this center there must be courses <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0551.jpg" n="5"/>in Jewish history and literature; in short, this center must be the center of the activities of the Jewish youth.</p>
   <p>The large Jewish settlements, such as the Lawndale District, the Northwest Side, the South Side, etc., must have their local Jewish centers for the youth, and at the helm of these centers should stand academically trained Jews, who have great pedagogical and administrative abilities, and who also have an excellent Jewish education.</p>
   <p>Let the Jews of the Lawndale District take the initiative in establishing such a center. We are convinced that the results will be so favorable that the other Jewish groups will soon follow the example of the Lawndale Jews by establishing their own centers.</p>
   <p>We are firmly convinced that only Jewish centers can bring the Jewish youth <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0552.jpg" n="6"/>back to their people and make them a driving factor in the life of our people in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
