<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-17">Jan. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-17">Jan. 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Henry Moss bought the five-story Beach View Apartment Hotel at Sheridan Road and Rogers Avenue from Barney Fogel, Joseph Goldberg, and Max Schubert for $550,000. The sellers made a profit of $65,000, having bought this property six months ago for $485,000.</p>
   <p>Joseph Goldberg and Max Schubert bought the twenty-room hotel at 1234 South Wabash Avenue from M. Friedberg for $90,000. Leo Edelman, of Edelman and Kaplan, was the attorney. The buyers plan to build a hundred-room hotel on the site at a cost of $400,000.</p>
   <p>A. Silverman and Ben Greenstein bought the apartment building at the southeast corner of Congress Street and Kildare Avenue from Morris Schultz for $59,000.</p>
   <p>Jessie Katz bought the twelve-apartment building at 721 Briar Place for $57,000. Rosenfeld and Terman were the brokers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0369.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A. Miller bought the twenty-four apartment building at 7632 Marshfield Avenue from Barney Handler and Hyman Jacobs for $140,000.</p>
   <p>Julius Ash and Jacob Goldberg bought the alley lot on Madison Street west of Jefferson Street, 38 by 100 feet, for $57,000. Rosenberg and Lurie were the brokers.</p>
   <p>Julius Landman bought the eighteen-apartment building at 6205 Langley Avenue from Leon Frank and R. Lubin for $92,500.</p>
   <p>The fifteen apartment building at the southeast corner of Douglas Boulevard and Clifton Park Avenue was sold by Max Rosenberg, A. Goldberg, and Hyman Cohen to H. Carl and S. Krivit for $125,000. Katz, Sokoloff, and Company were the brokers; Ed. Berkson and Samuel Rosenthal the attorneys.</p>
   <p>Jacob Alpert sold the forty-four and the thirty-six apartment buildings at 5645 and 5649 Washington Boulevard for $555,000. Ed. Berkson was the attorney.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0370.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>P. Feldman bought the property at North and Western Avenues for about $20,000.</p>
   <p>P. Abramowich bought the property at the northeast corner of Central Park and Grenshaw Avenues from I. Handler for $25,000 in cash.</p>
   <p>R. Simon bought the property at Washburne Avenue and Loomis Street from I. Erzman for $15,500.</p>
   <p>Joseph Meizel bought the property at Troy Street and Roosevelt Road from M. Pollack for $20,000.</p>
   <p>Dora Bloom bought the property at 3027 Madison Street from Sam Stalk for $33,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Finkel bought the property at Springfield Avenue and 13th Street from Solomon Marque for $12,000.</p>
   <p>Isidore Rappaport bought the property at Turner Avenue and 13th Street from <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0371.jpg" n="4"/>Lina Sackheim for $13,000.</p>
   <p>Max Kaplan bought the property at 3326 West Adams Street for $33,000.</p>
   <p>Isa Baikowich bought the property at Roosevelt Road and Mozart Street from David Shachter for about $24,000.</p>
   <p>Dora Goldstein bought the property at 5706 Madison Street from Nathan Beller for $58,000.</p>
   <p>I. Kendler bought the property at 3345 Douglas Boulevard from N. Levin for $65,500 in cash.</p>
   <p>Isaac Brook bought the property at the southeast corner of Sacramento Boulevard and Division Street for $136,000.</p>
   <p>Hyman Hurwich bought the property at 2638 Jackson Boulevard from Max Jaffe for <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0372.jpg" n="5"/>$39,000.</p>
   <p>M. Bronstein, 1529 Clifton Park Avenue, is building a three-story residence at 3819 Filmore Street. Rosen and Eisenberg, 5 North LaSalle, are the architects. The cost is estimated at $22,000.</p>
   <p>Rogers Park</p>
   <p>Wolf Leibowitz and J. Linder bought half of the 141 foot lot at Pratt Boulevard and Clark Street from Jerucham Zevin for $333,000.</p>
   <p>Isaac Hurwich sold the property at 1452 Farragut Avenue for $44,500.</p>
   <p>Lina Cohen sold the property at 1884 Devon Avenue for $85,500 in cash.</p>
   <p>Henry Moss bought the property at the northeast corner of Sheridan Road and Rogers Avenue from Joseph Goldberg for about $550,000.</p>
   <p>Morris Podolsky sold the property at the northwest corner of Estes Avenue and Paulina Street for $165,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0373.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In Other Neighborhoods</p>
   <p>Morris Faiwel sold the property at the northeast corner of Granville and Winthorp Avenues to the Granville Building Company for $78,000.</p>
   <p>M. Kanter bought the property at 5815 Winthrop Avenue from Leo Ginsberg for about $40,000.</p>
   <p>Harry Javitz sold the property at the southwest corner of Elmdale and Linkwood (sic) to Bernard Kirschbaum for $23,500 in cash.</p>
   <p>Blanche Cohen bought the property at the southwest corner of Winchester Avenue and Argyle Street from Lena Nathan for $18,500 in cash.</p>
   <p>Aaron Levy bought the property at 4940 North Lincoln Street from Joseph Kammer for $22,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0374.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Sophia Levinson bought the property at 2629 Glenwood Avenue from Isidore Marcus for $42,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Arner bought the property at 4910-20 North Kedzie Avenue for $100,000.</p>
   <p>Lina Nathan bought the property at 3908 Lawrence Avenue from Blanche Cohen for $25,000.</p>
   <p>Samuel Siegel bought the eighty-eight feet on Albany Avenue at Argyle Street from Abe Sacks for $15,500.</p>
   <p>Abraham Matlevitz bought the property on the northeast corner of Drake Avenue and Ainslie Street for about $29,000.</p>
   <p>Morris Cohen bought the property at 4918 North St. Louis Avenue from Sam Meyrowitz for $49,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0375.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Jacob Liebman sold the property at 4941 North St. Louis Avenue for about $74,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
