<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1928-02-23">Feb. 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Young Judaea Column</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Fanny Slobod. Mid-West Conference Special.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1928-02-23">Feb. 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG JUDAEA COLUMN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Fanny Slobod. MID-WEST CONFERENCE SPECIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saturday and Sunday, February 18th and 19th, were momentous days in the annals of Chicago Young Judea, for it was on those two days that Chicago was host to out-of-town Young Judaeans who arrived to attend the Mid-West Conference. The guests began to arrive Friday afternoon and those who had made no housing arrangements were taken to the homes of leaders for their stay in the city. Representatives from six states were present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1569.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>THE GREETINGS.</p>
   <p>Saturday saw the visitors exploring our fair city and the evening saw them gathered at the Stevens Hotel where they were officially welcomed. Mr. Sigmund W. David, chairman of the Advisory Board, extended greetings in the name of that body; Mr. S. J. Borowsky, on behalf of National Young Judaea, and Mr. Chayes on behalf of the Zionist organization.</p>
   <p>THE DANCE.</p>
   <p>Following the greetings the guests were escorted to the South Ball Room where they participated in the Re-Union Dance. Many Young Judaeans who had not been present at Young Judaea functions for a long time were in <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1570.jpg" n="3"/>attendance and many were the greetings exchanged between friends who had not seen one another for two or three years. The orchestra which consisted of blind men, played remarkably well and all the dancers enjoyed themselves.</p>
   <p>SUNDAY'S SESSION.</p>
   <p>Sunday morning saw the visitors and Chicago leaders and workers at the Jewish People's Institute where the most important part of the Conference was to take place. Mr. Borowsky opened the session and told the group the status of the Leader's Manual, which he said would soon be printed, in two or three sections. He also urged leaders to see that all clubs were registered and that leaders themselves should register as this would <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1571.jpg" n="4"/>entitle them to special consideration when it came to distributing material. A songster is to be published by Young Judaea and distributed to registered leaders.</p>
   <p>National Young Judaea is to hold another Oratorical Contest. Mr. Borowsky also outlined the financial situation. Money is needed for carrying on the Oratorical Contest and for the Young Judaean Magazine.</p>
   <p>YOUNG JUDAEA'S POLICY.</p>
   <p>There followed a great deal of discussion regarding Young Judaea's policy and the attitude of the Zionists towards Young Judaea.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1572.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. Cohen of Indianapolis was of the opinion that Young Judaea should be an educational agency only and should not try to concern itself with financial matters. Mr. Whitebook of Iowa City, stated that it was deplorable that the Zionists had repudiated Young Judaeans so far as finance was concerned, in view of the fact that Young Judaea was aiding the Zionists. Mr. Borowsky replied by stating that the rank and file of the Zionists would not stand behind the present administration on its present attitude toward Young Judaea.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Eugene Cohen of Youngstown, Ohio, stated that Young Judaea was now old enough to have developed some definite stand in regard to its relation to the Zionist organization and that the question was one not only regarding Young Judaea but concerned other cultural agencies, such as Avukah, as well.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1573.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The question of clubs raising money for Young Judaea was brought up and Mr. Borowsky stated that under no circumstances would he recommend that clubs raise money for the organization, but that leaders running affairs should consider the National Office when it came to the point of distributing the proceeds. Rabbi Cohen again took the floor and stated that one of the fundamental issues facing Young Judaea was its relation and attitude towards the Zionist organization, that Young Judaea could not depend upon the word of the Zionists as several times they had promised subsidies and had withdrawn them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1574.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>MAX SHULMAN.</p>
   <p>Mr. Shulman came in and greeted the audience. Mr. Borowsky introduced him as one of Young Judaea's best friends. Mr. Shulman stated that the present Zionist attitude towards Young Judaea was merely temporary, that it was forced upon them by the financial crisis in Palestine and that at the earliest possible moment the Zionists would again support Young Judaea and in the meantime the Chicago Zionists would certainly cooperate in every possible way.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1575.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>MUSIC, ARTS, AND CRAFTS.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry Coopersmith gave the audience an opportunity to relax when he illustrated the use of song in Young Judaea clubs and the booklets which he passed out were appreciated by the visitors. Mr. Todros Geller spoke on the use of arts and crafts in the Young Judaea Club. He stated that the Jewish attitude towards art had changed and that clubs should be urged to cultivate art. A buffet supper was served and many songs were sung. Then followed what proved to be one of the high spots of the entire conference, the symposium on "Young Judaea and its Relationship to Jewish Education in the Community and the Jewish Community Center", in which all participated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
