<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-15">May 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Gangster Terror</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0112</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0112.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-15">May 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">GANGSTER TERROR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The murder last week of two policemen in Chicago was the climax in a long series of crimes committed by that special type of gangster known as the bomb-thrower, whose business it is to terrorize the public. The blood, which has been shed, has aroused the law-abiding, peace-loving citizens of the city, irrespective of class, and from all sides one hears the cry that an end must be made, once and for all, to this gangster terror, and that those guilty of that terror should be punished to the fullest extent of the law.</p>
   <p>Organized labor in Chicago is more [vitally] interested than anybody else in the destruction of the gangster terror because certain people who are connected with the labor movement are accused of having had a hand in this <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0113.jpg" n="2"/>crime. This fact gives the enemies of the working class a chance to hold the entire labor movement responsible for that crime. Of course, this is a shameful libel. Even if we assumed that those accused are really guilty, we still would have no right to hold an entire class responsible for the crimes committed by individuals who found their way into its ranks. The great majority of the workers of Chicago condemn the crime and the criminals no less than do all other law-abiding citizens, and applaud the energetic work of the police, the States Attorney's office, and the courts to bring the criminals to justice.</p>
   <p>Condemnation alone by the workers is not sufficient. In their own interests, the organized workers must guard against having in their ranks, and particularly in the ranks of their leaders, anyone who might be suspected of terrorism, or gangsterism. We are not sure whether those indicted in the double murder are guilty or not, but we are certain that persons who have long police records of crime and violence must not be officials and leaders of labor unions. Such people do the greatest harm to unions in general and <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0114.jpg" n="3"/>to the labor movement in particular. No decent society, least of all a labor organization, can afford to have within the ranks of its members, men with a criminal past. It is the duty of all unions to get rid of such persons as soon as they are found out. It is the duty of all unions to demand the same procedure from their sister unions because the interests of all the unions are similar.</p>
   <p>We hope that this brutal crime, irrespective of the guilt or innocence of those who are suspected in that double murder, will cause the rank and file of organized labor to clear their organization of those suspicious elements who have somehow managed to crawl into the union.</p>
   <p>The organized workers are as interested as all other citizens of the city in making an end to the orgy of gangsters who work for nobody's interests but their own. The organized workers should be even more interested than anybody else because the presence of gangsters among them gives to the enemies <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0115.jpg" n="4"/>of labor a weapon with which to fight labor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
