<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-09-07">Sept. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-09-07">Sept. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From New York comes the announcement that all the departments of the Zionist Organization are busy preparing for the convention in Chicago. The various offices there are feverishly engaged in the preparation of all the reports, including the completion of the financial reports. Then the offices will be moved to the Congress Hotel in Chicago, where the headquarters of the convention are located and where several sessions of the convention will also be held. The main sessions of the convention and the great mass meeting, as has been previously announced, will take place at the Auditorium Theater.</p>
   <p>The Chicago committee, which is supervising the arrangements of the convention, is naturally very busy. There isn't a street in Chicago that doesn't have large blue posters, announcing that the convention of the Zionist <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1752.jpg" n="2"/>Organization will take place here. The English newspapers of Chicago are paying a great deal of attention to the convention. The Courier is planning to print further explanations of the present condition of Zionism, as well as pictures and reports of the convention and its accomplishments.</p>
   <p>The convention opens officially on Sunday, September 14, but the large majority of delegates from out-of-town will be here on Thursday or Friday. Registrations will begin on Friday and a number of caucuses will be held. The Zionist ball, which will take place at the First Regiment Armory, on Saturday evening, September 14, in honor of the delegates and guests to the convention, will be distinguished by its specifically national character. The request for tickets is so large that the list is as good as closed. It has been suggested that women who wish to attend the ball, should wear white and blue gowns.</p>
   <p>A number of reservations have already been made in various hotels by delegates from a number of towns and villages in the West. Many are preparing to come <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1753.jpg" n="3"/>here with their whole families. Everyone wants to be present at the great, historic convention in Chicago. Most of them want to see Justice Louis D. Brandeis personally and to hear what he has to say about conditions in Palestine.</p>
   <p>According to an announcement by the Chicago office of the Zionist organization, there are, among the fourteen hundred delegates already registered, sixty-seven rabbis and one hundred and fifteen women. The rabbis are among the most prominent in Jewish Orthodoxy, and the women are among the most sincere Zionists.</p>
   <p>In short, it will be one of the largest, if not the largest, Jewish gathering ever held in America, and it will be indeed a privilege to attend at least one of the sessions, especially the one which will be addressed by Justice Brandeis.</p>
   <p>Chicago Jewry, have you managed to provide yourself with Zionist flags with <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1754.jpg" n="4"/>which to decorate your office, store, and home in honor of the convention?</p>
   <p>We are having a great celebration today on the West Side: the dedication of the Douglas Park Jewish Day Nursery, 1300 Independence Boulevard. The celebration of the opening of the institution will begin with a mass meeting at the Herzl School, Douglas Boulevard and Hamlin Avenue, at 1 P. M. There, several prominent Jews will deliver brief addresses. A line of march, made up of men, women, and children, carrying Jewish and American flags, will then be formed, and, led by the Band of the Marks Nathan Orphan Home, will proceed on Douglas Boulevard, Kedzie Avenue, 12th Street, and then to Independence Boulevard where the institution is located.</p>
   <p>We should like to see a large crowd in the line of march, first because it will give courage to the handful of noble women who have dedicated themselves to the task of establishing such an institution, and second, because, after <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1755.jpg" n="5"/>all, the crowd will not come empty-handed and everyone will contribute as much as he can for the maintenance of the institution.</p>
   <p>The Douglas Park Jewish Day Nursery is an institution which has been established for underprivileged children who have no home. The widowed mother, or the father who is a widower, and is compelled to work for a living, will be able to leave his children there under proper care. There are cases where the mother is compelled to work to support not only herself but also a sick husband--and thus she will be able to leave her children in the institution for the day.</p>
   <p>You can hardly estimate the value of a contribution for the upkeep of such an institution; it is an act of charity, a privilege, and a human duty as well. Without such an institution, the children are exposed either to [physical] danger or to moral degeneration.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, hope to see a large crowd at the dedication of the Douglas Park <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1756.jpg" n="6"/>Jewish Day Nursery. Those who for various reasons cannot attend, can show their sympathy to the widows and the orphans, by sending in their contributions through the mail. Buy a money order or make out a check and mail it to 1300 Independence Boulevard. We are appealing to you for support; especially do we appeal to the women because their understanding is deeper, and their sympathy broader. They know that when a mother is compelled to work for a living, she will at least be free from worry, when she knows that her children are properly fed and are protected from danger. Jewish women, make your own contributions.</p>
   <p>The Jewish citizens of Chicago and citizens from the entire state of Illinois are urgently requested to bear in mind the great duty which they must perform; a duty which concerns them personally as well as the state in which they live. At the next election we are to elect delegates to the Constitutional Convention, which will open January 6, 1920, in Springfield.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1757.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Should we fail to assist in electing suitable delegates, we will pay dearly for it in the future. Indifference to the Constitutional Convention will have only one result: small groups of extremists, impractical theorists, and selfish minority groups will control the membership of the Convention with the result that the great mass of citizens will refuse to ratify the convention's resolutions in the general election of 1920, and Illinois will remain in the same situation as she is at present.</p>
   <p>The primaries are next Wednesday, September 10. At that time, you will have to help nominate the proper candidates to be delegates to the Convention, and on November 4, you will have to help them get elected. Will you do it for the benefit of your own as well as future generations, and for the benefit of the State?</p>
   <p>The Constitutional Convention must deicde the following questions: tax-system reform, the short-ballot project, direct legislation (initiative and referendum), <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1758.jpg" n="8"/>and the question of recall--that is, the recall of incompetent officials by a vote of the citizens, and the question of "home rule" for Chicago. In short, an effort is being made to abolish the old state constitution and to replace it with a new one.</p>
   <p>There are Hebrew classes at the Marshall and Medill High Schools. This is the second year of their existence and they are very successful. Jewish boys and girls who did not know Hebrew at all, are receiving instruction there and are fascinated by the knowledge of Hebrew they have acquired. The classes are conducted by competent Hebrew teachers and are an "inheritance" from Mr. Harry A. Lipsky, who established them while he was member of the Chicago Board of Education.</p>
   <p>The teaching of Hebrew in the high schools is not and cannot be a compulsory subject because it is nothing more than a voluntary act on the part of the organization which has the supervision of the education of our children in <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1759.jpg" n="9"/>Chicago. The above-mentioned classes are not as well attended as they should be.</p>
   <p>Although the schools have been open for a week, it is still not too late for Jewish parents to encourage their children to register in the high schools and also to study the Hebrew language there.</p>
   <p>Hebrew is the national language of the Jews, and we must insist that our children study it in order to prevent their estrangement from the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>In comparing the number of members of the Jewish National Alliance to that of the Workmen's Circle of Chicago, the writer stated that the latter organization numbers 4,400 members. The truth is that it has 5,077 members and we are glad to correct our error. The Workmen's Circle in Chicago has 4,677 more members than the Jewish National Alliance has.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1760.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>The reason for this is not that the Workmen's Circle has a better insurance system and offers greater inducements, nor that the Jewish workers here are far from being nationalistically inclined, but simply that it carries on a vigorous membership drive. This activity is conducted by volunteers, headed by a secretary who also volunteers his services.</p>
   <p>The Jewish National Alliance of Chicago does not attract new members; in fact, it repels the old ones. The person who stands at the helm of this local organization receives a yearly salary of two thousand dollars in addition to three thousand dollars a year for expenses.</p>
   <p>The general management of the Jewish National Alliance should become a bit more interested in its Chicago organization, where many members could be enrolled. It is a crime that the hard-earned money of honest members throughout the country should be wasted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
