<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-10-22">Oct. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Patience of American Jews</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-10-22">Oct. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE PATIENCE OF AMERICAN JEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fanaticism was never a Jewish trait. No matter how fanatical the earlier Jewish generations were, they were not as fanatical as the non-Jews. We have always listened calmly to the grumble of an opponent, and only in rare instances did we resort to rigorous methods against an adversary who was proven to be an enemy of our people. In instances where we had to resort to excommunication, it was mostly where the persons were considered to be a peril to Judaism. Also, the excommunicating was practiced mostly by Spanish Jews, who came from a country of fanaticism and inquisition. It is a question, whether the Ashkenazim (Jews of northern Asia Minor and Germany) would have excommunicated Spinoza.</p>
   <p>The Jews, as a people, are far from being fanatical. A Jew can tolerate the biggest heresy, listen to persons of revulutionary tendencies, and not cause any scandals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1236.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Upon this Jewish merit of tolerance, the Jewish reformers in America now base their policy. A gang of so-called Reform Rabbis have, in the last few months, engaged in public accusations against the American Zionists, that they are not loyal to America, that they are hyphenated, and as such are not entitled to American citizenship and American freedom.</p>
   <p>The leader of this gang, David Phillipson of Cincinnati, is not ashamed to declare in the American Israelite, that the best proof that American Zionists are not loyal to America is, that the Zionist Convention at Pittsburgh adopted a resolution of loyalty to America. With genuine Jesuitic versedness, this fine Rabbi claims, that the resolution proves clearly that the American Zionists are not loyal to America, for, if they were loyal, they wouldn't have adopted any loyalty resolution.</p>
   <p>Since the war broke out, all American organizations have adopted loyalty resolutions at their annual conventions. The paramount business of every convention for the last year and a half was to express its loyalty to America. The <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1237.jpg" n="3"/>Zionist Convention did only what other conventions found it advisable, patriotic, and proper to do. If they had not adopted a loyalty resolution, then the American public would have asked: why are the Zionists making an exception? Now Rabbi Phillipson is attempting to strangle us with this loyalty resolution.</p>
   <p>In time of peace we would have disregarded this policy of a Reform-Rabbi. But now, in time of war, all tempers are impatient, the atmosphere is filled with powder, and one spark can cause a terrible catastrophe. The Jewish people have too many enemies as it is, and if the enemies of Israel should heed the assertions of Phillipson and use them for anti-Semitic propaganda, then a catastrophe, of which even a Phillipson did not dream, can happen.</p>
   <p>For many months, millions of American Jews have been hearing how a gang of Reform Rabbis betray them, condemn them, bait then, and still they keep quiet.</p>
   <p>Is it patience or negligence? If this is patience and tolerance, then we are more patient than sheep; if it is negligence, it is criminal. Have we the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1238.jpg" n="4"/>right to sit quietly while a few troublesome Israelites try to poison the American people and American Government against us? The American Christian knows no difference between Rabbi Phillipson and a genuine Jewish Rabbi. He thinks that Rabbi Phillipson is a representative of American Jewry, and of the Jewish religion. Naturally, when he hears this representative and leader of American Jewry condeming hundreds of thousands of American Jews of not being loyal to America, he must have a suspicion that all American Jews are alike.</p>
   <p>Can we stand quietly while someone sets fire to our house? Or is it our duty to put the fire out?</p>
   <p>We are not alarmists--but in this case, we think, it would be criminal negligence on our part to let a gang of reformers do as they please, and not protest against their actions, because silence is badly interpreted by the public.</p>
   <p>What can we do to close the mouths of these reformers and in addition not give them the publicity they so desire?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1239.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We don't have to give advice to the leaders of the American Zionists on how to close the mouths of the reformers, but we do say that our patience is at an end; we must once and for all exterminate and destroy the Black Hundred of Cincinnati, which has also a branch in Chicago. We are convinced that it could be done. At this time, a well-needed piece of work could be accomplished--to tear down the false mask of Reform Judaism, a plague that ravenously eats our national body. If the leaders of American Zionism possess enough courage, they can now get rid entirely of the inner Jewish foe--they have now the opportunity to complete the work....</p>
   <p>We can only advise them to take advantage of this opportunity. Reform Judaism has now appeared in its true color--in its entire horribleness. Now we can deliver a death blow to this horrible creature, never to revive. A protest against the individual reformer will not help at all. We must point out that there is a system to this reforming, and that system is called Reform Judaism, the meanest fraud of this century.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1240.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Will we lose patience with the reformers who are working frantically to bring misfortune upon Jews? Will we have the courage to relate the whole truth?</p>
   <p>What do the Zionist leaders in Chicago say?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
