<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-31">Mar. 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate News</title><title level="a" type="sub">West Side and Northwest Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-31">Mar. 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE NEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">West Side and Northwest Side</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sol Graf bought the commercial and apartment building on the southwest corner of Madison Street and Waller Avenue for $91,500.</p>
   <p>Walter Levine bought the property on the southwest corner of Long Avenue and Washington Boulevard for $36,500. The buyer plans to erect a thirty-six-apartment building on the site.</p>
   <p>Joseph Levin and Rudman bought the eighteen-apartment building on the southeast corner of Jackson Boulevard and Springfield Avenue from A. Rotberg and J. Stein for $124,500.</p>
   <p>Joseph Blanus bought the twenty-six-apartment building on the northeast <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0268.jpg" n="2"/>corner of Washington Boulevard and Ridgeway Avenue from Kaplan, Ross, and Zaretzky for $170,000.</p>
   <p>William Sorkin bought the commercial and twenty-room hotel building at 758 Milwaukee Avenue for $20,000.</p>
   <p>Isidor Shlesinger sold the property on the southwest corner of Ashland Avenue and Augusta Boulevard for $35,000.</p>
   <p>Jenier Rosenblum bought the property on California Avenue, near Fillmore Avenue, 25 by 125 feet, for $18,000.</p>
   <p>David Fox bought the property on the southeast corner of California and Potomac Avenues for $11,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0269.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>David Gutgeld bought the property on the northeast corner of Central Park Avenue and Twelfth Place from Jennie Cohen for $42,500.</p>
   <p>Max Birenbaum and others bought the property on Clifton Park Avenue, near 18th Street, for $12,800.</p>
   <p>Morris Lika bought the property on the southeast corner of Division Street and Hoyne Avenue from Ida Hoffman for $38,000.</p>
   <p>J. Rosen sold the property on the southeast corner of Elston and California Avenues for $97,500.</p>
   <p>Max Agranowsky bought the property on Evergreen Avenue, near Winchester Avenue, for approximately $18,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0270.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Israel Rosenstein bought the property on Fillmore Avenue, near Springfield Avenue, 25 by 124 feet, from Jacob Boloton for $16,000.</p>
   <p>Hyman Walensky bought the property on Kedzie Avenue, near 15th Street, 38 by 111 feet, for $29,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Digelhaupt bought the property on Ogden Avenue, near Turner Avenue, from Pincus Singer for $14,500.</p>
   <p>Morris Fogelson bought the property on the northeast corner of Taylor Street and Hermitage Avenue from Max Grossman for $35,000.</p>
   <p>Hyman Lipman bought the property on the southeast corner of Taylor and Throop Streets for $22,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0271.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Paul Friedman bought the property on Troy Street, near Roosevelt Road, 25 by 125 feet, for $13,500.</p>
   <p>The Daily Worker Publishing Company bought the property on Washington Boulevard, near May Street, from Leo Goldblatt for $33,500.</p>
   <p>Isidor Shalwitz bought the property on the southwest corner of Washington Boulevard and California Avenue for $57,000.</p>
   <p>Anna Friedman bought the property on the northwest corner of Wilcox Street and Karlov Avenue from Simon Smolensky for $21,500.</p>
   <p>Albany Park and North Side</p>
   <p>Harry Metal bought the property on the southeast corner of Leland and <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0272.jpg" n="6"/>Campbell Avenues from Bessie Hillman for $95,000.</p>
   <p>Dorothy Braude bought the twelve-apartment building on the southwest corner of Ashland and North Shore Avenues for $85,000.</p>
   <p>Harry Altzman bought the twelve-apartment building on the northeast corner of Wilson and Spaulding Avenues from M. D. Cohen for $62,000.</p>
   <p>Joseph Rubin bought the new commercial building on the northwest corner of Montrose and Central Park Avenues from H. Brumfeld for $135,000.</p>
   <p>J. Zaran bought the fifteen-apartment building at 6457 Kenwood Avenue from I. Weiss for $115,000.</p>
   <p>Isidor Diemer and A. Schwartz bought the eighteen-apartment building at <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0273.jpg" n="7"/>1615-23 Wallen Avenue from A. L. Weiss for $84,000.</p>
   <p>Louis Kanter bought the sixty-apartment building at 4116 Sheridan Road for $335,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Epstein bought the commercial and seventeen-apartment building on the northwest corner of Lawrence and Winchester Avenues from Abe Loeb for $128,000.</p>
   <p>Abraham Cohen bought the six-apartment building at 6331 Wayne Avenue for $50,500.</p>
   <p>Ben Harris bought the property on Central Park Avenue, near Sunnyside Avenue, from Saul Hymowich for $11,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0274.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Clara Greenberg bought the property on the northwest corner of Lawrence and Hamlin Avenues from Seder Grossman for approximately $66,000.</p>
   <p>David Dolnick sold the property on the northeast corner of Lawrence and Crawford Avenues for $45,000.</p>
   <p>Isidor Klein sold the property on the southwest corner of Winnemac Avenue and Rockwell Street for $12,000.</p>
   <p>Samuel Katz sold the property on the northeast corner of Halsted and Melrose Streets for approximately $62,000.</p>
   <p>David Rabnick bought the property on the northeast corner of Pine Grove and Brompton Avenues from H. Tumansky for $660,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0275.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>In Other Neighborhoods</p>
   <p>Bernstein Cohen and Company bought the one-story commercial building at 129 South Market Street for $65,750.</p>
   <p>Morris Zevin and Sam Rosenthal bought the apartment building at Cicero and Gladys Avenues from Nathan Plier, builder, for $210,000.</p>
   <p>James Biederman bought the property on Forest Avenue and South Boulevard, Evanston, for $100,000; he was acting in behalf of a syndicate consisting of D. S. Klafter, Isaac Miller, and others, who plans to erect on the site a ninety-eight-apartment building to cost $1,500,000.</p>
   <p>Harry B. Friedman bought the commercial and eighteen-apartment building on <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0276.jpg" n="10"/>the northeast corner of Grand Boulevard and 48th Street from Louis Sorkin for $160,000.</p>
   <p>Morris Rosenthal, Jacob Rosenthal, and B. Hirsh bought the eighteen-apartment building at 5316 Cornell Avenue for $115,000.</p>
   <p>M. Telchinsky bought the property on the northeast corner of Hyde Park Boulevard and Ellis Avenue for $33,000. The buyer plans to erect an apartment building on the site.</p>
   <p>S. J. Rosenblatt and Z. D. Klaper bought the commercial building on the southeast corner of 61st Street and South Park Avenue for approximately $89,000.</p>
   <p>Sophie Cohen bought the twenty-four-apartment building at 5417 Ingleside Avenue from Isidor Sabath for $135,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
