<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929">1929</date>.
<title level="a">Civics and Citizenship.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0438</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0438.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929">1929</date>.
<title level="a">CIVICS AND CITIZENSHIP.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The work of this department extends over many years. Already in 1913 and 1914 the department was in charge of a competent paid attorney. All persons seeking information, whether technical or general, were able to apply and receive the information they solicited. The Bureau also dealt with individual cases, giving each applicant the necessary information and advice that would enable him to qualify for citizenship. It supplied him with the necessary papers and blanks, aided him in filling out the same and assisted him in his preparation for passing the examination for final naturalization papers. It conducted also a series of lectures which presented to those desiring citizenship the following phases of Americanization: (1) The necessity of citizenship; (2) the advantages and privileges which citizenship entail; (3) the duties and obligations of a citizen to his country; (4) a course in Civil Government, outlining of Federal, state and municipal governments, including a review of the history of our country until the adoption of the Constitution and a brief <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0439.jpg" n="2"/>study as well of the geographical divisions of the United States; (5) the study of political parties; (6) the study of English as the language medium of the country.</p>
   <p>The department even at that time included special classes for women, a neighborhood city bureau, whose main purpose was to give particular attention to the needs from the standpoint of public health and efficiency. During the year 1914 to 1917, over 2,000 individuals came to the Bureau either to sign the Declaration of Intention or to prepare for the getting of their final citizenship papers. In this connection, the Institute organized The New Citizens' League. The League aimed at promulgating the ideals of good citizenship and its program can best be gleaned perhaps from the Preamble of its Constitution, adopted in 1917, which read as follows: We, the Jewish Citizens of the City of Chicago, realizing the importance of promulgating the ideals of good citizenship, of actively encouraging the unnaturalized among us to become citizens of this country, and <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0440.jpg" n="3"/>the promoting of Civic Education and participation among those already naturalized, organize herewith an association which shall hereafter be known as The New Citizens' League.</p>
   <p>I remember very distinctly in 1917, when at the end of the first year's existence of this League, all of the new citizens were entertained at a banquet and as many as 400 of them were present in the Gymnasium Building. On this occasion there were excellent addresses made by outstanding persons in the community, urging the continuation of this splendid work. This banquet was not a complimentary one given to the citizens by the Institute or by an individual; it was a banquet which was arranged by the new citizens themselves and for which banquet they paid out of their own pockets. The object of a Citizenship Bureau of the kind that we conduct is to maintain a high standard of citizenship and to that end intelligent service must be offered, but as far as coercing or encouraging entirely too much on the basis of "Me thinks thou protesteth too much," that must be avoided. We have been successful - indeed very successful - because of <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0441.jpg" n="4"/>the fact that we have not pushed citizenship. We encouraged it. We used no high pressure methods. We taught it in an indirect method and it is due very largely, if not entirely, to this method that we have succeeded in the manner we did.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
