<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-10-03">October 3, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.7"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-10-03">October 3, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Naturalization Aid League, the organization which was founded with the object of naturalizing our masses, has systemized and enlarged its work. It opened branches on the West Side, on the North West Side and in Douglas Park District, in order to inform those desiring to become citizens, without any difficulties.</p>
   <p>A manager was also appointed, who will devote himself to this important work and see that the work should be carried through accurately. Sophie Rodiriguse, a former school teacher and noted lecturer, who contributed much to naturalization work, was appointed manager. The offices of the League are open Monday evening - in the Northwest Side Socialist Institute, Tolman and Lemoine; Tuesday evening in the Douglas District Workmen's Circle school, 1224 S. Albany Ave.; and Saturday evening on the West Side, in the office of the United Hebrew Trades, 1126 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>Organizations, Unions, Workmen's Circle branches, societies, all those who organized the league - the league is in need of money! Not one cent is taken for all information given out by the league. The league is financed by contributions from Jewish organizations. If your organization decided <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0554.jpg" n="2"/>to contribute to the league, see that the money is submitted. If your organization did not as yet decide to donate anything, see that it should immediately be done.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
