<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1928-01-08">January 8, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Junior Hadassah</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0932</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0932.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1928-01-08">January 8, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO JUNIOR HADASSAH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>December 10, nationally known as Hadassah Sabbath, officially opened Hadassah's membership campaign. On that day Rabbis all over the country described to their congregations the service that Hadassah, senior and junior, is rendering in Palestine along medical, sanitary and educational lines. As the work of Hadassah is becoming better known more and more girls are joining the ranks.</p>
   <p>Junior Hadassah, the young women's Zionist organization, has an unusually strong appeal to all young ladies. Junior Hadassah's specific work being the caring for young children, through the maintenance of Meier Shfeye, the children's village in Palestine.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0933.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Annette Jacoby, Chicago membership chairman, is assured that Chicago juniors, who now number over one thousand strong, will go over the top in this drive as they have done in all Hadassah undertakings. Another interesting feature of junior work is redemption of land of Palestine, known as the National Fund. Through the National Fund the land is lawfully bought back into everlasting possession of the Jewish people. National Fund boxes are distributed and each junior assumes the responsibility of collections of all boxes distributed through her efforts.</p>
   <p>In connection with the National Fund work and the membership drive a meeting of all Chicago juniors will be held, Sunday afternoon, January 29, at the Congress Hotel. Irma R. Baron, Chicago junior National Fund Chairman, is planning a most interesting National Fund stunt and along with the rest of the program planned a pleasant afternoon in assured.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
