<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-20">Aug. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Celebrate Ratification of Palestine Mandate]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-20">Aug. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[CELEBRATE RATIFICATION OF PALESTINE MANDATE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tonight is a great holiday in Chicago. The Jews of Chicago gather tonight not to lament, not to weep, not to protest against pogroms, not to demand money for relief, but to rejoice. This is the first time, in my memory, that the Jews of Chicago and the Jews in other cities have gathered to celebrate and not to lament something, to express their gratitude to a government instead of protesting against a government.</p>
   <p>The Jews of Chicago will celebrate tonight the ratification of the Palestine mandate, which makes it possible for us to begin building Palestine on a large scale, and which removes from our path all obstacles, so far as Palestine redemption work is concerned.</p>
   <p>Since the mandate was ratified, Palestine has ceased to be a dream of the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1070.jpg" n="2"/>Jews and has become something real, something tangible. This great historic event will be celebrated tonight by all the Chicago Jews who are realistic and who understand the greatness of this moment.</p>
   <p>Men who have done a great deal to ensure the ratification of the mandate, will speak at the meeting: Senator McCormick, who helped pass the Zionist resolution in the American Senate, Congressman [A. J.] Sabath, who aided the passage of the Zionist resolution in the House of Representatives, the English consul in Chicago, and the well-known Zionist orator, Rabbi Hillel Silver of Cleveland.</p>
   <p>Were all the Jews of Chicago real Jews, healthy-minded Jews, then not one but twenty such meetings would have been crowded and this great event in the life of our people would have been celebrated in a way which would have resounded in all parts of the city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1071.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, Chicago Jews are divided into various classes. First, there are Jews who have a healthy Jewish mind and a healthy Jewish heart; second, there are "little" Jews who are busy during the day with real estate or junk deals, and at night, with poker or pinochle; third, there are indifferent Jews whose motto in life is: "Eat, drink, and be merry, for tomorrow we die".</p>
   <p>I do not expect the last two classes to participate in Jewish joy or in Jewish sorrow. Those Jews do not lack anything; they have money, they are having a good time, and they do not demand anything else from life.</p>
   <p>I do expect, however, the first class of Jews, the real, the sincere Jews of Chicago to join in the celebration of the great Jewish holiday in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Tonight's meeting in the gymnasium of the Hebrew Institute should be a historic demonstration of the Jews of Chicago in honor of the rebuilding <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1072.jpg" n="4"/>of Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
