<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-26">Feb. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Symbol of Time</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-26">Feb. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A SYMBOL OF TIME</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A young woman who killed her husband has been recently acquitted by a jury in a New York Court. In no more than ten minutes, the jury unanimously agreed that the young mother should go free, although she confessed the shooting of her husband with his own revolver.</p>
   <p>This was due to recent sentiment prevailing among those who think that crime should not be treated as a common occurrence, that above everything the motives which led to the crime should be thoroughly investigated.</p>
   <p>The jury listened to the motives which were responsible for this act of the 16-year-old mother, who had borne a child of her husband a year after <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0204.jpg" n="2"/>their marriage. He, the husband and father of the child, drove her out into the streets to earn money licentiously, and when she, as a devoted mother and respectable woman, refused, he beat her brutally and then left her in great misery and want.</p>
   <p>How horrible is the fact that life compels young girls to marry such men, who are the refuse of society, because they want to free themselves from hard work where dreadful conditions exist. And the result is that in married life they have it still worse, having to face conditions that are far more dreadful.</p>
   <p>Everybody can readily realize how aggravated the young mother's grief was, while holding her child with one hand, she fired the shot at her brutal husband with the other hand.</p>
   <p>But still a light ray penetrates this darkness, which is, namely, the jury's <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0205.jpg" n="3"/>decision. The jury understood that not a criminal took the witness stand, but one of the thousands of victims of present day conditions. The young woman remains at any rate punished. Can anyone picture anything worse than a mother shooting the father of her own child?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
