<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-17">Aug. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Bloomson Flees from Chicago with Two Handbags of Money</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-17">Aug. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">BLOOMSON FLEES FROM CHICAGO WITH TWO HANDBAGS OF MONEY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On August 8, the Courier printed a notice regarding the disappearance of the well-known Jewish merchant of the Northwest Side, H. J. Bloomson; it appeared that his creditors had brought a petition for his bankruptcy. Last Friday, that is a week after this news was printed in the Courier, the English newspapers appeared with sensational headlines about a "Jewish peddler who had swindled Chicago banks". The Courier, as always in the case of Jewish news, "scooped" all the English newspapers in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The story goes that Bloomson owes about four hundred thousand dollars in Chicago. A large part of this is due the Corn Exchange Bank and Greenebaum and Sons Bank, from which he received loans on falsified bills of lading. But Bloomson's creditors are certain of the return of the greatest part of the money that is owed to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0125.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. A. Whipple, the receiver appointed by the court, explained yesterday that Bloomson's fortune in Chicago is valued at $245,000, at least. The factory and merchandise of Bloomson's Milling Company alone is worth $135,000. The value of his real estate is set at $75,000.</p>
   <p>Samuel Leavitt, Bloomson's former partner, testified to the fact that the Milling Company's profits for last year were $100,000. The unknown reasons that forced Bloomson from the straight and narrow path while he was succeeding so brilliantly in business, are fast becoming a great mystery.</p>
   <p>It is believed that Bloomson fled to South Africa. He came from there about four years ago. He has a wife and five children there. It is known that shortly before he fled, Bloomson applied to the State Department for a passport to Pretoria, South Africa, but his application was rejected.</p>
   <p>Notices to detain Bloomson were sent to all American and Canadian ports for it <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0126.jpg" n="3"/>is believed that he has not yet succeeded in sailing to Africa.</p>
   <p>It is definitely known that Bloomson left Chicago for Detroit. A Pullman porter named Orlando Grey stated with certainty that Bloomson had ridden in his train to that city. He further states that Bloomson had with him two black handbags, which, it is believed, contained the money he was carrying out of Chicago. The porter adds that Bloomson asked him about trains leaving for Toronto, and it is, therefore, believed that from Detroit he traveled to Canada.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
