<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1915-12">December, 1915</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0734</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0734.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1915-12">December, 1915</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Citizenship Bureau is open Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday and Saturday, from 7:30 to 9:30 P. M. and on Sunday morning from 10:00 to 12:00 o'clock. The Civics and Citizenship department is being followed up through a specific survey regarding the citizenship situation of Jews in Chicago. The city has been divided up into districts and the most thickly populated of these districts having the largest Jewish population, are being investigated first, by means of a house to house canvass made by an intelligent investigator who is experienced in making social surveys. The object of the survey is to find out who is and who is not a citizen in the district. From those who are not citizens, the following facts are ascertained. Why they have not become citizens; whether a declaration of intention has been made and the taking out of the final papers has been neglected; how long they have been in the country; their social state - their occupation - the number of children in the family.</p>
   <p>The first 1,600 cards have been completely tabulated and the tables worked out. The task was much simplified by the device used - a card index system <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0735.jpg" n="2"/>for the different tables, and as the work progresses, tabulation will be made each week. Thus it will be possible to know the results as shown by the tables, at any time, instead of waiting until the end. In this manner, group differences can be readily seen and changes in policy or plan of the survey can be made without any extra work.</p>
   <p>The following additional information of social value has been noted on cards, and which will be shown on a spot map: Other nationalities, business establishments, shops, industries and factories, civic agencies, such as fire departments, police stations, etc., educational agencies, such as public and private schools, religious agencies, recreational agencies, anti- social agencies, such as saloons, cheap amusement places, dance halls, pool rooms, etc., all designated by pins of various colors.</p>
   <p>Thus far in our questionaire we have neglected showing the relation of literacy to citizenship. From now on, this item will be included on all <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0736.jpg" n="3"/>cards and properly tabulated. The spot map that accompanies the survey, on the surface gives us impressions which, without analyzing, would convey very erroneous deductions. The general impression, as a result of our investigation, is that the Jews are more apt to take advantage of the opportunities for citizenship than other foreign born people. So far it is merely an impression. A comparative study of similar surveys made in other sections of the city of other foreign born people would be interesting, in order to affirm the general impression. At this time, the survey has not progressed sufficiently far for us to be able to make definite deduction nor to be able to interpret facts which seem strange on the surface.</p>
   <p>In order that you may have some idea of the reasons given for tardy citizenship, to our investigator, the following few typical examples are cited: A saloon-keeper, before the enforcement of the Sunday closing law, could not become naturalized, because he was violating a state law. A saloon-keeper's wife told our investigator that her husband would take out his <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0737.jpg" n="4"/>papers now that the enforcement was in effect. Another man had never taken out his papers because he had no time. He is a tailor by trade, working twelve to fifteen hours a day, and always works with other foreigners in the shops: thus he was slow in acquiring English and the real needs for citizenship. A third man, who is also typical, counted the cost - especially for the witnesses, which he seemed to consider beyond reach, although he is educating his children at public expense. One man, when questioned, said he did not know, himself, why he had never taken out papers, "Sometimes too lazy, sometimes had no money or time, and at other times had forgotten about it," he said. He expressed a desire, since his attention has been called to it, to become a citizen soon. - This type is by no means unusual. Frequently our investigator reports that a man desires citizenship for the sake of his children, although his lack of English would make the taking out of papers no easy matter. Some learn English so that they may take out papers, others who come to this country in later years have illiteracy to blame for their non-citizenship. Their children, however, thanks to our splendid system of public education, will not have <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0738.jpg" n="5"/>this excuse, and will be the future citizen of our country. Our investigator reports even humor in some of her investigations. She has often been told that a man has not taken out his papers because he is too bashful or that he is ashamed to go before the judge. Most of them hardly know what is required, imagining that a great deal more is expected than is really the case and therefore do not feel equal to the effort. There are many women, even widows with children, who own a little shop and who feel the need of citizenship and who do not know that women can take out citizenship papers. Among recent immigrants are quite a number who have no desire for citizenship. They are, as a class, ignorant of our institutions and have wrong ideas of conditions in this country. Their influence is remarkably strong. This type is by no means an exception in Chicago. In New York, Philadelphia, Boston and other large cities in this country, where there exists foreign localities, similar instances are known. Just what the solution is in changing the point of view of this type of individual, is hard to say. Their attitude often, at first, is fair and carries a logical <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0739.jpg" n="6"/>basis. Usually they are of an idealistic type coming from European countries, who dreamed of America as the real home of the free and the land of the brave. They expected, upon coming to our shores, to find a citizenship and patriotism pure, honest, dignified and irreproachable. As soon as they became acquainted, however, with the many unfortunate pitfalls in our political and civic situations, learning from their own press and experience that there are many types of lawmakers of out cities and our states and our nation, who are far from the ideal he had portrayed, - realizing, too, that there are laws on our statute books that some must obey and others need not because of so-called methods to avoid these laws and regulations, made possible through cheap type of wardheelers, they say to our investigator: "How can you expect us to respect your laws and grow up to become citizens of a country where your politics, - the very life of your nation rests in the hands of the corner saloon-keeper. Why should I take any interest in a cheap citizenship?" and so on and so on. I think we must admit that there is something not altogether wrong with the criticism of these <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0740.jpg" n="7"/>idealist aliens, who might become the fine type of our citizen were it not for the defects which he emphasizes existing around him, causing him to have a lack of interest in what many of us consider the holiest privilege of the free American, viz., the right of franchise.</p>
   <p>Some 2,000 different families, representing over 7,000 human souls, have been visited in the interest of this survey, and the tables and "spot" maps are based on actual facts gathered. The survey consists of fourteen tables - among them - The nativity and the period of residence inthe United States - Citizenship of the foreign born and nativity - Period of residence and citizenship - Citizenship and marital condition - General and civic status of the home - Attitudes of aliens toward citizenship, and reasons for failure to be naturalized, subdivided as follows: those who desired citizenship, but could not get it because they haven't been in America long enough <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0741.jpg" n="8"/>because of ignorance and neglect, or those who tried and failed, those who did not desire citizenship because of illiteracy, did not like America, general indifference, or expected to go back to Europe - Citizenship and social state of women, such as the unmarried, the widowed, and the divorced-Nativity and literacy of women - and The literacy and the citizenship of the heads of families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
