<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-10-23">October 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">United Hebrew Trades Determine to Start a Campaign against the New Constitution.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0856</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0856.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-10-23">October 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED HEBREW TRADES DETERMINE TO START A CAMPAIGN AGAINST THE NEW CONSTITUTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The thousands of Jewish organized workers of Chicago, who are citizens, are urged by the United Hebrew Trades to vote against the new proposed constitution (for Illinois), December 12. This decision, to agitate against the constitution, was accepted yesterday, at a special meeting of the executive board, by the United Hebrew Trades, after thoroughly discussing the issue. A resolution was read, which was unanimously adopted at the convention of the Illinois State Federation of Labor, urging all trades unions to conduct a campaign against the new constitution.</p>
   <p>The executive board, of the United Hebrew Trades, has decided to invite all central labor bodies to a conference, where they shall appoint three delegates, who will attend the meeting of the United Hebrew Trades, Sunday morning, November 5, in the Workmen's Circle Lyceum, to elaborate plants as how to carry on a written and oral campaign against the constitution, which deprives many privileges from citizens of Illinois and especially from Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
