<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-20">May 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Becoming Accustomed to the New Zionist Flag</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1325</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1325.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-20">May 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Becoming Accustomed to the New Zionist Flag</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If anyone doubts the present revitalization of the Jewish Flag of the Jewish People, he should see the spirit and work of our Youth in the Zionist Movement. They, the Youth of Free America, are not motivated because of persecution, but because of an inherited desire to aid their people.</p>
   <p>The beautiful Zionist Flag we had was burned in the Institute fire. But already it has been replaced by an even more beautiful flag, with much finer ornamentations.</p>
   <p>The coming Lag Ba-Omer Programs promise to be very interesting. The Junior Gates of the Knights of Zion will sing Hebrew Songs and the Boys' Gymnasium has prepared a flag. Drill speakers will be Leon Zolotkoff, Max Schulman, D. Aberson, and Rabbi Morris Levin. Admission is free, and everybody is invited.-- -- Rumanian Jewish Chicago Organization for Zion.</p>
   <p>Dr. Rosenzweig has informed us that two-hundred members will work in uniform at the Decoration-Day Parade.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1326.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Rumanian Jews of Chicago have of late been very active in organizing Gates of the Zionist Organization.</p>
   <p>Benefit for Consumptives:</p>
   <p>The Jewish Consumptive Relief Society of Chicago will have a benefit at the Colonial Theatre, 79 W. Randolph Street, Sunday Evening May 29. A very entertaining program has been arranged and all interested in this very fine organization are asked to be present.</p>
   <p>Strawberry Festival and Dance:</p>
   <p>The West Side Ladies Aid of the Old People's Home has arranged a Strawberry Festival and Dance at West End Woman's Club House, Ashland Avenue and Monfoe Streets.</p>
   <p>(Signed) "The Cook Spoon"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
