<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-31">Aug. 31, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1763</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1763.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-31">Aug. 31, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As has been previously announced, the twenty-second annual convention of the Zionist Organization of America will be held in Chicago. It will take place in the Auditorium, Wabash Avenue and Congress Street. A number of the most prominent Jews in America will participate in the convention.</p>
   <p>This is the first time that such a convention has come to Chicago. It will mark a new era in the annals of the Zionist movement because it will devote itself to the practical work of rebuilding Palestine as a Jewish homeland. The work will be directed by Justice Brandeis and Dr. Chaim Weizmann, who are largely responsible for the fact that Palestine is to become a Jewish republic. The presence of Justice Brandeis and Dr. Weizmann at the convention in Chicago is assured.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1764.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The task of the Chicago convention for the rebuilding of Palestine will rest upon the platform which the Zionists adopted at their last convention in Pittsburgh. The platform consists of the following three main principles: 1) Nationalization of the soil. 2) Co-operative system. 3) Equal rights.</p>
   <p>The nationalization of the land means that the soil of Palestine will belong, or will be under the control of the Jewish people as a whole. This is no place to discuss the means by which this is to be carried out. What is important for us to understand is that the Zionists of America have decided that the benefits derived from the rising value of the land should not fall into the pockets of land speculators, but should always remain in the public treasury. The above is only a modern interpretation of the biblical verse: The land is mine, said the Lord, and you are its inhabitants.</p>
   <p>The second principle, according to the Zionist leaders, does not mean the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1765.jpg" n="3"/>endorsement of socialism within Palestine. It proves clearly, however, that the Zionists of America are determined to encourage co-operative enterprises to the greatest extent, so as to enable its development, step by step, into a co-operative state, preserving thereby individual initiative. No established formula exists whereby a co-operative state can be attained--it must develop from tests and experiments. All we can do is to point out the ultimate aim.</p>
   <p>The third principle is one with which every American is acquainted, at least in theory, although his experience may be far from satisfactory. But then, whereas we Americans apply our program of equal rights to the narrow field of politics, we Zionists of America apply this principle to all phases of life: to politics and economics, to law and industry, to every man and woman, and to every sect and every faith.</p>
   <p>This program, which is imbued with the spirit of the Jewish prophets and American idealism, was confirmed by the conference of Zionist leaders <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1766.jpg" n="4"/>throughout the country, held two weeks ago in New York, and it is to be hoped that it will also be supported at the coming Zionist convention in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The coming Zionist convention in Chicago should interest every Jew and all our organizations should hold special sessions and adopt resolutions to help the convention to be as impressive and successful as possible. It is a great privilege to attend the convention. The local Zionist organization calls your attention to the following program:</p>
   <p>1) Decorations: The house and store of every Zionist in Chicago should be decorated, during the convention, with American and Zionist flags, which will be sold by the Decoration Committee at cost price at all district headquarters.</p>
   <p>2) Reception: A ball in the First Regiment Armory will be given on Saturday evening, September 13. This will be the biggest entertainment ever <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1767.jpg" n="5"/>seen by Chicago Jews. Get ready to attend the ball. The cost of a ticket is $1.50, including wardrobe charges.</p>
   <p>3) On the eve of the convention, a celebration will be given at the Auditorium Theater, on Wednesday, September 17. This will be the big event of the convention for all the Jews of Chicago--for everyone who will be fortunate enough to get a seat. The prices of admission are $1.50 and $2. Tickets for the ball, as well as for the celebration at the Auditorium Theater can be obtained at the convention headquarters, 1212 [South] Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>Registered Zionists! Do your duty immediately! The Zionist organization is the central authority of the Zionists, and its strength depends upon the number of its membership. See to it, you nationalistically inclined Jews, that your applications, which have been distributed by the Zionists, are filled out, and send them in to Mr. Leon Zolotkoff, director of the local Zionist bureau, 1212 [South] Ashland Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
