<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-04">July 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">This Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1381</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1381.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-04">July 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THIS DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Just 143 years ago today, the bell in Philadelphia tolled the happy news: the thirteen states had declared their independence and freedom would reign from then on; freedom, equality, and brotherhood for all the peoples in the states.</p>
   <p>A hundred and forty-three years ago, brave men risked their lives, fortunes, and possessions to fight for freedom; a freedom which is spreading now to all corners of the earth. Those heroes must have had great courage to fight against Great Britain, a rich and powerful nation. Yet they risked everything and won.</p>
   <p>This Fourth of July is especially important because for these past five years, all the nations have been engaged in a horrible war. They tried to bring freedom to the world, and they won the war. Militarism is broken and Peace will again establish itself on this earth--a Peace which we hope will no longer be shattered. Nations that for many years had suffered oppression, have gained their freedom.</p>
   <p>For all this--for the freedom we have here under the "Stars And Stripes", and for <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1382.jpg" n="2"/>the freedom our brothers have secured "Over There" across the sea, we must, this year, especially celebrate July 4. Everyone, the native born as well as the foreign settlers who have since become citizens, all must celebrate this holiday of our United States. Even those who have not yet become citizens will also celebrate Independence Day which has such a great significance to all who live here in this country.</p>
   <p>Freedom has come and is here to stay. The days of oppression have vanished, not to return again, especially to us in America. Let the flag of the Stars and Stripes fly on high as the emblem of equality, brotherhood and true freedom. Let us all participate in the celebration of July 4, the day independence was proclaimed in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
