<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-27">Aug. 27, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The  of </title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-27">Aug. 27, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> OF <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Heeding the advice of Justice Brandeis who is a great inspiration on matters pertaining to organization, the Zionist organization of the Middle West has set out to organize the Zionist societies that are under its supervision into state organizations. The beginning was made a year ago in Wisconsin where all Zionist societies have built a State League. The result of their unity has been that the number of Gates in Wisconsin has practically doubled, and the Zionist activities have grown steadily in proportion.</p>
   <p>Now it is Illinois' turn, and a conference will be held Sunday, September 17, in the Chicago Hebrew Institute of representatives of all Zionist Gates in Illinois. the purpose of the conference is to organize a Zionist State League in Illinois.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt but that such state leagues--and they are now being instituted throughout America under the influence and through the encouragement of Justice <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1277.jpg" n="2"/>Brandeis--will work well in consolidating and fortifying the organizations in each separate state. Just as soon as such a state organization is instituted, local welfare workers will arrive on the scene to carry on the work. Such was the case in Wisconsin, in Ohio and in Texas. But we are inclined to put more weight on the educational value of organization, and from this point of view the founding of Zionist State Leagues assumes greater significance.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the greatest merit of the Zionist movement can be attributed to the stress it puts on organizational work. It has practically become a great maxim of Jewish life in America, as in other countries, that wherever a Zionist society is organized, Jewish activities in other directions also increase. It is acknowledged that the Zionist movement has raised Jewish education, has brought Jewish studies more into fashion, and has increased the number of Jewish schools throughout the country. And as most teachers now come from the ranks of the Zionists, national thought and the love for the Hebrew language are being slowly implanted within the hearts of the Jewish youth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1278.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The chief objective of the Zionist movement, as we all know, is to secure a home for the Jewish people in the historic Jewish land. But whereas the movement strives to attain that goal, it is reforming, innumerable aspects of Jewish life in all countries. Above all, it [Zionist movement] organizes the Jews. The existence of a gigantic Jewish organization is, in itself, of the greatest importance to Jews. It awakens the Jew's self-consciousness, makes him prouder of his ancestry, and last but not least, teaches him to think like a Jew instead of always taking his ideologies from strangers and viewing the world through the wrong kind of spectacles.</p>
   <p>A Zionist State League, which we hope will be organized next month, will be a great stimulus in awakening Jewish lives in such communities around Chicago as Springfield, Peoria, Champaign, Aurora, etc., communities which are now practically moribund. The League will find welfare workers in these small communities and with the upswing of Zionist work there, interest in Jewish matters in general will become intensified. It will be worthwhile to watch the success of this undertaking and to see to what extent the smaller communities in Illinois will participate in the founding of the Zionist State League.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
