<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-03">Jan. 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[Inspiring Program at Zionist Celebration]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-03">Jan. 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[INSPIRING PROGRAM AT ZIONIST CELEBRATION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tuesday evening, the Zionists of Chicago celebrated with such magnificence and exultation of spirit that even people with a highly developed aesthetic sense and exacting aesthetic standards were charmed by the attractive and colorful atmosphere. A crowd of about fifteen hundred people, all of whom were dressed in their best, filled the ballroom of the La Salle Hotel. They sat so close to each other that the people who were sitting on the platform saw in front of them a sea of faces, a sea of shining eyes. A deep silence prevailed from the first words of Mr. Harry A. Lipsky, the greatest Zionist of Chicago, to the last strains of "Hatikvah". Just as the ears of those present absorbed every tone of the music, so the minds of those present absorbed every word spoken from the platform. One could see on their faces happiness, satisfaction, as well as intellectual and aesthetic pleasure.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1601.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The holiday mood which prevailed throughout the entire evening was inspired by the singing of David Hirsch's choir, which sang first "The Star-Spangled Banner," and then "The Oath". The first stanza of "The Star-Spangled Banner" inspired a mood of exultation, and the first stanza of "The Oath," one of reverence. The beautiful and powerful altos of David Hirsch's choir sang so clearly and magnificently that they immediately won the hearts of the audience. The Chicago Zionists are very grateful to Mr. David Hirsch, whom the toastmaster rightfully called "the father of Jewish music in Chicago," for his fine contribution to the great success of the evening. I can only recommend that all other such meetings begin their program with David Hirsch's choir, because as a musician he is capable of achieving great effects and of inspiring a powerful and enduring mood. The Zionists will always be good "customers" of Mr. Hirsch, who is, of course, a good Zionist, and a member in good standing.</p>
   <p>Jews are practical people and they will ask, what of it? What if fifteen <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1602.jpg" n="3"/>hundred Jews in Chicago did spend a pleasant evening? What if they did hear beautiful music, and listen to inspiring speeches? They had a good time--and that is all. But that is not all. Everyone of the fifteen hundred who witnessed the initiation ceremony in the La Salle Hotel not only spent a beautiful evening, and was inspired spiritually and artistically, he, also carried away with him a great deal of Jewish enthusiasm and many Jewish hopes. Everyone of them will go to his friends and acquaintances and will talk to them about Jewish hopes, Jewish ambitions, and Jewish activity in Palestine. He will become a bearer of glad tidings; he will become an enthusiastic supporter of our work for the Redemption. You will find out what this work is during the next Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization] drive, which will begin in a couple of months. You will see then that everyone who was present at the La Salle Hotel that evening will become a Keren Hayesod worker.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
