<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-02">September 2, 1913</date><title level="a">The Zionist Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1308</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1308.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-02">September 2, 1913</date><title level="a">THE ZIONIST CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eleventh world Zionist Congress opens today in Vienna.</p>
   <p>It is more than a meeting of party delegates, where only matters pertaining to the concerned organizations are discussed. The Zionist Congress is a collosal tribune from which the scattered people - Israel - proclaim their wants and demands.</p>
   <p>At the first Congress in Basel, the Zionist tribune proclaimed to the world, the first independent declaration of the Jewish people. Until that time the nations, among which the Jews are dispersed, never knew that the Jews considered themselves as a national unit having their own demands and needs; that the Jews have their national mission to fulfill; that the Jews seek ways and means to confirm their historical unity on their own national economic, social and political grounds. In other words, the Jews want to materialize the dream of a thousand years, to return to their land, and to establish there an independent nation.</p>
   <p>To say that prior to Zionism the Jews had given up their hopes entirely would not be true. However, the Jews only dreamt of returning to their own land. They were afraid to reveal their dream openly before the world for fear it <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1309.jpg" n="2"/>would impair their lot amid the foreign nations.</p>
   <p>The merit of the Zionists consist chiefly in that they have enough courage to declare themselves openly.</p>
   <p>When the first Congress-tribune proclaimed the proud call for freedom and when our own Jewish flag was unfolded, the Jewish elements could be seen organizing the regiments to carry on the struggle for Jewish freedom and independence.</p>
   <p>It is a great distance from the first to the eleventh Congress.</p>
   <p>We extend our heartfult greetings to the representatives of the Jewish people and we wish that the eleventh Congress shall come closer to the realization of our ancient dreams to see the children of Israel on the grounds of Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
