<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate News</title><title level="a" type="sub">West Side and Northwest Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE NEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">West Side and Northwest Side</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Charles Coopersmith bought the new forty-two-apartment building at Monroe Street and Homan Avenue from Ben Weinstein and Harry Gudinsky for $269,000.</p>
   <p>Louis Newman bought the property on the southwest corner of Avers Avenue and 15th Street from H. Thiers for $46,000.</p>
   <p>Alex Ginsburg bought the property at Blue Island Avenue and 14th Street from Isidor Marshek for $24,000.</p>
   <p>Dora Gross and Jennie Gross bought the property on the northeast corner of Central Park Avenue and Grenshaw Street from Philip Abramowitz for $71,000.</p>
   <p>Minnie Kaplan bought the lot on Clifton Park Avenue, near 15th Street, 25 by <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0310.jpg" n="2"/>125 feet, from Charles Silberman for $10,000.</p>
   <p>Max Gertner bought the property on the northwest corner of Crawford Avenue and 25th Place from Morris Bender for $21,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Handler bought the property on the northwest corner of Crawford and Potomac Avenues for $11,000.</p>
   <p>Glick's Music Store bought the property on the southwest corner of Division Street and Hoyne Avenue from Morris Lakin for $38,500.</p>
   <p>Louis Bowman bought a lot on Douglas Boulevard, near Spaulding Avenue, 50 by 164 feet, from H. Cohen for $20,400.</p>
   <p>Solomon Denkof bought the property on the northeast corner of Fillmore Street and Sacramento Boulevard for $24,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0311.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Philip Abramowich bought a lot on Hamlin Avenue, near 19th Street, 50 by 116 feet, for $10,000.</p>
   <p>Max Greenblatt bought a lot on Millard Avenue, near 13th Street, 36 by 125 feet, for $13,000.</p>
   <p>Jacob Nieman bought the lot on Western Avenue, near Division Street, 24 by 124 feet, from Israel Lehrsfeld for $8,500.</p>
   <p>Joseph Zimmerman sold the lot on Armitage Avenue, near Hirsch Street (sic), 25 by 120 feet, for $8,800.</p>
   <p>Albany Park and North Side</p>
   <p>Sam Fishman bought the property on the southwest corner of Burling Street and Belden Avenue from Zigmund Fox for approximately $94,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0312.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Sam Trelitzky bought the lot on North Albany Avenue, near Ainslie Street, 30 by 125 feet, from A. Bloom for $12,500.</p>
   <p>David Elenstein bought the property on the northwest corner of Drake and Leland Avenues for $28,500.</p>
   <p>Herman Cohen bought the lot on the southwest corner of Henderson Street and Lavergne Avenue, 100 by 125 feet, from Louis Rosen for $9,000.</p>
   <p>Leon Silvertrust and others bought the property on the northwest corner of Irving Park Boulevard and Sacramento Avenue from Jacob Goodman for $75,000.</p>
   <p>Nathan Rubenstein bought the property on the northeast corner of Lawrence Avenue and Troy Street from Abraham Shapiro for $93,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Eisenstein sold the property on the northeast corner of Lawrence and Crawford <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0313.jpg" n="5"/>Avenues for $170,000. He bought this property two years ago for $69,000.</p>
   <p>Mollie Latman bought the lot on Leland Avenue, near Hamlin Avenue, 65 by 124 feet, from Sam Yellin for $18,500.</p>
   <p>Aaron Kaplan bought the property at Montrose and St. Louis Avenues for approximately $20,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Kopel and Sam Horwich bought the property on the northwest corner of North Avenue and Hancock Street from Louis Metchkoff for $62,000.</p>
   <p>Carl Goldberg bought the lot on the northwest corner of Spaulding Avenue and Ainslie Street, 50 by 125 feet, for $10,000.</p>
   <p>Joe Schwartz bought the lot on Troy Street, near Ainslie Street, 30 by 125 feet, from S. London for approximately $16,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0314.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Judah Greenspan bought the property on the northeast corner of Troy and Grace Streets for $36,000.</p>
   <p>Simon Michaels and Milton Michaels bought the property on the northwest corner of Troy Street and Sunnyside Avenue from Louis Weinstein for $46,500.</p>
   <p>Israel Kriloff bought the property on the northwest corner of Washtenaw Avenue and Ainslie Street for $119,000.</p>
   <p>Isaac Hurwich bought the property at 7724 Lakeside Terrace for $33,000.</p>
   <p>In Other Neighborhoods</p>
   <p>Charles Perlman bought the lot on the northwest corner of Ashland Avenue and 43rd Street, 25 by 120 feet, for $16,000.</p>
   <p>William Sheinbloom bought the lot on Halsted Street, near Marquette Road, 25 <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0315.jpg" n="7"/>by 125 feet, from Sol Graff for $15,000.</p>
   <p>Harry Gill bought the property on the southwest corner of Michigan Avenue and 59th Street from S. Grossman for $55,000.</p>
   <p>David A. Klafter bought the property on the southeast corner of 75th Street and East End Avenue from Louis Goldman for $23,500.</p>
   <p>Abe Monaster bought the twenty-four-apartment building on the northwest corner of University Avenue and 54th Street for $125,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
