<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-13">Apr. 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Welcome, Leader of Israel!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1025</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1025.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-13">Apr. 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">WELCOME, LEADER OF ISRAEL!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The metropolis of Israel, the Chicago Jewish community, extends a hearty welcome today to the great leader of our national movement--Dr. Chaim Weizmann. In a holiday spirit, the three hundred thousand Jews of Chicago will receive, for the second time, the leader of the greatest people's organization, which is building our national home, and is forging, with Jewish forces and means, our future in the Jewish land.</p>
   <p>Inspired by the visit of the great leader of Israel, the nationalist Jews of Chicago impatiently await the report of Dr. Weizmann regarding the progress in the Jewish homeland. They are anxious to hear the story of the self-sacrificing work of our heroic halutzim on the historic soil of our people.</p>
   <p>Chicago Jews, who encouraged and strengthened the hands of the worthy president of the Zionist organization during his first visit to our city, are now prepared to support his historic mission and effective leadership of our work <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1026.jpg" n="2"/>for our liberation with twice as much enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>As loyal, disciplined children of an awakening nation, they will bring their offerings to the great leader of the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>They hope that the second visit to Chicago of the president of the international movement will yield practical results for the constructive work in Palestine, and will morally encourage and strengthen the hands of the local Zionist workers to new productive organizational work in behalf of our ideal.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Jewish community greets the great leader of Israel with complete confidence in the fulfillment of the Zionist ideal; it has faith in the effectiveness of his political and practical work for the Jewish renaissance in our historic Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
