<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-02">Jan. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">"Palestine Will Be a Jewish Land Despite All Enemy Attacks" Says Dr. Weizmann</title><title level="a" type="sub">Zionist Leader Greets Opening of Middle West Convention in La Salle Hotel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1603</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1603.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-02">Jan. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">"PALESTINE WILL BE A JEWISH LAND DESPITE ALL ENEMY ATTACKS" SAYS DR. WEIZMANN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Zionist Leader Greets Opening of Middle West Convention in La Salle Hotel</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Palestine will be a Jewish land, and all the complaints against England and against the Zionist organization are no more than idle chatter. Three years ago we owned only two per cent of the land of Palestine; today we own not less than four per cent. As one travels from Tarbiah to Jaffa one passes through Jewish land, bought and cultivated by the Jews.</p>
   <p>"We now have enough money to buy land for eight thousand families. In the course of time, twenty-five thousand Jews will settle on that land. I admit that the path to our goal is a difficult one and that the road is strewn with rocks but we are clearing the way, which is a much more difficult task than throwing stones, as our enemies are doing. I hope to God that this convention will help to clear many rocks from the path."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1604.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Chaim Weizmann delivered this brief speech yesterday afternoon before the audience gathered in the convention hall of the La Salle Hotel. He spoke in a very serious tone and one could see by his pale face that he was very serious.</p>
   <p>The president of the World Zionist Organization made this speech when he greeted the second annual convention of the middle-western Zionist organization. The hall was quiet for a few moments after the conclusion of his speech. Then the audience burst into spontaneous applause; cries of "Hurrah!" and the strains of "Hatikvah" filled the hall.</p>
   <p>The convention opened yesterday at twelve o'clock noon. It began its routine and technical work immediately after Max Shulman, president of the middle western organization, striking the table with his small gavel, declared the convention open. When Max Shulman finished his brief opening address with the words: "Everyone to his camp and his banner," the delegates understood that this was to be a serious business convention, and refrained <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1605.jpg" n="3"/>from making the hundreds of "points of order" with which a Jewish convention usually distinguishes itself.</p>
   <p>Mr. Shulman pointed out in his speech that Zionism had been very successful in the Middle West during the past year, in spite of all the obstacles created by internal and external enemies. He urged the delegates to keep on working for the holy ideal, which demands so many sacrifices of men and money. The president of the middle-western Zionist organization assured the delegates that Chicago will fulfill its quota in the membership drive, and that Chicago's quota of the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization] will also be fulfilled.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Zionist district has five thousand members now. New districts and new members are enrolled every day, thanks to the energetic work of Dr. Abramowich, secretary of the district.</p>
   <p>Immediately after Mr. Shulman's speech, Leonard J. Grossman greeted the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1606.jpg" n="4"/>convention in the name of the Chicago Zionists. In the main, Mr. Grossman dealt with Zangwill's recent statements against the present Zionist leaders and against political Zionism, and reprimanded the great English-Jewish writer for his statements. "Israel Zangwill is creating a lot of publicity for Israel Zangwill, but he is doing very little for the Jews"." With this remark, Mr. Grossman concluded his greetings. The first session ended with Mr. Grossman's speech. The various committees immediately began their work.</p>
   <p>The second session opened at two o'clock in the afternoon. The credentials committee reported that there were one hundred seventy-one delegates at the convention, of whom one hundred twenty-one were from Chicago and the rest from neighboring communities.</p>
   <p>Mr. M. Steinberg, chairman of the National Fund Committee, brought in a very encouraging report. He declared that thirty-five hundred National <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1607.jpg" n="5"/>Fund boxes were placed in Chicago about a year ago and that four months later they brought in three thousand six hundred dollars. He also declared that sixteen thousand dollars was collected in Chicago in 1923 for the National Fund; this is seven thousand dollars more than in 1922.</p>
   <p>The convention then turned its attention to the task of electing the officers of the convention. Max Shulman was unanimously elected chairman. Dr. Fink of Terre Haute, [Indiana], Robert Hess of Milwaukee, [Wisconsin], and L. D. Grossman were unanimously elected vice-chairman, and B. Hodes was elected secretary.</p>
   <p>Saul Raskin, the poet, made an appeal in behalf of Zionist work. The ninety-year-old, white-haired Joseph Szold, an uncle of Henrietta Szold, made a deep impression in his brief speech appealing for aid to Palestine.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ben Zion Soloveichik of Poltava, [Russia], one of the oldest Russian <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1608.jpg" n="6"/>Zionists, was an unexpected but welcome guest. He left Russia a short time ago. He moved everybody to tears with his description of the present condition of the Jews in Russia. He said that the Russian Jews made sacrifices and fulfilled their Zionist duties during the worst days of the terrible Cheka. The worst cruelties of the Cheka and the Euseks did not prevent the Russian Jews from doing their Zionist duty; even now many of them are in prisons, martyrs of the holy, Jewish ideal.</p>
   <p>Louis Lipsky, president of the American Zionist Federation, and member of the World Executive Committee, received a warm welcome in appreciation of his great achievements in the field of Zionist work. Lipsky, who had returned from a tour of the Middle West, declared that not only Jewish minds but Jewish hearts had been affected by the attacks which the enemies of the Jews have recently made against them. He said that the American Jews are prone to forget that they are responsible for seventy-one per cent of the Palestine budget. Mr. Lipsky made an appeal in <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1609.jpg" n="7"/>behalf of the National Fund. His powerful speech was enthusiastically received.</p>
   <p>The third session began with a report by Dr. Abramowich on Zionist work in Iowa, Wisconsin, Illinois, and Indiana. There are twenty-five hundred members in Chicago. The original six districts have grown to thirty-two. Eleven thousand dollars in dues was sent to the main office in New York.</p>
   <p>Max Shulman devoted his closing speech, during the third session to the wonderful work of the Courier in behalf of Zionism and Judaism in the Middle West. He said that the Courier deserves special thanks from the midwestern Jews for its fight for everything that is Jewish, and that Mr. [P.] Ginsburg and Dr. [S. M.] Melamed deserve a song of praise from American Jewry.</p>
   <p>The Hadassah of Chicago and the neighboring states also held a convention, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1610.jpg" n="8"/>in connection with the convention of the middle western Zionists. Forty women came together and discussed, in an intelligent and reasonable manner, their share of Zionist work. Mrs. Dushkin, who has recently returned from Palestine, gave a very encouraging report on Hadassah work in Palestine, which is not political but is purely humanitarian. During the afternoon, the delegates were the guests of Hadassah at a luncheon in the La Salle Hotel. Mrs. Stein, Miss Pearl Franklin, and Miss Perlstein entertained the guests appropriately and beautifully.</p>
   <p>In the evening, all the local delegates, as well as the delegates from other cities, were guests of the Chicago Central Zionist Committee at a banquet at the La Salle Hotel, where Chicago's five thousand new members were installed.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry A. Lipsky was toastmaster. He complimented himself, in a brief <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1611.jpg" n="9"/>but humorous speech, upon the success of the Zionist drive and assured his listeners that the drive was a success because of his inactivity!</p>
   <p>Daniel Dever, son of Mayor Dever, brought a message from his father who could not be present at the banquet. He promised Zionism his full support.</p>
   <p>Dr. S. M. Melamed, in a powerful speech, exposed the falsity of those who claim that Zionism is a dogma. Zionism, declared Dr. Melamed, is not a dogma but a conviction based upon fact. The Jews are hated because they have no country. It is the task of the Zionists to obtain the Jewish land for the Jewish people. A Jewish home in Palestine will unite the Eastern and Western cultures.</p>
   <p>The new members were then installed by Mr. Louis Lipsky, president of the American Zionist Federation, who delivered a long speech, which <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1612.jpg" n="10"/>was very favorably received. Between speeches, the choir, directed by David Hirsch, sang beautiful Jewish songs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
