<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-05-03">May 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Volume 79. Page 317.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0431</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0431.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-05-03">May 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Volume 79. Page 317.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Another sympathetic figure of exceptional ability and with a deep devotion to Orthodox Judaism in its broader and finer sense, is that of Mrs. Benjamin Davis (nee Jeanette Isaacs).</p>
   <p>She was born, educated, and taught school in the city of New York. From her scholarly father and brother, she received a fine conception of Talmudic and prophetic literature.</p>
   <p>Endowed with a fine imagination, keen, analytical mind and a wide secular knowledge, her Jewishness is at once philosophical, ethical, and poetical. Mrs. Davis has been a Chicagoan since 1881 and may claim a large share in the contributions to the early culture of Orthodox Jewry in this city. I know of no movement among the immigrants of eastern Europe, or in the furtherance <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0432.jpg" n="2"/>of some good cause, in which Mrs. Davis did not take a leading part. Her activities, however, did not end there. She also took part in movements sponsored by liberal and Reform Judaism provided that they proved consistent with her own religious views. Her widest field of action began with renaissance of Jewish Nationalism. She was founder and head of many groups of women whose aim was to help rebuild Palestine and to ease the lot of those already there. Mrs. Davis has been active in the practical work of the local and national Zionist organizations. She was also more than instrumental in the building of several large institutions for the Jews of the West Side.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
