<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-10">Apr. 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate News</title><title level="a" type="sub">West Side and Northwest Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0240</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0240.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-10">Apr. 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE NEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">West Side and Northwest Side</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Max Kaplan sold the commercial building on the Northwest corner of 26th Street and Kedvale Avenue to M. Coat for $86,000.</p>
   <p>Rosa Shapiro sold the eight-apartment and commercial building on the southwest corner of Polk Street and Crawford Avenue to R. Cavallo for $105,000.</p>
   <p>Congregation Anshe Sholom bought the lot on Independence Boulevard, near Flournoy Street, 55 by 46 feet, for $23,000.</p>
   <p>Moses Shapiro bought the seventeen-apartment building on the southwest corner of Douglas Boulevard and St. Louis Avenue from M. Cantor for $85,000.</p>
   <p>Harry Goldberg bought the property on Albany Avenue, near Fillmore Street, for <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0241.jpg" n="2"/>$15,000.</p>
   <p>Nemtie Sitron bought the property on Central Park Avenue, near Grenshaw Street, for $13,000.</p>
   <p>M. Friedber bought the property on the northeast corner of Chicago and Crawford Avenues for $103,000.</p>
   <p>Ben Hurwich bought the property on Crystal Street, near Washtenaw Avenue, from the Liberty Trust and Savings Bank for $21,775.</p>
   <p>Hyman Becker and others bought the property on the southeast corner of Irving and Potomac Avenues for $39,500.</p>
   <p>Charles Silberstein bought the property on the southeast corner of Kedzie Avenue and 27th Street from H. Pinder for $27,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0242.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Annie Resman bought the property on the southeast corner of Keeler Avenue and 13th Street from Jacob Cohen for $32,500.</p>
   <p>Sam Lipowsky bought the property on Millard Avenue near 16th Street, from B. Sternberg for $12,550.</p>
   <p>Hyman Horwich bought the property on the northeast corner of Roosevelt Road and St. Louis Avenue from Samuel Weitzman for $115,000.</p>
   <p>Harry Rosenfeld bought the property on Sacramento Avenue, near Fullerton Avenue, 64 by 129 feet, from Janet Goldblatt for $9,500.</p>
   <p>Sam Brandzel bought the property on Turner Avenue,near Roosevelt Road, from Bessie Spector for $26,600.</p>
   <p>Albany Park and North Side</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0243.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Harry Goldstein and others bought the property on the northwest corner of Pensacola and Spaulding Avenues from Morris Zitman for $94,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Spector bought the property on Spaulding and Argyle Avenues for $52,000.</p>
   <p>Harry Gottlieb bought the property on the northwest corner of Spaulding and Balmoral Avenues from M. Baumgarten for $32,000.</p>
   <p>Anna Silver bought the property on the southeast corner of Belmont and Hoyne Avenues for $18,000.</p>
   <p>Sarah Block bought the property on the northwest corner of Lincoln and Grace Streets from S. Fierstein for $19,000.</p>
   <p>Morris Fishman bought the thirteen-apartment building on Lawndale Avenue, near Lawrence Avenue, from M. Wenig for $78,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0244.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Charles Bierman and Henry Krakow bought the Santa Barbara apartment building on Greenleaf Avenue, near the lake, for $255,000.</p>
   <p>Samuel Blatt and Benjamin Bartz bought the property at 1667-73 Farwell Avenue for $24,900. The buyers plan to build a court-apartment building for $300,000.</p>
   <p>Joseph Lebowitz bought the forty-two apartment building at 1354-62 Estes Avenue for $235,000.</p>
   <p>Abraham Gombiner bought a one-fourth interest in the ninety-four-apartment and commercial building on the northeast corner of Broadway and Melrose Street for $47,500.</p>
   <p>E. Weil and Siegfrid Lazarus bought the Blofus Manor, a fifty-four-apartment building at 4215 Broadway for $255,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Novak bought the property on Cicero Avenue, near Belmont Avenue, from <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0245.jpg" n="6"/>Hyman Goldstein for $13,500.</p>
   <p>Libie Lieberman and Fannie Greenhouse sold the property on the southwest corner of Kedvale Avenue and Byron Street to V. H. Davis for $146,000.</p>
   <p>Abe S. Bloom bought the property on the southeast corner of Oakley Avenue and Ainslie Street from P. Jacobson for $55,500.</p>
   <p>In Other Neighborhoods</p>
   <p>Ida Goodman, Goldie Goodman, and Ella Goodman bought the fifteen-apartment building on the southwest corner of Throop and 81st Streets for $88,000.</p>
   <p>Morris Barnet bought the three-story apartment building on State Street, near Maple Avenue, Evanston, for $92,000. The buyer plans to erect a hotel for $300,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0246.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>I. Konigsberg sold the twenty-four-apartment building on the southeast corner of Wabash Avenue and 50th Street to H. Overman for $65,000.</p>
   <p>Israel Nudelman bought the commercial building at 1146-52 West 63rd Street from I. Schur for $45,000.</p>
   <p>Morris Jacobson bought the fifty-four-apartment building at 4523-31 Drexel Boulevard for $392,500.</p>
   <p>Abe Weinstein and Harry Weinstein bought the four-story apartment building on the northwest corner of Cottage Grove Avenue and Oakwood Boulevard from Alexander and Sam Flower for $225,000.</p>
   <p>Max Goldstein and Harry Nirlmor who a month ago bought the commercial building at 404-12 South State Street for $340,000 sold this property to the John R. Thompson Restaurant Company for $380,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
