<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[Struggle against Missionary Plague]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. A. Margolin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[STRUGGLE AGAINST MISSIONARY PLAGUE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. A. Margolin</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fight, which is being conducted in mass meetings in our synagogues, against the missionary plague will help to advertise the activity of the "soul snatchers" rather than weaken it. The danger to Jewish children of missionary propaganda cannot be removed by resolutions of condemmation, or by appeals to the parents to protect their children from the pestilence by a voluntary police guard. Negative ways of struggle, prohibitions, and condemmations will only serve to inflame the minds of our children, and their desire to taste the forbidden fruit will drive them to visit the nests of the "soul snatchers" where their young minds will be poisoned.</p>
   <p>The missionary plague can only be removed by positive and productive means of struggle--primarily by propaganda for national and religious Jewish education. Our religious leaders, representatives of national movements, community and <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0460.jpg" n="2"/>cultural workers must provide the West Side with Jewish cultural institutions, with educational institutions for adults, with Jewish clubs, libraries, lecture halls, and lecturers to spread Jewish thought, Jewish knowledge, and national ideas. These will be the most productive means of struggle against the plague of conversion.</p>
   <p>The national education of Jewish youth, a strong Jewish consciousness, and atmosphere of Jewish ideals--all these will form a powerful front against the missionary pestilence. The "soul snatchers" will not be able to sneak through such a fortress of Jewish culture.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
