<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-22">Feb. 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Albany Park</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-22">Feb. 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH ALBANY PARK</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish settlement in Albany Park, on the Northwest Side of Chicago, is becoming more and more prominent. Our brethren there live in the finest residences. There are many Jewish business establishments there. There are butcher shops, bakeries, fruit stores, groceries, millinery, and men's and women's clothing stores. There are also a few synagogues and Talmud Torahs. As the Jewish population in Albany Park increases, so the number of such institutions will also increase. Albany Park is a fine and large part of Jewish Chicago. The Jews keep moving into the neighborhood.</p>
   <p>A. Fried, vice-president of the newly established Congregation Beth Mordecai in Albany Park, writes us an enthusiastic letter about the undertakings of that organization, about the possibilities of establishing a real Orthodox center there, where the old-fashioned Jew would be able to worship God the way he used to in the old country, and where the youth would receive a traditional Jewish <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0464.jpg" n="2"/>education. He also says in his letter that Congregation Beth Mordecai holds its religious services in a hall at the present time, but that it will start building a synagogue right after the holidays. In the meantime, they have organized a Talmud Torah where quite a number of Jewish children of the neighborhood study Hebrew and the Old Testament.</p>
   <p>All this was to be expected from the members of Beth Mordecai. They were Jews when they lived on Canal Street, or on other streets in the wards of the West Side, and they remained Jews when they moved to Albany Park. There are many Jews in Albany Park who have not yet had time to enroll as members of Congregation Beth Mordecai. They are urged to do so now. The planned Orthodox center--a synagogue, a Talmud Torah, reading rooms, and other necessities--must be large and beautiful, appropriate to the needs of a district like Albany Park. A great deal of money will be required to establish that center. A small group of people should not be held responsible for everything.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
