<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-07">Sept. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The End of a Nasty Controversy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-07">Sept. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE END OF A NASTY CONTROVERSY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The long-drawn controversy between the Brandeis-Mac group and the executive of the World Zionist Organization is not over yet, but it seems that the Twelfth Zionist Congress, meeting now at Carlsbad, will put an end to it. As could be foreseen, the opponents of Dr. Weizmann and his colleagues have tried to capitalize [on] this controversy with the object of hitting their adversary, but their efforts are in vain. The two men who are mainly responsible for the controversy, Mr. Julius Simon and Mr. De Liema have attacked Dr. Weizmann bitterly in the course of the general discussion on the report of the executive. But the American delegates, who are committed to a policy of real Zionism instead of parlor Zionism as well as many notable European and Palestinian leaders have not been silent either. They have not only defended vigorously the present executive of the World Zionist Organization, but they have accused the Brandeis-Mac group of bad faith and of falsifying Zionism. To judge from the report <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1114.jpg" n="2"/>emanating from Carlsbad, the Brandeis-Mac group has lost its case because the vast majority of the Congress is committed to the policies of Dr. Weizmann, and means to uphold the able leader. Our people in Europe appreciate the services Justice Louis D. Brandeis and Judge Julian W. Mac have rendered to the Zionist cause in the past, and are also aware of the fact that both gentlemen are men of influence and that they command respect everywhere, but still all these considerations notwithstanding, the majority of the delegates are not willing to let the above-mentioned gentlemen control the Zionist organization and remake Zionism in their own way. Even if an organization is under obligation to a few persons it cannot sell itself entirely to these very few persons. The interest of the organization comes first, and it is for this reason that Brandeis and Mac have lost the game.</p>
   <p>Here in America Zionism may or may not be a philanthropic proposition. Anyhow, there are any number of Zionists in this country who are not conscious Jewish nationalists and do not give a rap for Jewish nationalism. Since they are doing their duties towards Zionism, the leaders do not care about the theories <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1115.jpg" n="3"/>and sentiments of these Zionists. In Europe, however, it is different. In Europe every Zionist is an outspoken nationalistic Jew. There, Zionism is indisolubly connected with Jewish nationalism, and the one cannot be separated from the other. The main charge against Brandeis is that he is not a Jewish nationalist, and that his Zionism is only philanthropic in nature. If Justice Louis D. Brandeis would be one of the rank and file of the organization, the Zionist leaders would not give a tumble for his theories on Judaism. It would be immaterial to them whether he is a good Zionist or not, just as it is immaterial to them what many other Zionists in America think of the theories of Zionism. But since Justice Brandeis is not a private but a general, and since he wanted to arrogate to himself the power of dictator, it is not immaterial to the other Zionist leaders what Mr. Brandeis thinks of Zionist theories, and since it is known to them that his Zionism is not based on Jewish nationalism, but is philanthropic in nature, they cannot only not accept his leadership, but they cannot even tolerate him as one of the leaders, and under these conditions, of course, the Mac-Brandeis group had to lose the fight and was bound to lose it. To judge from the memorandum the Brandeis-Mac group has addressed to the Twelfth <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1116.jpg" n="4"/>Zionist Congress, one must assume that the leaders of this group are still hoping that the Congress would repudiate Dr. Weizmann and reinstate them. Of course they were badly advised. Any well-informed Zionist here or abroad, could have told the gentlemen that they are hoping against hope, because European Zionism is nationalistic to the core, and will never make any concessions in this direction. But we are of the opinion that the origin of the whole trouble was the ignorance of the leaders of the Brandeis-Mac group regarding Zionist sentiments, because if they were familiar with Zionist sentiments they would never start the trouble. They would have either resigned without any reason, or they would have yielded to the demands of the World Zionist executive. But ill advised and misled by a few politicians, they have been drawn into a controversy the end of which they could not foresee, and now the controversy will be ended by the Twelfth Zionist Congress. In spite of all criticisms and accusations leveled against Dr. Weizmann, he and his colleagues will again be placed in power and that, of course, will mean the finale of the controversy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
