<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-21">Mar. 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1454</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1454.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-21">Mar. 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>He who did not see with his own eyes that meeting cannot believe at all that such a meeting is possible in Chicago. I refer to the Purim celebration of the Zionists in the Grand Ball Room of the Sherman Hotel. There came in at first about a thousand men and women who, to judge by their looks, do not belong to any synagogue. They came on time and heard the reading of the Book of Esther. The men came in into the hall with their hats on, because they knew that they would hear the reading of the Book of Esther. Another thousand men and women came in about an hour later. They had already heard the reading of the Book of Esther in their synagogues. The men came into the hall bareheaded because they knew that the reading was over. The big hall was overcrowded. A cheerful holiday mood prevailed. Cantor Eli Krechmer, a handsome Jew, with a beautiful beard like Herzl and a fine tenor voice, was <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1455.jpg" n="2"/>in good humor and charmed the public with his singing of Jewish folk songs--mostly national and Zionist folk songs. The public wanted him to sing some more, but it was already late. Dr. Thon, the guest of honor of the evening, still had to speak, and the call for volunteers for the Keren Hayesod still had to take place. The public was so aroused emotionally by Canton Krechmer that two hundred Jewish men and women volunteered for the Keren Hayesod with pledges from one hundred to one thousand dollars. Dr. Thon proved in his brilliant speech that he has a keen mind and that he is a brilliant speaker. The magnificent Purim celebration closed under the strains of "The Hatikvah". Chicago Jews will not so soon forget this Purim celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
