<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-04-08">April 8, 1910</date><title level="a">An Appeal and a Request.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0900</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0900.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-04-08">April 8, 1910</date><title level="a">An Appeal and a Request.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brothers and Sisters: --</p>
   <p>On the 15th of April and for about two weeks thereafter, the United States Government will conduct it's census. We, the members of the Verien, "Jewish Culture" together with other Jewish nationalistic organizations, request your utmost co-operation with the census takers who will visit your homes. These enumerators, census takers, will ask you many personal questions such as the size of your family, their ages, their birthplaces, and their occupations.</p>
   <p>They will also ask you of your nationality and your mother tongue. Our plea is, do not deny that you are Jews. This information goes only to the government and cannot be used against you by any anti-semitic groups. Denying your Jewish heritage would, in this instance, be a cowardly act. A census is taken only one every ten years, and this is one opportunity for Jews to be proud of themselves. The insertion of this question into the census was a victory for the recognition of the existance of national minority groups. We Jews certainly have something to be proud of. We have certainly contributed our share to world culture and civilization in the past, and, of our languages, Yiddish and Hebrew, we can well be proud. The Hebrew language has nurtured civilization with such treasures <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0901.jpg" n="2"/>as the Prophets and Yiddish is already asserting itself.</p>
   <p>We are Jews and let us show this world that we are Jews. Be sure to answer this question properly. The "Jewish Culture" group will carry on much activity to acquaint the Jewish public with this request. Let us help these census takers in their very difficult task.</p>
   <p>The Verein "Jewish Culture" Committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
