<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-24">Sept. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Attend Slihoth Services</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-24">Sept. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ATTEND SLIHOTH SERVICES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is a prosaic world. Everything is so new, everything is in such good order in the American Beth ha-Midrash [house of study, sometimes synagogue], everything is so very pompous. The parvenu made a clean sweep of the poverty that had accumulated among his parents and grandparents, and put in brand-new things and established a new order. Along with this poverty, he swept out several antiques, several hidden treasures, but he is not aware of this and if he is, it does not concern him. His only desire is--the new.</p>
   <p>It is needless to speak of the Reform temple. From it, the memories of the past have disappeared. It is beautiful, pompous, magnificent, but it does not speak to the Jew who clings to the past and who envisions a future based on traditional Judaism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1475.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But even our Orthodox synagogue is no longer as appealing to the Jewish heart as it was at one time. Jewish bodies are stronger, cleaner, and larger, just as all bodies are larger in America. But the soul seems to have vanished. So many side issues creep into the synagogue that hardly any room remains for the soul of the old synagogue. To this very day, the synagogue still appeals strongly to the Jews. For no other cause can money be so easily raised as for the building of a synagogue. However, the synagogue of today lacks its traditional holiness; it lacks its ancient antiquity. Everything is so new, so fresh, and so badly made; it resembles the ready-made garments which are bought for a few dollars in a department store.</p>
   <p>Yet, there is one day when even the American synagogue seems to be, for a short while, the ancient house of worship, when the spirit of genuineness, of profundity, and of devotion prevades it. This day is not Rosh Hashanah, nor is it Yom Kipur, because on those days the pinochle players, the poker players and the "sports" go to the synagogues; on Yom Kipur especially, they drag along with them, into the synagogue, a spirit of levity and flippancy which makes <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1476.jpg" n="3"/>everything about them seem commonplace. The day [we refer to], the first day of Slihoth [prayers of forgiveness recited before Rosh Hashanah].</p>
   <p>Jews who play pinochle do not attend the Slihoth services. They usually play cards on Saturday evening and this makes it hard for them to get up early, should they want to attend the Slihoth services, although they don't even want to attend. The "sports" and the energetic American Jews would ridicule an individual who asked them to get up at four o'clock in the morning to attend the Slihoth services. Those who attend Slihoth are the Jews who still cherish the past. The early hour, before the world with its everyday business awakes, contributes to the spirit of cleanliness; and at that time, there prevails in the American synagogue something of the ancient sanctity. For a moment, the spirit of the ancient synagogue seems to be present. Anyone who wants to be spiritually refreshed, even for a moment, should attend Slihoth services. The person who understands the meaning of the Slihoth prayers is more deeply impressed.</p>
   <p>If you wish to know the source from which Jews derive their strength to endure <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1477.jpg" n="4"/>the afflictions visited upon them--attend Slihoth services.</p>
   <p>If you wish to have a conception of an urn into which have been poured the tears of a nation, its pain and its despair--attend the Slihoth services.</p>
   <p>"Look at our condition--we are poor and we have nothing," recites the Jew during the Slihoth prayers. The synagogue is solemn and the atmosphere is holy. The greyness of dawn that creeps through the windows, the bright lights inside, the song of the cantor, and the absorption of the worshipers--all combine to give the impression of something unreal that awaken the sweet memories of the old synagogue--not its outward appearance, but its essence, its spirit.</p>
   <p>A little later, it is daybreak, and the synagogue returns to its usual, everyday aspect. Therefore, do not miss the blessed hour--attend Slihoth services.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
