<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01">December 1918-January 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Northwest Branch</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0640</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0640.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01">December 1918-January 1919</date>.
<title level="a">NORTHWEST BRANCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Throughout the report you will have noticed that I have inspected in connection with the departments spoken of, the fact that what ever is being conducted in the main branch, in as many of the departments as possible there activities are duplicated in the branch on the Northwest Side. I will therefore go at length into a discussion of our Northwest Branch problem at this time; other than the fact that it will be almost imperative very shortly to renovate the building on such a manner as to make possible for us to do the work there satisfactorily.</p>
   <p>Only a few of you probably know that our Northwest Side building was previously occupied by the Jewish Educational Alliance, and that was originally built for the Marks Nathan Jewish Orphan Home. This building is situated at 1242 North Wood Street.</p>
   <p>During the year, we have had a total attendance inthe branch of 72,503. This makes a very splendid beginning in view of the fact that the facilities were by no means adequate to meet the needs with the program that we have introduced there, which is an innovation in that section of our community, <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0641.jpg" n="2"/>we feel quite certain, if the facilities can be put into good shape (reconstructed, inother words,) the building painted, and the gymnasium building on a part of the playgrounds, that the attendance would easily be doubled within another year. We feel that the need for our activity in that section of the city is great.</p>
   <p>The architects are at the present time preparing plans and getting prices of the cost to thoroughly remodel and rehabilitate the branch. Unfortunately the building is situated almost on the outskirts of the Jewish section, making it inaccessible, in a great many ways, for the largest number of people who really should have the use of it. Before long we will be in a position to make definite recommendations as to just where the Northwest Branch should really be located. A superficial study of the neighborhood brings me to the belief that such a center should be located between Palmer and Logan Square, that the largest Jewish population of the Northwest Side lives within that radius, and that when the time comes for the building of the branch in that locality, or wherever else we may find that such branch should be built, we are justified in making the expenditure of twenty- or twenty-five thousands dollars on our quarters, because it will undoubtedly take two and probably three years before we will be able to make any change, and at the end of that time the present building will be fully worth not only the money spent on it, but probably again as much.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
