<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1916-02-18">February 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Resolutions about Peace and Jewish Rights.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0872</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0872.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The World</title>,
<date when="1916-02-18">February 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTIONS ABOUT PEACE AND JEWISH RIGHTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whereas, it has been the good fortune of the people of the United States to be comparatively free from the turmoil of the European strife, its hatred and prejudices, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the people and government of the United States are in a position to exercise a beneficial influence in aiding the world to lay a foundation for a durable and permanent peace based upon justice to all, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, in some of the war countries of Europe, the Jewish people are still deprived of elementary, political and civic rights, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, every form of religious oppression and discrimination is contrary to the spirit of the American people, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, there was introduced by Representative London of New York, on the 6th day of December, 1915, in the House of Representatives, a joint resolution known as H. J. R. 39, in which the Congress is urged to call upon <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0873.jpg" n="2"/>the President of the United States to convene a Congress of neutral nations to offer mediation to the belligerents, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the said resolution requests the Government of the United States to urge upon the governments of the other nations of the other countries to cease the discriminations wherever they exist against the Jewish people and to grant the Jews the same rights and privileges, which other citizens of the same countries enjoy, be it resolved, at a</p>
   <p>Meeting of the-----</p>
   <p>Held at-----</p>
   <p>On-----</p>
   <p>that we communicate to our Representative in Congress the knowledge of our unanimous approval of the resolution introduced by Representative London, and that we urge upon them and upon the United States Senators, that <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0874.jpg" n="3"/>they support in every way possible the aforesaid resolution.</p>
   <p>-- Chairman.</p>
   <p>-- Secretary.</p>
   <p>Cut out this resolution and send it to the Chairman of Foreign Relations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
