<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-10-15">October 15, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Broslawsky under $10,000 Bail.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-10-15">October 15, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">BROSLAWSKY UNDER $10,000 BAIL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wladimir Broslawsky, who was considered a very "useful" person by the Holy Synod, has many embezzlement charges against him. The convert, Wladimir Broslawsky, who was the right hand man of Schlifenbach, was yesterday held under $10,000 bail, while Federal agents were conducting an investigation of his shady activities.</p>
   <p>As it is known to the readers of the Courier, Wladimir Broslawsky, who flew to the bosom of Mr. Schlifenbach, had been recommended by the Holy Synod of Russia, as an extremely "useful" person.</p>
   <p>He was arrested for selling Russian passports to those, who wanted to return to Russia - passports that were absolutely worthless, and on which he had made a huge sum of money. However, since his arrest, many other crooked affairs of his were revealed. Masses of witnesses were questioned <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0146.jpg" n="2"/>by States Attorney Sims and his assistants, in reference to this handsome man.</p>
   <p>Wladimir Broslawsky, as it was disclosed during yesterday's hearing, was also engaged in the business of dealing with young Russian men, who were called for regular government service. Having received large sums of money, he freed these young men from their duty of serving the Tzar. According to Russian laws, every Russian subject residing in the United States, may be freed from serving the Russian government if a medical commission at the consulate declares him totally unfit to serve the Tzar. Thus, the young men in the case, receive from the consul a white or blue ticket signifying disqualification. Mr. Broslawsky, who was only Mr. Schlifenbach's adviser and not an actual official, has handled this very skillfully. He composed the "medical commission," and handed out certificates. His hat decorated with an eagle, his good looks and his refined manner facilitated his preying upon the Russian subjects.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0147.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thus he was able to act under the guise of a consul, and the poor, fearful subjects of the Tzar trusted him and gave him all the money he asked for.</p>
   <p>Baron De Shilling, the present Russian consul in Chicago, and prince Nikolai Engalitchev, the Russian vice-consul, were also at the District Attorney's office, at the time the witnesses were cross-examined. They assisted the Federal agents in questioning those who were unable to speak English.</p>
   <p>The names of the victims of Broslawsky are not as yet officially revealed. The investigation was postponed until next Monday, but from all indications many Jews were trapped in his net. Mr. Broslawsky has been "at work" in Chicago for quite some time. It is believed that Mr. Broslawsky has many thousands of dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
