<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-23">Apr. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0497</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0497.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-23">Apr. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When one reads Jewish newspapers regularly, one arrives at the conclusion that Jewish life is productively one-sided. What one reads every day in Jewish newspapers is either about pogroms or struggles against pogroms or reports on planned pogroms, and one is impressed that the entire Jewish life is marked only with pogroms. This impression, however, is false. It is true that millions of Jews are constantly facing the danger of being massacred, and yet, despite this menace, the Jewish mind, Jewish working hands, and the Jewish people are more active now than ever before. Slowly but surely, Palestine is being built. The Jews of Diaspora are active in many fields of life, and we do not remain stationary. The pogrom menace hinders the work in many countries, but it does not paralyze it completely because the impetus of Jewish life will not permit itself to become paralyzed.</p>
   <p>What Jews are doing today and how Jewish work is progressing can best be seen in Chicago, where the Jews are advancing public life. In the past few years <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0498.jpg" n="2"/>we have built many beautiful institutions; we have learned to give large sums for charity and Torah; we take more interest in Palestine; we have become more interested in Jewish problems, and we now have a stronger sense of duty than ever before. In lesser communities than Chicago, where Jewish life moves faster, Jewish progress makes greater strides. Despite pogroms and the constant menace of pogroms, we have given much of our attention, money, and time to further Jewish life, and we have still found time to solve important problems as they arise from day to day and from year to year. Then, why isn't this reflected in the Jewish press? Very simple. The report of a pogrom makes a greater impression than the announcement of the opening of a certain beneficial institution. The eye catches the abnormal much quicker than it does the normal.</p>
   <p>A bill has now been introduced in the New York Legislature, which proposes to establish a severe censorship on books. A bill has been recently introduced in the Springfield Legislature, which proposes to establish the blue laws in Illinois. The fanatics of many other states are now girding their loins.... <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0499.jpg" n="3"/>but there is nothing to fear. The American people have a sound sense of responsibility and will not permit themselves to be dragged into the mire.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
