<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-07">Aug. 7, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">City Authorities Promise to Protect Insulted Jews</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-07">Aug. 7, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">CITY AUTHORITIES PROMISE TO PROTECT INSULTED JEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Notwithstanding the unbearable heat yesterday, Netherwood's Hall was crowded with 800 Jews from the vicinity of Cypress and Taylor Streets. They assembled there to listen to what our city authorities had to say about the heinous attack perpetrated on them by a group of young Irishmen.</p>
   <p>As chairman, Mr. Max Levitan, well-known West Side businessman, opened the meeting and immediately introduced the first speaker, Judge Philip Bregstone. The judge explained the purpose of the meeting and expressed the hope that its cause would not occur again.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. Leon Zolotkoff, editor of the Jewish Courier, who emphasized chiefly the fact that Jewish citizens were denied police protection. He also pointed out that such attacks can easily occur in a country of many nationalities like America. He was promised that the city government <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0175.jpg" n="2"/>will see to it without question that such an incident does not happen again.</p>
   <p>In the name of State's Attorney Maclay Hoyne, Mr. D. A. Ramsey, assistant State's attorney, who is now in charge of grand jury indictments, addressed the mass meeting. He expressed deep regret for last Monday's incident. Mr. Ramsey assured the Assembly that if Irish ruffians again dare to attack peaceful Jewish citizens, they will be severely punished.</p>
   <p>Mr. A. Shaffer, who co-operated with Mr. Levitan in informing the authorities about this whole matter, gave a brief talk in which he stated that thirteen bullies have been arrested so far, and will be arraigned before Judge Harry Dolan of the Boys' Court. Four more are being sought.</p>
   <p>At the close of the meeting, a resolution was unanimously adopted by a rising vote, expressing gratitude to Mayor Thompson, State's Attorney Hoyne, and their representatives who were present, for the great interest that they have <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0176.jpg" n="3"/>taken in the whole affair and for promising protection, which will serve as the best warning to the Irish ruffians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
