<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-07-26">July 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Not a Jewish Case.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-07-26">July 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">NOT A JEWISH CASE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A young man of Jewish parentage killed a Jewish business man in Chicago and the state naturally seeks, if not the death penalty, then life imprisonment. It is understood that the one, to whom some one else's life was of little worth, does not want to die prematurely himself, and does not even want to spend his life behind prison bars, repenting for his crime. He wants to save himself, and therefore engages a well-known criminal lawyer to defend him. Incidentally this criminal lawyer is also of Jewish faith, and has much in common with the defendant.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0138.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This, however, does not make the case a Jewish one, and if this noted criminal lawyer intends to distort this into a Jewish question, he will thereby commit a great crime against the Chicago Jewry.</p>
   <p>The Jacob-Simon's case is not a Jewish case, in spite of the fact that both the killer and his victim are Jews. The whole trial is in general a social one. Such crimes, defendants, witnesses, and lawyers are to be found in all countries, among all nations, and we, Jews, who contribute to the world a large percentage of artists and educators, fighters for freedom, and scholars, might also produce a little apostasy which would wind up around the noose or in jail.</p>
   <p>The witnesses who testify for the defendant, and perjure themselves, will not find sympathy anywhere. No Jew will feel sad, or consider it as a Jewish question if the state prefers charges against and sentences a Jew for perjury.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0139.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Jews have always wanted the Jewish community to be pure and sacred and they have no desire to obstruct justice in its attempt to punish a Jewish sinner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
