<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-06-16">June 16, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Three Reform Groups Hold Meeting in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1548</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1548.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-06-16">June 16, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE THREE REFORM GROUPS HOLD MEETING IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many leaders of American Jewry, representing reformed congregations in all parts of the United States, convened here for the Council of the Union of American Hebrew Congregations. The meeting, which lasted through Thursday, was held simultaneously with the conventions of the National Federation of Temple Brotherhoods, and the National Federation of Temple Sisterhoods. More than 1,500 delegates attended the conventions of the allied organizations.</p>
   <p>At the meeting of the Union's Executive Board of which Ludwig Vogelstein of New York is chairman, approval was given to the appointment of Henry Morgenthau, former Ambassador to Turkey, and Robert P. Goldman, as members of the International Committee of Social Betterment recommended by the World Union for Progressive Judaism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1549.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Board also announced that the Manny Straus Propaganda Fund of $25,000 had been dissolved with Mr. Straus' consent, and would be used to defray the Union's debts.</p>
   <p>The Board approved the Hebrew Union College budget of $239,497 for 1933; and 1934, and voted a Union budget of $174,272 for the same years.</p>
   <p>THANK ROOSEVELT.</p>
   <p>Gratitude to President Roosevelt for his attitude of "sympathy for those Jews and others who are suffering under the present German administration," and, "abhorence at the return of medieval prejudices in Germany," were expressed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1550.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The message of thanks sent to the President also commended his leadership in "stemming the tide of depression," and said:</p>
   <p>"The Union of American Hebrew Congregations and its Sisterhoods and Brotherhoods in convention assembled, are happy to join in the practically universal sentiment of our country in congratulating you upon your patriotic, efficacious and successful efforts in stemming the tide of depression and restoring the confidence of the people in the stability, effectiveness and adaptability of our institutions, to meet and conquer any emergency - industrial, economic and financial.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1551.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Our country is indeed fortunate in having at this time a leader so energetic and capable, and one commanding the confidence of the whole people. Our organization pledges its earnest and whole-hearted support.</p>
   <p>"We are particularly grateful that in conformity to your love and justice and humanity, your administration has shown its sympathy for those Jews and others, who are suffering under the present German administration."</p>
   <p>THE THREE OFFICERS SIGN MESSAGE.</p>
   <p>The message was signed by Ludwig Vogelstein of New York, chairman of the Union's Executive Board; Mrs. Maurice Steinfeld of St. Louis, president of the National Federation of Temple Sisterhoods, and Charles P. Kramer of New York, president of the National Federation of Temple Brotherhoods.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1552.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. Vogelstein suggested to the 1,500 delegates that the Synagogue Council of America, formed by the Union two years ago, be made the organization to represent the opinion of Jews in America, both at home and abroad, on all questions affecting Jewish rights. The Synagogue Council is composed of representatives of the Orthodox, Conservative and Rabbinical bodies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
