<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1891-04-17">Apr. 17, 1891</date>, p. 138
<title level="a">Pessach</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1891-04-17">Apr. 17, 1891</date>, p. 138
<title level="a">PESSACH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is true enough that the festival is older than Israel's history and was celebrated as the birthday of the New Year's spring glory by the nations and tribes who never had intercourse with the sons of Jacob.</p>
   <p>It is the birthday of an idea which is sung in the hymns of the festal-tide, and it is the force undying of ideas which is projected into our wondering consciousness when the Pessach morning relates the old story of the pass-over from slavery to freedom.</p>
   <p>When the chains of Egypt fell from his hands, the son of Israel assumed the historical task to become the barometer of social pressure wherever he dwells, to be the acid searching whether the pretense of freedom is founded on reality.</p>
   <p>The Jew is the exponent of the degree of civilization attained by the world at large. Quarrel, if you will, with the powers that make the <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1442.jpg" n="2"/>world of facts. The fact does stand. The Jew has been destined to do this duty. He confronted and confounded the old Pharaoh; he does confront now the new, and he will confound him, too.</p>
   <p>The historical festivals unite in the spirit the dispersed sons of Judah. Whatever our differences, the festal seasons bring out the fact we have much in common. The most liberal Jew cannot as yet forego the inspiration of the days which stand for all Israel, symbols of the essential unity of the descendants of the shepherds who once upon a time tented in the Sinaitic peninsula and part of whom had ventured into Egypt.</p>
   <p>Among their number none is so gay with music, none so quick with elevating thought, none so chaste as is the annual birthday of Israel, the season of the glad springtide and the redemption of Israel from slavery - promise of that greater redemption which to bring about, Israel was sent on his pilgrimage; the redemption of man from the bondage of spiritual and moral thralldom.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
