<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-03-28">March 28, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1703</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1703.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-03-28">March 28, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Semi-Annual Conference of the Workmen's Circle opens Sunday, March 26, in Bacon Hall, 3039 E. 92nd Street.</p>
   <p>Friend Rosenblatt, of Branch 524, opened the meeting with a brief talk declaring that the conference should lay the foundation for peace in Workmen's Circle and more deputies should appear on account of Party-opposition. Friend Lambert of Branch 162, Chairman of the District Committee, called the meeting to order and turned to the agenda. Friend Blumenthal of Branch 306, was appointed Chairman. Friend Rosenblatt of Branch 433, was appointed Secretary.</p>
   <p>The following were appointed on the Credential Committee:</p>
   <p>Terr of Branch 127, Slavin of Branch 118, and Chadash of Branch 224.</p>
   <p>The Credential Committee reported that fifty delegates were present, representing twenty-five branches, and three delegates of the District Committee.</p>
   <p>Friend Benenson, Secretary, District Organization Committee, reported the activities of the District Organization Committee, and what it had done for Chicago and other branches. <!--5423972_8_1_1704 omitted, duplicate of 5423972_8_1_1703--></p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1705.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In conclusion, he said that the Workmen's Circle made no progress this year, due to the "Depression", unemployment, and opposition within its branches.</p>
   <p>At a second session, Mr. Benenson gave a report of the National Board of Directors. After speaking for two hours, he summed it up as follows:</p>
   <p>The W.C. contributed $22,000. worth of products to Russia. The report was approved, and the Conference thanked Benenson for his work.</p>
   <p>L. Rosenblum,</p>
   <p>Member of Kiev Branch, 433 W. Circle, Secretary of the Conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
