<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-12-04">Dec. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Jews, Catholics, and Protestants Assemble at Hanukah Festival to Preach Love and Tolerance Toward All Races</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1926-12-04">Dec. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">JEWS, CATHOLICS, AND PROTESTANTS ASSEMBLE AT HANUKAH FESTIVAL TO PREACH LOVE AND TOLERANCE TOWARD ALL RACES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Hanukah feast was served in the banquet hall of Kehilath Anshe Mayriv, the oldest Jewish Reform congregation in Chicago, last Thursday evening. The chief guests were the Catholic and Protestant representatives. It was a feast of "brotherhood" among the Jews and the Christians, and many compliments were exchanged.</p>
   <p>The Hanukah feast was arranged by the congregation of Kehilath Anshe Mayriv. Seventy Jewish guests were invited. Each guest was to bring a Christian friend who was introduced as "my best Christian friend". At the head of the table were seated both rabbis of the congregation, Tobias Schanfarber and Solomon [B.] Freehof; the Catholic priest, Father Joseph Reiner, dean of Loyola University; and the Reverend Ralph Davis, pastor of the Hyde Park Presbyterian Church. The feast lasted three hours. The clergymen praised the Jews in <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0444.jpg" n="2"/>their speeches, and the rabbis, in return, complimented the Christians.</p>
   <p>Reverend Ralph Davis, who was introduced by the president of Kehilath Anshe Mayriv as "our good friend and neighbor", gave a lengthy talk in which he said that we should no longer think in terms of the intolerant concepts of the Middle Ages. We should now live peacefully like brothers, respecting each other's convictions and working together in a mutually sympathetic and friendly manner. Then Father Reiner, dean of Loyola University, was introduced. He said that he preached intolerance, but that he was intolerant only toward the criminal, the immoral, and the home breaker. Rabbi Freehof ended his speech, the last of the evening, with these words: "How unimportant are the things that divide us, and how great are the things we have in common!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
