<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-14">Apr. 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Second Shot</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0974</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0974.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-14">Apr. 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE SECOND SHOT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The active and leading Keren Hayesod workers will gather this evening at the Congress Hotel at a banquet in honor of Mr. David Brown, who, as soon as he returned from Palestine, became absorbed in Keren Hayesod work. Mr. Brown has something of importance to say to the Keren Hayesod volunteers of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The city's Karen Hayesod drive begins with tonight's meeting. The drive aims to raise three hundred thousand dollars in cash from now until May 14. This sum, which is much bigger than the sum raised last year, must and will be raised, because the entire Keren Hayesod work in America would become demoralized if it is not raised. A successful beginning of this drive will bring in new life to the Keren Hayesod work in America and will have a tremendous influence upon the growth of this work east <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0975.jpg" n="2"/>and west of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Palestine can be built, maybe, without the couple of hundred thousand dollars which Chicago must give for the Keren Hayesod, but Palestine cannot be built without the Keren Hayesod work in America. The success of the Keren Hayesod work in America depends upon the success of Chicago, because Chicago is the capital of American Jewry, the capital of the Middle West.</p>
   <p>The Chicago workers should understand the heavy responsibility that rests upon them. They are not only responsible to the Keren Hayesod for the three hundred thousand dollars which must be raised here, but they are also responsible for the Keren Hayesod morale of America. They can either strengthen or weaken the morale of the Keren Hayesod workers. They can create enthusiasm or destroy it. They bear, to put it briefly, a big responsibility. They will begin to do their great work seriously and enthusiastically if they will only realize what a tremendous responsibility rests upon them. They will not seek to rest till the success of <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0976.jpg" n="3"/>the undertaking is assured.</p>
   <p>Three hundred thousand dollars is a big sum. When one considers, however, that there are in Chicago more Jews than in the whole of Lithuania, and that Chicago is numerically the second largest Jewish community in the world, then the quota of three hundred thousand dollars does not look so big. The field is big. Many Jews understand already what the Keren Hayesod is and they do not need much persuation. Many Jews have only heard about the Keren Hayesod, and the importance of the undertaking has to be explained to them. The work may be successful because all Jews want to help Palestine. The desire to work will assure its success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
