<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Building Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-27">Feb. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">BUILDING ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ed. Steinborn, architect, 111 North Dearborn Street, has completed plans for the remodeling of the premises at 3451 North Avenue into a modern restaurant and store building. The work will be done for Dave Motz, and the estimated cost is $30,000.</p>
   <p>S. I. Berger intends to remodel the seven-story building at 330 South Franklin Street at an estimated cost of $28,000.</p>
   <p>Moris and Storr intend to erect a commercial building at 3351 South State Street at an estimated cost of $6,000.</p>
   <p>The Weber Furniture Company intends to remodel its building at 200 South Wabash Avenue at an estimated cost of $30,000.</p>
   <p>Louis Skolnik, 1245 South Avers Avenue, intends to erect a thirteen-apartment <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0317.jpg" n="2"/>building at 4501-05 West Adams Street at an estimated cost of $75.000.</p>
   <p>Max Bath, 1320 North Robey Street, intends to erect an apartment building at 1820 South Central Park Avenue at an estimated cost of $18,000.</p>
   <p>B. Marks, 1517 South Millard Avenue, intends to erect a commercial building at 5435 Wentworth Avenue at an estimated cost of $8,000.</p>
   <p>Sam Handelsman, 4715 North Lawndale Avenue, intends to erect an apartment building at 4848-58 North Ridgeway Avenue at an estimated cost of $150,000.</p>
   <p>Albert and Bernstein, 10 South La Salle Street, intend to erect two apartment buildings: one at 5720 West Washington Boulevard at an estimated cost of $150,000, and the other at 4400 West Washington Boulevard at an estimated cost of $125,000.</p>
   <p>Fisher and Mann intend to erect a thirty-seven apartment building at 201-09 <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0318.jpg" n="3"/>North Central Avenue at an estimated cost of $200,000. Rubin and Eisenberg, 14 West Washington Street, are the architects.</p>
   <p>Herman Cohen, 3143 Eastwood Avenue, intends to build eleven two-story apartment buildings at 5104-34 North Avers Avenue at an estimated cost of $132,000.</p>
   <p>Cohen and Weinstein, 1123 South Kedzie Avenue, intend to erect a commercial building at 3007 North Kedzie Avenue at an estimated cost of $6,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
