<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-30">Apr. 30, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Fifty Thousand Dollars in Cash at the Synagogue Banquet for the Keren Hayesod</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_0944</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0944.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-04-30">Apr. 30, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTY THOUSAND DOLLARS IN CASH AT THE SYNAGOGUE BANQUET FOR THE KEREN HAYESOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over seven hundred and fifty Jewish men and women from all parts of Chicago attended the Zionist banquet given last night at the Capitol Building. Dr. Chaim Weitzman was the guest of honor. All members of the Rabbinical Association, excepting Rabbi [J. L.] Gordon, who could not be present on account of illness, attended this affair, which was one of the most beautiful and biggest in the history of the Jews of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the synagogues had with them at the banquet fifty thousand dollars in cash which the synagogues had raised for the Keren Hayesod. They promised that they would help raise the entire quota of three hundred thousand dollars which Chicago has to contribute this year to the great Keren Hayesod fund.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sam Ginsburg, president of the United Orthodox Synagogues of Chicago, was toastmaster of the evening. This Association arranged the banquet.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0945.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Ginsburg called upon Rabbi Ephraim Epstein to greet the guest of honor and the gathering in the name of the Association of Rabbis. Rabbi Epstein, in his speech, made a heartfelt appeal for the Keren Hayesod and won the public to the support of the fund with which Palestine is being built.</p>
   <p>Max Shulman, chairman of the Keren Hayesod, thanked the representatives for the honor they had rendered to Dr. Weitzman and for their participation in the Keren Hayesod drive. He then appealed to the synagogues for cash and the synagogues responded beautifully.</p>
   <p>Dr. Weitzman, when he arose to speak, was greeted with a big ovation, which lasted for a few minutes. In his speech, the Zionist leader thanked the Orthodox Jews of Chicago for the great interest they had taken in the Keren Hayesod and appealed to the American Jews to go and settle in Palestine. "It is the great duty of the American Orthodox Jews," said the Zionist leader, "to emigrate to Palestine and settle there, which will strengthen the Jewish spirit in the Holy Land."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0946.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The speech of Dr. Weitzman was a brilliant one. He painted the Jewish prospects in Palestine in bright colors. He concluded his speech by expressing the hope that the Orthodox synagogues of Chicago will march in front of everyone in their effort to raise Chicago's entire quota for the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <p>Dr. Weitzman's speech was applauded thunderously and the meeting closed under the strain of the "Hatikvah."</p>
   <p>The food was served by Shure Brothers, 1231 North Ashland Avenue. Cantor Manowich sang Jewish songs.</p>
   <p>The Hadassah [Chicago chapter of the Women's Zionist Organization of America] gave a luncheon yesterday afternoon at the Morrison Hotel in honor of Mrs. Weitzman. About one hundred women were present. Mrs. Berkman was chairlady. Mrs. Frederick Fetchheymer (a sister-in-law of the late Attorney Levy Meyer), who has just returned from Palestine, was the main speaker. She spoke <pb facs="5423972_8_1_0947.jpg" n="4"/>enthusiastically about Palestine and the settlements there.</p>
   <p>One thousand dollars for the Hadassah was raised by the women present. This women's organization has raised fourteen thousand dollars this year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
