<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-12-25">December 25, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Christmas in America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1507</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1507.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-12-25">December 25, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTMAS IN AMERICA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Throughout the entire country, as well as the entire Christian world, the birth of Christ - the man - God or God - man, is being celebrated today. The Jews of America are perhaps the only ones (Jews) who can dare comment upon this holiday.</p>
   <p>In Russia, for example, no one would dare to speak of or write about this......But the Jews obviously feel different in America. We are not afraid to walk freely about the streets. We did not fear a hostile enemy or wild revenge. On the contrary, we even forget that the holiday has anything to do with faith.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1508.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many Jews exchange Christmas gifts and do not think, at the time, that they are committing a wrong against Judaism. The word, Jesus Christ, which is so frequently used by the Christians in daily conversation in order to emphasize what they say and do, is as frequently used by the Jews, especially by the young Jewish generation. Should anyone ask a Jew, who is so enthused about exchanging Christmas gifts, why he forgets to celebrate Chanukah, pure Jewish holiday, and why he becomes animated with joy on Christmas, he will answer that the American Christmas is not a religious holiday, which caused so much blood and tears of Israel to be shed; on the contrary, Christmas is a social holiday, when good-will, between Jews and Christians is being created.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1509.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The opinion of many is that the Jewish instinct, the deep national and religious sentiment of the Jew, will protect him from every danger against Judaism. Christmas is no Jewish holiday as long as it is associated with faith and with hatred toward the Jews. Christmas is, however, a general holiday, in as much as it is a day for expressing sympathy and compassion of brotherhood and equality. The public, i. e. the world, is becoming more civilized and educated, and the qualifications of man is the principle factor today, but not the family, race, or religion to which man belongs. This is the opinion of many Jews.</p>
   <p>The majority of Jews can not, under any circumstances, approve such superficial thinking. They do not believe that Christmas became a non-religious holiday among the Americans. The name, alone, reminds them of the great abyss, that divides Christianity from the Jewish faith.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1510.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Consequently, it is no more than the superfluity of contentment and freedom - the lustre of generosity covers, with warm rays, the anti-Jewish sentiment, that Christmas awakens in all Christians throughout the entire world. The wide Jewish masses are, therefore, not unjustifiably opposed to celebrate this strict Christian holiday and therefore criticize and attack the Jews who take an active part in the Christian world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
