<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-06">May 6, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Hebrew Institute</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Speech of Mr. Jacob M. Loeb at the Yearly Gathering of the Hebrew Institute Members in the Standard Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_8_1_1213</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1213.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-06">May 6, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE HEBREW INSTITUTE</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Speech of Mr. Jacob M. Loeb at the Yearly Gathering of the Hebrew Institute Members in the Standard Club</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the World War and all its horrors, the activities of the Institute during the last year were very successful. It was visited as in normal years, and its work continued without a break. Interest in the Institute continued. Our income was the same as in previous years. The War itself probably indicated that the Institute is a useful and necessary factor in our communal life.</p>
   <p>Eight hundred of our young people have gone to War for Democracy. As far as we know, five of them fell as heroes in the field of action. Our service flag has many gold stars. Many of the youngsters have shown exceptional ability and have been rewarded with well earned promotions. Many were these promotions in the army and the navy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1214.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They are a credit to the Institute which had exerted its good influence on all.</p>
   <p>In the naval fleet on the Great Lakes, in the training camps, and at the Western Front our young men did their duty and we are proud of them. We have received thousands of letters from them. Superintendents, teachers and department heads have always received the same message:</p>
   <p>"We long first for our families, and then for the Institute."</p>
   <p>It is true, our influence is not exactly definable. In normal times we cannot tell definitely what it is. But now, in this crisis, it is revealed as something actual, solid, and definite, as something of importance to us.</p>
   <p>Our girls, too, have contributed their share. Four hundred of them <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1215.jpg" n="3"/>have devoted themselves to preparing and sending postcards, writing encouraging letters to soldiers and sailors, and buying Liberty Bonds and Thrift-Stamps. Tirelessly they gave their services to their country.</p>
   <p>These activities, new and astounding, have not interfered with their work at the Institute. Two hundred and fifty young men have already returned from the War. The girls, too, have returned from war to peace work-all with their interests still centered in their Institute. And they are performing interesting work at the Institute.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we must not forget they have no American tradition of a hundred years ago. Their parents did not come here on the Mayflower.</p>
   <p>They are children of immigrants, or are themselves immigrants, but <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1216.jpg" n="4"/>yet are patriotic Americans and can compare with patriotic citizens in their love for America. Much that they have learned, they received from the Institute, and a part of what they are, they owe to it. This, they know and acclaim openly. Through them, the Jewish community has profited even more from the Institute. This too, is acknowledged, but not to the extent as is shown by the young folks.</p>
   <p>There are still many who regard us rather skeptically; who judge us, though they know us not. Some believe we are harmless or superfluous. They tolerate us in their goodness. Others again believe we are a wasp nest of radicalism, perhaps only mislead, but still very dangerous, and are, therefore, angry with us. Do you wish my dear friends, to tell these people: "You do not know what the Institute is"? It is not a plaything or a shovelful of building material, though it is both <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1217.jpg" n="5"/>something very much alive and joyous, a moving force that instills and molds true human souls. It does not revive radicalism, but swaddles it, nor does it call to Bolshevism, but, actually makes it impossible. It does not honor anarchism, but destroys it. The Institute builds fine, growing, red-blooded Americans.</p>
   <p>You do not have to take our word for it. Examine our records, our accomplishments and then tell us if we were lazy or simply playing. Thus, you may tell your friends about the Institute.</p>
   <p>When you have done this, return to help us enlarge the Institute on a broader, more influential scale. It has often been suggested that the Institute needs a new home. The War, of course, has directed our attention from this problem. But, now, it is over, bringing victory, and we hope a lasting peace will be ours. An epic of rebuilding and <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1218.jpg" n="6"/>adjustment, now lies open before us. It will bring on very important problems that must be solved. In the solving of these problems the Institute may play a very important part which, of course, is to be expected.</p>
   <p>People everywhere are still groping in the dark, and cannot as yet see clearly into the future. There is much misunderstanding and doubt, that must be clarified.</p>
   <p>Somewhere there must be clear eyes, and a steady hand, to lead our people from the darkness to the light. There must be clear thinking to remove misunderstanding, and constructive, orderly forces to rescue an honest government and Democracy. The Institute was created for just such a purpose. The duties we accept will be very difficult <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1219.jpg" n="7"/>ones, we need, therefore, not only more and newer energies, but, also better materials and equipment. Thus, we wish to create the necessary means to erect a new home. We shall do so soon, very soon.</p>
   <p>There is much new work to be done. Three and one-half miles south west, lies the Lawndale district with a Jewish population of 80,000. Four and a half miles northwest is another Jewish district, with a population of 75,000. In both neighborhoods, the youth is in need of just such opportunities as the Institute can offer them. These are working spheres, from which they grow into good or bad citizens-all depending on whether the lands are well kept or neglected.</p>
   <p>The fields in which the seeds grow, so fruitfully, should continue to be sown, and to be fruitful. The officials and employees of <pb facs="5423972_8_1_1220.jpg" n="8"/>the Institute, must search for ways and means to realize the intensive cultivation of these fruitful fields. There is not another community in the country for which more interest and work has been done. Communities one-third our size, have met their cultural problems satisfactorily. In the Jewish neighborhoods of the Northwest side and Southwest side, nothing has as yet been done or even attempted. The fulfilment of this remarkable program is the task of the Institute and we need your aid.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
