<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-05-22">May 22, 1926</date>, p. 7
<title level="a">The Value of Matter.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-05-22">May 22, 1926</date>, p. 7
<title level="a">THE VALUE OF MATTER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago is not free from unsound minds. Among the Greeks (and maybe among others) we still find some remnants of Platonic philosophy, that, "Matter is worthless, and everything depends upon the mind, mind is all there is and the value of material things is nothing." Many volumes of books have been written upon mind and matter, and the sound mind of today knows and acknowledges the importance of matter.</p>
   <p>As an impartial exponent of truth and sanity I write these few lines, for the interest of all of us. There has been a time in the life of humanity when people were mentally and morally dwarfs, and would have been much disgusted with the present prevalent era.</p>
   <p>Upon their inability to think sanely, they turn and began to advocate and practice hate against matter, as a thing that beclouds the luminous potentialities of spirit or mind. This erroneous conception spread very much, due to the fact, that it was enhanced by Platonic philosophy that "matter is unable to move by itself."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1206.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This advocacy of Plato, that matter is an impediment to mind in acquiring wisdom, spread like wild fire upon the already abused mind of that period. The fanaticism was so great, that people began to torture the human body as an obstacle to spiritual and moral advancement.</p>
   <p>The Greek race in general, with the exception of a few scholars, did, and does acknowledge the value and importance of matter, and it was said: "Healthy mind is healthy body." Of course, the existence and progress of the human, race does not depend upon what one school of thought be advocated but upon what the many have advocated. The Greek remnants of Platonic philosophy in Chicago are not criticized for their advocacy, but they must be admonisted and given counsel. Their children, in going to school must have shoes and clothing, against the inclemency of nature, for they are not living in the tropical-like climate of Greece, where Plato expounded his anti-materialistic tendencies.</p>
   <p>("Opou en eikio topo ta theonta" means, "to do the proper things at the proper time."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
