<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1919-08-09">Aug. 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Capital, Labor, and the Middle Class</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-08-09">Aug. 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CAPITAL, LABOR, AND THE MIDDLE CLASS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One thing gives rise to another, and due to the increase in cost of the basic necessities of life, the laboring class is demanding a raise in wages. In order to obtain their demands, the workers have formed unions which will protect and fight for their rights. Therefore, organized capital, which had the worker more or less at its mercy, is now finding an opponent in organized labor. Fighting between the workers and capital has resulted in many deaths. Finally it has ceased and the workers are receiving more pay and are working fewer hours.</p>
   <p>Between the labor class and the capitalist class is the middle class, which is slowly being smothered to death.</p>
   <p>This group includes members of the professions, professors, artists, teachers <pb facs="5422062_2_0068.jpg" n="2"/>small businessmen, and all the white-collar workers. A Harvard professor has said "that while a streetcar conductor earns sixty cents an hour, a professor, who directs the thought of the future, gets eighteen cents per hour". How, then, can this unorganized group combat capitalism? Can they secure justice in the same way as did the laborers? Surely not!</p>
   <p>The capitalist prospers, and the laborer daily obtains more humane conditions; the middle class, however, pays the expenses for both of them, and does so meekly and without complaint. The increasing price of foodstuffs, which is due to exploitation, is the greatest danger to the middle class. As long as the government does not pass laws forbidding excessive prices and exploitation of the consumer, the middle class will continue to suffer.....</p>
   <p>We hope that the lawmaking bodies of this country will recognize this sad situation and pass laws to remedy it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
