<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-02-19">Feb. 19, 1930</date><title level="a">The Laziness of Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-02-19">Feb. 19, 1930</date><title level="a">THE LAZINESS OF WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When woman meets woman in church, at dances, meetings, or over the telephone, this is what you hear: "You know, I am so busy. What with my six-room apartment and the children, I don't have time for anything."</p>
   <p>Isn't it a shame! They shirk their duty and association with the progressive world by saying they have hard work to do. It is mere laziness!</p>
   <p>The newly married woman, the housewife, the mother--all say they are tired from keeping the house in order. With all the modern improvements and conveniences, does it tire one out so much to take care of an apartment, a baby and a husband? Did their husbands marry them to wash dishes and clean house? I thought they wanted wives not dishwashers.</p>
   <p>Some women take all day to clean house. They take a nap every hour or so. They begin reading a book in the middle of the morning, or gossip with <pb facs="5422062_2_1162.jpg" n="2"/>their neighbors for several hours. The end of the day finds them untidy, unpleasant and tired. They complain they have too much work to do.</p>
   <p>They have not learned to manage their homes that they may be cleaned up in a jiffy. They don't know the enjoyment one gets out of life when one's afternoons are free for any desired activity or amusement.</p>
   <p>In this particular, American women are far superior to Greek women. They take pride in their personal appearance, their homes and their families. We must learn to systemize housekeeping as they do, to cut most of our irksome duties in half, so as to find time for pleasure and relaxation.</p>
   <p>Stop grumbling about hard work and do something! All that is necessary is tenacity and a little liveliness. Don't grow old before your time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
