<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-07-20">July 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Woman Suffrage</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Place of Woman in the Society of Five Thousand Years Ago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-07-20">July 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WOMAN SUFFRAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Place of Woman in the Society of Five Thousand Years Ago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The idea seems to be prevalent that women's quest for rights and privileges in the political life and affairs of nations is a matter which has arisen only in recent years. The discovery of placques in Asia Minor, bearing inscriptions which were translated at the University of Pennsylvania, shows that women had equal political rights with the men in Asia Minor five thousand years ago.</p>
   <p>In addition, women were elected to the office of mayor and were appointed to many high public offices.</p>
   <p>Historically, it has been proved time and again that women like Cleopatra, the Queen of Egypt, combined political ability and shrewdness with exquisite beauty to subdue such men as Caesar and Anthony of Rome. By her ambition and <pb facs="5422062_2_1171.jpg" n="2"/>intellectual power Cleopatra forced Anthony to fight against Octavian Augustus.</p>
   <p>If Cleopatra had not fled with the Egyptian fleet in the ensuing naval battle at Actium, she would have undoubtedly become the world's greatest leader.</p>
   <p>But, did not ancient Greece, the mother of civilization, produce great women who occupy a conspicuous position in Greek history?</p>
   <p>The center of Greek civilization, the violet-crowned city of Athens, produced Pericles, and Pericles produced the Golden Age of Greece.</p>
   <p>Now, if we study history carefully and profoundly, we shall see that Pericles obtained his great ideas and ideals from, and was inspired by, his great companion, his wife: the Milesian and brilliant Aspasia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
