<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-01-05">Jan. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">War Savings Stamps and Certificates of the United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0786</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0786.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-01-05">Jan. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WAR SAVINGS STAMPS AND CERTIFICATES OF THE UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Your adopted country is at war. We must win this war. In order to win it, we must attain one of the most important objectives--money. This money must be contributed by the people of this country. In order to offer and lend this money to the government, and earn interest and invest safely at the same time, you must save. It is easier to save a small sum than a large one. In order that it may become possible for all of us in this country to save, a plan has been devised, whereby one can start with twenty-five cents, a quarter of a dollar.</p>
   <p>Stamps and Savings Certificates</p>
   <p>Buy a savings stamp for twenty-five cents and attach it to a savings certificate. This certificate is given to you when you buy a savings stamp. The certificate has blank spaces for sixteen such stamps.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0787.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As soon as you fill out a savings certificate, you can get a war savings deposit stamp. Then your money starts paying an annual interest of four per cent, payable at five different times during the year. You can earn this [war stamp] by buying these stamps (savings stamps) with cash. The value of these savings stamps differs, according to the time at which they are bought.</p>
   <p>During December 1917 and January 1918 it is four dollars and twelve cents; beyond this, the value of these stamps rises by one cent per month during 1918.</p>
   <p>The difference between a savings certificate, which represents four dollars, and the value of a war savings deposit stamp is paid in cash. In other words, if you buy a war savings deposit stamp in December 1917 or January 1918, you give a savings certificate and twelve cents in addition. In February 1918, you will pay thirteen cents, that is, you will be paying one cent per month from then on. This difference and increase represent the earned interest, <pb facs="5422062_2_0788.jpg" n="3"/>which shall be paid at a specified time. The time [of redemption] is set for January 1, 1923, when the government will pay five dollars for every such war savings deposit stamp.</p>
   <p>War Deposit Certificates</p>
   <p>On purchasing the first war savings deposit stamp, you will be given a war deposit certificate. This certificate has blank spaces for twenty stamps. You attach these stamps on this certificate, which, when filled, has a value of one hundred dollars, payable on January 1, 1923.</p>
   <p>What You Pay and What You Earn</p>
   <p>If you fill the twenty blank spaces of the certificate with stamps in December 1917, or in January 1918, it will cost you $4.12 for each stamp, or twenty times $4.12, that is, $82.40 for the whole certificate.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0789.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On January 1, 1923, the government accepts this certificate by paying one hundred dollars. This means that the holder of such a certificate makes a profit of $17.60 for the money which he has loaned.</p>
   <p>Cash Value</p>
   <p>In case you need cash, you can have it by presenting your war deposit certificate, either completely or partially filled. The government will pay you the value of your certificate in addition to interest of one cent per month for the war savings stamps on the certificate. A table of the cash value (of the stamps) is printed on the opposite side of each certificate. In any case, it is hoped that this (demand for cash) will come only in cases of great need.</p>
   <p>Where Stamps and Certificates Are Available</p>
   <p>You may purchase stamps and certificates at the post office, banks, loan companies, railroad companies, business firms, organizations, and at other <pb facs="5422062_2_0790.jpg" n="5"/>officially authorized places.</p>
   <p>Security</p>
   <p>Since the entire treasury of the United States is back of them, and since they will be redeemed in the aforementioned manner, depreciation of either the [war savings] stamps or the certificates is out of the question.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
