<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1913-11-15">Nov. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">War or Peace</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0947</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0947.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-11-15">Nov. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WAR OR PEACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From day to day Greek national affairs are taking a turn for the worse. The international situation in the Balkans, especially after the defeat of Bulgaria and Turkey by Greece, is becoming very critical.</p>
   <p>The signing of the peace treaties is merely a short respite from bloody wars, which may be resumed at any moment. Many lands and islands awarded to Greece, because ethnographically and historically they were genuine Greek territories, are being menaced and coveted by Italy, Turkey, and Bulgaria. Our people, the army, King Constantine, and Mr. Venizelos are determined to contest any contemplated seizure of Greek territory. The entire nation is determined to fight again for the preservation of its honor, integrity, and just claims.</p>
   <p>The Greek people of Chicago, who reflect the sentiment and desires of the Greek <pb facs="5422062_2_0948.jpg" n="2"/>people throughout America, are watching the developments in Greece with eager hearts. The Greek people of Chicago and of America in general, from whose bosom fifty thousand Greek soldiers have gone forth to fight, are waiting impatiently for the final solution of our national difficulties.</p>
   <p>While the Greeks of America are waiting for the favorable outcome of the nation's struggles, they are not remaining idle. Generous and magnanimous as usual, the Greek people of Chicago and other American communities have contributed great sums of money to finance our wars. At the same time, thousands of dollars are sent daily to our families and relatives and to our brothers in the army. Many thousands of our young men who have been called up are leaving for Greece daily, while those who are not yet trained for service are given two months to go to the barracks and begin training. Thus, new blood is being infused in the army.</p>
   <p>These are the duties of the Greek people of America in these critical times. In war or peace, each and every Greek in America must do the patriotic duty <pb facs="5422062_2_0949.jpg" n="3"/>which is imposed upon him. In war or peace, every man that is called must hasten to respond to the call of his country. Whether we be at war or at peace, every Greek in Chicago, every Greek in America, must think of returning to the sacred soil of our expanded country. Whether she be at war or at peace, the sons of Hellas must gather around our common and loving mother, Greece, so that all may share in her happiness as well as in her perils.</p>
   <p>We do not see any immediate danger of war in the next few days. Nevertheless, there is no doubt that within the next decade Greece will be involved in new wars. This is inevitable, since one half of the Greek race and the best portion of Greece is still sighing under the heel of two despicable tyrants. This is why--whether we are at war or at peace--every Greek citizen, not only in Chicago, not only in America, not only in Greece, but wherever he may be, must do his part to protect and preserve our country.</p>
   <p>Only thus will all our vital national problems be solved in our favor. Only thus will our great nation be happy and prosperous again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
