<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-02-02">Feb. 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Restaurants of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-02-02">Feb. 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK RESTAURANTS OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The subject under discussion is one that has always been of profound interest to me. I have written and spoken about it every time I have had the opportunity.....But I have not written about the problems of the Greek restaurant men of Chicago merely because of an egotistical desire to see my name in print.....</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, in an effort to keep from hurting my fellow countrymen, I have shut my eyes to their obvious deficiencies, and have spoken softly at times when only the blunt truth should have been said.</p>
   <p>But all individuals cannot possibly have the moral strength and the ability to analyze plain truths in their writings. Only such men as Clemenceau in his Free Man and Gavrilides in his Acropolis can write bare truths and make them <pb facs="5422062_2_1474.jpg" n="2"/>understandable and tolerable to all..... Moses was a great leader when he ascended Mount Sinai; but he became more admirable and greater in moral stature when he broke the tablets of the Ten Commandments over the heads of the unbelievers.</p>
   <p>Each time the press has dealt with the varied social problems confronting the Greek people, it has used a hypocritical, cowardly approach. We Greek journallists have endeavored to flatter and comfort the reader at times when our pens should have been used as cudgels. We have called him Omogeny [meaning of the same birth or one of us], and have told him he was doing well and was a superpatriot, without seeking to help him attain the status which we ourselves bestowed upon him.</p>
   <p>Let us return to the original subject. Immediately after the war, while I was editing a magazine, I happened to visit in Cleveland, Ohio. I was the guest of Mr. Philip Peppas, of the firm Peppas and Alex. He took me with him to the meeting of the American Restaurant Association. There, in that meeting, I heard <pb facs="5422062_2_1475.jpg" n="3"/>the doom of the Greek restaurant men pronounced.</p>
   <p>There was not even one Greek member of that organization, so there was no one to contradict or deny the statements made by various members. The Association has refused membership to Greek restaurateurs on the ground that the Greeks respect "quantity" rather than "quality".</p>
   <p>I returned to Chicago and wrote many articles in the magazine, playing upon the dangers and heartbreaks the Greeks were bringing upon themselves by continuing along the road of apathy and indifference, and by refusing to form themselves into a strong, unified body. Later, no longer having my own organ, I used the columns of the National Herald, the Daily, .....</p>
   <p>Now I seek to unburden myself again--this time bluntly and unsparingly. "History," says an English historian, "is a record of civilizations that have developed in adversity and died under the weight of their own fat. With success came softness and degeneration. The tragedy hidden in every success lies in the fact <pb facs="5422062_2_1476.jpg" n="4"/>that men simply will not keep their weapons polished in times of peace."</p>
   <p>The story of a nation can also be the story of an individual, because a group of individuals forms a nation. As individual units you have fought a hard battle to achieve economic security. You have conquered and have made marked and enviable progress not, however, as a result of planning and of thought, but as a result of chance and circumstance. You have forgotten that the days following the victory are more trying than those before the battle. And that is the greatest tragedy that can befall a human being. It is necessary that you attune yourselves to the spirit of the day. What was good and beneficial ten years ago has ceased to be of any value today. Each year brings new changes in thought, action, and attitudes.</p>
   <p>I know that no one cares to be told he is wrong. But each logical human being admits that to err is human, and that we are all apt to be wrong at some time or other. It is natural for men of our race to resent criticism of their actions and conduct. Let us remember, however, that although Lincoln dearly <pb facs="5422062_2_1477.jpg" n="5"/>loved his own plan, he appreciated the fact that Stanton often had a better one.</p>
   <p>Greek Press, Feb. 9, 1933.</p>
   <p>John the Theologian, who founded the Church of Ephesus, was in the habit of saying to his students each time he came before them, "My children, love one another." When he was asked why he kept repeating the same phrase over and over, he answered, "If my advice is taken, there is sufficient justification for the repetition".</p>
   <p>Basing my own actions upon this bit of philosophy, I, too, keep repeating a piece of advice to my fellow countrymen in the restaurant business: "Unite, organize yourselves--upon this does your salvation depend."</p>
   <p>Immediately after the war, this country underwent a great many changes in attitudes and customs. New thoughts and ideals swept through the business world.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1478.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>But, unfortunately, the Greek businessmen remained blind to the changes going on around them. No effort was made to assimilate the new concepts. To rid ourselves of this blindness, our eyes must be fitted with spectacles which our opticians are not in a position to prescribe. They can only examine the eye and remedy its defects. But our trouble is more deep-seated and harder to cure because it is in the mechanism called the "Mind".</p>
   <p>Your mental powers have diminished because yours was an undersized, undeveloped, pulpy brain, continually shrinking for lack of mental 'daily dozens'. Your minds need daily exercise if they are to function efficiently. The mind has to be educated just as do all the other organs of the body if it is to serve its purpose. You have let your mental faculties rust and deteriorate from lack of use. Your eyes have seen many things changing all around you, but they could not help you because "the mind commands and the senses or organs obey". You resemble the blind who walk in total darkness.</p>
   <p>"There is a sure cure for every ill and ailment," and in this case strong <pb facs="5422062_2_1479.jpg" n="7"/>determination and good judgment are needed if a cure is to be effected. So far, none of you have had either of these prerequisites, for the simple reason that you are not in step with the times. Such synchronization demands organization and systematic methods. In the midst of changed attitudes around you, you have remained stubborn and resistant. There is a decided resemblance between you and Rostand's rooster. You sit in your little stores and feel that you only have to crow a little to cause the sun of your success and security to rise in the heavens.</p>
   <p>And if someone who happens to have foresight enough to see the dangers ahead warns you and tells you to organize and to synchronize yourselves, he is looked upon askance. The truth disturbs the peace of your slumbers and the light hurts your eyes, so accustomed to darkness. Without being Mohammedans, you unwaveringly believe in kismet completely overlooking the advice of the ancient Greeks who said, "To achieve success use your mind and your hands".</p>
   <p>You have achieved certain possessions by virtue of chance or sheer luck; and an <pb facs="5422062_2_1480.jpg" n="8"/>indifferent attitude will cause them all to be taken from you. Most of you have spent from twenty-five to thirty years in America. Nevertheless, your line of thinking is no different now than it was when you sat on the front step of your native village home and meditated. The surrounding environment has not influenced you in the slightest degree. It does not seem as if you had spent twenty-five hours in this country.</p>
   <p>After all, of what benefit is the daylight to the blind? What difference does it make to the world if you have lived here twenty years or twenty minutes if you are in no way sensitive to your environment and are blind to golden opportunities? Someone once said, "A man can learn twice as much from defeat as he can from victory". Even this saying means nothing to most of you. None of you chose to learn when you were victorious and had power. Why don't you have sense enough to arouse yourselves now--when you are in grave economic danger?</p>
   <p>Circumstances at the time of your successes were calling in stentorian tones, <pb facs="5422062_2_1481.jpg" n="9"/>"Unity! Organization! Synchronization!" The same call is being made now, when you are on the brink of failure, and when business the world over is in a state of depression.</p>
   <p>Do you not realize the precariousness of your position? Remaining as you are now--unorganized and divided among yourselves--you are in no position to advance or even remain stationary. How can one win a battle against aeroplanes, submarines, and other modern instruments of warfare if he is armed with only a prehistoric club or some other outmoded weapon?</p>
   <p>Unless you do something drastic about this intolerable situation immediately the utterance of Gavrilides [an Athenian journalist] will become the inscription upon your tombstones: "Wake up, bedraggled Hellenism of America! You emigrated from your sunny fatherland to America--the land of opportunity. The main purpose thus far seems to have been: to labor at the hardest tasks which help <pb facs="5422062_2_1482.jpg" n="10"/>build the nation, to pay high rents and help the real-estate salesmen, and to sit idle, content with your lot, while the Jews become millionaires. And you shall pass on without having left a footprint of your existence upon the sands of time for the following generations to see."</p>
   <p>You must unite! Each drop of water flowing over Niagara is in itself incapable of generating power, but all the water drops falling together produce enormous quantities of power. That potential power causes towns and cities to grow. It creates light and energy and promotes industrial growth. This example, taken from Nature--which has no logic--should prove my oft-repeated contention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
