<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-05-17">May 17, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">To the Greek Business Men in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-05-17">May 17, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE GREEK BUSINESS MEN IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What will become of the proposed pure food bill, which is before the State legislature, is a matter of conjecture. The bill was amended so many times that it is doubtful if it passes both houses. Nevertheless, a warning is sent out to the Greek business men in Chicago and in the whole State. Those who wish to be in the good grace of the public, and for their own interest, must not wait for the passing of the bill but of their own invitation sell nothing but the best foodstuff whether it is ice cream, candy, or any other edibles.</p>
   <p>Special attention is directed to the Greek confectioners who cover the entire city, with their thousands of stores.</p>
   <p>Analine and other substances, used in the dye of sweets, have met with the public's condemnation. Perhaps analine may not convey injury to the human <pb facs="5422062_2_1219.jpg" n="2"/>organism, and government analysts in Washington may approve its use, however, public opinion is bitterly against analine and similar substances.</p>
   <p>A good, conscientious, and successful business man takes the welfare of the public to heart, and law or no law, he will not sell to the public something of injurious or dubious nature.</p>
   <p>The Star earnestly urges the Greek confectioners, for their own salvation and for the good of the Greek name, to personally supervise the making of ice cream, candies and things of that kind so that no analine is used by their employees, who may not be conscious of the public's disapproval of using injurious dyes.</p>
   <p>If a sudden death occurs to a young boy or girl and it is shown that the child ate ice cream, candies, or drank soda, the death will be attributed to the bad quality of the thing consumed, and the press of the city will <pb facs="5422062_2_1220.jpg" n="3"/>start a crusade against the Greek confectioners in general, with a disastrous result not only for the guilty one but for all the Greeks.</p>
   <p>It would be a good business principle, and at the same time very profitable, if those who do not use analine, make it known to the public by having conspicuous posters in their establishments. Not only would it increase business but would be a protection against unforseen dangers.</p>
   <p>Do it now before it is too late. Let the public know that your store uses no analine, or other injurious substances.</p>
   <p>Gain the good will of the public and do not give a hoot whether the pure food bill is passed, amended, or killed.</p>
   <p>A good business man never deceives the public. Be a good business man by serving the public honestly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
