<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-02-28">Feb. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Meatless and Wheatless Days.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0778</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0778.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-02-28">Feb. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MEATLESS AND WHEATLESS DAYS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The prosperity and the welfare of a country do not depend upon its revenues nor upon its gold mines nor upon its beautiful buildings, parks, and other things but upon the enlightenment of its citizens. Enlightened people unquestionably obey and respect the laws of their country.</p>
   <p>Our country right now is at war, and obedience to the laws is more necessary now for the welfare of the whole country than it is in time of peace. There is a federal law prohibiting the consumption of meat and of wheat on certain days of the week. All citizens must cooperate enforcing this law. It is the duty of every enlightened citizen to obey the law. The unenlightened citizen who breaks the law, which operates in the interest of the whole nation, must be and is punishable for his disobedience.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0779.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Out of four thousand Greek restaurant-keepers in Chicago there are a few who violate this law and consequently set a stigma upon all the Greeks in Chicago. Why should the rest of the Greeks suffer for this handful who are not up to the standard of enlightenment and good citizenship? Why should good Greek citizens be stigmatized on account of the unintelligence of delinquent Greeks? Unfortunately it is so. The good must suffer for the evil wrought by their brethren. These restaurant-keepers who violate the law of the country and cause other Greeks to suffer for their misdoings cannot and will not go on indefinitely violating this war-time regulation without unpleasant consequences. The far-reaching arm of the Government will eventually reach them put them where they rightfully belong. They think that they are smart to display very conspicuously their Libery Loan certificates and other similar evidence of war-contributions and on the other hand to break the law of the land.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0780.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Of course their patrons, who eat meat and wheat on prohibited days, are just as guilty as the restaurant-men, but right now we are dealing with the restaurant-keepers; the accusation and trial of the patrons will come later.</p>
   <p>The Greek-American Restaurant Association will do an honor to its name and a great service to the country by rooting out these rascals and letting the ax of the law fall where it may. People who are against the Government are enemies of the country. And a Greek cannot be a good citizen when he buys Liberty bonds and war-savings certificate and obeys certain laws and then violates other laws. A good citizen, an enlightened citizen obeys all the laws of his country.</p>
   <p>Before it is too late, it will be wise for these few Greek restaurant-keepers to put an end to their dishonest practices and obey the law of the land.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
