<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1919-09-29">September 29, 1919</date>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1015</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-correspondence"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1015.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1919-09-29">September 29, 1919</date>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Merchants of Hellenic Descent:</p>
   <p>The Achaian League, in carrying out its objects and purposes, again calls on all unnaturalized Hellenes to become American citizens.</p>
   <p>There is at this time a national movement on foot to Americanize all aliens. Numerous organizations are interested in the movement, but The Achaian League is the only organization that can reach the Hellenes directly, as its membership is composed of Americans of Hellenic descent.</p>
   <p>Every effort should be made to have all alien Hellenes become American citizens without delay, so that they may aid in overcoming the prejudice now existing against them because of their failure to become citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1016.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That such prejudice exists cannot be denied. To illustrate, attention is called to a news item recently published in one of Chicago's daily papers, referring to the invasion of alien proprietors of lunch rooms, grocery stores and ice cream parlors. In part the article said, "We wouldn't have the slightest objection if they would take out citizenship papers and conform to American standards. If they would do that, we would welcome them like any other business men, etc."</p>
   <p>Again the Chicago Tribune recently quoted a public speaker as having said: "There are 2,800 restaurants and lunchrooms in Chicago, and over 30% are conducted by aliens who never have applied for citizenship. Unless the public is aroused, etc." The Achaian League resented the attack, so far as it concerned the Hellenes, but there must be some reason for this apparent prejudice, and we believe it is due to the lack of interest of Hellenes in public affairs and their failure to promptly become American citizens. If you desire copies of the articles referred to, and the reply of The Achaian League thereto, same will be sent to you on request.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1017.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Achaian League will render all necessary aid to aliens of Hellenic descent in the filing of declarations of intention to become citizens of the United States, and in obtaining final citizenship papers where such declarations of intention have already been made.</p>
   <p>If you are the employer of any aliens you have not yet filed their declarations to become citizens, or if you know of any such aliens, we appeal to you to have them become American citizens.</p>
   <p>Ask them to come to our headquarters and we will assist them.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>A. A. Pantelis,</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
   <p>The Achaian League,</p>
   <p>Anthony C. Coorlim,</p>
   <p>President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
