<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-14">Sept. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">[Dissatisfaction]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0996</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0996.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-14">Sept. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">[DISSATISFACTION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only thirteen years ago Turkey and Greece were engaged in a death grapple in Asia Minor. Five hundred years of constant fighting between the two peoples ended in the expulsion of the Greeks. At that time it seemed as though a new antagonism between the two races would arise. Two days ago, however, Premier Tsaldaris of Greece and Premier Ismet Pasha of Turkey signed a ten-year Turko-Greek amity pact, guaranteeing reciprocal frontier security against aggression. The enemies of yesterday are the friends of today--a sure proof that no difference exists between peoples; for hatred is psychological and not biological.</p>
   <p>Long before the New Deal was formulated and the administration appealed to the country to rally around the Blue Eagle, this column contended that sooner or later a situation would arise--in the form of strikes--which would bring about open strife between employer and employee. That state <pb facs="5422062_2_0997.jpg" n="2"/>of affairs seems to be at hand now. Everywhere we see picketing, crowds assembling, and police dispersing them. As a result of General Johnson's explanations regarding the NRA in its relation to employer and employee, each side feels that the NRA is protecting its interests.</p>
   <p>The employer dreams of an open shop; and the employee of minimum hours of labor with maximum pay.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
