<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-10">July 10, 1929</date><title level="a">The Law on Communism--By K. Benizelos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0404</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0404.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-10">July 10, 1929</date><title level="a">THE LAW ON COMMUNISM--BY K. Benizelos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the communistic party follows the leads of the 3rd International, accepting inspiration and checks outside of the dominion, from Moscow and come not to reveal theoretical communistic ideas, but to organize the means needed for enforcing and strengthening any overthrow they are planning; it has the status quo of an infant when left alone to feed and preserve itself.</p>
   <p>This is the substance of the situation, as someone said, and from this knowledge, the Government asks you to vote this law, believing that your votes will be of the utmost use, because up till today all governments realize that if we don't turn communistic energies away from governing bodies, business will be at a standstill.</p>
   <p>We must prevent this! We must refer these injustices to the courts. That is the course we are pursuing. You tell me our future is not in peril. I believe that--but it isn't possible for a self-respecting duty--conscious Government to stand aside every time a strike occurs and watch the communistic factors intervene and push the workers into differences which will result in riot and bloodshed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0405.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is my belief that the Communistic Party is an enemy to the working class. Whenever a strike occurs, the Communists are always there doing their best to ensnare workers and employers, seeing how many victims they can add to their lists. We all know that and that is what is behind every strike.</p>
   <p>We know very well that this party receives orders from outside and has no other purpose than to cause a split between employer and employee and their joy is unbounded if a strike fails and the workers return to their jobs, discouraged and with bitterness in their hearts. These are the reasons we want your vote on the Communistic Bill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
