<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-11-15">Nov. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The White-Slave Traffic</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-11-15">Nov. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE WHITE-SLAVE TRAFFIC</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>White-slave traffic is a social tragedy.</p>
   <p>White-slave traffic is trade in the gutter. We are dealing with this subject in a rather comprehensive way because Saloniki is issued too infrequently to enlighten the public more fully.</p>
   <p>The term "white slavery" was first used in London, England; it referred to the transporting of young women abroad for commercial purposes. Today, the term has lost its original meaning and is applied both to those girls who are corrupted forcibly and to those Magdalenes who are living in sin.</p>
   <p>The city of Chicago has begun to hunt down and relentlessly prosecute those who are responsible for this grave social evil. The moral corruption of most of our young girls is attributed 1) to the lack of a proper home environment; 2) to the <pb facs="5422062_2_1053.jpg" n="2"/>lack of a Christian education; 3) to luxurious living; 4) to obscene motion pictures; 5) to disrespect for married life; 6) to the avoidance of child-bearing; 7) to the operators of houses of prostitution. This disease is like a devouring fire, which is undermining the very foundations of our social structure.</p>
   <p>The Greek community as a whole is not at all responsible for the serious proportions which white-slave traffic has reached in Chicago. We are sorry to note, however, that an alarming number of Greeks are being arrested of deported from Chicago for engaging in this cursed business.</p>
   <p>Thus, the Greek name is brought into serious disrepute because the people of Chicago are so violently prejudiced against the tragedy of white-slave traffic. The laboring element among our people of Chicago has been directly affected by the professional promoters of white-slave traffic and by the houses of ill fame. Many are condemning the laboring class for the increasing and flourishing business of white-slave traffic. The real victims of this whole rotten business are <pb facs="5422062_2_1054.jpg" n="3"/>these very workers who are so unjustly accused of contributing to this abominable evil.</p>
   <p>Why not blame the professional exploiters of innocent and helpless young girls? Why not punish the owners and operators of the numerous houses of prostitution?</p>
   <p>We will take the opportunity to touch once more upon the subject of white-slave traffic when we deal with the labor problem of the Greek people of Chicago, because in some strange way both social problems have some important connection with each other.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
