<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-10-23">Oct. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Bulgaria's Treason</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0877</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0877.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-10-23">Oct. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">BULGARIA'S TREASON</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Lincoln said, "You may fool all the people some of the time; but you can't fool all of the people all the time." Bulgaria did fool all the people for some time, but she is fooling them no longer.</p>
   <p>Bulgaria is the only Balkan State that does not owe her independence, her liberty, and her political aggrandizement to herself. Others fought for them and still others financed them. Russia, time and again, spent hundreds of thousands of roubles and sent thousands of muzhiks (Russian peasants) to help in the liberation of the most barbaric tribe in Southern Europe.</p>
   <p>Great Britain helped Bulgaria to become greater in 1876--when British diplomacy was strongly anti-Russian--believing that Bulgaria could hinder the Pan-Slavistic <pb facs="5422062_2_0878.jpg" n="2"/>tendencies of Russia.</p>
   <p>Austria-Hungary, on the other hand, was also playing up to Bulgaria because she thought that Bulgaria could open the road to Salonika for them.</p>
   <p>King Ferdinand, considered the most astute of the present Monarchs, and by far the most ambitious took advantage of every opportunity that the antagonistic policies of the three mentioned countries afforded him; and he played his game with dexterity and without scruples. He fooled Kaisers and Czars alike, one at a time, until he pushed the game too far; and now he can fool no one.</p>
   <p>Treacherous Bulgaria! There is nothing new under the sun. The history of the last Balkan war is only two years old; and only those who refuse to admit what they know to be true, can refrain from calling Bulgaria, treacherous.</p>
   <p>The Russians know of their little cousins' lack of honor and their perjurous instincts. The British had, at least, one opportunity to judge the value of <pb facs="5422062_2_0879.jpg" n="3"/>Bulgaria's gratitude, and that was during the Boer War. Yet for reasons of far greater importance, these shortcomings were willingly forgotten. The English press magnified temporary advantages gained by the Bulgarians during the first Balkan War into great victories; and minimized the Bulgarian atrocities.</p>
   <p>Bulgaria, today, is more treacherous than she was two years ago. During the war against Turkey, Serbia saved Bulgaria. A few months later she turned all her guns, without reason or warning, upon her former allies, and lost in a fair struggle. If Bulgaria lost she ought not to blame anything but her insatiable ambition to become, at the expense of all her other allies--the predominant factor in the Balkans.</p>
   <p>Bulgaria, today, is trying to regain her lost prestige. She offers to bargain for giving her assistance in the present struggle, and she goes from one door to another offering her military power at auction; without any sentiment or feeling of gratitude.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0880.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Bulgaria has no sense of gratitude, and yet is not entirely to blame for her actions. The powers--that kept the Greek, Serbian, and Rumanian armies from entering Sofia in 1913 and abolishing the most selfish misrule--cannot but regret, now, their liberal support of the most selfish, ungrateful nation on earth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
