<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-02-21">Feb. 21, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Halsted Street Can Regain its Former Activity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1423</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1423.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-02-21">Feb. 21, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">HALSTED STREET CAN REGAIN ITS FORMER ACTIVITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since our offices are located in the center of the Greek neighborhood of Chicago, and since we have lived all of our years in the midst of Greek people and commodities....it is only natural that we should take an active interest in all that is Hellenic. We believe, as do many others, that Hellenism will continue to live in Chicago as long as the "Little Greece" of Halsted Street survives.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the fate and plight of this neighborhood or community is of major interest to most of us.</p>
   <p>This community is regarded as characteristically Greek because Greek stores as well as Greek people can be found there in abundance. People of our <pb facs="5422062_2_1424.jpg" n="2"/>nationality come from all parts of this great city to shop here, where they can buy those commodities without which a Greek's life is incomplete. This insures a certain amount of security for the Greek Halsted Street merchants.</p>
   <p>However, we all know that they could do much better if they systematically tried to win more customers. This cannot be successfully accomplished through the efforts of one or two individuals. Co-operation and co-ordination are the keys to that success.</p>
   <p>These can be simultaneously acquired through the formation of a merchants' chamber of commerce. Such an organization was started a few years ago by the Halsted Street Greek businessmen. In the beginning it was conducted systematically and methodically. Before the year was up it began to show evidence of lethargy and indifference in the conduct of its affairs. Today <pb facs="5422062_2_1425.jpg" n="3"/>it is an organization in name only, for it completely ignores its program of purpose and activities.</p>
   <p>Now with the boom period for Greek stores rapidly approaching--Lent and the Easter holidays--this is the best time for a combined effort on the part of the merchants to awaken this organization and force it to function. If this is done, Halsted Street can regain its former prominence and prosperity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
