<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-06">April 6, 1931</date> p. 1.
<title level="a">To the Greek Voters of Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-06">April 6, 1931</date> p. 1.
<title level="a">TO THE GREEK VOTERS OF CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A leaflet, issued by an organization whose name we omit, has been arranged in a similar way to the one issued by the Greek-American Division of the Democratic Party.</p>
   <p>In the Republican leaflet we find, on one side, the statement that Thompson recognizes, The Greeks; and on the other side, the contention that Chicago has a real and sincere American Mayor in the person of William Hale Thompson. I am wondering how these deceived Greek-Americans can explain this stand of Thompson before the naturalized citizens, when he says, "I am a native American citizen. My rival is a big Bohemian, who came from Bohemia, and ought to be sent back where he came from."</p>
   <p>Do these deceived Greeks know that if one from among them was to put up as candidate for Mayor, he would be called by Thompson, a Greek peddler, who ought to have been sent back where he came from? Do they know that the majority of Greek-American merchants are compelled to pay, everyday, tax to the City Hall machine, and the exploiters that are connected with it?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0373.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If those deceived Greeks have selfish interests to serve, we can forgive them presupposing that self-preservation is the first law of nature, but, if they are interested in their adopted city, the country that recognizes neither race nor creed, where all are welcomed, and where Americanism invites all to prosper, their conduct is inexcusable, and the only thing we can do is to forgive them, "For they know not what they do."</p>
   <p>Our social dignity, the good name of Chicago, the people's interests, cry out stentoriously: "Get rid of Thompsonism, the Exploiters, and all evils that go with them. Save Chicago." Make the World's Fair a success, and reward the consciencious and capable public servants by electing Anton Cermak, Mayor of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Achaeans Association recommends to its friends, A.J. Cermak.</p>
   <p>The Achaeans Association</p>
   <p>A.A. Pantelis, President.</p>
   <p>(Full)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
