<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-05-14">May 14, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Wars and Revolutions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0619</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0619.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-05-14">May 14, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">WARS AND REVOLUTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before the revolutionary movement in England was averted, the news reached us that a revolution had broken out in Poland. If we examine the internal situation of Serbia and Roumania, we shall see that these nations are not far from revolution either.</p>
   <p>If we consider the internal situation of the various nations, we shall conclude that a deep uneasiness prevails everywhere.</p>
   <p>It is generally believed that this situation results from the World War, the wounds and miseries of which humanity has not yet succeeded in healing.</p>
   <p>This explanation seems to be justifiable, and many are satisfied with it. We should notice that the same uneasiness prevailed before the war the same fear and uncertainty about the future, particularly dread of the outbreak of the World War for which every one had been preparing for years.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0620.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Consequently, this uneasiness, this fear, these internal disturbances and revolutionary movements are not the result of the World War, to which they are generally attributed, but are due to the fact that humanity was not benefited by the war, and the same conditions which existed before the war still exist and continue to trouble it.</p>
   <p>This anomaly and these fears of new wars and internal disturbances and revolutions will continue until the more fundamental causes are removed and business is regulated to satisfy completely the needs of the working people.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
