<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-05-05">May 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Monster in Human Form</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0849</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0849.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-05-05">May 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A MONSTER IN HUMAN FORM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American papers printed an article saying that a Greek in a well-known meeting place took the most sacred symbol, the American flag, and viciously tore it to pieces.</p>
   <p>Oh, the beastliness of you--you viper! Oh, the greatness of your baseness! Oh, the unheard-of ingratitude of you towards this great and holy country of freedom, safety, and refuge, which welcomed you with open arms! Arms which probably have prevented you and your children from living in semi-slavery and darkness in some other land.</p>
   <p>You dared to be disrespectful, and by your filthy actions you have imperiled all of us, and we are ashamed of calling you a fellow countryman. You have besmirched all of us by your dirty deed.</p>
   <p>You criminal! You desired to jeopardize the security of thousands of Greeks <pb facs="5422062_2_0850.jpg" n="2"/>who live in this land; and who are thankful and joyful because they are allowed to do so. You tried to wreck thirty years of understanding and trust which has been created by progressive and responsible Greeks. You evidently desire to have the trouble in Omaha re-enacted. [Evidently referring to some trouble which occurred between the Greeks and some Americans a short time previous to this date.]</p>
   <p>But you are not alone; another beast had the temerity to insult the President by his loud indecent remarks. However, he was punished by some individuals who felt that he really deserved hanging by the neck.</p>
   <p>Shut up, you beasts! Do not dare to dirty the Greek honor by saying that you are Greeks. The Greek soil has never given birth to such monstrosities. Luckily, you and your kind are numbered, and will soon be punished for your actions.</p>
   <p>Then you will realize how ungratefulness is punished and how great is the strength of this country. Her laws--which have no eyes--can see; her laws--which have no ears--are capable of hearing; her laws--which have no tongue--can <pb facs="5422062_2_0851.jpg" n="3"/>speak. These laws have arms which can reach out and grab the offenders of this country's honor.</p>
   <p>The time has come, and the command has been given; it remains only for action to be taken, which shall show you what you should be and what you are!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
