<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-05-08">May 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Medical Quack</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-05-08">May 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A MEDICAL QUACK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Up to now various roving thieves and unsuspected "salesmen" have often sold hot air, pamphlets, or fraudulent mining stocks to the Greek people of our community, and thus have cleverly picked the pockets of our poor workers. Naturally, they cannot stay in one town or city for any length of time. They travel from state to state and sometimes take advantage of our common nationality; at other times they use our faith and church; and at all times they exploit the credulity and the traditional hospitality of our people to defraud the latter of their money, the product of their sweat and hard labor.</p>
   <p>For some time now, several notorious charlatans and medical quacks, who know nothing whatsoever about medicine, have appeared in Chicago. With their well-known methods, they pretend to know how to treat and cure any illness or disease. They are especially adept at using their surgical skill on the pocketbooks of many of our simple--minded and unsuspecting people. In addition, they are a menace to the very life of the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1210.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The name of a particularly dangerous charlatan and quack, who has been among us several times, is George Gioupis. Six months ago this "medical wizard"; having smelled America's attrative and abundant dollars, arrived at Washington, D. C. from Thessaly, Greece.</p>
   <p>Here he began to build up a profitable practice by announcing that he was a member of the famous and historical family of the Gioupis of Sparta, Greece--a family which has for many years given to our fatherland a great number of celebrated doctors. It is needless to inform our readers that this shameless character has no relation whatever with that distinguished family. His record in Washington proves that he is a worthless fake.</p>
   <p>Four months ago, he came to Chicago, and sought to establish himself here as a professional practitioner of medicine. Immediately, Saloniki asked him to produce his doctor's diploma, but he contended that he had secretly left his home in Greece in great haste, after having become estranged from his wife; therefore, he said, he was unable to take his diploma with him. He said, <pb facs="5422062_2_1211.jpg" n="3"/>however, that Messrs. Polimeris and Rigas, New York City restaurateurs, come from his home town and that they can supply us with the necessary recommendations.</p>
   <p>Certainly, the editor of Saloniki cannot ask Messrs. Polimeris and Rigas for Gioupis' diploma, because, in spite of their honesty and integrity as well-known restaurant owners, they have no right to issue medical diplomas.</p>
   <p>Fortunately, the quack Gioupis became so exasperated that he disappeared from, Chicago in a short while. However, he did not fail to leave some trace of his brief stay in Chicago, for he found the opportunity to use his art on a few trusting souls.</p>
   <p>We now hear that our friend has been arrested in Minneapolis, Minnesota, for performing an illegal operation on a Greek woman, who is in a critical condition. Having somehow been released, however, he is now wandering through the towns of Iowa looking for new victims.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1212.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This paper wishes to warn its many hundreds of subscribers in the State of Iowa to beware of this dangerous imposter, and we ask them to keep us informed as to his whereabouts so that the public may be protected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
