<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-05-09">May 9, 1918</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">L. Choromokos and the Liberty Loans a Splendid and Unique Idea.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0701</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0701.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-05-09">May 9, 1918</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">L. CHOROMOKOS AND THE LIBERTY LOANS A SPLENDID AND UNIQUE IDEA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greeks of Chicago be they friends of his or not, must be proud of the activities and patriotism of Mr. Louis Choromokos, who is one of the pioneers of the Greek community in Chicago, His name is associated with everything good in the annals of the Greek-American community. If it is philanthropy, education, generosity, enlightenment, church patriotism, or any other good thing, Louis Choromokos is on the front line in full panoply to bring results. That is Louis. Everybody knows and esteems the old boy. Why? Because he is real and true. What he does (he does) methodically, sincerely, and well. Here is what the Liberty Loan Shrapnel, a government publication for Cook County, says of Mr. Choromokos:</p>
   <p>We have heard of all kinds of psychological method applied to Liberty Loan sales, but Mr. L. Choromokos, who sells Liberty bonds by mail, has something new and unique. His letters, signed"I Sell Liberty Bonds," with his picture printed on one of the four corners of the letterhead have brought incredible results. Thousands of such letters were mailed, and the psychological response was tremendous.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0702.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Loxias note: Those who for one reason or another resent Mr. Choromokos's popularity must take a lesson or two of his ingenuity. He is a wonder; he brings home the bacon. He is not a piker; he outwits everybody. He is a credit to us all. Bravo, Louis, old boy! The country needs more of your type.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
