<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-04-20">Apr. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Here Again We Are Called by Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-04-20">Apr. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HERE AGAIN WE ARE CALLED BY DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Again the bell of liberty rings, calling the children of the United States of America to duty. We need money, say the leaders and official political heads of this country; without it we can do nothing.</p>
   <p>We are all called upon to contribute whatever we can afford--as did the widow of whom we spoke yesterday [last week]--with gladness and joy, for both our mothers [America and Greece] demand this. Our two beloved mothers are struggling desperately and bravely with mutual adoration and support, as the hens do when, in order to protect and save their young chicks from being killed by the furious storm, they gather the little ones under their feathers. One of these mothers in our parable is Greece, our first love, our mother country; the other one is America, our kind, foster parent.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0725.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are Greeks by birth and descent, but Americans by choice and domicile. We have a two-fold sacred interest in being Americans, directed toward the same common goal. We have Greek blood in our veins, but we also have American stamina and fortitude based on the fact that we are given limitless opportunities and a wide scope within which to expend our energies and give full expression to our abilities and genius.</p>
   <p>For both these heritages and gifts we are justly proud and immeasurably happy; in our pride, as Greeks, we do not spare anything to justify them. Lo! the hour of danger has come, the greedy and bloodthirsty foe threatens to destroy everything by iron and fire. The danger alarm is sounding, inviting all faithful and true children from everywhere to rally in the defense.</p>
   <p>Some are rushing to swell the ranks of the army and navy, ready to sacrifice their lives for their country engaged in struggle; others, who have not been favored to be called directly in the military services, are asked to contribute <pb facs="5422062_2_0726.jpg" n="3"/>their material support. All, everyone, are now summoned to fight for "hearth and altar," for our own safety.</p>
   <p>If we think that this necessity, this obligation is sacred and inevitable for the native-born, those who are not immediately threatened by the barbarous foe, but who are fighting with the inspiration of noble ideals and principles for the vindication of justice, how are we to regard this same obligation, for which they gave up comfort and a peaceful life in order to go to the battle-fields of Europe to fight for our safety and spare us the dreadful experience of becoming enslaved? We are truly in danger of slavery and degradation if Kaiserist Germany and Hun atrocities are successful and victorious. We have the same obligation to serve, to fight, to be motivated by the same ideology, and be ready to defend it. It is a holy obligation; it is a patriotic duty. And is there any more glorious sacrifice than for one's country?</p>
   <p>Has love for country been better expressed than by our great ancestors, the heroes of Marathon, Salamis, Themopylae, and Periclean Greece, who proclaimed:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0727.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"The country is holier, more deserving of honor and reverence than father or mother, or all the ancestors; and it is held in incomparably higher esteem by the gods and men who have reason"?</p>
   <p>What shall we profit if we preserve all our treasures, when we lose our country?</p>
   <p>Can we really be masters and possessors of anything when we lose our freedom and our country is put under the weighty yoke of a humiliating subjugation, especially under the yoke of the Huns?</p>
   <p>Is there any more valuable and precious treasure than liberty, thanks to which we can think freely, and consequently decide and act in such a way that anything can be accomplished?</p>
   <p>Who can deny that, given the indispensable presupposition of freedom, anything can be accomplished, while by submission and suppression all is lost?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0728.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Who can deny that the individual is part of the whole, and that the former is less than the latter? Therefore, who will spare the individual or the component part, when he is certain to save and win the whole, the group?</p>
   <p>There is where our interest lies, and this is what is recommended by our leaders and those who are masters of our fate. It is asked to dispose of the part to save the whole. The most remarkable observation is that it is not demanded that we give part of our wealth and resources, but to loan that part of our money which we can afford to invest, in order to secure and protect our material and general interests.</p>
   <p>By whom is this asked? By the one to whom all belongs and from whom everything flows in great abundance. After all these blessings, who can deny help?</p>
   <p>With such thoughts our government has the courage to issue the Third Liberty Loan bonds, to the subscription of which it calls upon all to come with a <pb facs="5422062_2_0729.jpg" n="6"/>willing heart.</p>
   <p>Onward then, let us take part in this sacred loan, which is being launched for the safety of our two countries and ourselves, and let us exclaim in stentorian voice that we are standing here ready to sacrifice our all, to destroy the barbarian and save ourselves!</p>
   <p>Let us go to the banks and savings vaults with hands and pockets filled with money, which we earned with the freedom and blessings of this land; let us buy the sacred papers of the Liberty Loan. These papers are United States Government bonds, which secure our wealth, guarantee our freedom, and constitute a good investment.</p>
   <p>The purchaser of Liberty bonds is an honorable and a true patriot, while he who is indifferent and refuses to make any offer is considered dishonorable and countryless.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0730.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Let us all, in this great city, march forward and do our duty, giving succor and adding strength to our two imperiled countries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
