<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1914-02-07">Feb. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks of Chicago Honor Mr. George Knapp</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0933</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0933.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-02-07">Feb. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS OF CHICAGO HONOR MR. GEORGE KNAPP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A dinner in honor of Mr. Knapp, a prominent journalist with the Chicago Journal and a great friend of the Greek people, was given last Wednesday by the Greek-American Political Club.</p>
   <p>Mr. James Manousopoulos, our prominent and well-known businessman in the Greek community, together with a committee of other leading Greeks, had prepared the dinner program. Many American newspapermen, bankers, and businessmen were invited to attend.</p>
   <p>Our people are happy to grasp this opportunity to honor Mr. Knapp, to express their everlasting gratitude and to extend to him due recognition for the voluntary support and the sympathy which he has offered the Greek people in general on many occasions.</p>
   <p>Mr. Knapp has written several articles in the Journal lately in connection with <pb facs="5422062_2_0934.jpg" n="2"/>the attempt of the Bulgarians of Chicago to defame the character of the Greek people in Chicago and to accuse the Greek government and army of horrible massacres and atrocities in Macedonia and Thrace during the recent Balkan wars. This true friend of the Greeks has denied these malicious accusations, which are especially frequent in the Bulgarian press of Chicago. In an article in the Journal entitled, "The Balkan Question Again," he writes in part as follows: "....Since a group of yellow journalists and misinformed sentimentalists is working day and night to whitewash Bulgaria and blacken the reputation of all other Balkan states, especially that of Greece, the Journal desires to state once more:</p>
   <p>"That Greece and Serbia did not attack Bulgaria; Bulgaria attacked these two countries in the most shameful and treacherous manner, and got properly thrashed for it.</p>
   <p>"That there is no first-hand evidence of cruelties committed by Greek troops, whereas there is a mountain of such evidence concerning the villainies of Bulgarians."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0935.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greek people of Chicago, with the help and support of such American friends as Mr. Knapp, are assured that their good name as Greeks will be protected. Saloniki wishes to thank the Journal and Mr. Knapp for defending our country and our people from unjust and malicious accusations.</p>
   <p>Mr. James Manousopoulos acted as toastmaster at this impressive dinner. Mr. Protopapas, the owner of the Grecian Cafe, had made wonderful preparations to accommodate and feed more than two hundred persons.</p>
   <p>Many prominent Americans and the outstanding leaders and representative individuals of our Greek community sat at the dinner.</p>
   <p>The Greek consul general, Mr. Nicholas Salopoulos, thanked the distinguished philhellene and guest of the evening, Mr. Knapp, for his work in behalf of the Greek people.</p>
   <p>Several veterans of the Balkan wars, among them Messrs. Photius Paparostas and <pb facs="5422062_2_0936.jpg" n="4"/>George Matalas, spoke about their experiences in the war and declared that the recent Bulgarian publications, which were sycophantic attacks against the Greeks, were false and malicious.</p>
   <p>The French philhellene and well-known diplomat, Georges Lassare, Mr. Kontax, and other speakers spoke enthusiastically about the excellent and instructive work of the Journal, with special praise for the efforts of Mr. Knapp, in behalf of the Greeks of Chicago and the Greek nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
