<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-01-09">January 9, 1926</date><title level="a">Dictatorship in Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-01-09">January 9, 1926</date><title level="a">Dictatorship in Greece</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks of America are informed that the Prime Minister of Greece, General Pangalos, proclaimed a dictatorship in Greece, making himself dictator. The declaration took place at a dinner given by himself, at which his ministers and high officers of the army were present.</p>
   <p>He pledged himself to serve the country, and that in a short period of time he would build the army and navy to such proportions that Greece would be the most important Balkan Power at sea and on land. He announced that he would postpone indefinitely the coming elections of Congress, and sent to exile four hundred communists who conspired to overthrow the government. He also said that the expedition of 1909 put Greece at the Doors of Proussa and at the Gates of Constantinople, but the Congressional Elections of 1920 put Greece in the hands of a conniving clique, with destructive results for Greece.</p>
   <p>The dinner was successful, and the guardians of Greek destiny swore allegiance to the Dictator. The many Divisions of the Army sent messages of allegiance to the Dictator. The majority of the populace seems to be satisfied with the declaration of the Dictatorship.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0060.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Pangalos said, "the refusal of all political leaders to take part in the coming elections for Congress compelled him to take such a decision." Not a single disturbance, or disorder took place after the declaration.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pangalos continued, "for six months I was negotiating with leaders of Pro and con Vinizelists, and to my chagrin, I discovered that they were more Individualists than Nationalists. They would not listen to reason nor to my invocation for unity to my plea to save our country from the common enemy, Communism, within and without. My appeal fell upon deaf ears. They audaciously requested my retirement. The Dictatorship was the only means to stop what would have been an inevitable chaos. My decision was reached after prolonged deliberation and consultation with sane heads."</p>
   <p>The populace of Greece looks upon Mr. Pangalos as a liberator of Greece from the hands of the conniving clique.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
