<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-24">October 24, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Political Campaign Activities Among the Greeks.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-24">October 24, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL CAMPAIGN ACTIVITIES AMONG THE GREEKS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 1. - The Greek political leaders are feverishly active these days due to approaching election.</p>
   <p>Republicans and Democrats are arranging for Mass meetings and giving sumptuous banquets in honor of their friends who are candidates on either ticket, respectively, in order to give them a chance to place their political program before the Greek voters and show them their political strength.</p>
   <p>The Republican Greek leaders have given two political dinners already are preparing a third one.</p>
   <p>Next Sunday's dinner by the Greek American National Republican Club, at the Sherman Hotel, is expected to be a grand one. The president of the organization is Mr.A. Kolias and the treasurer is Mr. John Koliopoulos. The South Side Hellenic American Republican Club, whose president is Mr. C. Rekas is sharing the expenses.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0268.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Both these organizations have exhausted every effort to make this gathering a success. The following will be present to take part in the program, the Honorable Charles E. Deneen, State Senator; Lewis E. Emerson, candidate for governor; Martin Glen, candidate for Senator; and John A. Swanson, Prosecuting Attorney; and others.</p>
   <p>For tonight, the Greek Democrats, composing the Greek American National Club whose president is Dr. N. Salopoulos and whose secretary is Mr. A. Pantelis, are arranging a political dinner, at the Sherman Hotel. Mr. Floyd E. Thomson, candidate for governor; Anton F. Cermak, for Senator and Mr. Linzi, Prosecuting Attorney will speak.</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
