<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1926-03-25">March 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Lenroot Sent Here to Boost Mc Kinley. Senator to Address Greek Club as Coolidge Emissary to Help Candidate.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1926-03-25">March 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">LENROOT SENT HERE TO BOOST Mc KINLEY. SENATOR TO ADDRESS GREEK CLUB AS COOLIDGE EMISSARY TO HELP CANDIDATE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Senator Irving L. Lenroot of Wisconsin is the next representative of the Coolidge administration to come to Chicago and speak for Senator William B. McKinley's renomination by the Republicans of Illinois as a friend and supporter of President Coolidge. Senator Lenroot is announced as the principal speaker at a banquet at the Hotel La Salle Sunday night in honor of Senator McKinley. The Greek-American Republican Club of Cook County is giving the banquet. Senator McKinley is expected to reach Chicago from Washington with Senator Lenroot, Sunday morning.</p>
   <p>Attorney Paul Demos, president of the club, is chairman of the committee on arrangements and Peter S. Lambras, editor of the Greek Star, is actively interested. Mr. Lambros said today there were 20,000 Greek stores in Illinois and upward of 50,000 Greek votes. Most of the Greek leaders are behind Senator McKinley, and they predict he will get the votes of practically all the Greeks in Illinois. More than 1,000 <pb facs="5422062_2_0296.jpg" n="2"/>plates will be laid at Sunday night's banquet, at which Mr. Demos will be toastmaster and, in addition to Senators Lenroot and McKinley, Miss Harriet Vittum, Mr. Lambros, Felix J. Streyckmans, Edward J. Hess, and John R. Palandech will speak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
