<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1918-06-22">June 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Official Celebration of the First Anniversary of Greece's Entrance into the War</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0679</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0679.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-06-22">June 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OFFICIAL CELEBRATION OF THE FIRST ANNIVERSARY OF GREECE'S ENTRANCE INTO THE WAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By order of the Greek Government, the Greek diplomatic and consular authorities have been instructed to organize a national celebration for June 27, the first anniversary of Greece's entry into the war. This decision was made because there are some who doubt that Greece entered the war of her own will.June 27 is the date on which the diplomatic representatives of Greece left the capitals of the Central Powers and their allies, with whom Greece was at war.</p>
   <p>On June 27, Te Deums will be offered in the three Greek churches of Chicago as well as in those of other cities in the United States. A great meeting will take place in a hall which will be specified by the Greek Consulate General of Chicago. Prominent individuals in our community will deliver speeches appropriate to the occasion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0680.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is, therefore, necessary from a nationalistic point of view and a matter of personal obligation that the Greek people of Chicago attend and lend the proper atmosphere to the occasion so that we may show the American public in a most convincing manner that the Greeks are inspired by sentiments of loyalty, devotion, and enthusiasm for the Allied cause. This obligation becomes greater when we think that although this great nation is far removed from the slightest danger, it sends it armies and ships to fight for our sake and for civilization. America is fighting for great moral issues, for no territorial or other interests whatsoever.</p>
   <p>Therefore, onward! Let us all participate in this sacred national celebration, for we are doing honor to ourselves and to America, with which we have common ideals and interests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
