<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Child Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">Letter from a Shoe-shine Boss</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1033</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1033.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">CHILD LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Letter from a Shoe-shine Boss</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Dear Sirs: I have read many letters that you have published in your paper in which the owners of shoe-shine shops are severely criticized and called inhuman. It is not just that an entire group should be judged by the actions of nine or ten individuals. The sheep must be separated from the goats.</p>
   <p>"The boys only work a few hours during the day; besides, if they do not like the work, they are free to go elsewhere. Let them go to some ice-cream parlor and stand on their feet nineteen hours a day.</p>
   <p>"In regard to Sundays, I want to say this: there are three thousand shoe-shine shops in Chicago, and Saturday and Sunday are the only days on which they can make any profits.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1034.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"It is not the fault of the bosses if these boys come from Greece uneducated, and without money or knowledge of the English language. The bosses pay these boys twenty-five dollars a month and all their living expenses, which amounts to about fifty dollars a month. This sum is more than the average clerk earns. Therefore, why persecute the bosses?</p>
   <p>"I remain,</p>
   <p>"C. Panagiotopoulos"</p>
   <p>This letter presents a series of justifications for the actions of the bosses. The weak point in the argument of Mr. Panagiotopoulos is where he writes that the youth who come from Greece are uneducated. This is exactly what we are endeavoring to change. We want these boys to learn the [English] language.....If the bosses find it impossible to close their shops on Sunday, they can arrange to close early two or three nights a week, in order to enable the boys to attend night school.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
