<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-07-10">July 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Psychological Effect</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0899</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0899.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-07-10">July 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE PSYCHOLOGICAL EFFECT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek people of Chicago, and indeed the Greek population of all of America, is considered an inseparable part of the entire Greek nation. As such, it is experiencing the psychological effect of the wars and crises in Europe, particularly when they have some important bearing on the political and economic situation in Greece.</p>
   <p>Although we are enjoying the blessings of American tolerance, hospitality, and peace, it is very interesting to notice that the Greeks of America, and especially of Chicago, are strongly attached to the mother country by indissoluble bonds. This is....plainly evident in our confused thinking and vociferous discussion of the dramatic upheaval and changes in warring Europe. We in this country are showing more interest in the European crisis than our relatives in Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0900.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The serious illness of our beloved monarch, King Constantine of Greece, was the cause of grave concern for us, while the manifestation of our political sentiments has been very strong among us.</p>
   <p>But these are not the most significant psychological phenomena of our times. The discussion which is centered around strategic, military, and diplomatic developments in Europe and the manner in which they may affect Greece are the chief concern of this editorial.</p>
   <p>All Greeks in America sympathize with the British and French. They say that these great powers helped to determine the outcome of our War of Independence in 1821 by destroying the powerful Turco-Egyptian fleet at Navarino Bay. Russia is excluded, however, because she covets Constantinople. Many Greeks in Chicago exclaim that they would like to see Britain and France victorious, but not Russia. Yet how can Russia be destroyed, while her allies are triumphant?</p>
   <p>But we are not content with hating Russia; we are also desirous of witnessing <pb facs="5422062_2_0901.jpg" n="3"/>the downfall of Italy, because she has gained a foothold in Avlona, Albania, and the Balkan peninsula; because of her reign of terror in Rhodes, which formerly belonged to Greece, and in the Dodecanese Islands; and because of her scheming ambition to expand in Asia Minor.</p>
   <p>So, in the minds of our people, the quadruple alliance of Britain, France, Russia, and Italy has been divided into victorious Britain and France and vanquished Russia and Italy to suit our desires and purposes.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, we would have the Bulgarians allied with the Turks and the Greek army fighting both at the same time. For our people, no such thing as Bulgaria exists!</p>
   <p>We have visions of Rumania and Greece carving up the Kingdom of Krummus (ancient Bulgarian king), while with the support of the French and British fleets we can capture Constantinople, which we consider a traditionally Greek city. In the meantime, we are expecting Mr. Venizelos to secure Asia Minor for Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0902.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Of course, these are only a few of the most common opinions expressed by our people. We are mentioning them for the sole purpose of showing the political attitude and aspirations of the immigrant Greek. We are also hopeful that the historians of the future will study them.</p>
   <p>In our opinion all of us are right! There is no profit in opening a political discussion with Greeks!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
