<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1927-01-28">Jan. 28, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to the Greek-Americans of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1927-01-28">Jan. 28, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO THE GREEK-AMERICANS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I have never been unmindful of the tribute America and the entire world owe glorious Greece. My love for Greece has been warm since my school days, when I learned about the marvelous victories of Salamis and Marathon and the Golden Era of Pericles, in the days of "the glory that was Greece."</p>
   <p>My personal contact with numerous Greeks has instilled me with greater admiration for their motherland, as well as greater respect for the seventy-five thousand Greeks of this city who have contributed their share toward Greater Chicago and Greater America.</p>
   <p>I deeply appreciate the support given me politically by the Greek-Americans during the past, and now I am extremely pleased that the Greek-American Litsinger Club has been organized to further my campaign as Republican candidate for Mayor of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0285.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Moreover, I am happy to learn of the banquet and rally to be given in my honor by that splendid organization on Sunday evening, February 6, at the La Salle Hotel.</p>
   <p>Such an enthusiastic demonstration in my behalf by thousands of my Greek friends and friends and fellow Americans is indeed great encouragement to me in this campaign and leads me to believe that, with your assistance and co-operation we will be victorious at the polls on February 22.</p>
   <p>If I am nominated and elected Mayor of Chicago, it will be my duty to give a square deal to peoples of all races, regardless of nationality, religion or creed. I shall treat the people of Chicago as Americans, and equals, for the good of the commonwealth. If I am elected Mayor, I shall do my best to help make Chicago a safe place in which to live and do business, and the center of progress and of every idealistic thought and action.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>E. R. Litsinger</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
