<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-10-11">Oct. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Thousand Men</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0950</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0950.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-10-11">Oct. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A THOUSAND MEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In groups of fifty or a hundred, our men have been gathering late at night at the Union Railroad Station, preparing to leave for the battlefields of Greece. These men are fully aware of their most urgent duty, to serve and fight for Greece at a time when she is shaping her historic destiny. All this has been done without any parades, demonstrations, pompous exhibitions, music, or fanfare. While the midnight church bells were tolling, these men have been quietly and thoughtfully saying good-by to Chicago, to their friends and loved ones here, before speeding to New York, where they will board the ocean liners headed for the fair shores of Greece.</p>
   <p>These departures have been taking place for twenty days. We doubt whether all of us understand the full significance of this gesture on the part of one <pb facs="5422062_2_0951.jpg" n="2"/>thousand of our men, a thousand genuine sons of Hellas, who are on the high seas speeding to seek the comradeship of their brothers on the European battlefields.</p>
   <p>The probability of renewed hostilities against our age-long tyrannical enemy and nightmare, the Bulgar and Turk, has caused our loyal and courageous youth to answer the call to arms. As soon as the call for their particular classes was announced by the Greek government, these young men hastened to obtain the necessary consular certificates and thereupon departed immediately, with a silent prayer on the lips of all. The Greek consulate has been packed with army reserves and men eligible for service in the last few weeks. According to the most conservative estimates, more than one thousand draftees were given consular certificates.</p>
   <p>This exodus was carried out so smoothly and noiselessly that we can justly take pride in the seriousness and quiet dignity of our departed men. Happy are those countries whose citizens know and perform their patriotic duties in such <pb facs="5422062_2_0952.jpg" n="3"/>a way. The Greece of today owes all her greatness and glory primarily to the fact that most of her citizens have not only learned their duty but know how to do their duty.</p>
   <p>The Greek people of America, of whom our Chicago Greeks constitute a great number, this fighting, determined, and hard-working group of immigrants, has added a glorious and monumental chapter to the history of modern Greece in one of her most critical periods. It has been affirmed beyond any doubt that about fifty thousand Greeks from all over America took part in the two victorious wars of last year and this year against Turkey and Bulgaria. And now that two more classes have been called up, ten thousand new soldiers will within a few days join the ranks of King Constantine's army. The king himself will again be with the troops on the front, if this threatened new war breaks out.</p>
   <p>Saloniki has published a series of articles on the new opportunities which are offered our people by the expansion of Greece's territory. It has urged the reversal of the immigration trend and the return of the wandering and scattered <pb facs="5422062_2_0953.jpg" n="4"/>Greeks to the bosom of our happy and prosperous motherland. It has also stressed the inescapable patriotic obligation that those who are called upon to serve their country must fulfill.</p>
   <p>This newspaper has cause to rejoice, for its urgent appeals have found a response in the hearts of our fellow countrymen. We wish to extend our heartiest congratulations to all those true Greeks who have hastened to offer their much-needed services and even their lives for their motherland.</p>
   <p>The thousand men who have left us in the last few days are a thousand loyal Spartons and Athenians of old; they are a thousand true men. May our heartfelt wishes and prayers strengthen them and may God keep them during their long journey.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
