<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-07-03">July 3, 1926</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">The Danger to Greek Business</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1679</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1679.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-07-03">July 3, 1926</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">THE DANGER TO GREEK BUSINESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Business in America one could say is more successful than in any country. However, corporations and companies have more success than individual merchants.</p>
   <p>The Greeks in America at the beginning were very successful in their business, especially in the restaurant and confectionary business. And it was rather difficult for anyone to compete with the Greeks, owing to their industry and the great number working in these two trades.</p>
   <p>But things change, (and the good business may change with the time) and the Greeks are losing ground, because they have failed to catch the spirit of the present times. Big companies and corporations with huge combined capital, take the business away from the Greeks (those who continue the horse and buggy methods).</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1680.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many times, through this publication, we have urged the necessity of Greeks to unite themselves in companies and corporations, in order to remain in business successfully. The competition has become too keen for the individual merchant, the combined wealth of capital has invented and promoted up to date methods for restaurants and confectionaries a single merchant cannot afford to adopt. Hence, in union is strength and power. It is hard to compete with it.</p>
   <p>Among our progressive Greeks, we bring with pride, and for emulation, to the publics attention, the names of Raklios and Co., DeMets, Lily Candy Co. Andes Candy Co. The above mentioned companies are in a position to compete with other big companies, and they are doing it successfully.</p>
   <p>If this warning and counsel is not heeded, in a short time from now, the Greek business world ,undoubtedly will become wrecked.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
