<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-11-06">Nov. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Forward! to Battle</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0872</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0872.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-11-06">Nov. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FORWARD! TO BATTLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Again, we say, there is no doubt that Greece will enter the war. It is a great but necessary sacrifice that must be made. First, because Greece has signed a treaty to help Serbia; second, because Greece must protect herself from her barbarous neighbor Bulgaria; and third, because it gives her an opportunity to avenge herself on the Turks for the five hundred years of slavery and torture suffered at their hands. At the same time we will be given a chance to regain lands that are truly ours, such as Ionia and Constantinople.</p>
   <p>Every Greek realizes the importance of these statements. He feels the obligation of his generation to the previous generations that have left him such a glorious heritage.</p>
   <p>The fate of mankind is being determined with cannons and rivers of blood.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0873.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even now, the future freedom of our motherland is being endangered because the tyrannical heel of the Turk is again near her neck. The Turks and the audacious Bulgarians seek to impose their tyranny upon Greece to such an extent that she will never again be able to regain her freedom.</p>
   <p>English generosity has offered us Cyros, Dodecanese, and territory extending to Constantinople. It is impossible to believe that there exists even one Greek who would put his own personal safety above that of his country. The British offer us a chance to realize our five-hundred-year-old national dream. Our enslaved ancestors, who suffered tortures and agonies at the hands of their oppressors, raise a mighty cry from the grave; they demand that we avail ourselves of the chance to recover our rightful possessions, and that we avenge the murder of innocent women and children.</p>
   <p>"Frenchmen!" said Napoleon, when he addressed his army in Egypt. "Do not forget to live up to the glorious history of six thousand years which is recorded on the face of the pyramids".</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0874.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Greeks!" calls our history, from the time of the Persian Battles to Alexander the Great, from the Byzantians to the Turkish battles of '21 and the Bulgo-Turk battles of '13. "Be careful and determined to show the world you are worthy of your glorious history. Prove that you are truly descendants of a great race. Show the world that the Greek blood in your veins is hot and racing with determination to defend your country's past and present!"</p>
   <p>And the Hellenic spirit hears these dead--but nevertheless living--voices with enthusiasm;it insists upon entering this bloody contest in order to regain the former glory of Greece.</p>
   <p>For that reason, the hopes of Greece and Greeks all over the face of the earth are fixed upon Venizelos. The gallant voice of this brave Cretan will at any minute declare war against Bulgaria--an action which will make every Greek spirit rejoice.</p>
   <p>We are sure this patriotic action will have the approval of the king. We <pb facs="5422062_2_0875.jpg" n="4"/>believe that Constantine is in agreement with the plans of Venizelos because he is interested in the fate of his country. He is awaiting the proper time to give the reins into the hands of Venizelos. Then, together, they will lead the armies of Greece to the fields of Thrace, and from there to the walls of Constantinople.</p>
   <p>Patience is necessary, and more courage is needed; and infinite faith in the country's leaders.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of America must not allow themselves to be misled by certain selfish or biased newspapers which print lies and scandals about the king and other Greek statesmen. It is not proper that the patriotism of any individual should be questioned or doubted--unless, of course, there is proof to the contrary; and it is far more improper to question the patriotism of a king or a statesman as long as the actions of these men are of an absolutely patriotic nature.</p>
   <p>As the days go by, the horizon is widening and becoming far brighter. Soon <pb facs="5422062_2_0876.jpg" n="5"/>the Greek dreams will be realized. The moment that the Bulgarians seize the Greek towns in Serbian Macedonia, the military machine in Athens will begin to carry out its secret plans. When Rumania finally decides to join the fray on the side of the Allies, then King Constantine, wearing the uniform of a common soldier, will lead the charge of the Greek army; and there on the battlefield the ancient dreams of Greece will be brought to life.</p>
   <p>The Greeks in America can be sure of that; and as true children of the great motherland, they must prepare themselves to be ready to aid in the fulfillment of our national dream.</p>
   <p>Yes, all indications point to the rapid entrance of Greece into the war, and a harmonious agreement between Constantine and Venizelos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
