<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-01-04">Jan. 4, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Hellenic Land Company Buys 1500 Acres in Alabama for Colonization and Timber</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-01-04">Jan. 4, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">HELLENIC LAND COMPANY BUYS 1500 ACRES IN ALABAMA FOR COLONIZATION AND TIMBER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sixteen Chicago Greeks who had purchased seven hundred acres of undeveloped land in Alabama left last week to colonize their land under the guidance and assistance of the Hellenic Land Company, a Chicago Greek firm with offices at 1-11 Blue Island Avenue. Twenty more Greeks, with their families, are preparing to depart for Alabama in a few days.</p>
   <p>The fifteen hundred acres bought by the Chicago Greek firm for timber and colonization are already disposed of, and negotiations are under way for the purchase of a new tract of land.</p>
   <p>That the projected enterprise will be successful is beyond dispute, for those who have already left and those who are about to leave are almost all businessmen with money who will continue to derive a steady income from their business here, operated in their absence by their partners or their relatives.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1188.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The pioneers of the future Alabama Greek colony are Antonios Lymberopoulos, Demetrios Diamantopoulos, John Spyropoulos, Soter Kontaratos, Basil Gouvalaniris, Spyridon Michalos, Anthony Barbagiannis, Constantine Katchirounis, John Docos, D. Kostopoulos, Aristomenes Kostopoulos, Nicholas Docos, P. Nestos, Charalampos Stavropoulos, Constantine Kotchiopoulos, and Nicholas Roupas.</p>
   <p>Directing our activities to enterprises of this kind is not only good business so far as profit is concerned; it is also an indication that we are catching the progressive spirit of our adopted country. Future Greek generations in that part of the country will be thankful to those Chicago Greek pioneers who had the foresight to buy this undeveloped land, which in years to come will be valuable property.</p>
   <p>This enterprise also reveals that the immigrant Greek of former years has abandoned his intention of going back to his native land, and little by little is being absorbed by the greatness of his new country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
