<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-04-18">April 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Mass-Meeting for Third Liberty Loan Greek Ambassador Here for That Purpose Enthusiasm and Patriotism Thunder through the Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0737</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0737.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-04-18">April 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK MASS-MEETING FOR THIRD LIBERTY LOAN GREEK AMBASSADOR HERE FOR THAT PURPOSE ENTHUSIASM AND PATRIOTISM THUNDER THROUGH THE HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- A crowd of five thousand Greeks packed Orchestra Hall at the rally for the Third Liberty Loan. Noted Americans delivered patriotic speeches, and the Greek Ambassador, Mr. Rousos, who came here from Washington to assist in the Liberty Loan campaign, addressed the crowd in a heart-to-heart talk, eliminating the usual oratorical phrases and identifying himself with the spirit of Isocrates, arousing thereby unparalleled enthusiasm in his auditors. He said that to-day history is repeating itself.</p>
   <p>"America to-day is fighting the war of liberty and democracy to save the world from barbarism, as Greece did in the past. To-day Greece, the mother of democracy, and America, the true daughter of democracy, are fighting shoulder to shoulder for these divine principles. Helping <pb facs="5422062_2_0738.jpg" n="2"/>America to win the war not only benefits you here; it also benefits Greece and all your friends and relatives there. Before you think of food and clothing for yourself, you must think of America, which is fighting the holiest war in the history of the world. America is not fighting to expand in territory but to spread American enlightenment all over the world. Buy Liberty Bonds - buy more than anybody else. You and I owe many things to America; let us show America and the world that we are Greeks to the last drop of our blood, that we will fight for these divine principles not only by purchasing Liberty Bonds but by standing ready to shed our blood if need be, as our famous forefathers did."</p>
   <p>Because many distinguished Americans were present, His Excellency delivered a second speech in English. And by a pre-arranged understanding, as soon as he finished his English speech, the orchestra began to play the American anthem, which swept the people off their feet. The thunderous enthusiasm was heard blocks and blocks away.</p>
   <p>The Greeks are to be congratulated for this patriotic demonstration because like begets like. It has a great effect upon the masses. Bravo! Let us keep the fire burning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
