<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-01-26">Jan. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">United States Government Thrift Cards</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Card lithograph - 3" x 3")</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-01-26">Jan. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT THRIFT CARDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Card lithograph - 3" x 3")</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is a United States Thrift Card. Have you got yours yet? Every man, woman, and child in Illinois should have one. To have one is proof of patriotism. It is the card which gives every man, every woman, every child the opportunity to enlist in the great army of economy for the support of the men in the trenches. Every time you buy a stamp, which is affixed to the card, you are buying a bullet which may save the life of an American soldier, or you are helping to buy a pair of shoes, or a warm blanket which will protect him from catching pneumonia. Every time you affix a stamp on this card you are bringing the defeat of the Kaiser closer at hand. If you are getting along without a few luxuries in order to economize your savings with which to buy stamps, you are doing a double service to your country. You are not only helping to buy something useful for the soldiers, but you are assisting in freeing workers, whom your country needs as much as the soldiers. When, for instance, American labor is occupied in making small useless objects, <pb facs="5422062_2_0783.jpg" n="2"/>naturally, they cannot manufacture shells and ammunition, and thus aid in winning the war.</p>
   <p>In this way, you are not only helping your country, but yourselves as well. When you fill out this card you should exchange it for a War Savings Certificate Stamp for which you will be paid five dollars by the government on January 1, 1923. The government pays four per cent interest. At any time, you may redeem your cards at the post office, receiving three per cent interest.</p>
   <p>I do not think that you would want to redeem your card; you will prefer to add it to the war savings card until you have twenty such cards, whereupon they can be exchanged for a War Deposit Certificate, for which one hundred dollars will be paid on January 1, 1923.</p>
   <p>This deposit shall be of much greater use to you at that time, without seriously depriving yourselves of funds with which to buy it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
