<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-08-14">Aug. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Venizelos Returns to Power--Will Greece "Go In?"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0893</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0893.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-08-14">Aug. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">VENIZELOS RETURNS TO POWER--WILL GREECE "GO IN?"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Venizelos triumphed in the June elections, and the certainty that his supporters in the new Greek parliament will be in a majority, assuring his return to power, has led many to suppose that this will mean the immediate entrance of Greece into the war on the side of the Allies. But, while this is quite possible, it is by no means certain; for much has happened since last February. The outlook of the Allies is by no means as bright as it was then. Bulgaria still nurses her wrath and, most important of all from the Greek standpoint, Italy has "gone in".</p>
   <p>What have the Allies promised Italy? That is the vital question for Greece. The Italian occupation of Avlona and other points in Southern Albania is painful enough to Greek susceptibilities. If Greece discovers that the Allies <pb facs="5422062_2_0894.jpg" n="2"/>have promised Italy any part of southern Asia Minor, it is decidedly unlikely that the Greek people will be willing to sacrifice a single Greek soldier in the Allied cause.</p>
   <p>The recent triumph of Venizelos at the polls should be interpreted as a vote of confidence in his leadership, rather than as a distinct mandate for war under any circumstances. The Greek people feel that the man who plucked them from a bad situation and set their feet upon the pathway of success, is the man to guide their country in this, the supreme hour of its need. On this point it is worthy of note that Venizelos himself has publicly stated that conditions have changed since February; and what was then possible, may not be feasible today.</p>
   <p>In closing this sketch of Greece's strong man, we must not forget that, great and successful as has been his work, it is the Greek nation which made that success possible. No one, however gifted, can create something out of nothing.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0895.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That Venizelos, in less than three years, could transform the apparently hopeless Greece of 1897 and 1909 into the Greece of the Balkan Wars shows that the heart of Hellas was always sound. The Greeks have some serious failings, but they also have certain high virtues. Notably, an ardent patriotism, rising to the dignity of a religion, and, like all real faiths, it ennobles and purifies. This patriotism, joined to a quick understanding, brings it to pass that when the true interests of Hellas are clearly set forth, the Greek people devote themselves thereto with such great fervor as to accomplish miracles in a very short period of time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
