<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1936-07-10">July 10, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">[Professional Men Honor Graduates]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1225</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1225.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1936-07-10">July 10, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">[PROFESSIONAL MEN HONOR GRADUATES]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek Professional Men's Club has again served its annual supper, followed by a dance, in honor of Greek graduates of American colleges and universities. The function was held in the Bismarck Hotel on Thursday evening, July 2, and the Flamingo Room and part of the Walnut Room were filled with Greek people of all walks of life.</p>
   <p>The president of the Greek Professional Men's Club, Mr. George D. Arachovitis, presided, and after welcoming the guests, he presented Bishop Kallistos of San Francisco, who addressed the graduates on behalf of the Church. The Most Rev. Father Kallistos explained the meaning of university education and emphasized that the moral part of education is the most valuable element of learned man's culture.</p>
   <p>"Society," he said, "demands conscientious service of the new men of learning. They ought to be proud of their descent."</p>
   <p>The Bishop wished them success in practical life.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1226.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. A. Pantelis, lawyer, followed and suggested to the graduates that only by work, and often by hard work, must they seek success.</p>
   <p>The main speaker of the evening was Prof. Nicholas Cheronis, of Wright College, whose address is listed in the Star for our compatriots to study. The celebration was honored by the presence of the former lawyer, journalist and author, Mr. Serafeim Kanoutas of New York, who delivered a significant address which held the attention of the audience.</p>
   <p>"We all honor and love," said he, "our youth as students and graduates; we extol them for the honors and awards which they receive as undergraduates; we are proud of them. But when they enter their practical careers, we abandon them to God's mercy, and consider them incompetent and unworthy of our support!"</p>
   <p>He then turned to our merchants and adjured them to support these young men and women in their practical careers, if they would not see our race, language, and religion extinguished in a short space of time.</p>
   <p>A dance followed the program, continuing to 1 A. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
