<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-09-06">Sept. 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A New Commercial Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1716</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1716.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-09-06">Sept. 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW COMMERCIAL SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2....The Greek community of Chicago has been progressing rapidly for the last ten years, those of us who have dealt with experienced and honest real-estate operators have derived large benefit of our dealings.</p>
   <p>The real-estate office of George Tsiagouris, founded in 1908, is the oldest of the Greek real-estate offices and handles the real-estate business of the Greek restaurant enterprise, the Raklios Company. The latest successful transaction concluded by the Tsiagouris office for the Raklios Company is the negotiation of a long lease on the building at the northeast corner of Madison and Clark Streets. The announcement of this transaction came as a surprise to most people; it is the most important deal ever made by the Tsiagouris office.</p>
   <p>According to the agreement the Raklios Company will pay during the term of this lease the sum of two and a half million dollars in rental. The negotiations were completed by the Tsiagouris office and the Albert H. Wetter Company.</p>
   <p>We wish to extend our sincere congratulations to Mr. John Raklios, who came to this country in 1900 without means and without knowledge of the language and the business methods of America. Yet he was able so to elevate himself that he is now considered one of the big and shrewd businessmen of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1717.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The progress of the Raklios Company has been remarkable under the guidance of John Raklios, president, Vasilios Kotsonis, vice-president, and Andrew Chrones, secretary: These three compatriots of ours began their careers as poor immigrants and by hard work, honesty, and commercial ability have successfully competed with other big and powerful combinations in the restaurant business.</p>
   <p>The sixteen big, luxurious, magnificent, and clean restaurants of the Raklios Company throughout the Loop district of this windy city are evidence of the splendid commercial spirit of the Greeks and of the success of the Raklios Company in selecting its real-estate agents.</p>
   <p>When Mr. Venizelos, the noted Greek statesman, visited Chicago recently, he said that the commercial achievements of Mr. Raklios and his Company were really Herculean.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
