<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-09-01">Sept. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Americanization and Citizenship</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-09-01">Sept. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICANIZATION AND CITIZENSHIP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5. A great celebration will take place on September 11, commemorating the adoption of the Constitution, which is the foundation upon which the government of the United States operates.</p>
   <p>The preservation and enforcement of the Constitution are the greatest protection for every citizen because the Constitution defends the rights of citizens and maintains peace and order, so that industry can exist and life will be secure. Is it possible for any one to be a good citizen if he does not know the Constitution and obey it?</p>
   <p>Yes, if the citizen attends strictly to his own business and does not try to meddle in other people's affairs.</p>
   <p>Each provision of the Constitution is for the general benefit of the citizens. A law may take away the rights of a few bad citizens, but as a rule it protects the interests of the majority.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1105.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Therefore, we should all obey the Constitution, the fundamental law of the land.</p>
   <p>The United States is one of the largest nations in the world, and it works for universal peace and prosperity.</p>
   <p>Let us all offer a helping hand to a great cause and a great effort.</p>
   <p>George Washington, the father of our country, wrote in 1789: "My greatest pleasure is to see that everything rests upon a better and more secure basis."</p>
   <p>Every one should obey the law for his own sake and for the sake of his family, his city, his country, and the entire world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
