<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-07-10">July 10, 1926</date><title level="a">Why Greek Partnership Fail?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1676</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1676.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-07-10">July 10, 1926</date><title level="a">Why Greek Partnership Fail?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1. It is noteworthy here and in Greece, with few exceptions, that the Greek, as an individual, made wonderful progress in business and commerce, but failed in partnerships. We often see Greek partners quarreling, fighting, and lastly, taking refuge in court litigations.</p>
   <p>Each partner, in a Greek enterprise, considers himself the basis and the foundation of the partnership's business, and underestimates the ability and value of the other partners.</p>
   <p>Many impartial minds think that this habit is a national characteristic of our race, nevertheless, I think and know that the cause is lack of system and lack of business knowledge.</p>
   <p>The Greek without business training and from almost nothing, through his persistance, industriousness, and hard work, can usually acquire much money. His egotism, however, that is to say, the conviction that he is the only factor in a partnership, that the other partners are of insignificant consequence <pb facs="5422062_2_1677.jpg" n="2"/>causes him to fail.</p>
   <p>Failure under such an attitude is inevitable. Self-hypnotism and lack of systematic business methods brings down the whole edifice of Partnership.</p>
   <p>Only scientific, systematic, and methodical knowledge would keep Greek partnerships from failure. The Americans succeed because they are equipped with business knowledge minus blind egotism. In American business organizations everyone of the partners performs the duty to which he is assigned, just like a machine, without interfering with somebody else's duty and activity. Consequently each recognizes the service of the other, and obediently takes and executes orders from his other partners who are wisely chosen to execute efficiently their respective responsibilities.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, urge the Greeks, if they wish to better themselves and remain in business, to follow the perfect American ways and methods. By doing so, not only will they become strong and prosperous, but they will prove to those who entertain the erroneous conception, that it is a National characteristic of the Greek to be egotistic, ignoring to recognize the preponderance of others, that Greeks could and would succeed in partnerships as well as in individual enterprises.</p>
   <p>(Full)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
