<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1918-03-02">Mar. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">What Every Man Should Do for the Sake of His Own Interest</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The Committee on National Preparedness)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0775</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0775.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-03-02">Mar. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT EVERY MAN SHOULD DO FOR THE SAKE OF HIS OWN INTEREST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The Committee on National Preparedness)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are pleased to publish the following statement of the Committee on National Preparedness:</p>
   <p>"On this day, a critical moment in the nation's history, Germany is endeavoring in every possible way to make traitors of the American workers.</p>
   <p>"What is the use of sending our sons to the war front, when we are bent on betraying them by not sending ammunition, which we have ceased manufacturing?</p>
   <p>"By confusion and various other methods, Germany is seeking to retard our preparation for war. The entire American nation is fighting for its freedom and independence, which we will lose, if defeated. We must all work to preserve our good fortune; each strike means the <pb facs="5422062_2_0776.jpg" n="2"/>murder of our brothers and our own suicide.</p>
   <p>"Why talk about increasing wages and reduction of working hours, when the enemy is about to win the war? The slaves of America lived better than the prisoners of Belgium, who are living and working in the various German factories and mines. The prisoners of Belgium are being beaten and brutally handled, while working as unfortunate slaves of the Germans. Who wants to support a pitiless tyrant that seeks to subjugate so good a people?</p>
   <p>"The faithful and honest worker who remains faithful to his work is offering the greatest service to himself and to his country. How can one be called a man, when he sells his manliness, and directly or indirectly betrays his country? What liberty-loving worker can tolerate the sight of the oppressed Belgian people? These people cannot win their freedom by being left to perish, or by seeing the Allies defeated.</p>
   <p>"Let us all remain firm in our determination to work faithfully and <pb facs="5422062_2_0777.jpg" n="3"/>loyally, especially those of us who are working for the government, in order to safeguard our life, honor, and property, together with our freedom, which are threatened by the brutal and inhuman German slave drivers."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
