<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-03-30">Mar. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Circular of the Treasury Department to All Organizations in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Picture of Mr. McAdoo, one-column half-tone, 3"x6"]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0757</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0757.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-03-30">Mar. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CIRCULAR OF THE TREASURY DEPARTMENT TO ALL ORGANIZATIONS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Picture of Mr. McAdoo, one-column half-tone, 3"x6"]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Registration for the Third Liberty Loan begins on April 6, the first anniversary of this nation's entrance into the war for freedom and justice. On this occasion, W.G. McAdoo, the United States Secretary of the Treasury, addressed the following circular letter to the various associations, clubs, and churches:</p>
   <p>"Ladies and Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>"In order that the present war in which we are engaged may come to a happy and victorious conclusion for the satisfaction of the honor and rights of America and the freedom of the world, your government is forced to ask for more funds. For this reason it has been already announced that the Third Liberty Loan issue is out.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0758.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Registration for this Liberty Loan will begin on April 6, 1918, that is, on the first anniversary of our entrance into the war on the side of the hard-pressed Allies.</p>
   <p>"Americans of foreign birth and descent, both individually as well as through their organizations, clubs, and churches, have responded to the two previous appeals for Liberty Loans in such a way that I was deeply pleased. I am confident that the Third Liberty Loan will receive your wholehearted and spontaneous support, regardless of sect, sex, age, or place of birth.</p>
   <p>"To insure the success of our purpose, the success of the drive for the Loan, organized and systematic efforts must be made. Therefore, it is absolutely necessary that all organized bodies co-operate and assist in the forthcoming Liberty Loan campaign. I hope that the government will be offered this co-operation without reservation.</p>
   <p>(Signed)"William G. McAdoo</p>
   <p>Secretary of the Treasury."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0759.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>With this circular, the following communication from the Liberty Loan Publicity Bureau of the Treasury Department was sent to us:</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>"Referring to the above request of your government, issued by the United States Secretary of the Treasury, Mr. W.G. McAdoo, and assured in advance that you will receive this appeal willingly, inspired by the desire to again give proof of your patriotism, I request that your organization or church immediately take proper action to participate in an organized fashion in the Liberty Loan campaign.</p>
   <p>"A special committee which may have been already appointed, or which will be appointed shortly, must meet at once to make plans for systematic organization and operation.</p>
   <p>"Enclosed herewith we are sending you all the necessary directions and information so that your committee may be enabled to work effectively among the <pb facs="5422062_2_0760.jpg" n="4"/>members of your organization for the Third Liberty Loan.</p>
   <p>"Very truly yours,</p>
   <p>"Frank R. Wilson Director of</p>
   <p>the Publicity Service."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
