<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek-American News</title>,
<date when="1936-03-15">March 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The Hellenic Club of Professional Men of Chicago Elects New Officers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1227</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1227.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek American News</title>,
<date when="1936-03-15">March 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE HELLENIC CLUB OF PROFESSIONAL MEN OF CHICAGO ELECTS NEW OFFICERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 8.- On Friday, March 6, at the annual meeting of the Hellenic Club of Professional Men of Chicago, the new officers for the term of 1936-1937 were elected as follows:</p>
   <p>Mr. George Arvites, an engineer in the employ of the City of Chicago, was elected as its president; Dr. D. Galanos, a dentist, was elected first vice president; Mr. A. Teacherson, an engineer, was elected second vice president. Attorney Theodore N. Constant was re-elected secretary and Dr. E. Despotes, a dentist, was re-elected treasurer. The following persons were elected as governors:- Dr. G. Varounis, a dentist; Attorney Paul Koken, Dr. E. Nittis; a physician, Dr. J. Nicholson, a physician and an eye specialist; and N. Skoul, an engineer. Mr. S. Kotakis, a journalist, was elected to fill the office of historian.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1228.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Hellenic Club of Professional Men of Chicago is the only club of its kind in Chicago. It was established and has succeeded in its efforts wonderfully well, to uphold the dignity of the Greek professional men, to promote their interests and to help and promote worthy causes of the Hellenic race in Chicago and elsewhere.</p>
   <p>From time to time it sponsors lectures and other public functions, which tend to enhance better cultural tastes among its members and the community, and bring about a closer and more co-operative understanding between our professional men and our public.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1229.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greek American News take this opportunity to congratulate the new officers on their election, and wishes to assure them, as well as the rest of the members, that this paper will be glad to give space from time to time to the publication of news and comments on the activities and achievements of our professional men. We need their help and they need ours.</p>
   <p>We believe firmly in close cooperation and the policy of this paper in this connection will be to promote and strengthen such cooperation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
