<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-01-19">Jan. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Important Announcement for Eligible Service Men</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-01-19">Jan. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT FOR ELIGIBLE SERVICE MEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"To the Editors of Saloniki;</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen: Will you please publish the present communication to you concerning a matter which is of great importance to those of your readers who are between the ages of twenty-one and thirty-one, as of July 5, 1917. By this notice the government will be benefited as well as those who are in doubt in regard to orders of mobilization. Whoever of the aforementioned individuals has not secured military questionnaires should do so immediately by asking for them at their district offices.</p>
   <p>"A great number of those who registered on July 5, 1917 have moved without leaving any forwarding address, and without communicating with the local office, since their departure. Consequently, their questionnaires have been returned to the post office without any notice. The papers may have been lost in the mails and those drafted may have never received them.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0785.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"A special service announced to all that they must obtain and fill out questionnaires. There is no excuse for failure to do so. These men shall be reported to the Department of Justice and may lose their rights and be put in the "first class" [sic].</p>
   <p>"All district offices have special advisers who shall assist in filling out papers. This service is free of charge. There is an information office at 615 West Adams Street, telephone, Randolph 5370. You must make this information known to your readers in a manner that will make them realize the official character of the questionnaires, which they should properly fill out and return to the district office within seven days as specified by the Selective Service Regulations.</p>
   <p>"Yours truly,</p>
   <p>"R. D. Lee</p>
   <p>"District Board Division No. 2, Northern District, Illinois."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
