<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-10">July 10, 1929</date><title level="a">The Greek Press Co-Operating with the Greek Business Men.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-10">July 10, 1929</date><title level="a">THE GREEK PRESS CO-OPERATING WITH THE GREEK BUSINESS MEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greece in America have for the last generation or so, been the precursors in many retail lines, and chiefly in the restaurant, fruit and vegetable, candy and soda fountain business.</p>
   <p>Today, as in the past quarter of a century, they are still retaining the lead in all the afore mentioned lines. The candy store at the corner, or the restaurant, next door from the corner, is a byword of knowledge to every man, woman and child, throughout the length and breath of this land, as belonging to a Greek.</p>
   <p>In the years gone by all these store owners, being newly arrived immigrants, were considered by the natives as being intruders and were thought to be people who had come to take and go. It was more than natural for the native-born to look with suspicion and sometimes with envy at the foor-hold that the Greeks were gaining on certain retail lines.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1602.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But as time went on and the Greeks be an to master the language of the country, as soon as they too become citizens of the land of their adoption and took interest in local, looked upon as forming part and parcel of the municipality in which they resided.</p>
   <p>Shortly after the Greek merchants joined the local clubs, some even went to churches of different denominations--for the Greek is not a religious stand-patter-a large number inter-married and at the outbreak of the war their quota in the ranks exceeded that of any other nationality in America. When it is considered that the number of Greeks, who were then naturalized Americans was very small, the percentage of their numbers in the army was realy astonishing. It has been estimated that one out of six, of the entire Greek population in America, was serving under the stars and stripes.</p>
   <p>It has been observed, and very rightly so, that the Greeks are successful business men and are looked upon--by the people in every town and city of the country--as forming quite a progressive element, one that is absolutely <pb facs="5422062_2_1603.jpg" n="3"/>law-abiding and loyal to the basic principles and law of the land. The idea of overthrowing existing governments never enters into the mind of any Greek. Coming from a land where liberty reigns and persecution never existed, they fit themselves in the country which has for its standard the natural rights of man.</p>
   <p>As a single racial unit the Greeks are recognized as forming a very solid block of independent merchants. Their patronage is growing and the number of stores owned by them is increasing daily. The wholesalers and the distributors, in the persons of the Greek store-owners, have their best mediums to distribute their wares to the men and women of America. Being the bulwarks of the retail merchants they resist with tenacity the aggressiveness displayed, of late, by organized finance in the form of controlling all channels of distribution.</p>
   <p>As such they are receiving the support and the patronage of all people who believe in free trade and fair competition. In appreciation of the patronage extended to them they are offering to the public personal and jovial service, quality goods and a variety consistent with the demands and the desires of the purchasing public.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1604.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Greek Press has been welcomed by all the Greek business men in Chicago and its suburbs, and bids fair to become their organ and instrument. All its influence will be exerted and all its policies molded to the end of co-operating with them and offering its columns to their interests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
