<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1929-06">June, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Community of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1929-06">June, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK COMMUNITY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many articles have been written dealing with the economic condition of the Greeks of Chicago; they have described the great peril that will fall upon us if we continue to sit idle with folded hands.</p>
   <p>With great sorrow we hear that none of the large Greek organizations of Chicago are interested in commercial progress. What is the matter? Why is there so much indifference? Must we believe that the Greeks are so dumb and so stubborn that they don't realize what is the best for them? Do they want their commercial interprises in America to be wiped out completely?</p>
   <p>Leaving this on the side a minute, we will discuss another subject. It has come to our knowledge that the Bishop Filaretos of Chicago organized a society "Agios Pantos" and bought an extensive piece of property, <pb facs="5422062_2_1612.jpg" n="2"/>twenty-five miles from Chicago, which he plans to make a cemetery. He also intends to build a chapel of Byzantine style, entirely of marble.</p>
   <p>We are sure all Greeks will be filled with pride and enthusiasm upon hearing that now they can be buried in a beautiful and expensive cemetery. We who understand the grave economic condition in Chicago at the present time look upon it with sorrow and dread.</p>
   <p>Our countrymen are divided into two ranks - the Royalists and the Venizelist. A third and more dangerous party has made its appearance - the ecclesiastical - one that has much power and can do much danger. Even during the economic crisis the church treasuries have thousands of dollars in hiding, waiting to build marble chapels, while the poor people die of starvation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1613.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We Greeks must get together and use our heads. If we don't preserve ourselves, our families, and our businesses, there will be no need for churches, schools, and cemeteries. Economic conditions will force us not to support these institutions and they will slowly disappear.</p>
   <p>G. A. Kyriakopoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
