<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-01-16">Jan. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Salopoulos Discusses the Importance of the Pharmacy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-01-16">Jan. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">MR. SALOPOULOS DISCUSSES THE IMPORTANCE OF THE PHARMACY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Ten Years ago I opened the first Greek pharmacy in America. Since that time I have handled countless prescriptions which were written by quacks. Of course I never filled these prescriptions, since they were usually of an injurious nature.</p>
   <p>"Whenever I received them I would discard them and advise the patient to consult a more reliable doctor. However, the grave import of these many prescriptions cannot be ignored. Had each of these prescriptions been filled, many persons would be either dead or seriously ill, since all of the formulas included large quantities of harmful drugs.</p>
   <p>"In Greece, persons who wish to practice pharmacy must study, as do the medical students, certain specified subjects at a university. The laws of the United States demand that a pharmacist pass a rigid state examination before he may practice his profession. A physician may neither fill prescriptions <pb facs="5422062_2_1216.jpg" n="2"/>nor work in a pharmacy. The regulations must be strict because a patient's life may depend upon the correct interpretation of a prescription. The slightest mistake might result in death."</p>
   <p>These words of Mr. [Nicholas]Salopoulos need no explanation or clarification. He has made his point very clear. He has emphasized the importance of accuracy in the interpretation of a doctor's prescription. Care must be exercised in the selection of a competent family physician and a reliable pharmacist; they should be men who would neither write nor fill a harmful prescription.</p>
   <p>Saloniki is doing its best to enlighten the Greek community of Chicago, and to rid it of all cheats, quacks, and liars. We ask that all quack victims assist us in this matter by supplying us with the names of the sham doctors who treated them. We will see to it that these scoundrels are dealt with by the law, and thus prevented from preying further on the <pb facs="5422062_2_1217.jpg" n="3"/>community. We will not suffer such parasites to live at the expense of the innocent and ignorant immigrants!</p>
   <p>Saloniki advises its readers to call a reliable physician when illness occurs; we also urge our readers to patronize a well-known and reputable pharmacy. In this way we shall rid ourselves of the accursed parasites who are now preying upon us.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
