<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-09-29">Sept. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0819</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0819.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-09-29">Sept. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is our duty and to our benefit to be "American" even more than we are "Greek". We are Greek by descent and training; because we will never be able to forget the country which has such a glorious name, was a center of culture and civilization; and because it is a truly Christian country. But we are American in our actions, our speech, and our interests; because this is the land in which we are living and the land which gives us our material gains.</p>
   <p>We must love both countries equally, and should respect and honor both as we do when we have two sisters. Today, they are really similar to sisters, since they are fighting on the same side and for the same cause.</p>
   <p>We are Greeks, it is true, but we are very proud of being American citizens.</p>
   <p>Greek blood courses through our veins, but our minds are filled with <pb facs="5422062_2_0820.jpg" n="2"/>American ideas and ways of doing things. We are proud offspring of two great countries; one having a glorious past, and the other a glorious future. Our hearts are divided in our love for the two countries, but we are just as ready to sacrifice our lives for American as we are for Greece.</p>
   <p>We have a natural mother for whom we bear an inexpressible love; we also have an adopted mother at whose hands we have known only the greatest kindness and help, and whose benefits we can never fully repay.</p>
   <p>If you wish to be loved by the Americans, you in turn must love America.</p>
   <p>This is our duty! And it is the sacred duty of all the Greeks in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
