<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-03-02">March 2, 1929</date><title level="a">The Duties of the Greek Professionals in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. Cleomenes G. Papatheodorou</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1314</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1314.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-03-02">March 2, 1929</date><title level="a">THE DUTIES OF THE GREEK PROFESSIONALS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. Cleomenes G. Papatheodorou</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Every man, regardless of his social class, has duties and obligations to perform, not only to his family and to himself, but to society also, and to mankind in general. Man must not live only for himself, but to be of service to others. Anyone thinking contrary to this, does not fulfill the object of his existence in this world.</p>
   <p>The Greek professionals in Chicago for a good many years have done their duty and in every way assisted the Greek community of Chicago. As professionals they know their imperative duty to society, and accordingly they have acted. They knew the value of being united and so they formed their society; its activities are known and appreciated by all the Greeks, not only in Chicago but in the rest of the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1315.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Unfortunately this society today is inactive. Its leader, who for a long time has struggled for the accomplishments and achievements of the society, today is inactive, inspite of his promises. Why? The why, I am not going to delve into, but I'm going to remind our society of its duty of enlightenment and service to humanity.</p>
   <p>1st. The promotion of each respective profession. That is, those professionals practicing medicine should strive to better that particular profession. But all the professions should be united under a central society so that united action may be had when it is required for objects of a general nature.</p>
   <p>2nd. Fight against pseudo-professionals, who are not only detrimental to society but to ourselves also.</p>
   <p>3rd. The elimination of the "Tooth for a Tooth" idea among ourselves and promoting friendship and noble connections.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1316.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>4th. The elevation of general interest. Our conduct should be taken as example by the masses and we should influence, many of our brother-Greeks, away from corruption and crime. Americanize them, and show them the way to become good and useful citizens</p>
   <p>5th. Beneficence and philanthropy. These two virtues of Christianity should be our object in life.</p>
   <p>6th. Love and esteem for Mother Greece. No one with sane mind can forget Greece.</p>
   <p>7th. Devotion to our religion, and devotion and faithfulness to our new Mother country and its laws.</p>
   <p>8th. Abolition of war. War is a detriment to civilization. And the promotion of good will and peace for all the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1317.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>9th. "Gnothe Seauton" (know thyself). Respect yourself and others will respect you.</p>
   <p>These are, according to my humble conception, the duties of the Greek professionals, and I suggest that our society, which is now inactive, begin to act again for the interest of society and our own.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
