<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Proud Declaration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0854</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0854.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PROUD DECLARATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is the declaration that the Greeks of Chicago should voice to the President of the United States: "O Beloved President!"</p>
   <p>"We want you to know that we are ready, willing and proud to offer every possible assistance to this, our adopted country. We believe, as did our forefathers, that there is no word sweeter than Patritha (Fatherland)--even if we are only its adopted children...."</p>
   <p>Using that as a basis, we state that although born in Greece and therefore called Greeks, we became adopted children of America when we immigrated to her welcoming shores. Spiritual and physical forces have since then linked us even closer to this our second fatherland; and we believe that we have an equal right as that of its natural children to show our appreciation at this time.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0855.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Appreciation and thankfulness were preached by our Saviour; and He was led to punish those who lacked these virtues. Does not the Bible say "I was hungry, and ye gave me food; I thirsted and ye gave me to drink; I was naked and ye covered my nakedness"?</p>
   <p>Therefore the voice of our country should be able to say to us, "You honored me when dishonor was attempted. You spared me from the injustice that threatened me. And when in danger, you saved me." Let us enable America to say to us, "To you belong the glory, the honor, and the benefit of your good deeds."</p>
   <p>Forward! then, to our sacred duty. Let the Star-Spangled Banner decorate our breasts; and let it wave as a symbol of freedom from our housetops, and the front of our stores. We, the Greek-Americans of Chicago, are true to America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
