<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1913-09-20">Sept. 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Who Is to Blame?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0954</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0954.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-09-20">Sept. 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WHO IS TO BLAME?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Why this indifference and lack of interest on the part of the Greek people of Chicago, especially after our two victorious Balkan wars? Why the spiritual inertia on the part of our Greek organizations and societies? At this time we should all rejoice for our nation's triumph.</p>
   <p>Is it perhaps because we cannot believe that what has happened in the last ten months in the Balkans is true and real? Have we any doubt that our most cherished dreams have materialized? Or have the vast distances from Greece affected our hearts to such a degree that our sacred enthusiasm and patriotic loyalty need rekindling?</p>
   <p>We have seen and applauded many magnificent demonstrations and celebrations which our organizations have arranged in the past. But how is it that they have failed to participate in the celebration and rejoicing after the great Greek military and naval victories against Turkey and Bulgaria? Why haven't the Greeks <pb facs="5422062_2_0955.jpg" n="2"/>of Chicago, the Greeks of America, hastened to rejoice with and congratulate two million liberated brothers of ours in Macedonia, Epirus, Crete, and the Aegean Islands? Is there any more beautiful, timely, and more appropriate occasion for a Panhellenic celebration?</p>
   <p>Will any better opportunity arise for our American friends to give actual proof of their noble sentiments? At what other time could our host, the American people, find a better opportunity to congratulate us warmly for the good fortune that has befallen our country? Would they not share our happiness and jubilation? Strange as it may seem, the Greek colony of Chicago, and the Greeks of America in general, have shown such great indifference on this important occasion that we have not given an inappropriate title to this editorial.</p>
   <p>Yes, who is to blame for this state of affairs? This is a question which we shall endeavor to answer. It is a fact that ten thousand Greeks from Chicago, and forty thousand from the United States as a whole, fought bravely and shed their blood in our two glorious wars, defending country and faith. This is one <pb facs="5422062_2_0956.jpg" n="3"/>more reason why we should attach more significance to our national victories and triumphs.</p>
   <p>No one will fail to notice our great, populous Greek communities in America, where disorganization and complete moral and spiritual degeneration have taken a firm hold of our people. Only a few of the leaders of our church communities and organizations are struggling superbly and valiantly to revitalize and regenerate our religious and patriotic ideas and ideals. Unfortunately, however, the noble efforts of a few genuine Greeks are being shattered against the cold indifference which has chilled our enthusiasm and dampened our interest.</p>
   <p>Why should this happen? Do not seek far for the cause. Do not look outside for the real cause. The root of all evil is to be found in our individual hearts. Protracted disunion, incessant personal passions, and continuous civil wars are the incurable diseases with which the Greeks of Chicago, and indeed all the Greeks in the United States, are afflicted. This is why we are neglecting important duties. This is why we are not responding to the heart throbs of our <pb facs="5422062_2_0957.jpg" n="4"/>brothers in Greece. Instead of educating and guiding, the Greek press is adding to the curse of disunion and disaster.</p>
   <p>We are sure that most Greeks were horrified and embittered when instead of paeans and victorious songs they read the most defamatory and disgusting articles against Premier Venizelos, Minister of Foreign Affairs Koromilas, and King Constantine, in the Greek press of Chicago and New York. When the Greeks of Chicago are forced to read such unpatriotic and unsympathetic publications, when the Greek people of our community are being offered the intellectual poison of the press, there is no wonder that every interest in our national affairs has disappeared.</p>
   <p>The continuation of this indifferent attitude, this callous indifference to the great historical events occurring in Greece and to the fate of our country, indicate that our future welfare, our unity, and our very existence in America are seriously threatened.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
