<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1936-02-15">Feb. 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Biographical Notes on Mr. Andrew John Vlachos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1936-02-15">Feb. 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">BIOGRAPHICAL NOTES ON MR. ANDREW JOHN VLACHOS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6- Born in the village of Samarades, near the city of Tripoli in Arcadia, Andrew John Vlachos was reared in Tripoli and there attended school. At the age of sixteen he enrolled in the law school of the University of Athens, Greece, from which he graduated after four years with the degree of doctor of law.</p>
   <p>He came to Chicago in 1902, where he studied law at the Northwestern University Law School and at the Hamilton College of Law. From both these institutions he received the degree of bachelor of law.</p>
   <p>In 1916 Mr. Vlachos was admitted to the bar of the State of Illinois, of which he has been a member ever since, enjoying the support and esteem of the Greek people of Chicago, who respect his integrity and his conscientious ability.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0546.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For some time Mr. Vlachos shared offices with the Hon. Edward R. Litsinger, a member of the Board of Review. Since 1924 he has been a member of the law firm of Adelman and Vlachos, with offices at 127 North Dearborn Street.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vlachos entered politics ten years ago and has been active in elections. He supported Mr. Litsinger for mayor and has worked for other candidates, among whom were Senator Deneen and Judge John Swanson.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vlachos went to Greece in 1909 to serve in the army, returning to Chicago after a year and a half. In 1912 he went back to Greece with a large number of Greek volunteers and fought in the Balkan-Turkish War, first as a soldier and afterwards as sergeant. He took part in the capture of Jannina in Epirus and in the battles of Saloniki, Kilkis, and Kresna. He was honorably discharged and he returned to Chicago in 1914.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0547.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Vlachos has delivered many lectures in his twenty-five years of active life here, discussing those national, political, social,and educational subjects which are connected with the progress of Hellenism in America.</p>
   <p>The appointment of Mr. Vlachos as assistant prosecuting state's attorney for Cook County has great significance for the Greeks of Chicago and the county.</p>
   <p>Perhaps this article will inspire the Greeks of Chicago to cooperate in public affairs, to appreciate more thoroughly the value of energetic participation in the politics of this country, and to seek at the hands of great American political leaders further tokens of recognition and esteem for the 25,000 Greek voters of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0548.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The commercial genius of the Greeks is recognized. Now their political strength and acumen must be recognized also, and such recognition can be gained only by political unity and by clean, honest political action.</p>
   <p>We hope that this appointment indicates the favorable attitude of American politicians toward the Greeks, and we heartily congratulate Mr. Vlachos and wish for him still greater success hereafter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
