<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-12-22">Dec. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Duty to This Country</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0794</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0794.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-12-22">Dec. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR DUTY TO THIS COUNTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The moral worth of an individual is proportionate to his realization and fulfillment of his duties. The person who desires to obtain and retain the respect of his community or country, must be ready to shoulder his share of the burden, no matter what its nature may be. By doing so he acquires certain rights and privileges in the country and community in which he lives.</p>
   <p>In view of the truth of the above statements, we offer some advice to our fellow countrymen. If we strive to live decently and in harmony with the laws and customs of this country, we shall, in turn, be allowed to perform our duties as citizens, businessmen and individuals, without any interference. We must always remember that, if we are obligated to do our duty towards our native land, where we were born and raised; we are doubly duty-bound to this, our adopted country; because we were welcomed here with open arms, and the only thing required <pb facs="5422062_2_0795.jpg" n="2"/>of us was good citizenship.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to conduct ourselves in such a manner that we will earn the respect and good will of the American people. We must show by our actions that we are worthy of the kindness and welcome proffered to us. Therefore as individuals, in both our private and public lives, we must be trustworthy and honest; and must respect the moral codes of this country. By doing these things we shall be able to live harmoniously and happily with our neighbors; but if we do not do them we shall live in a world of antagonism and resentment. Such a condition will be harmful for all concerned.</p>
   <p>We must right our attitudes towards business, and improve upon our standards of conducting it. We must improve our education and our business training and bring them up to par with American business levels for our own good...let us be rid of our empty egoism, and merge our interests; for by so doing we strengthen ourselves immeasurably. Unity gives strength, and strength makes all things possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0796.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>So far, we have emphasized the commercial benefits to be gained by having a good business reputation, but we must give heed to our private habits also. An earnest desire to do good must govern all our thoughts and actions. Our friends and pastimes, must be carefully selected because others will judge us by them.</p>
   <p>Finally, as citizens and residents of this country we are duty-bound to offer ourselves and our services to this country; and as sincere citizens we must keep wide awake to serve her needs at this crucial time. By giving our aid to our adopted land we are helping our own interests at the same time, because the interests of a nation and its citizens are irrevocably bound to one another. It is unforgivable for us to sacrifice the country's interests to the selfishness or egoism of any individual or group.</p>
   <p>These are just a few words of advice that are much needed by the Greeks in America. Try to comprehend the magnitude of the obligations of the Greek people to the American nation; and then expend all your efforts towards fulfilling them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
