<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-06-15">June 15, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Spider Webs</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0998</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0998.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-06-15">June 15, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SPIDER WEBS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night my lawyer friend and I visited the Police Court: he, to defend a Greek who had committed a minor offense, and I, to seek material for this column.</p>
   <p>For over an hour a continuous stream of humanity flowed past the front of the judge's desk. I was impressed with the fact that the majority of the accused were boys charged with petty crimes. In my opinion, formed from an acquaintance with their background, environment, and enforced idleness, most of them were completely innocent of crime. Among other accusations was the one that they annoyed other people by begging for nickels and dimes on the streets. Not only are they innocent, but they can with justice accuse the world of far more serious offenses than theirs.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0999.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One by one, they passed in front of the judge. He spoke kindly to them; but this does not satisfy justice, for he also warned each not to repeat his offense. That was his duty. He even advised the culprits to leave the city. That was entirely unjust for the simple reason that they were homeless. Therefore, no matter where they should go, they would be nomads.</p>
   <p>The kindly judge freed them. Free! But where should they go? To another town where they would be picked up by the local police and given the same advice? And so, on and on--until a real crime is listed after their names. For, although they are not criminals now, they will most certainly turn to crime. And who will be responsible for the delinquency of our youths? Who else but the entire nation, which allows its youth to be chased from one place to another? Its youth--which will be the citizenry of tomorrow! Nomadic youth! Betrayed youth! In this, the richest country of the world!</p>
   <p>Would it not be better and more just, when a boy or young man is apprehended for loitering or begging, because of lack of work; to give him employment <pb facs="5422062_2_1000.jpg" n="3"/>or show him a way to earn an honest living?</p>
   <p>We can, of course, put our young offenders in jail. But that is terrible to contemplate. In prison, all are treated like hardened criminals. If they are not criminals when they enter, they come out completely-trained enemies of society. The very words "prison" and "guilty" bear the stigma of hundreds of years of association with all that is evil and sordid. A young man sent to prison will have a black mark on his reputation for the rest of his life.</p>
   <p>So, it is evident that our laws are wrong and that justice does not reign in our courts. Even in normal times, our courts have many cases of homeless, bedraggled, hopeless nomads. We should remember the words spoken by Anaharsis two thousand years ago: "The best civilization is the one in which the smallest injustice against the poorest man becomes an in-justice against all the people."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1001.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This is not a small, but a tremendous crime which is being committed by our nation against its youth. We do not understand that soon we shall feel the effects of this injustice because its victims will soon be adult citizens of this country. Our present laws are like spider webs. They catch and hold flies and bugs--but not eagles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
