<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-02-21">Feb. 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Federal Constitution of the United States of America</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Andrew J. Vlachos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1129</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1129.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-02-21">Feb. 21, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE FEDERAL CONSTITUTION OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Andrew J. Vlachos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the request of our esteemed Chicago newspaper, The Greek Star, I am happy to translate, discuss, and publish the Federal Constitution of the United States of America in this newspaper. I think that this will contribute much to the education of the Greek people of Chicago as well as to all those who wish to learn more about this important and fundamental written instrument of our adopted country. There is no doubt that we have much to profit from such a study and from a detailed knowledge of its provisions.</p>
   <p>However, before I translate the text of the constitution itself, I propose to make some introductory remarks on the Federal Constitution and its significance to our people.</p>
   <p>Commencing with the basic notion that not only the native-born but also the <pb facs="5422062_2_1130.jpg" n="2"/>newly arriving immigrants and non-citizens in the United States are obligated to abide by the provisions, of the constitution, we deem it necessary to acquire a thorough knowledge of the organic law of the land. Compliance with this law and obedience to its explicit and implied legal and political provisions more or less depend on the degree and extent to which it is studied and minutely examined. Regardless as to whether this is our native, adopted, or prospective homeland, it is highly desirable, by those with political power and the Government of the United States, that citizens and residents of this country be acquainted with the most important constitutional, political, and social institutions of our republic.</p>
   <p>It is a truism that regard for and consciousness of the law is deeply imbedded and ingrained in human nature not only among the civilized societies but also among the less civilized or barbarian societies of men. Because of the innate conceptions of justice and injustice, right and wrong on the part of all humans even without having to study law formally, there is a great variety of laws and <pb facs="5422062_2_1131.jpg" n="3"/>there are innumerable conceptions regarding the purpose and function of the law and the established political or social customs.</p>
   <p>In spite of man's realization of the necessity for laws to regulate society, the natural tendency of man to conform to law is not sufficient. We are not fully conscious of the importance of laws and methods which are used unless every citizen or at least those who are to become leaders acquire a thorough and complete knowledge of the nature and process of the law.</p>
   <p>It is characteristic of man to use the power of speech, nevertheless, to speak properly and to express ideas there is need of education, guidance, and experience imparted and offered by our parents, teachers, and society in general. Man is naturally susceptible to the power of expression and communication of emotions, ideas, and desires through the power of speech but to increase and perfect this power there is need of intellectual development and advancement. That is why those who were taught the Greek language speak Greek, those who <pb facs="5422062_2_1132.jpg" n="4"/>were taught in English speak the English language, and those who were first taught the Turkish language use that particular language.</p>
   <p>Accordingly, among those of us who speak the Greek language, those who are lacking in educational attainments and opportunities speak Greek imperfectly, while the educated and those who have had more schooling speak the Greek language as easily and as freely as their intellectual power and development permits.</p>
   <p>So, man possesses numerous qualities which when left in their natural state contribute nothing or very little toward the progress and advancement of the individual and of society in general. On the other hand, by training and developing his mental powers and consciousness, man reaches beyond the narrow horizon of his biological existence and enters into a newer and higher life in the world of conscious and rational thought and mode of life.</p>
   <p>The same can be said about the rational and conscious conceptions of law by <pb facs="5422062_2_1133.jpg" n="5"/>every man. The natural tendency and regard of man for law are cultivated and developed as a necessary requirement in order that the individual may thus know which are the fundamental laws of society or the state. In this manner he will be able to enforce as well as to obey all laws not unconsciously but knowingly and consciously.</p>
   <p>Rational and conscious action is the highest expression of man's life and the highest end of his life. On such a life depends man's and the state's greatest happiness.</p>
   <p>This obligation of man's to know, study, and conform to the laws of society or the state in which he lives, an obligation which applies to all the states of the greatest state of all, that is, the world, applies also to the Greek immigrants of the United States of America in their relation to the laws of this country.</p>
   <p>The fundamental or constitutional laws of a nation are and must be the <pb facs="5422062_2_1134.jpg" n="6"/>constitution of both native-born and alien residents and inhabitants in the land. Superficial thinking might lead one to assume that the Federal Constitution of the United States and the laws of the several states which are based on it are intended for those who have been born or who have been naturalized in the states and not for the resident aliens. Many are under the impression that only the former are obliged to read and know the constitution and comply with it and the laws of a particular state and not the non-citizen residents.</p>
   <p>Can there be any more unreasonable thought? Who can support this idea without the risk of being called a blind idiot? It would do us good to remember that in case any alien's personal, family, or property rights and interests are injured or theatened, prompt recourse to the courts and authorities of the state in which he lives may be made for immediate help and support of the law against any third party, alien or native-born, who attempts to prevent him the free exercise of his rights. Or do we remain under the impression that in case <pb facs="5422062_2_1135.jpg" n="7"/>the rights and interests of aliens are questioned and endangered, that the Constitution and state laws do not apply to the aliens, but only to citizens? Would it be to our interest to allow our alien Greek groups to become the victims of lawlessness and predatory influences endangering their rights and interests, which they have created through hardships and great sacrifices?</p>
   <p>Such a notion could be entertained and in order, if the idea that, as such, the alien is under no obligation to study, know and conform to the laws or the Constitution of America, was accepted.</p>
   <p>In dealing with the Greek people of Chicago specifically and of the United States in general, we have not failed to notice that we too as a minority and immigrant group have been enjoying the natural advantages of this new land and great country; we breathe the free and clean air here; we are sustained by the sunlight which gives us warmth. In this country we also enjoy the privilege of using the American communication facilities, lighting, and all the public <pb facs="5422062_2_1136.jpg" n="8"/>conveniences. Is it not true that our people are protected by the police authorities and that they are secure and living in peace with their families? In every instance the life, health, liberty, honor, labor and possessions of every Greek in this country are guarded and protected by the states or the Government of the United States. In return for all these blessings and privileges which are extended to both the native-born as well as to the foreign-born, it is only proper and just that our people should not neglect to acquire a through knowledge of the political organization and the fundamental laws of this country. It is our duty not only to know the law but also to obey and respect it. We might even say that the alien groups in America should obey the laws with greater willingness than the native-born, because any alien violating laws is a bad reflection upon the entire nationality to which he belongs. If any laws are thus violated often enough the state might make more severe laws affecting aliens and may even take measures to restrict the immigration of a particular nationality. An example of this kind is the anti-immigration laws or Exclusion Acts which prevented Chinese and Japanese workers from entering <pb facs="5422062_2_1137.jpg" n="9"/>the United States. We can all understand that not only is obedience to the laws required of us but we must be grateful and recognize the obligations which we have assumed toward the government of America. We are expected to obey the laws of this country in the same way that Americans in Greece would respect the laws of Greece.</p>
   <p>The Greek who reads, knows, and lives by the Constitution of the United States does honor to himself and distinguishes himself by being obedient to the supreme laws of the land which has received him with such great hospitality. If he has become an American citizen, he is thus considered a loyal and useful citizen in the country of his adoption. By knowing and applying the laws of this country the Greek protects his interests and at the same time benefits and advances himself morally and materially.</p>
   <p>The obedience and conduct of the law-abiding Greek reflects honor and glory to our Greek homeland. All our actions and our entire behavior in America affects <pb facs="5422062_2_1138.jpg" n="10"/>the standing and the reputation of our nationality in this country.</p>
   <p>If our glorious ancestors have given Greece imperishable fame by their genius, by their eloquence, drama, philosophy, and arts; and if the human race has been profoundly affected thereby, it does not necessarily imply that every Greek today is equally worthy of admiration and respect. It does not necessarily imply that every Greek adds to "the glory that was Greece" simply because he happens to be descended from that great people of old. Unless he too can prove himself to be deserving of some praise for good works and unless he distinguishes himself in some way, he has no right whatever to claim any honors. Works of progress, peace, and order on the part of our people wherever they might be reflect honor and glory to our nationality and to our country.</p>
   <p>No Greek should refuse loyalty and obedience to all the laws, but especially to the Federal Constitution of the United States. Everyone, everywhere, and at all times must be a shining example of conscious and deliberate respect for the <pb facs="5422062_2_1139.jpg" n="11"/>law and civic morality. Every Greek in this city as well as throughout the United States should consider the liberties and privileges which are granted him the products of his obedience to and regard for the laws of our adopted country. Each of us must attempt to become intelligent and enlightened guardians of our laws by acting, working, and living in conformance to them.</p>
   <p>I have made this rather extensive introduction to our study and interpretation of the United States Constitution because I felt that such a study would be meaningless if every Greek of this community did not know that this also implies the necessity of living up to the fundamental laws of this land.</p>
   <p>I have proceeded to translate the Constitution of the United States in Greek not only for the benefit of the Greeks of Chicago, not only for the Greeks in the United States but also for our people in the homeland. Those who are interested in the law in Greece and those who have no knowledge of English may thus learn about the provisions and text of the supreme law of this great and <pb facs="5422062_2_1140.jpg" n="12"/>powerful republic on the other side of the Atlantic. With the guidance of such a great liberal, wise, and democratic instrument of law this country has developed, grown, and eventually advanced to the high station of the most progressive, wealthiest, and most promising nation on earth.</p>
   <p>The political system of this country is the nearest thing to perfection because it harmonizes all the many complex relationships among all citizens.</p>
   <p>So, I deemed it necessary to translate the Constitution of the United States with its fifteen amendments.</p>
   <p>Andrew J. Vlachos</p>
   <p>[In a future issue of The Greek Star Mr. Andrew J. Vlachos will give a summary of the historical events which preceded and climaxed the drafting and adoption of the Federal Constitution of the United States.- The Editor]</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1141.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>I here propose to give a running historical account of the American Revolution of 1776 and its outstanding protagonist, George Washington, the great general and statesman, whose life and influence had a direct and decisive effect on the formulation of the Federal Constitution of the United State of America.</p>
   <p>It would interest the Greek people of Chicago to know that America too had to fight hard and suffer indescribable trials and hardships before she won her political independence and before she laid the foundations of a great and powerful independent and free republic. The long struggle for freedom from dependence on the power and discretion of a tyrant and foreign power gave us a keen sense of appreciation for the many blessings of peace, justice, and prosperity which we now enjoy.</p>
   <p>The Revolutionary War of 1776-1787 can be compared to the Greek Revolutionary War of 1821-1829. Both insurrections were motivated by the strong desire of the subject American colonists and Greeks to vindicate their inalienable human <pb facs="5422062_2_1142.jpg" n="14"/>rights to freedom and justice.</p>
   <p>There can be no doubt that the government of the United States of America as well as the confederated states of this republic are the direct result and outcome of the great struggle of the colonists of this continent to liberate themselves from the despotic and oppressive tyranny of the British Empire. The original thirteen states were British colonies until 1776 when the latter took up arms to shake off the British yoke in a long, bloody war which lasted until 1783, or the year when a truce was declared between the two opponents.</p>
   <p>July 4 is considered a great National Holiday in the United States of America, for on that day the seven-year war for independence began. This is a holiday comparable to ours which is celebrated on March 25, because on March 25, 1821 the Greek people took up arms to regain their freedom from the Ottoman Empire.</p>
   <p>The thirteen British colonies which waged the war of liberation against Great <pb facs="5422062_2_1143.jpg" n="15"/>Britain were: New Hampshire, Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Providence Plantations, Connecticut, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, and Georgia.</p>
   <p>This great American Revolution which occupies a brilliant place in the history of the nations of the world was directed and guided by a great military leader by the name of George Washington, who was born in Westmoreland County, Virginia, on February 22, 1732 and died at Mount Vernon on December 14, 1799. This great historical figure is considered the founder and father of the American Republic as well as the greatest fighter for American independence. For these reasons, he is revered and gratefully remembered by the American people.</p>
   <p>George Washington, who was one of the delegates of Virginia's State Assembly to the Continental Congress of the Thirteen Colonies at Philadelphia on May 10, 1775, was chosen commander in chief of the American armies which were to engage the powerful forces of the British Empire on the field of battle. He was to <pb facs="5422062_2_1144.jpg" n="16"/>fight for the rights and privileges of the American Colonies of which they were deprived by a powerful oppressor. It was this abridgment of privileges and rights which precipitated the revolt of the colonies against the British. Taxation without representation was the issue mainly that gave rise to unrest and dissatisfaction of the American Colonies with the mastery of the British Empire.</p>
   <p>We shall certainly overstep the bounds of this study if we attempt a detailed analysis of the many causes which contributed to the Revolutionary War, an extensive knowledge of which can be obtained by reading the American history. Even if we attempt to give a brief account of the tremendous difficulties and handicaps under which George Washington assumed the responsibility of leading the armies, especially in the beginning of the Revolution, we shall be transcending the scope of this article.</p>
   <p>However, in order to give a wide perspective of the important events and <pb facs="5422062_2_1145.jpg" n="17"/>circumstances which led up to the conclusion of the war in 1783 and to the adoption of the Federal Constitution of the United States in 1787, it is permissible to recount briefly not only the military difficulties which were encountered by the Revolutionary heroes of 1776 but also the lack of a unified and strong government; the lack of a properly trained and permanent army; the lack of perfect political unity of action between the thirteen colonies which participated in the Revolution. Lastly, it is worthwhile to remember the financial difficulties which had to be overcome by the provisional government of the Thirteen Colonies.</p>
   <p>We can only say this, in passing; the circumstances under which the Revolutionary armies were laboring were so difficult and the well-trained, well-equipped, and magnificently organized British military and naval forces were comparatively so overwhelming at the inception of the insurrection, that even the bravest and most cool-headed general would be confounded and discouraged.</p>
   <p>This is even attested by a private letter of Washington's to his brother in <pb facs="5422062_2_1146.jpg" n="18"/>which are described the fears and uncertainties which were experienced by the general because of the desperate state of affairs in connection with the army. Washington writes, "....I am wearied almost to death with reverses and I solemnly declare that a pecuniary reward of twenty thousand pounds a year would not induce me to undergo what I do; and perhaps, lose my disposition after all, as it is impossible, under such a variety of distressing circumstances, to conduct matters pleasing to public expectation, or even to the expectations of those who employ me, as they will not make proper allowances for the difficulties their own errors have occasioned."</p>
   <p>But all the nations on earth during their long and adventurous history and national struggles have experienced critical and painful setbacks and upheavals whose repercussions were felt, by all the people, but, primarily, by those who govern the affairs of the nation during its most stormy periods.</p>
   <p>During the time of Washington, the people and the army also expected the <pb facs="5422062_2_1147.jpg" n="19"/>commander in chief to lead the cause, organize the armies and finances, and unite the governments and the peoples of the several colonies towards a common effort. One man had to bear the tremendous burden of guiding the destiny of a desperately fighting nation. George Washington suffered many bitter experiences and anxieties with patience and exemplary fortitude, especially noteworthy because of the deplorable condition in which the army was found and because there was no strong and well-organized government which could have a decisive influence over the affairs of all thirteen colonies, disunited and loosely organized as they were at the beginning of the war.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, it is very true that such trials and sufferings make for great nations and great leaders. In most instances they bring forth their good fruits.</p>
   <p>In the beginning of the Revolutionary War of 1776-1783, undoubtedly, the sufferings, the privations, and the lack of men and materials to carry on the war, all contributed powerfully to increase Washington's political wisdom <pb facs="5422062_2_1148.jpg" n="20"/>besides giving him the opportunity to know the various political and military needs of the country. They also contributed to his winning the loyalty, devotion, and trust of the people through personal contacts with most of the representatives of the separate colonies. All these experiences had much to do with the success of the Constitutional Convention and the adoption of the Constitution of the United States of America, on which rests the magnificent political organization of this republic.</p>
   <p>The power and might of Washington and the American people were born primarily of the innumerable sacrifices, the weaknesses of the government and other military and political vicissitudes which had to be met and remedied.</p>
   <p>It is highly questionable if the American people today could have made so much progress and become so strong had their mettle not been tested in war and in a desperate and unequal struggle for the assurance of their freedom. It is no exaggeration to say that the formulation and formal adoption of the Constitution <pb facs="5422062_2_1149.jpg" n="21"/>of the United States was made possible to a very large extent by the influence of George Washington's character, wisdom, and great prestige as a soldier and statesman. Under his general command the American armies were victorious against the British and the colonies became free and independent from oppression and tyranny. He presided over the Philadelphia Constitutional Convention of 1787 which debated, drafted, voted, and finally adopted the supreme law of the land, the Constitution of the United States, with all its historic and very important articles. Thus the political union and federation of the colonies was effected naming the liberated colonies, the United States of America, forming the greatest confederation in the world which is respected and admired by all.</p>
   <p>Honored and loved by the American people, George Washington not only was called from his home in Mount Vernon, after the conclusion of the war, to preside over the Constitutional Convention at Philadelphia but upon him was bestowed the supreme honor of being elected the first president of the United States--March 4, 1789. At the expiration of his first term of office, he was again elected <pb facs="5422062_2_1150.jpg" n="22"/>president having guided the affairs of the newly born nation brilliantly until 1797.</p>
   <p>The trust which the people put in Washington was not betrayed because during the eight years of his administration he was the outstanding example of political wisdom and virtue. From his time till today the political life of America has been guided by the Constitution and men who followed the example which the first president of the United States set in obeying and defending the greatest written legal document of this country.</p>
   <p>The policies and ideas of the "Father of Our Country" who was "first in war, first in peace, and first in the hearts of his countrymen" have become cherished political traditions which have been faithfully kept by the people of the United States.</p>
   <p>Andrew J. Vlachos</p>
   <p>February 25, 1908.</p>
   <p>(To be continued)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
