<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-03-07">Mar. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Historic Evolution </title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0928</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0928.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-03-07">Mar. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR HISTORIC EVOLUTION </title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By the great revolutionary war of 1821, and by the victorious wars of 1912 and 1913 fought for our complete liberation, the Greek nation has been resurrected and reconstituted after many centuries of subjection to the cruel and barbarous Ottoman Empire. A casual review of Greek history will reveal the long and unequal struggle the Greek people have waged to regain their freedom and political independence. Today, the Greek people are fighting one more battle--the battle for the reconstruction and the organization of our domestic, political, economic, and social life. These efforts may in some respects be more strenuous than those required to defeat and expel the foreign enemy. We should not forget that some things are easy to acquire, but difficult to keep. All our spiritual, intellectual, physical, and moral forces are required to preserve and defend what we have gained in <pb facs="5422062_2_0929.jpg" n="2"/>wartime. In times of peace, our vigilance should not slacken, our desire to work hard and to put our internal affairs in order and perfect harmony with our needs should not weaken. We have many difficult problems to solve, among which is the satisfaction of Italy's demands on the Greek province of Epirus. We know that Italy envies Greece her victories and expansion as a result of the Balkan wars. The disaster which befell Turkey and Bulgaria should remind Italy of the determination of the Greek people to preserve and protect what we have rightfully gained with blood and superhuman efforts. The people of Epirus are determined not to yield one inch of the territory which is historically and traditionally theirs.</p>
   <p>The Greek people of Chicago, indeed the Greeks throughout America, have their eyes and hearts turned to our revitalized and reconstructed fatherland; they are now vitally interested in the evolution of our historical destiny in the Balkans and in Europe. While the Greeks of this community are confident that Greece will emerge victorious from any involvement or international <pb facs="5422062_2_0930.jpg" n="3"/>difficulty they have never stopped thinking of how they can support our beloved fatherland and offer her every possible moral and material assistance.</p>
   <p>The natives of Epirus living in Chicago have showed great concern over the struggle of their brothers in Epirus to ward off the new enemy. Many hundreds of Epirotes [Chicago Greeks who are natives of Epirus] have been leaving en masse for Greece, eager to defend Epirus and save their loved ones from the tyrannical Italian rule. Their example will inspire many Greeks of Chicago from other parts of Greece to go to the support of their brothers. Most of us cannot forget that there are many thousands of subjugated and unredeemed Greeks in Albania, Thrace, Constantinople, and Asia Minor. We have never abandoned our hope and aspirations to see them incorporated into Greece and become a part of a great and powerful Greek nation.</p>
   <p>While we, the Greeks of Chicago, indeed all American Greeks, are occupied with <pb facs="5422062_2_0931.jpg" n="4"/>the important problem of Epirus, we have never forgotten, as our brothers in Greece have not, that Constantinople, the Great Ideal of historic Greece, has always been and must permanently become a part of the Greek kingdom.</p>
   <p>In vain are the enemies of Greece trying to prevent our people from realizing their most cherished national dreams and ambitions. Greece will continue to be triumphant and glorious.</p>
   <p>Divine Providence has decreed that Greece is to live, grow, and become a great nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
