<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1913-12-13">Dec. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Woman Suffrage Movement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-12-13">Dec. 13, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE WOMAN SUFFRAGE MOVEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the greatest problems of the twentieth century is woman suffrage. Indeed, every century seems to be notable for a new major social or political problem. The twentieth century must cope with the thorniest of problems--the revolt of the rank and file of womanhood against the inviolate social custom or tradition of accepting the superiority and dominance of man over the woman in every social, economic, and political matter. Man has long considered him-self the absolute master of his wife. He has always exercised many exclusive and indisputable privileges and rights which were taboo for womanhood.</p>
   <p>Lately, however, the world of women is beginning to assert itself with all the passion, forcefulness, and fury which woman is capable of expressing.</p>
   <p>Saloniki is very much interested in the controversy and the veritable battles which have arisen even in our own Greek community between those who would give woman complete equality with man in many fields of activity and those who <pb facs="5422062_2_1176.jpg" n="2"/>violently oppose any such attempt.</p>
   <p>Many heated arguments take place, especially between men and women. Women say that without women there would be no men. They say that the race cannot be perpetuated without the assistance of women. Why shouldn't women exercise the same political rights as men? Why shouldn't they be permitted to vote, and to be elected to civic or political offices?</p>
   <p>In vain does man invoke the Gospel and Christ, who teaches that woman must fear man. In vain do many male scholars and historians invoke the opinions of the wise men who have declared that woman is merely an object, a tool, "res", according to the Romans. In vain do the descendants of Adam tell of what happened to the first man because of the stupidity of the first woman, Eve.</p>
   <p>Regardless of these humorous allusions, women are determined to win the right to vote.</p>
   <p>Thus far everything is going well for the women. Some men seem to be satisfied <pb facs="5422062_2_1177.jpg" n="3"/>with the progress of the woman suffrage movement, for they say that the fair sex will not win more than equal rights with men. One Italian proverb says, however, "the appetite grows in the process of eating". Evidently, the women are preparing to give new battle in order to discourage the idea that the "strong" sex is superior to the "fair" sex.</p>
   <p>Let us see what the outcome of this battle will be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
