<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1919-05-31">May 31, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning Journalism</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-05-31">May 31, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING JOURNALISM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Standards in the profession of journalism are at present practically ignored by the Greeks. No requirements or qualifications are demanded and for this reason we see journalists spring up like weeds. They are tolerated by the Greek community, not because their worthlessness is not recognized, but because the community is kept too busy in its struggle for existence to devote any time to other matters. Greeks are so occupied with seeking dollars that they pay no attention to these gentlemen, who take advantage of one of the most dignified professions.</p>
   <p>Society is composed of cultured people, educated people, literates and illiterates. All four groups need journalism; therefore, should not a journalist have many qualifications if he is to guide society? He should be a master of the language, and at the same time he should be encyclopedic in his knowledge.....For instance, a community wants to form an opinion <pb facs="5422062_2_1350.jpg" n="2"/>about some political situation. The only way it can be done is through the newspapers. Society expects the journalist to determine whether the issues are good or bad, and whether or not it should support them. It can be seen that the journalist is a kinetic influence who educates and influences the community. Do we, today, know the wishes of the people as they are expressed in the newspapers? Are the newspapers a "spiritual mirror of the people"?</p>
   <p>When some situation arises, as exists today, various selfish and ignorant men who masquerade as journalists influence the people by their writings, and cause more confusion and dissension than existed previously. This is why many fine minds of our community are not given the chance to unite the people. The various journalists, with the power of the press behind them, spend all their efforts in keeping the various groups at swords' points. A journalist without the proper background resembles a small <pb facs="5422062_2_1351.jpg" n="3"/>child playing with a razor--there is fear either that he will cut himself, or that he will injure his playmates.</p>
   <p>....The church and the professional groups must unite to raise the level of Creek journalism here in Chicago; for by so doing they will be aiding the community to become better informed and to function in a wiser, and more just manner.</p>
   <p>Dr. C. Kalionzis</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
