<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1927-09-24">September 24, 1927</date><title level="a">The Two-Headed Monster: Appeal to the Greeks against Communism.-</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0096</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0096.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1927-09-24">September 24, 1927</date><title level="a">The Two-Headed Monster: Appeal to the Greeks Against Communism.-</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With a great chagrin I see, that not only in Greece, but here also, some of our Greek sons have communistic tendencies.</p>
   <p>In Greece, some years ago, a group of Bolshiviks invaded our country and united themselves with that element of Greece, which advocates the change of our language, forming the two-headed monster and making ingress into the hearts of the uninformed, advocating better language, better times and the abolition of capital. While our authorities thought that as silly, the poisonous and destructive propaganda worked smoothly and swiftly, initiating members and advocating a real paradise on earth. In order that our readers of Saloniki realize what kind of Paradise the Bolshiviks have prepared for Greece, I'll print, briefly, some of the writings of Mr. Aristides Andronicos, who until recently was Greek Consul-General in Petrograd and, who for many years studied the diabolic plans of the Bolshiviks.</p>
   <p>"The Moguls of Bolshivism in Russia are the biggest Demagogues of all history, instead of turning Russia to an earthly Paradise, they have turned it into Hades.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0097.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The tragic scenes of Nero and the Medieval Crusaders' were absolutely children's play in comparison to what took place under the Bolshivik yoke. The leaders of Communism in Russia applied the principle of their dogma to the extent of grabbing the wealth of the rich, which they did not distribute to the poor, as they said, but kept it for themselves." Their advocacy, that manual laborers should govern the country is contrary to the laws of Nature and God. In my future publications, I will analyze the matter thoroughly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
