<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-02-23">Feb. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Twenty-Seventh Ward Greek Political and Educational Club.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-02-23">Feb. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE TWENTY-SEVENTH WARD GREEK POLITICAL AND EDUCATIONAL CLUB.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5-To the Greek voters of the twenty-seventh (formerly nineteenth) ward:</p>
   <p>We hereby notify all Greek voters of this ward with reference to the primary election of February 27, 1923, that the twenty-seventh ward Greek Political and Educational Club has seen the candidates who are listed on the ballots and has decided to support with all its power, these Democratic candidates: William Denver, for the office of mayor of the great city of Chicago and John Touhy for the office of alderman of the twenty-seventh ward.</p>
   <p>As you know, what was formerly the nineteenth ward has been divided among other wards, and since the twenty-seventh ward now includes the Greek colony of the West Side, and since among the candidates for the office of alderman Mr. Touhy is the only friend of the philhellenic politicians, Messrs. John Powers and James Bowler, we deem it best for all Greek voters of the twenty-seventh ward to vote for Mr. Touhy in this election.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0321.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Touhy is at all times willing to serve the interests of Greeks as individuals and as a community.</p>
   <p>Any one who desires to meet Mr. Touhy and to be assured of his philhellenism may come in the evening to our Club, which is located above the candy-store of Mr. K. Livanos, Madison and Paulina street.</p>
   <p>We hope that we shall receive your kind approval, and we remain sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>C. Leyanos</p>
   <p>P. Agriostathis</p>
   <p>G. Nielson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
