<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-02-03">Feb. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Out of Resfect [For America]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0862</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0862.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-02-03">Feb. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUT OF RESFECT [FOR AMERICA]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Certain individuals who are active in the founding of patriotic Greek societies have inquired why Saloniki does not devote more space to the activities of those organizations. These clubs are usually representative of some particular section of Greece, and are thus vitally interested in the political situations affecting those sections. These individuals desire to have Saloniki justify its omissions, which are felt to be unpatriotic. Our reason for not giving more space to these societies is not indifference toward Greece, nor a lack of interest in the political problems of these societies; our reason is our respect for the government of the country in which we now live. We are trying to remain neutral, in accordance with the neutrality policy of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0863.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Having emigrated from our homeland to the shores of America, it is our duty to respect the laws and the political viewpoint of this country. We were admitted into the United States on the understanding that we were to become good citizens. Let us live up to that understanding.</p>
   <p>It is evident that our interests lie in respecting the laws of this country, which at present is strictly neutral. Therefore we will make every effort to live in accordance with the law, and will avoid taking sides on issues which will sooner or later cause strife and disagreement among the Greek people. To have a political opinion is the privilege of everyone; but political activities must be conducted discreetly, so that they will not become dangerous to the general welfare.</p>
   <p>Political opinions should be exchanged in a friendly spirit lest they become cause for dissension. When they lead to arguments and fist-fights they <pb facs="5422062_2_0864.jpg" n="3"/>invariably come to the attention of the law--and cast a reflection upon the entire group involved in them.</p>
   <p>It is necessary that we refrain from meetings which have no chance of accomplishing anything, because they cause dissention instead of harmony and unity. If we were all united and co-operative, then we could make our requests in a calm, dignified, attention-commanding manner which would produce results.....</p>
   <p>Every one has his own logic and judgment, and can make his own decisions, based upon his mental and spiritual knowledge.</p>
   <p>Do not form opinions as to what is going on in Greece, and in the rest of the warring countries, since other conditions exist over there, and matters are looked at from a different point of view. Perhaps if we were living there, matters would look quite different to us. We are not advocating indifference, <pb facs="5422062_2_0865.jpg" n="4"/>but "when in doubt between two evils, choose the lesser evil".....Those who believe in the king, or in Venizelos, have a right to their opinion; but let them adopt a peaceful attitude.</p>
   <p>That is the humble opinion of the editors of this newspaper, and this article has been written to clarify the attitude of Saloniki.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
