<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The New Generation</title><title level="a" type="sub">Two Thousand Shoe-shine Parlors in Chicago--Three Thousand Greek Children Kept in Semislavery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW GENERATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Two Thousand Shoe-shine Parlors in Chicago--Three Thousand Greek Children Kept in Semislavery</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the Saloniki began the campaign to help the poor Greek youths employed--to be more exact, enslaved--in the shoe-shine establishments, its offices have been deluged with letters.</p>
   <p>We have received letters from some of the slaveys themselves, full of poignant and heart-breaking revelations. We have received letters from humane citizens, pledging themselves to aid the plight of these children.</p>
   <p>Today, we have published as many letters as we could possibly make room for. These letters are full of encouragement and support, and give us added courage in our fight for the salvation of our young Greek boys.</p>
   <p>Various remedies have been suggested, such as organizing the shoe-shine <pb facs="5422062_2_1036.jpg" n="2"/>employees into a union, or forming a protective association composed of members of the community.</p>
   <p>We suggest that the employers put themselves at the head of such a movement. They should decrease the hours of work and improve the working conditions; and they should abide by these rules.</p>
   <p>They must agree to close their stores on Sundays, to allow one hour for lunch and one hour for supper, to provide hygienic sleeping accommodations, and to protect the morals of these boys by keeping depraved individuals from preying on their innocence, or ignorance, as the case may be.</p>
   <p>Every Greek is a lover and defender of liberty, and such conditions must not be tolerated any longer.....</p>
   <p>All the Hellenes are ready to fight the fierce Turks or Bulgarians because <pb facs="5422062_2_1037.jpg" n="3"/>they enslave and degrade the Greek patriots who are unfortunate enough to fall into their hands. Why, therefore, do the Greeks allow the exploitation and enslavement of thousands of small Greek children who work in shoe-shine shops?</p>
   <p>The Saloniki has undertaken the task of exposing these conditions in the name of humanity and patriotism. We are proud of the public response to our editorials. The whole Greek community is aroused, and clamors for an immediate improvement of these conditions.....</p>
   <p>Forward, all patriotic and sensible Greek employers! Call a general meeting in order to find the solution of this major social problem. After[various] ideas have been discussed, it will be a simple matter to take steps to alleviate these conditions.</p>
   <p>When the employers do that, they will receive the applause of the whole Greek community; they will be esteemed by other businessmen, and they will, <pb facs="5422062_2_1038.jpg" n="4"/>in time, attract a large American clientele.</p>
   <p>At present they are not patronized by many Americans because of their obvious ill-treatment of their employees.</p>
   <p>Let us all take an active part in this campaign, so that it will benefit both the employers and the employees.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
