<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material (Manuscript) in Possession of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title>, 221 M. La Salle St. Chicago, Illinois.
<title level="a">The Achaian League Minutes of the First Meeting of the Committee on Extraordinary Matters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0358</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
   <catRef target="#source-miscellaneous"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0358.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material (Manuscript) In Possession of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title>, 221 M. La Salle St. Chicago, Illinois.
<title level="a">THE ACHAIAN LEAGUE MINUTES OF THE FIRST MEETING OF THE COMMITTEE ON EXTRAORDINARY MATTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first meeting of the Committee on Extraordinary Matters of the Achaian League was held at its office, at 13<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> N. Clark St., Room 816 Ashland Block, Chicago, Illinois, on the 2nd day of January, A.D., 1914, at 8:30 P.M., pursuant to a written notice as provided by Section F. of Article 8 of the By-Laws of the Achaian League.</p>
   <p>Mr. A. A. Pantelis, the President of the Achaian League and Chairman ex-officio of the Committee on Extraordinary Matters called the meeting to order and Mr. A. C. Coorlim, the Recording Secretary of the League acted as secretary of the meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0359.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The chairman stated that the object of the meeting was to consider a proposition for combining or uniting with a certain other organization recently created and known as the Greek-American Political Club of the United States.</p>
   <p>After a full statement of the proceedings of a meeting of the Greek-American Political Club of the United States held at Blue Island Ave., and Polk street, on the 28th day of December, A.D., 1913, at which meeting a Committee had been appointed to meet with a similar Committee from the Achaian League to be thereafter appointed for the purpose of arranging the details of the proposed union of the Achaian League and the Greek-American Political Club of America, the Chairman called for expressions of opinion from the members present.</p>
   <p>After a full and free discussion of the proposition the President on motion was empowered to name a Committee to consist of the President, Secretary and Historian of the Achaian League to meet with the Committee <pb facs="5422062_2_0360.jpg" n="3"/>from the Greek-American Political Club of America with full power to act and with full power to bind the Achaian League in any manner, and on any matter agreed upon by the two Committees aforesaid, in joint meeting assembled.</p>
   <p>The majority of this Committee being empowered to bind the full Committee, provided, however, that the Committee from the Greek-American Political Club possesses power and authority from the Greek-American Political Club of America equal and similar to the power and authority possessed by the Committee from the Achaian League.</p>
   <p>There being no further extraordinary matter for discussion the meeting was adjourned.</p>
   <p>A. A. Pantelis,</p>
   <p>President.</p>
   <p>Attest:</p>
   <p>A. C. Coorlim,</p>
   <p>Sec'y.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
