<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1919-02-13">February 13, 1919</date>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0519</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0519.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1919-02-13">February 13, 1919</date>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Honorable Maclay Hoyne,</p>
   <p>States Attorney,</p>
   <p>Criminal Court Bldg.</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illionois</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>The Achaian League, which was organized in Chicago, September 9, 1910, for the purpose of promulgating among people of Hellenic descent proper ideals with reference to American Citizenship, and also for the purpose of promoting the legitimate interests of these Hellenic people who have assumed the allegiance and obligations of American citizens, will hold its Ninth Annual Convention in Chicago, February 15, 1919.</p>
   <p>In furthering the purposes of its organization, the Achaian League will, in conformity with its custom in this respect, attempt to assist citizens <pb facs="5422062_2_0520.jpg" n="2"/>of Hellenic descent in reaching fair, accurate and just opinions, as to the qualifications and fitness of the various candidates at the approaching primary and election.</p>
   <p>While the Hellenes more popularly but less accurately called Greeks, seek for themselves no privilege or consideration which is not due to all American citizens alike, regardless of ancestry, they resent the prejudice indulged against them by some public officials whose attitude toward the Hellenes is reflected by opinions such as must have brought forth the remark of a certain judge of the Municipal Court of Chicago, who said, "All Greeks are liars; with me in these cases between Greeks is who lied the least?" This attitude does not conduce to any desirable understanding between native citizens and those who become citizens by choice.</p>
   <p>In as much as you are a candidate at the approaching primary, we respectfully request that you submit for consideration on a brief statement touching <pb facs="5422062_2_0521.jpg" n="3"/>upon your qualifications and fitness for the office, as candidate for which you desire to be nominated, and particularly a statement setting forth your attitude towards the Hellenes and their rights.</p>
   <p>Yours very truly,</p>
   <p>A. A. Pantelis,</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
