<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-08-02">Aug. 2, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Problem of Distribution Is Always Left Unsolved</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0973</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0973.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-08-02">Aug. 2, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROBLEM OF DISTRIBUTION IS ALWAYS LEFT UNSOLVED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many people are beginning to ask themselves whether the recovery measures of President Roosevelt have brought, even to a small degree, the results expected from their radical plans and programs. After the terrible condition the nation found itself in, in the spring of 1933, every citizen in the country recognized the need for drastic measures. They all agreed that the President should do whatever he felt would lift the economic burden from their shoulders. The economic depression of America was judged--and rightly so--to be without justification. A nation which has not suffered any serious mishap, which has not been engaged in an expensive war, whose material wealth is nearly unlimited, and which is able to supply nearly all of its own needs; such a country has no cause to suffer an economic collapse.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0974.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The logical thing for the American people to do was to seek the cause. The only explanation for the situation that could be found was that the country had been in the hands of incompetent leaders. Not only the politcal leaders, but the powerful monied interests, as well, were blamed for the chaos of American business. The American people--liberal, but nevertheless conservative in some respects--gave their wholehearted support to President Roosevelt. He was told to carry out any program that would remedy the situation.....</p>
   <p>The plight of the American people was so serious that it assumed tremendous importance. To the President was given the right to set America on an upward path and stabilize her national economy. His keen mind and his knowledge of the entire situation made Roosevelt the ideal man for this superhuman task. If this had been any other country than America, there surely would have been a revolution or an upheaval of the government if it had allowed the growth of such a depression without trying in any way <pb facs="5422062_2_0975.jpg" n="3"/>to stem its tide. When all the power was given to the President by the people and by the Senate, not a few politicians thought that the President would use his power to seize the reins of government. The actions of the President did much to appease these fears. It was evident to all, that he did not seek a drastic political or economic change, but merely the imposition of certain regulations which would lessen existing evils.</p>
   <p>All the codes and regulations suggested by the Administration were well within the present economic and political order. There is no doubt that his actions have saved the nation from terrible disaster--perhaps, even, from uprisings. However, there is doubt as to whether or not these measures can safeguard the economic stability of the nation. The moment the proposed measures are seen to be, not a radical change in system, but merely temporary restoratives, it is recognized that they do not guarantee a stable economy. In other words, as long as the eternal problem of distribution remains unsolved, no change, no matter how radical, will be secure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
