<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-16">April 16, 1931</date> p. 1.
<title level="a">Monarchies and Democracies.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1931-04-16">April 16, 1931</date> p. 1.
<title level="a">Monarchies and Democracies.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Alphonso's monarchy has also ended, and Spain since, yesterday, is classified among the democracies.</p>
   <p>The falling of Kingdoms in the last few years has become such an ordinary thing that it has ceased to create any sensation whatever. Kings, now existing, may be counted on by the fingers of one's hand, and in a few years they will become a rarity. The question, however, is By abolishing monarchies and establishing democracies, do the modern problems confronting all Nations get solved?</p>
   <p>Democracy is as old a political system of government as monarchy, and the constitutional monarchy, or the democratic monarchy, brought such confusion between them as to make one unable to decide as to which is the more democratic: the English form of government, with its King, or the French form, with its president?</p>
   <p>The matter, however, does not lie any longer with the form of government. The economic problem that confronts, all people of the world today, cannot be solved either by monarchy or democracy. Before long the need of some more <pb facs="5422062_2_0085.jpg" n="2"/>timely form of government will appear through which the economic problem, as much for every State as for all the States together, will be solved.</p>
   <p>Before this new form of government takes form, monarchies and democracies, in their present form, will go down, and the new form, the real people's Democracy will prevail, in which the opinion of the many, and not of the few, as is the case today with monarchies and democracies, will guide the destiny of the people's of the World. Both monarchy and democracy, of the present day, are oligarchic and differ only in name.</p>
   <p>They are forms of government which serve the interests of the few and, for that reason, have created many economic problems which beset and afflict the whole world.</p>
   <p>In any case we Greeks and American democrats have the duty to salute the new Spanish democracy and shout: "Who is next?"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
