<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-04-14">Apr. 14, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">[All Citizens Should Vote]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-04-14">Apr. 14, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">[ALL CITIZENS SHOULD VOTE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The electorate again spoke on last Tuesday's elections, not perhaps in unmistakable terms; but, at least, according to the terms laid down by the bosses of the two major parties. For in the last analysis, politics as played today is nothing more than a business - and a good business at that. And the main trouble in this lucrative business is that, generally speaking, the unfit are always placed at the top of the ladder.</p>
   <p>Still, human beings would rather keep on electing those least fit for the job than forego the right to cast their vote, to lose that prerogative of self-assertion. And it is, after all, too much to ask the people, who but acquired their right to vote during the last one hundred years, to always use that privilege justly and intelligently. In the due course of time, when average intelligence of the masses reaches a higher level, man will perform his civil duties with the prime thought in mind of serving society, instead of a handful of politicians.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, the duty of every citizen is to take an interest in the affairs of society, and to use his vote to the best of his knowledge for the election of those who will make fewer mistakes and fill their position with honor. Especially, during the present crisis the citizenry in exercising its rights, should use reason and judgment to elevate men of sterling qualities,men who place the interests of the whole above party or class interests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
