<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-04-05">Apr. 5, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Political Interest of Our Fellow-Nationals</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-04-05">Apr. 5, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLITICAL INTEREST OF OUR FELLOW-NATIONALS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Vivid and undiminished is the political interest of our fellow-nationals of the city of Chicago and the County of Cook, and as the time goes on and the primaries approach, it becomes all the more apparent and vivid.</p>
   <p>That which pleases us and withal inspires us with confidence, is the total disappearance of the multiple and multi-named party leaders who for decades were numbered here among us up to the election that took place two years ago.</p>
   <p>The Greek, however, has not been deprived of his ambition. On the contrary, so long as he succeeds and progresses in his enterprises, his work, his trade, or his profession, so long will he develop socially, politically, and in other respects, and he will withal aspire. But, with this development come the practical experience and the correct and sound reasoning whereby he can see things more clearly. In other words, he realizes the futility of his individualistic political activities, of not combining and cooperating with others who have the same political views, for cooperation is necessary in politics.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0425.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That is why, therefore, we say that we are pleased and inspired with confidence.... As long as the activities are in common, and no petty futile ambitions develop, the question of joining this one or that of the major parties has not so much significance. It is sufficient that our fellow-nationals have realized the importance, effectiveness, and significance of working in unison, and their attachment to either party will be felt and respected beneficially and fruitfully. They will not have to seek to attach themselves to a party, but they will be begged to join and to form an inseparable part of the big group.</p>
   <p>The committee formed sometime ago by our upright and well-to-do fellow-national, the merchant Mr. John Koliopoulos, a committee enjoying full, undivided and official recognition by Mr. Allen, who is in charge of the preelection campaign of the Hon. Chas. S. Deneen, has made tremendous progress so far..... One way of keeping in touch with the electorate is the innovation of radio broadcasts, used by the committee, a method which is encouraging and effective.....For example, last Wednesday at <pb facs="5422062_2_0426.jpg" n="3"/>8 P.M., Mr. D. G. Mihalopoulos, a lawyer, spoke in English, and to-night at 8:30 Mr. Andrew Vlachos, assistant prosecuting attorney of Cook County, will speak in Greek, Mr. Koliopoulos in Greek and in English, and Mr. G. Porikos, a lawyer, and others will also make addresses. They will occupy the microphone for more than an hour, and along with their splendid musical program they make an evening purely Greek. Station WJKS.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
