<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-03-31">Mar. 31, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The Tax Bill</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-03-31">Mar. 31, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE TAX BILL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- The revolt against the tax bill in the House of Representatives was a complete shock to its sponsors. For the first time in many years party leadership and party responsibility were swept aside, and congressmen voted according to the dictates of their own consciences. The tax as proposed by the Ways and Means Committee has been buried beyond resurrection because it sought to tax rich and poor alike.</p>
   <p>The proponents of the bill will now come forward and demand of its opponents a substitute that will balance the national budget. The metropolitan press will bewail the rejection of the bill and will deal roughly with the congressmen who dared to vote against the wishes of the bosses of the two parties. America, the country of party discipline, is on the verge of a new party alignment, with the possibility of the formation of a third party.</p>
   <p>Being accustomed to the idea of the existence of two major parties, we cannot conceive of conditions justifying more than two. Present conditions, <pb facs="5422062_2_1072.jpg" n="2"/>however, are immensely different from those which prevailed in the last generation. From now on the object of the parties will be to serve the public against those interests which have brought the country to its present plight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
