<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-11-10">Nov. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Patriotism of the Hellenes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0802</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0802.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-11-10">Nov. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE PATRIOTISM OF THE HELLENES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is true that the Greeks in America, from the poorest to the highest class, have proven their regard for their adopted country beyond the shadow of a doubt. This has been accomplished by their large subscription to the second Liberty Loan drive. This has been publicly recognized by the American press.</p>
   <p>The mistake made by us, however, was this: instead of working together and making subscriptions as a group, each community acted alone; therefore we cannot calculate the exact amount of the subscriptions made by the Greeks in the entire country. If each city had worked as a body the results would have been much more in our favor. Due to many names having been Anglicized, they were not credited to the Greek subscription list.</p>
   <p>Behold, therefore, the value of unity and cooperation! But we, alas, who are egoistic to a superlative degree, have again failed to realize this. We are exhibitionists and refuse to have our name on a joint list; it must stand alone for everyone to see.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0803.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Nevertheless, this action of the Hellenes proves to the American people that the Greeks are ready to support and respect every worth-while cause, especially, one that involves liberty, such as the struggle in which both Greece and America are involved today.</p>
   <p>A desire for liberty caused the Greeks to sacrifice them selves in 1821. Enduring undescribable agonies and torture at the hands of the savage Turks, they succeeded in freeing them selves from the yoke of slavery.</p>
   <p>Our strong love for liberty has been transferred to America, and we are ready to sacrifice our selves again to uphold the freedom and honor of America. "Better to live one hour of freedom, than forty years of life in slavery."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
