<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1917-04-05">April 5, 1917</date>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0841</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-correspondence"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0841.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1917-04-05">April 5, 1917</date>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To American Citizens of Hellenic Descent:</p>
   <p>The Senate of the United States by vote of 82 to 6 at 11:15 o'clock P.M. April 4th, 1917, passed a Resolution declaring that a state of war exists between the Government of the United States and the Imperial Government of Germany.</p>
   <p>The Lower House of Congress will pass the same Resolution just as soon as it can be presented for a vote. The country will then begin to mobilize an army, and all of its resources, to carry on war against the Imperial Government of Germany.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0842.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is your duty as patriotic American citizens to offer your services and assist in the vindication of the honor and independence of your adopted country. You can serve this country better by joining the ranks of its own army than by joining any legions of any nationality.</p>
   <p>Nationalities, races and creeds must be forgotten in this crisis. We are all American citizens. The honor and independence of the country are at stake. The rights of the human race have been trampled upon in the ruthless war waged by the Imperial German Government.</p>
   <p>International Law has been violated. This is a time in which actions are necessary and not words. You can act by joining the United States Army now and when you do join, do so under your right name, be it a yard long, and in that way you will show that citizens of Hellenic descent consider themselves part of this country and are willing to fight and die for its liberty, honor and respect among nations.</p>
   <p>A. A. Pantelis, Sec'y.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>The Achaian League</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
