<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Fruits of the Soil</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by C. Salopoulos)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE FRUITS OF THE SOIL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by C. Salopoulos)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At this critical time in the events of the world, President Wilson gave some advice to the American people in one of his latest speeches. He urged that the American people devote themselves to the cultivation of the soil; saying that the progress of the world depended more upon agriculture than anything else.</p>
   <p>Today, in this ferocious war, the use of all the latest deadly machines and gases is nevertheless dependent upon agriculture. The country having the largest supply of foodstuffs will have a better chance to win the war than the country which has the most guns and ammunition but whose army cannot get nourishing food. Anyone who has witnessed the abandoned farms that have been stripped of all crops and livestock will clearly understand what the president is driving at. "We want bread", cry these starving people, "without bread we <pb facs="5422062_2_1184.jpg" n="2"/>will not be quiet. Gold, silver, or spacious mansions, cannot keep us alive; we feel weak and dull. Bread, the staff of life, is greater than all of these things. That alone is what we want even if we have to sleep in the cold all winter, and have to work both night and day. If you do not give us bread we will revolt".</p>
   <p>And revolts have come about.....And when do they occur? They occur at a time when the country is in danger and needs internal peace and happiness among its people. This internal revolt at a time of danger exposes a country to wreck and ruin by its enemies.</p>
   <p>And why do these revolts occur at those critical moments? Because the pangs of hunger are fierce, and people are forced to do terrible things to satisfy their needs. Naturally the people hunger when the supply of bread is not sufficient to take care of both the armies and the civilians. Necessarily, the civilian population is deprived in order to provide the country's <pb facs="5422062_2_1185.jpg" n="3"/>defenders with food. The fields are left bare, because of the conscription of men; thereby automatically a food shortage is created. It is evident that a war causes the existence of a vicious circle, which revolves around agriculture, hunger, and revolt.....</p>
   <p>In order that this condition be averted or at least eased, it is necessary that the people devote themselves to agriculture. It has been proven that the progressive, victorious nations are those whose citizens have cultivated the soil and raised livestock.</p>
   <p>Anyhow, there is no more healthful existence than that spent in the outdoors surrounded by the beauties of nature. City life, with its factories and splendors, its smoke and its slums, is the well of human misery and physical wrecks.</p>
   <p>Our long-lived fathers who gave philosophy to the world took their inspiration from nature.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1186.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Not only individuals, but even entire countries, benefit from agriculture. Take for example, England and Germany; both are large countries and very powerful, but they are dependent for their sustenance upon Serbia Roumania, and the United States; while a comparatively unimportant and small country such as Turkey, due to its farms and raising of livestock, is very often able to save a powerful country.....</p>
   <p>There is a need, therefore, that we, as good citizens and as members of the country, should make every effort to encourage the farmer, in order that the country may accumulate wealth, health and happiness. Agriculture and the raising of livestock are the true barometers of wealth of the earth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
