<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-07-20">July 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Business Methods</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-07-20">July 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">BUSINESS METHODS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In general, the Greek stores of this city are doing more business now than during the previous two years. This improvement is a natural condition resulting from a general upswing in the economic world; it is not due to any unusual ability shown by our businessmen. Despite their claims, we all know that they have not put any new ideas into practice which have resulted in better business. They have not gotten together to form a strong organization.</p>
   <p>Each Greek enterprise in Chicago continues to be the result of one man's labor, and when that man dies or retires the enterprise dies with him. The miracles we boast of when we speak of our success in the economic world are miracles which have been accomplished single-handedly. And these so-called miracles are not miracles at all; they are simply the results of hard and unending toil which have led <pb facs="5422062_2_1460.jpg" n="2"/>to a modicum of success. We do not have one successful firm that will live on after its founder is forgotten....The reason for this is not the lack of opportunity for the creation of such business organizations; it lies in the failure of Greek businessmen to appreciate the factors necessary to create a successful business and to expand that business into a powerful organization. We refuse to reform ourselves, and, worst of all, we do not allow anyone else to point out our deficiencies.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately those who come in contact with Greek businessmen find them undesirable to deal with. This fact is generally accepted by all of us, but not one of us believes it to be true of himself. It is much easier to delude ourselves into believing that we are practically perfect and that our competitors are all at fault. The truth of the matter is that, although we have many noble characteristics, we have even a larger number of mean and petty traits. If we wish to achieve lasting success in the business world, our pettiness must be removed or overcome.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
