<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-12-09">Dec. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[The Immigration Problem]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From Chicago Tribune)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1013</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1013.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-12-09">Dec. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[THE IMMIGRATION PROBLEM]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From Chicago Tribune)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Italy's problem should not become our own. Among other problems of the Fascist government of Premier Mussolini of Italy, is the question of how to dispose of the three hundred thousand annual increase in population, which is in excess of the number that can be employed in Italian agriculture and industry. It is officially obvious then that Italy cannot add three hundred thousand individuals to its population each year, for whom there exists no food or work. What is to be done with them? The answer is simple. Send them to the United States of America. This is the solution that Greece, Poland, Russia, and Japan found. If we accepted all those that are offered to us, then we certainly would have to accept annually over one million immigrants possessing divergent habits, mental attitudes, and ways of life foreign to America, which would draw us closer to the troubles and agonies of the old world; which would prevent us from becoming a country with close family ties and the consequent guarantee of greater security and unity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1014.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But Mussolini is not exactly of the same opinion. He asks of us that we increase the quota of Italian immigrants from 43,000 to 100,000. This, without exaggeration, portends many evils. But it is not so. The doors (of immigration) must open. Already Greece is striving to convince us to open the door for the admission of her excess population. If we open it to Italy, we should gladly open it also to Greece. If we in turn open the door to Italy and Greece, we will not have reasonable and just grounds to exclude Poles, Russians and many others.</p>
   <p>The only way and best policy to follow, if we want to make real Americans out of our present and future immigrants, is to keep the door closed, as it is at present. Australia, Canada, South America, all need men. There is no humanitarian reason by which the United States of America should always be a refuge for the overflowing populations of the old world, [which are] caused by economic, social, political, and religious reasons.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
