<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-11-04">Nov. 4, 1930</date><title level="a">The Meaning of Today's Election.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1073</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1073.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1930-11-04">Nov. 4, 1930</date><title level="a">The Meaning of Today's Election.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 1 The election of today, in so far as Representatives and Senators of the United States are concerned, would not, in any way, change the present trend of government, and consequently from the point of view of the administration the situation will remain the same.</p>
   <p>In other words, whoever believes that the present economic crisis, that prevails in the United States, is due to the maladministration of the present Republican Party and feels like changing the government, should not expect a change on the basis of today's election, even if the results favor the Democrats; because the election is not general, so that a thorough change in the make-up of Congress could result. No matter how many seats the opposition gains, the administration will remain the same, for the presidential election will take place a couple of years hence.</p>
   <p>The success of the Democrats in today's election, no matter how much it may be considered to mean a protest of the people against the party in power and present administration, will rather make the situation worse from the administrative point of view, because a Democratic Congress will oppose Republican <pb facs="5422062_2_1074.jpg" n="2"/>bills, and the Republican President will not approve bills of the Democratic Congress.....</p>
   <p>For these reasons, we are afraid that the success of the Democrats in to day's elections will rather aggravate the situation than improve it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
