<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1927-12-17">December 17, 1927</date><title level="a">The Restaurant Man.-</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1927-12-17">December 17, 1927</date><title level="a">The Restaurant Man.-</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek Restaurant Man in this country is held responsible for the welfare of its citizens at large. The delicate and important trade or profession of the Greek Restaurateur cannot be over estimated. It is universally known, and beyond any dobt, that in order to enjoy life and everything that is good, one must be in good health. Our stomach is the potent factor of health, the machinery of life, and the locomotive power of the individual. The Greek Restaurateur feeds that machinery of life and the locomotion of every man patronizing his place depends on him. Therefore, the Greek is responsible for the welfare of his patrons, and as we very well know the Greeks predominate in catering all over the United States, the Greek Restaurateur is intrusted with a delicate and very important duty to perform.</p>
   <p>The Greek must be proud of his trade and must devote his body and soul in performance of his duty. The Greek Restaurant Man in this country, whether he is in the trade by choice, or by circumstance, must know the following fundamentals, for the benefit of his patrons as well as for himself.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1631.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The preparation of food must be done by expert help, the selection and utilization of good quality victuals, cleanliness in the superlative, politeness, willing must be his responsibility service. Thus his patrons will not only enjoy the good and nicely prepared food, but also will be satisfied psychologically. The Restaurant Man, further, must maintain mutual friendly relations with his creditors and his bank; his honesty and integrity must be of the best. Above all he must remember that, "The customer is always right."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
