<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-09-11">Sept. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Greece Must Fight</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0884</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0884.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-09-11">Sept. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GREECE MUST FIGHT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If Germany and with her, Turkey wins this war, it is unnecessary that we describe the fate of our enslaved brothers in the Near East and in Greece.</p>
   <p>Today, while the Greek government is still neutral, thirty thousand people in Asia Minor are being expatriated, the Greek fortunes are being confiscated, virgins are being brutally raped, our Metropolites are insulted and spat upon; and everything that is Greek is trod upon, by the iron heel of the Mohammedan.</p>
   <p>The Turkish friends of the Kaiser plan to destroy everything Greek or Christian. Entire towns are being demolished and whole populations are left to die or meet even worse fates. So, no imagination is needed to see the doom awaiting our country, if the hated Germans are victorious.</p>
   <p>What does the pro-German Greek paper of New York think of this? Why does <pb facs="5422062_2_0885.jpg" n="2"/>Venizelos still wait with crossed hands?</p>
   <p>If, now, while the outcome of the war is unknown, the Turks are committing the greatest crimes, what will happen in case of a Turko-German victory? Stone by stone, they will demolish Greek civilization; they will destroy her glorious works of art; and they will reduce the culture of Greece to their own level--a state of barbarism. The danger exists, that the maniacal, thieving Turks will demand Macedonia as a reward should they be victorious.</p>
   <p>We do not intend to give our readers the impression that we believe that the Germans will win the war. We are just going on this supposition, in order to-in a small way-foretell the future fate of Greece, if that happens.</p>
   <p>The tragic events in the Near East, and even in free Greece, makes us wonder at the apathetic attitude of Greece. This comatose state is not in line with the precepts of our blue and white flag. That flag stands for the defense of the national honor, and for the defense of all those who are loyal to it, thereby including our enslaved Greek brothers who are being killed by the thousands <pb facs="5422062_2_0886.jpg" n="3"/>by our dishonorable and tyrannical foes.</p>
   <p>The terrible slaughter of Greek men, women, and children is greater now than it would be if Greece entered the war. At least, the Turks would have to face armed men whose courage is a byword, instead of murdering crying children. Now, they murder and rape with the boldness of those who are sure to go unpunished. They would sing a different tune, if there were a large Greek army at the gates of Smyrna. They would pay with their empty heads for every fingernail of a Greek that they dared to cut off.</p>
   <p>Greece should have declared her entrance into the war the day after the Turks declared war on the side of Germany.</p>
   <p>Of course, our diplomats and statesmen thought otherwise; but, if Kolokotronis or Karaiskaris [Greek heroic generals in 1821] were alive, the diplomats would not have had their own way.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0887.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The position of Greece is so apparent, in regards to this European upheaval, that it can be questioned by no sane person.</p>
   <p>England, the ruler of the seas, is, and always will be, the only nation to control the destiny of Greece. No matter what happens, Greece can never dare to become an enemy of either France or England; for reasons not only of appreciation for past favors but because of downright fear. When Greece had been blockaded only a few weeks, the population of Greece suffered severe hunger.</p>
   <p>We have given only a slight picture of what will happen to Greece in the event of a Turko-German victory.</p>
   <p>Who is the intelligent Greek who will align himself with those crying for neutrality? Who is the Greek who will sign the ballot for neutrality printed in the columns of a pro-German Greek paper published in New York?</p>
   <p>The Greek who thinks that Greece should not enter the war, because of his <pb facs="5422062_2_0888.jpg" n="5"/>pro-German sympathies, becomes a defender of Turkish atrocities and aids the Germans in their fight to subjugate the entire civilized world.</p>
   <p>The Turks have already lost fifty thousand men and naturally they are going to ask for payment if their side wins. Greece has more to fear from the Turks than from the Germans if she remains neutral.</p>
   <p>Hypocritical philanthropists bemoan the large loss of life if Greece were to enter the war, but they complacently shut their eyes to the rape, murder and torture going on unrevenged. The Greek army should be fighting the Mussulman army; and what Greek is afraid to die when he knows he is fighting his historic foe, the Turk?</p>
   <p>We sincerely hope that our beloved Venizelos will see matters in their true light, and make the decision which the Greek people are in favor of. The victory of Venizelos is proof enough of the sentiments of the people, and also of the sentiments of the Greeks in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
