<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1929-08-03">Aug. 3, 1929</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook, P. 7, of Mr. P. S. Lambros, 130 N. Wells St., Chicago, Ill.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Hamilton Club Picnic at Morton Grove August 25.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0570</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0570.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1929-08-03">Aug. 3, 1929</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook, P. 7, of Mr. P. S. Lambros, 130 N. Wells St., Chicago, Ill.</title><title level="a" type="sub">HAMILTON CLUB PICNIC AT MORTON GROVE AUGUST 25.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hamilton Club's annual picnic will be held at Morton Grove, Illinois, on August 25.</p>
   <p>"This year all Republican state, county, and city judges and officials have been invited as special guests," said President Will T. Bell. "The 1929 picnic will be greater than any held heretofore, and already a record number of prizes have been contributed," he said.</p>
   <p>Peter S. Lambros, editor of the Greek Star, is chairman of the picnic committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0571.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>His co-workers include Wallace Brown, E. A. Keplar, B. E. O'Grady, Walter Hoots, Lloyd D. Heth, Roy L. Wolfe, A. B. Messer, Harold A. Baum, Herman J. Haenisch, Charles G. Wiese, Alfred J. Thompson, Allan T. Gilbert, Bennett C. Johnson, John Raklios, J. B. Thiess, Glen E. Dewey, John A. Shank, Col. S. M. Murdoch, Clarence E. Anderson, Tom Gilmore, E. W. Roemer, Ben Trahan, Charles H. Lange, Roy Swanson, L. Merrell, W. H. Player, and Charles V. Barrett.</p>
   <p>A special women's committee has also been appointed to assist in the work. It is as follows: Mrs. Lloyd D. Heth, chairman, Mrs. John L. Case, Mrs. H. B. Ruddell, Mrs. Frank J. Conrad, Mrs. Hugh H. Kuhl, Mrs. Leslie B. Krumsick, Mrs. Glen E. Dewey, Mrs. A. G. Barnet, Mrs. P. S. Lambros, Mrs. Donald C. Oszum, Mrs. Eugene Kammerer, and Mrs. W. A. Simmons.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
