<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-02-26">Feb. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">New Political Club Formed by Chicago Greeks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0338</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0338.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-02-26">Feb. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">NEW POLITICAL CLUB FORMED BY CHICAGO GREEKS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Evidently the Greek-Americans of Chicago are beginning to take a more active interest in the political campaigns of their city. Such an interest is indicative of the rapid assimilation of our race with the other American citizens.</p>
   <p>All Greeks who are American citizens should join this organization [political club]. Those who are not yet citizens are urged to apply for their citizenship papers immediately.</p>
   <p>This organization is the result of the zealous and untiring efforts of one Greek-American citizen, Mr. Nick Katsavos. Over three hundred men attended the first meeting. A charter for the club was obtained and a definite program showing the aims and purposes of the club was laid out. The headquarters will be located at 161 West Madison Street.</p>
   <p>The Club will encourage and aid people who seek to become American citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0339.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It will be Republican in its sympathies.</p>
   <p>The charter members and Mr. Katsavos deserve hearty congratulations [for their good work in organizing this club]. We need political organization to protect our interests, and these men have shown much foresight by forming such a club.</p>
   <p>Officers of the Club were chosen, and various committees were established. The officers elected were Mr. James N. Manousopoulos, president, and Mr. John Gerasimos, vice-president....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
