<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-04-04">Apr. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[Democracy in Peril]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-04-04">Apr. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[DEMOCRACY IN PERIL]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Surely one must concede that a change is taking place in American life, judging by the spectacle of the mayoralty election in a city of over three million people. Bad as has been the manner of American elections, in the past, the complete lack of an opposition party in the elections of April 2, is an omen of worse things to come. Mayor Kelly may have deserved re-election for what he has done or for what he promises to accomplish in the next four years. The point at issue is not the eligibility of Mayor Kelly, but the state of affairs which permitted such an election--unparalleled in the annals of American history or in those of any other free country.</p>
   <p>The regimentation that some people are talking of and fear....has been effected in Chicago to a degree unthought of but yesterday. It is not the kind of regimentation which is practiced in Germany, where there is absolutely no freedom of the individual; but it is similar to it....The difference consists in this: in one case the people are forced to do things; in the other, they are persuaded to <pb facs="5422062_2_0363.jpg" n="2"/>do them. If a machine functions in the elections of 1936 similar to that which functioned in the elections of Chicago on April 2, then we may as well bid good-by to a democratic form of government. Such a state of affairs can easily come about with hardly a murmer of protest on the part of the citizens of a once truly independent and free people. But then, perhaps, it is not always pleasant or even profitable for man to be free.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
