<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-02-11">Feb. 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Bootblacks' Protective Union of Illinois a General Call</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-02-11">Feb. 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">BOOTBLACKS' PROTECTIVE UNION OF ILLINOIS A GENERAL CALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To all Bootblacks, Members and Non-members:</p>
   <p>Kindly be present at the regular meeting of the Union next Sunday, Feb. 12, at 5:30 P.M. in Cafeteria Hall, Hull House.</p>
   <p>It is about time, at last, to put everything else aside and be present at the meeting and find ways and means to cooperate and improve our business, for we are threatened from all directions.</p>
   <p>.... Although we have tried all means to find some way of reconciliation, it was found impossible on account of the egotism of Mr. Kanavos and the selfishness of the rest, and we are forced to abandon all our endeavors to please these gentlemen and to go ahead with our efforts to improve our condition.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1627.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Gentlemen, you all know that the hat-cleaning business has fallen into the hands of the Jews, mainly because of the inertia of the officials up to yesterday and the split in the membership of the union. The same thing is true of the clothes-pressing end of the business.</p>
   <p>.... These questions will be discussed at the meeting, and you must be present. The terms that will be submitted to the above gentlemen will also be discussed; the conciliators, who refused to appear in our two previous meetings, will be there; and the executive council of Mr. Kanavos is welcome.....</p>
   <p>Among the proposals to be submitted are the resignation of the executive councils of both sides and the election of new officials.</p>
   <p>Mark, also, that many persons of note will be present to speak in the interest of the bootblacks.</p>
   <p>Cons. Stavrakas</p>
   <p>President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
