<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-10-27">Oct. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Liberty Loan Drive</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0806</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0806.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-10-27">Oct. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LIBERTY LOAN DRIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks of America, in contributing their share in subscribing to the Liberty Loans, fulfill a duty of honor toward the country granting them such generous hospitality. Every true Greek should by all means help the great republic to bring to a happy end the great task she has undertaken, inspired from only a spirit of high humanity. Thus, the Greeks of America are helping their own country by fighting on the side of the United States. The support the Greeks give must be thorough and sincere. It will doubtlessly be so, if the Greeks in America will uphold the government, which is the one today carrying out a policy of an honest effective ally; and is the only government the other nations do trust.....</p>
   <p>Beware of some of those who howl that they want Greece on the side of the Allies, especially those under the old regime, as they do not mean a word of it. They want to prevent Greece from participating in this struggle, and thus help the Teutons and their burglarious accomplices, the Turks. No one can have the <pb facs="5422062_2_0807.jpg" n="2"/>slightest doubt of the pro-German sympathies of the old regime after the publication of....documents. Close the ranks and unite under the national colors; back to the road of honor! Let us all shout together: Long live the United States and Greece, their friend and ally!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
