<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-08-29">Aug. 29, 1931</date>, p. 8
<title level="a">Greek Competetion.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-08-29">Aug. 29, 1931</date>, p. 8
<title level="a">GREEK COMPETETION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is with sadness that I write this article. But after all it may be a lesson to the Greek merchants who, in the future may avoid the destructiveness of such a competetion.</p>
   <p>In one of the suburban towns of Chicago a German confectionery was thriving with business. A roaming Greek with an eye on the same business, after revisiting and for many days watching the German confectionery, decided to establish a Greek store opposite the German's place. The German knowing that the town was too small to profitably support two confectioneries offered his place to the aspirring Greek. The Greek being "wise" and young ignored the sensible proposition of the German and opened an up to date store. The German lost his trade to the young Greek. The German's accumulated capital was exhausted, in an effort to keep his place open. A Jew, friend to whom the German went for financial assistance, advised the old German neither to worry nor borrow money, but to sell his place on installments to any Greek and at any price.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1499.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The German confectionery, on secured notes, was sold to a Greek from Chicago, who had picked up the advertisement from this paper. The new owner of the German place after spending some of his money for alterations, etc., began a destructive competition with the other Greek across the street. "Greek against Greek," the cunning Jew was smiling and assuring his German friend that the ultimate outcome of his foxy scheme was just around the corner.</p>
   <p>The Persians in ancient wars did not feel the fury of Greek wrath, because when defeated they abandoned their arms and riches and went back to Persia, thus saving part of their army. But in Greek fighting Greek, there is not retreat. It is ultimate destruction. The war did not last very long and the little town enjoyed it.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1500.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Nowhere in the country could we buy as good and as cheap candy as you could buy there, in the battle of the Greek candy-men.</p>
   <p>The first candy man closed his doors and then the second Greek lost his place to the German, who with his Jewish friend was ready to foreclose on the Greek, for failure to meet payments on his mortgage.</p>
   <p>Both of the Greeks departed conjuring mortals and immortals! The Jew, undoubtedly, got the fixtures of the first Greek for a song, and also undoubtedly for as long as he lives, a daily ice cream soda from his German friend.</p>
   <p>The above war of extermination of the two Greeks must be heeded if we do not wish to realize the same result again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
