<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1917-10-03">Oct. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To the Greeks of the Land</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Second Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0817</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0817.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1917-10-03">Oct. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE GREEKS OF THE LAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Second Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the beginning of the month the United States Government has offered for public subscription the Second Liberty Loan of three billion dollars.</p>
   <p>Every citizen and every inhabitant of this great democracy, men and women together, must extend the hand of cooperation to the flag that protects us by subscribing to the Liberty Loan. It is a demonstrated fact in history that victory in war is brought about to a great extent by money, by which all provisions, ammunition, etc. are bought.</p>
   <p>The burden of the Allies' war, from the financial standpoint, has fallen entirely upon the shoulders of America. Since America has entered this war, she must win; otherwise we are lost, all of us. And in order to win, every one of us must give to America his heart and his purse. The security for this loan is the Government, which equals the security that we get from God.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0818.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every Greek in the land is exhorted to buy Liberty Bonds. Our patriotism must be revealed at every time of the country's need. The true citizen of a country is always willing and ready to do his duty and meet his obligation. Buy more bonds and send them to your loved ones in Greece. A person who possesses U. S. Government bonds has better security than real gold or anything else. Make the Greek community in Chicago and in the rest of the country notable by buying more Liberty Bonds than any other race. America must win by all means. Do your duty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
