<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1927-12-31">December 31, 1927</date><title level="a">Health.-</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1191</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1191.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1927-12-31">December 31, 1927</date><title level="a">Health.-</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The climatic influence upon the human body and soul is undisputable. The miracles of achievement of the Greek Race were done and performed under the clear, blue, Greek sky and the beauty of nature for which Greece is known everywhere. Health was a daily routine of the Nation. Health was considered as a sacred thing. The Greeks deified Health with the Statue of Athena. Writers within and without the nation eulogized the health of the Greeks, and proclaimed it the finest wealth of the Greek Race.</p>
   <p>In the ninth century before Christ, Lycourgos, the lawgiver, observed that the laws of the country could not be beneficial without healthy bodied citizens. He decided to improve the health of his Kingdom by imposing diet on all. His aim was to create the Spart an, to be conservative in thought and brave in body and soul, by teaching him from an early stage of life the principles and necessity of health. Hardship, therefore, was the daily training of the children.</p>
   <p>Socrates once told Kriteveulos "effeminate body, effeminate soul". The general axiom, "healthy mind in healthy body" was on the lips of all the citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1192.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The health of the Greeks today is not like their predecessors.</p>
   <p>Divorces, committing suicides and crimes, are the results of Pseudo-Civilization and Internationalism. Europe grows old very early, Europeans tend to degeneration. The deseases of a pseudo-civilization become numerous more and more .Three, of the many advocators of health, of the present day, tell us what to do in order to save life from destruction. A Bavarian Monk thought he discovered the mystery of health in advocating cold baths. An Austrian Doctor, named Rilko, advocates Sun Baths. An architect, from Dresden, advocates pure air, gymnastics, and dieting. Those that were not familiar with Greek history believed and accepted the above three individuals as prophets of the twentieth century. However, Pythagoras, Asklipios, Ippocrates, Aristotle, Plutarch and many other Greeks, centuries ago, advocated the "Ti-phisi-zin", equivalent to, "live close to nature." Zeno said, "Living close to Nature is living a life of virtue."</p>
   <p>"Greeks of today, our Race is in danger! The health of the Greek is not distinguished anymore. Nationalism and everything that made our Race superior, is diminishing. Oh! Greeks the World over, become united once more, --fight the common enemy of our Race, the conditions that bring about poor health."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
