<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-03">July 3, 1929</date><title level="a">Greek Trade Is in Peril</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-03">July 3, 1929</date><title level="a">GREEK TRADE IS IN PERIL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The problem confronting, not only the Greek Press, but all the Greek people, especially the Greek merchants, is that which has been threatening Greek business men in the last few years, namely, the chain stores.</p>
   <p>This new chain system is especially dangerous to the business' chosen by the Greeks, a few of which are candy stores, restaurants, groceries, fruit and vegetable markets, and shoemakers. The chain drugstore which is not really a drugstore, but a miniature department store, has been the most destructive to the small Greek business man. This type of chain store is a combination store of candy, grocery, book, tobacco, hardware, jewelry, restaurant and haberdashery stores.</p>
   <p>These chain stores which have been established in New York, Chicago, as well as in smaller towns and cities in America by tens, hundreds, and thousands, are slowly wiping out independent store-keepers by virtue of the sheer capital behind them and are now without a doubt practically recognized as monoplies.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1608.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So great is the strength of these chain systems that we are asking the support of the entire Greek population in America to cooperate for the suppression of these unjust monoplies.</p>
   <p>Anyone can readily see that if the individual restaurants, grocery, candy store, etc., disappear--so will the Greek business man disappear.</p>
   <p>A good example of what the economic consequences would be for the Greek business man in Chicago can be realized if we stop to think that three-fourths of the Greek population is engaged in one of the five important ventures mentioned above. Such a result would put about 15,000 Greeks in a serious situation. This condition is prevalent in all cities and small towns where Greek people reside.</p>
   <p>The Greek people of America have earned a good reputation for fair dealing, for clean and honest trading, for good fellowship and for economy. Their individual progress has been equally as great in the commercial world.</p>
   <p>It seems that Greek commerce is weakened, not by the union of powerful figures in the capitalistic world, in order to "break" the small man, but by the lack <pb facs="5422062_2_1609.jpg" n="3"/>of union of Greek business men to stand together.</p>
   <p>How else will the Greek business men of Chicago and elsewhere fight the chain system, if they don't stand together to help the small and helpless merchant?</p>
   <p>Do they think a large mechanical God will appear to attack the enemy and save all Greek merchants if they themselves do nothing about it?</p>
   <p>Only a speedy and complete change of our present ways will save and preserve the commercial businesses on which so many of our lives depend.</p>
   <p>Korakobrachos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
