<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-05-25">May 25, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">[The Modern Disavowal]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-05-25">May 25, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">[THE MODERN DISAVOWAL]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few weeks ago, I attended a church service in company with a man who has recently come from Greece. In front of us sat a young girl about fifteen years of age. Her lips were painted so scarlet that they appeared repulsive instead of attractive.</p>
   <p>I know both of the parents of that child and have no doubt as to their morals and standards of life. They are living up to all the things considered vital in the past. And now--look at their daughter! She is more of a painted spectacle than were the hetaerae of old Athens.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, it is no longer necessary for a person to sleep for twenty years, as did Rip Van Winkle, or for forty years, as did Epimenidis in Greek folklore, in order to awaken to an altogether different world, a world that <pb facs="5422062_2_1155.jpg" n="2"/>has changed its tastes in food, drink, dress, and pleasures. In these days, one can go to sleep at night, awaken at six the next morning, and find that countless changes have taken place while he slept.</p>
   <p>Ideologies, customs, and ethics do not undergo slow changes and transformations, as they did in former times. The only thing that society has kept more or less intact is a poetic ideology about life. It is expressed in this manner: When we have too much of a good thing, we seek to eliminate it as rapidly as possible. How this elimination is to be brought about, is of no great concern to us. If we no longer like the prescribed ethical code we seek to get rid of it. We do not ask our fellow men if they, too, desire its elimination. "We do not have, those shalt not have"--this attitude has become the accepted dogma. We seek to commit suicide, and we are not worried about the time, the place, or the manner. And people who are anxious to kill themselves do not give much attention to the beliefs and ideas of others. The injustices they perpetrate exist in the fact that these would-be suicides do not confine the results of their death <pb facs="5422062_2_1156.jpg" n="3"/>sentence to themselves, but inflict them upon the rest of society.</p>
   <p>What has this generation bestowed upon us? The automobile in 1905 gave us a tremendous leap forward. It has become as necessary to our daily existence as bread and love. That was followed by jazz, dinner parties, and the "movies". Then, one morning, when we awoke, we found we knew how to play bridge and how to work crossword puzzles. The World War brought added innovations. Our wives and daughters looked at Irene Castle and remarked that she looked like a shorn goat. The next day they lined up in the barber shops to have their hair cut in the "shorn-goat" style. At about the same time, they cut about a foot of material from the bottom of their dresses. They sport cigarettes on their painted lips even when taking care of their infant children.</p>
   <p>It seems that many worth-while customs and traditions have been thrown upon the rubbish heap during the last two decades.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1157.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Thus, all our ideals and customs have been cast aside. This is giving the male sex many perplexing problems in etiquette. A man goes out with a young girl who looks as if her mouth should still have the fragrance of her mother's milk and finds it reeking with the fumes of alcohol. In that case he is not sure whether he should offer a soda or a bite of chewing-tobacco.</p>
   <p>In this kind of a world, the down-hill road is the easiest one for a youngster to travel. Shame is carried away by the rapid current of progress. The ashheaps are full of priceless treasures, discarded Mona Lisas. The innocent, the simple, and the rare aspects of life have become objects of ridicule. Unnecessary and, often, harmful commodities and ideas are most widely advertized.</p>
   <p>We were suddenly told we had an inferiority complex, so we proceeded to be bold and loud in order to assure ourselves to the contrary. Then came the radio and the talking pictures. Now we can buy any kind of emotional thrills as easily as radishes.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1158.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Like chameleons, we change our colors to match our background. Panting and exhausted, we are forever on the run, trying to keep step with the times. But we cannot run and think at the same time. Therefore, of necessity, some day we shall cease to run. We will do an about-face and come back to our discarded ideals. Unless, of course, we prefer to run until we lose our sanity, and thus become for the rest of our lives a society of gibbering idiots running like mice in a maze.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
