<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1918-04-13">Apr. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">His Excellency the Greek Ambassador at Washington Arrives in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0739</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0739.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-04-13">Apr. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HIS EXCELLENCY THE GREEK AMBASSADOR AT WASHINGTON ARRIVES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. George Rousos, Greece's Ambassador to the United States, arrived in Chicago to visit our Greek community and participate in the observance of patriotic ceremonies.</p>
   <p>It is needless to write about the personal distinction and diplomatic accomplishments of the man, for the high official position which he occupies, especially in such critical times, attests the importance of our distinghished guest. We can only emphasize that his visit here is connected with general efforts to attain some purpose, so this purpose must be of great importance.</p>
   <p>The main purpose of Mr. Rousos' presence here is to encourage and give added impetus to patriotic sentiments, efforts, and activities which concern national affairs and especially the Third Liberty Loan, for which we must all do <pb facs="5422062_2_0740.jpg" n="2"/>our very best. It is incumbent upon every Greek of Chicago to do his duty and fulfill the purpose for which the Ambassador came here.</p>
   <p>Today, at 1:30 P. M., he will speak in the auditorium of Orchestra Hall, 216 South Michigan Avenue. During the mass meeting the distinguished Professor of Classical Greek Literature and Studies at the University of Chicago, Mr. Paul Shorey, and others will speak. A United States Navy band will play various national and patriotic pieces. A sumptuous and magnificent dinner will be given in the evening at the La Salle Hotel by the great and powerful patriotic National Security League. We take this occasion to urge all to become members of this organization. Mr. John W. Thomas, assistant cashier of the Central Trust Company of Illinois, will preside over this dinner, which is given in honor of the Greek Ambassador.</p>
   <p>Tickets for this patriotic gathering are distributed free of charge. Those wishing to secure tickets may call at the offices of Saloniki.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0741.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[(Saloniki) Editor's note:- A true translation of this article was filed with the Postmaster at Chicago on the 13th day of April, 1918, as required by the act of October 6, 1917.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
