<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-02-12">Feb. 12, 1910</date><title level="a">A Right Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-02-12">Feb. 12, 1910</date><title level="a">A RIGHT MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Last Sunday a meeting was called at Horan Hall to protest against the new law banning all peddlers from the streets. This of course seriously affects the Greeks, because we have practically had a monopoly on this phase of the fruit and vegetable business.</p>
   <p>The hall was crowded with Greeks who mutely saw their only means of livelihood swept away from them. They were all quiet and orderly, listening with great interest to all the speakers.</p>
   <p>The first speaker was Andrew Vlachos, the president of the organization. He explained the law to the Greeks and clearly drew the situation for them. The second speaker was an American. He informed the Greeks that they are handicapped because they have not yet become American citizens. He urged them to take out their papers immediately. Mr. Papaeliou, the president of the Greek Community of Chicago was next. He was followed by two other speakers.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0445.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following resolutions were drawn up:</p>
   <p>Resolved, that on this 6th day of February, 1910, at Horan Hall the Greeks of Chicago will unite to fight the ordinance prohibiting peddling in the city streets as it is their only means of livelihood and existence. The reasons for this resolution are:</p>
   <p>1. This ordinance will throw into unemployment, not only the Greeks, but people of other nationalities as well.</p>
   <p>2. It will ruin the entire South ater Street Market and will cause great difficulty in getting fruits and vegetables to housewives and other buyers.</p>
   <p>3. This ordinance will affect other enterprises such as, trucking, deliveries, newspapers, advertising, stenographic help, auditors, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0446.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>4. It will further decrease the standard of living of the foreign element instead of raising it.</p>
   <p>5. It will cause a great unemployment crisis which will greatly affect the entire city.</p>
   <p>We firmly resolve to send a petition signed by 2,000 Greek peddlers to the City Hall asking them to reconsider the ordinance. We further resolve to enlist all Greek and American newspapers to our cause.</p>
   <p>President Secretary</p>
   <p>A. Vlachos E. Koliopoulos</p>
   <p>A collection of $100 was made after the meeting to defray court expenses and lawyers fees.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
