<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-10-12">Oct. 12, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Coming Election</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-10-12">Oct. 12, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE COMING ELECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.- It is the duty of this paper as guardian of the interest of Greeks to inform the numerous Greek voters in Chicago, Cook County and the State of Illinois, that the welfare of this commonwealth is at stake in this coming election which will be held on November 6th. In consequence the interests and the welfare of Greeks will be affected one way or the other by the results of the election.</p>
   <p>In watching the two political parties in this great country, Republican and Democratic, the Star has clearly observed the retrogression of the Democratic party in recent years and the forward march and the progressive program of the popular and well-liked Republican party which has become the choice of the people and for years has wisely piloted the ship of State.</p>
   <p>The esteem, the hope, and the trust which the Republican party inspires in the American people are the result of its efficiency on the one hand and the hardships which the people have experienced under Democratic administration.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For example let us turn to Clevelands administration from 1893 to 1897 and remember the panic and the fears which the country and American commerce endured.</p>
   <p>The privation which the people experienced, the numerous bank failures, the strikes, the closing of factories and the unemployment of thousands of people were directly attributable to the Democratic administration.</p>
   <p>And while these terrifying conditions prevailed, under the Democratic administration we see that the country began to breathe easily when the ever- memorable McKinley took control of the affairs of State. The unemployed went back to work, commerce began to function properly, prosperity returned and progress resumed the creation of the wonderful things that we now enjoy.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0199.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Who among right- thinking Americans would venture to dispute or try to confute these facts? And who can deny that the administration of Mr. Roosevelt will surpass those of his predecessors. and be recalled as a brilliant period in the promotion of commerce, public welfare and good statesmanship? No one indeed!</p>
   <p>Under these circumstances the Chicago and Illinois Republicans who are conducting Mr. Roosevelt's campaign have a right to ask the people to vote Republican in the coming election so that prosperity may continue.</p>
   <p>When the country as a whole is prosperous and progressive under the leadership of a real hundred-per-cent wise and intrepid American statesman like Theodore Roosevelt, naturally all the elements which compose this immense commonwealth, including the Greeks, are affected by the nation's prosperity and progress.</p>
   <p>The Star urges all Greek voters in Chicago and in the State of Illinois, to vote for the party in which the country has faith and trust.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0200.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Register Tuesday, October 16th, and put an X at the top of the Republican, ticket on election- day, November 6th, Vote straight Republican ticket.</p>
   <p>When you go to the polls to vote you will notice the distinguished names on the Republican ticket. They are the best that we have in the country. Vote the straight Republican ticket from top to bottom.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
