<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-11-02">Nov. 2, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Twelve Greek Restaurants in the City Are Found by Inspectors to Be Very Far Below the Prescribed Standard</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1221</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1221.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-11-02">Nov. 2, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">TWELVE GREEK RESTAURANTS IN THE CITY ARE FOUND BY INSPECTORS TO BE VERY FAR BELOW THE PRESCRIBED STANDARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Food not fit for human consumption, cooking utensils not fit for dogs, and extreme uncleanliness" was the brief report of the Health Department investigators who visited the Greek restaurants referred to above.</p>
   <p>Nice business, and very nice advertisement for Greek restaurantkeepers in general!' It is incredible, but nevertheless it is a matter beyond dispute.</p>
   <p>In a recent general report of the Health Department we were delighted to see that the Greek restaurants in the city were highly commended by the commissioner for cleanliness, for purity of food, and for tidiness and up-to-date sanitary conditions in general. By all indications these twelve restaurants were not visited by the inspectors at the time of the issuance of that [favorable] report, for their filthy condition must be chronic and not temporary.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1222.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is the duty of the Greek Restaurant Association, for the sake of the welfare of the hundreds of thousands of people catered to in Greek places and for their own welfare and [continued] existence to keep a vigilant eye on places of dubious repute, in which such conditions may be found.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly there are good and evil in everything and everywhere, the measures are taken to remedy the situation; but this deplorable condition of the twelve restaurants merits neither sympathy nor pity. The proprietors of these restaurants have deliberately sinned; it certainly was a deliberate act and must be exposed to the public so that their places of business will not be patronized and will consequently be closed. The sooner the better, so that good restaurantkeepers may not have to be stigmatized by the unbecoming conduct of these twelve.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
