<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-08-10">Aug. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Red Cross Social Service</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-08-10">Aug. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE RED CROSS SOCIAL SERVICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>American citizens of Greek descent and subjects of the Greek government in Chicago are notified, that the Government of the United States of America has requested the Red Cross to undertake the responsibility of corresponding, with relatives and friends of Chicago residents, who are in countries or places which are occupied by the enemy or his allies.</p>
   <p>The Red Cross will endeavor to transmit all messages and communications to relatives in Europe without any charge. It will not be responsible, however, for any letters or communications which it is impossible to deliver because of the hazards and difficulties encountered due to the war.</p>
   <p>Those who are calling on the Red Cross to communicate with their relatives in Europe, must be known by the Red Cross and must be respectable individuals. They must,at least, be recommended by well-known and respected people, who must certify as to the good character, good intentions, sincerity, and truthfulness <pb facs="5422062_2_0658.jpg" n="2"/>of the applicants, before this service will be undertaken.</p>
   <p>Only personal and family letters are acceptable. A letter or a message cannot be transmitted to other than a person living on enemy territory. For more information inquire at the Correspondence Division of the American Red Cross, 58 East Washington Street, Room 511, daily at 3:30 P. M. including Saturday and Sunday.</p>
   <p>Those interested in this service, also may inquire at the Immigrants' Protective League, 824 South Halsted Street: 9 A. M. to 5 P. M. daily; Wednesday evening: 7 to 9; Saturday: 9 A. M. to 3 P. M., Sunday: 10 A. M. to 12 Noon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
