<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-09-09">Sept. 9, 1929</date><title level="a">It Is Time to Show Our Political Influence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0487</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0487.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-09-09">Sept. 9, 1929</date><title level="a">IT IS TIME TO SHOW OUR POLITICAL INFLUENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- The Greeks of America and especially the Greeks of Chicago, having become naturalized Americans long ago, have the privilege of voting. It is time for them, now, to occupy political positions and become officially known by the parties to which they belong.</p>
   <p>This recognition they deserve by reason of their activity in politics. They have established political organizations through which they give valuable support, during elections, to different candidates of the party to which they belong. There are Greeks, now, possessing the capabilities and virtues which are needed to occupy any political position. If any are won through political activity the Greek-Americans must distribute them between the organizations to which they belong, because it otherwise constitutes a drawback to the Greek race for it brings about division and the consequence is a failure of recognition by the political parties.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0488.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All the other races have long been recognized by the Americans politically and many politically active individuals of these races occupy political offices in the city, state, and U.S. Government offices. In order for the Greeks to obtain similar privileges in American politics they must ask continuously through their organizations and show a united front to American party leaders, making them understand that if they want the support of Greek votes, they must also allow to the Greeks political positions, and they must also recognize the necessity of having Greek candidates in the different elections, as Greek votes amount to thousands and that various American candidates have been elected due to Greek votes.</p>
   <p>Through their various political banquets for candidates, the Greeks proved to the Americans the strength of the Greek votes in Chicago during past years. The Greeks have shown that politically they are an important factor and that they are no longer to be ignored. In consequence the different candidates are seeking, in every way, the support of Greeks for election purposes.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0489.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is time that the Greeks receive their justifiable position with the candidates for different offices, because it is not possible for them to render their political support forever to Americans without being recognized by them and given political candidacies as has been done with other races.</p>
   <p>We are writing the above generally to Greek-American citizens, regardless of the party to which they belong. At present we are especially interested in the candidacy in future judicial elections of the well known and popular attorney-at-law, A.A. Pantelis, who, for a long time, took an active part in politics and who many American politicians know well as an energetic and capable man.</p>
   <p>A.A. Pantelis, for years has been put up as a candidate for the position of Judge by the Democratic Party, but now all the Greeks of our community will support him regardless of party sentiment and willseek with all their might his official distinction and success in the coming election.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0490.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Chicago Greek Daily, long a friend of A.A. Pantelis, rejoices as being the first to announce his candidacy and does not doubt at all that all the Greeks of our community will support this movement to put him in office.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
