<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1936-04-02">Apr. 2, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Political Gathering</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1936-04-02">Apr. 2, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL GATHERING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most ardent and most active Greek Democrats of Chicago are making every effort to make the Greek group acquire greater influence in the political field. Pioneers in this effort are George Becharas, A. Pantelis, Paul Kare, and Public Prosecutor James Geroulis. They are being assisted by many other prominent Greek Democrats. The first step taken was a visit to the general headquarters of the Democratic party. There, they explained their purpose and future program for the support and recognition of the Greek-American voters of the city as a bloc. The party leaders have agreed to help the Greek Democrats to accomplish their purpose.</p>
   <p>Secondly, a committee, composed of Doctor Minas Johannides, P. Agriostathis, Louis Collins, and George Bambakaris, was formed to organize the Greeks. Now all that is necessary is to give public expression to the plan. In order to do this, the aforementioned group decided to organize a Democratic rally. It will take place Saturday night in the Cameo Room of the Morrison Hotel.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0469.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Prominent American and Greek leaders will be present, including Mayor Kelly, Dr. Bundesen, Thomas J. Courtney, and E. J. Hughes.</p>
   <p>With such speakers and the preparations made by the Greek leaders for a fine artistic and musical program, there is no doubt that the Cameo Room will be completely occupied. By so doing the Greek community can also display its group strength to the politicians of both parties. In unity there is strength, so let us not cheat our own interests by neglecting to display this unity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
