<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1924-08-02">Aug. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">American Association of Greek Restaurant-Keepers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1719</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1719.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-08-02">Aug. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN ASSOCIATION OF GREEK RESTAURANT-KEEPERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1-We take pleasure in announcing that our countrymen who own restaurants have founded an association under the name of "The American Association of Greek Restaurant-Keepers." This association, they announce, will set the standard of service for the numerous persons engaged in this business here and all over the country.</p>
   <p>Following the example of other organized businessmen, the restaurateurs have started a good work. They have met and elected the proper persons to govern the association, and have determined by vote what amount shall be paid as dues by members, and have decided that those who work for the association shall be paid. This is an unusual procedure because heretofore the members of all Greek associations have demanded that the officials by them elected, namely, the presidents, secretaries, treasurers, and others shall leave their work and their business and work for the organizations gratis.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1720.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every one knows that the officials elected on these terms have not lived up to the expectations of those who elected them.</p>
   <p>The founders of this organization have done something else still more unusual and radical. They have established a place where members and their friends may meet by renting and furnishing in the Loop a luxurious suite of offices. There members and their friends and all those who have business with them may meet by appointment, rest, chat, smoke, and transact their business.</p>
   <p>There will also be a free employment bureau for those who need help and for the employees of the members, who will simply register with the clerk.</p>
   <p>All this, as we are informed, is only the beginning, for they plan to give us more surprises by inaugurating new methods of getting in touch with prominent Americans, bankers, merchants, lawyers, and all those with whom Greeks come in contact, to show them that Greeks are an asset to the communities in which <pb facs="5422062_2_1721.jpg" n="3"/>they live, and that they love this country and are not afraid to assert themselves, since they work hard and are law-abiding citizens.</p>
   <p>This is a good start and a solid foundation for the future, and it certainly guarantees the success of their efforts to serve Greek businessmen and their friends.</p>
   <p>We extend our congratulations to the officers and the members of this splendid organization. Its founders are inspired by high ideals and have realized them in this practical service to our community.</p>
   <p>Let them be assured that the Greeks of Chicago will heartily support the association and cooperate with it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
