<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-02-07">Feb. 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[Kimon Friar Reads Own Poems]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-02-07">Feb. 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[KIMON FRIAR READS OWN POEMS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At least once each year the Greek Women's University Club gives the community an opportunity to attend a purely philological affair. In the majority of cases these afternoon lectures have been given in the Ida Noyes Hall of the University of Chicago.</p>
   <p>This year, last Sunday afternoon this group had the honor or presenting Kimon Kalogeropoulos, a rising twenty-four-year-old poet, to an outstanding audience. This young philologist is more commonly known as Kimon Friar. He is the son of the well-known James Kalogeropoulos of Chicago, and has been in America since the age of three.</p>
   <p>In his very early childhood Kimon displayed remarkable aptitude for writing poetry. This talent won him scholarships at the University of Wisconsin. While studying there, his ability to write beautiful verses became well known among the professors and students.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1236.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He justified the many laudatory statements concerning his poetry when he read selections from his own writings for an hour last Sunday. He read them so well that he might easily have been a professional reader. Mr. Friar then paid a tribute to the famous poet of Greece, Kostas Palamas, and recited one of his most beautiful poems. He also recited a poem written by a Chicagoan, Andrew Vlachos.</p>
   <p>He was introduced to the various celebrities and professors of the audience by Miss Nina Pernokis. Tea and cakes were served.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
