<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title>, 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1919-02-15">February 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">(Typewritten Letter sent by Harry Olson, Room 917, City Hall, to A. A. Pantelis</title>, Sec'y, of the Achaian League.)

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
   <catRef target="#source-correspondence"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title>, 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1919-02-15">February 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">(Typewritten Letter sent by Harry Olson, Room 917, City Hall, to A. A. Pantelis</title>, Sec'y, of the Achaian League.)
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>My dear Mr. Pantelis:</p>
   <p>I am in receipt of your letter of February 13, and note what you say therein regarding the people of Hellenic descent.</p>
   <p>I expressed my views at a little meeting of Americans of Hellenic descent at the Morrison Hotel last Thursday night. I have spent four years in studying the Greek language, Greek classics, and the Greek civilization, and you need not be told what influence that has had on my mind, nor need you fear that I do not appreciate the great people from which our Americans <pb facs="5422062_2_0517.jpg" n="2"/>of this descent have come. No other people have any such heredity as yours, and I shall always take pride in meeting and becoming acquainted with our Americans of this descent.</p>
   <p>I admire their business ability, and their qualities of good citizenship, and consider them among the best types that come to this country.</p>
   <p>We have unworthy people in all descents. There are some Americans of Swedish descent that I do not admire, for instance, Fred Lundin and Alex Johnson, the men who are controlling the present Mayor and are responsible for most of his failures.</p>
   <p>You ask for a statement touching my fitness for the office. I can only say that the same is contained in my statement at Arcadia Hall, which was printed in full in the Daily News on Wednesday, February 12.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0518.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I might also add that my father was an immigrant and though I was born in this country, my foreign name and origin gave me the same obstacles that you Greek boys meet. I know how to sympathize with them, and in this connection, I wish to say that if a man behaves, he will find Americans enough of foreign descent who will give him a helping hand.</p>
   <p>My father was a brick-layer and died when I was thirteen years of age. Hence, I have known poverty, which most of our foreign classes know only too well.</p>
   <p>I think such experiences broaden one and fit him for the office I seek. He must come in contact with people of different characteristics. I am very sure all Americans of Greek descent, as well as any other descent, will not have occasion to regret having voted for me in the primary election. With sentiments of personal regard, I am,</p>
   <p>Yours very truly,</p>
   <p>Harry Olson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
