<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1923-08-19">Aug. 19, 1923</date><title level="a">Europe's Dancers from Asia and Africa</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1923-08-19">Aug. 19, 1923</date><title level="a">EUROPE'S DANCERS FROM ASIA AND AFRICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Europe, having long ago assumed the leadership of civilization, and having rendered herself superior in the industrial field, became the ruler of all countries that the Europeans had conquered.</p>
   <p>When subordinating the different Asiatic and African nations, the Europeans tried to impart to them European civilization, and, especially, their inventions not excepting the relating to war.</p>
   <p>And so we see, today, China, as well as the Bedouins of Tripoli, and Riffs of Morocco, using the same means of war as their conquerers.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the jealousies of the different European peoples, among themselves, strengthen the barbarians in their struggles against their conquerers.</p>
   <p>And we are confronted, on this very day, with a phenomena that if not heeded by European governing powers, it is not improbable, may show that a common action of Europe against Asia will be but a futile Struggle.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0622.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The "yellow peril", so called, about which so much has been written, not only does not seem to have vanished, but, on the contrary, with the armament developments of the Japanese and Chinese, it is getting constantly greater and more eminent.</p>
   <p>This danger is rendered more probably by the conflicts of the European nations and, most especially, by their internal troubles and revolutions.</p>
   <p>The labor and communist movements, so frequent lately, have compelled the governments of the different states to avoid conflict, and to out forth every effort towards settling peacefully such matters without injurious consequences. The case is similar to that of the French, who are totally incapacitated, at present, to terminate their fight with the Riffs in Morocco, the continuation of which may result in the loss of all their Africancolonies.</p>
   <p>But even the little frictions between England and France resulted in the domination of the Turks and the deprivation of European prestige and rights that European and their governments enjoyed in Turkey.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0623.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This loss of ground by Europe will have its effect in the uprising of other Musselmen in Syria, Tripoli, Morocco, and later, possibly, in Egypt and India. The great mistake was made by Europe in the Greco-Turkish war when France and Italy supported the Turks. When war once starts in Europe, it is very difficult to control disastrous consequences.</p>
   <p>While these events transpire in Europe the Near Easterns, will line itself against the Europeans, this time, not as unorganized hordes but as organized forces equal, and perhaps superior, in discipline, to those of Europe. Certainly it is not as easy for the Europeans to fight against the Chinese as it was formerly. Europe will be compelled to retreat.</p>
   <p>Thus, in time European prestige will become reduced and its superiority also, to that of the Asiatics and Africans, who may, in a few years, attack Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
