<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Evening American</title>,
<date when="1931-01-31">January 31, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Society Pledges Aid to Mayor.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Evening American</title>,
<date when="1931-01-31">January 31, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK SOCIETY PLEDGES AID TO MAYOR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Citizens of Greek extraction today presented the mayor with a copy of a resolution indorsing him. It was adopted at a meeting held in the council chamber last night.</p>
   <p>Nick G. Canellis is president of the group. Vice-presidents are:-Daniel P. King, Christ Smirlin, Nicholas Spiro, Constantine Licouris, Peter K. Semadis and George Prempas. Louis Nigal is secretary and Spiros Campas, treasurer.</p>
   <p>LIST ADVISORY BOARD.</p>
   <p>The Advisory board is composed of Nick G. Canellis, Daniel P. King, Georg Patris, Gus Canellis and Harry Broumas.</p>
   <p>Following were the resolutions adopted:-</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Mayor William Hale Thompson is now a candidate for renomination and re-election and comes before the people of Chicago with a 100 per cent fulfillment of every pledge and promise he made to the people as a candidate four years ago".</p>
   <p>"Whereas, the death rate has been reduced to 10.4 per 1,000 population-the <pb facs="5422062_2_0417.jpg" n="2"/>lowest of any large city in the world,- tuberculosis reduced 20 per cent and the baby death rate reduced from 122.4 per 1,000 birth to 54.5,- a saving of 4,000 babies a year.</p>
   <p>"Whereas, the official statistics show that for the nine-month period ending September, 30, 1930, there were sixty-seven cities of over 100,000 population which had more crime per capitol than Chicago, and,</p>
   <p>JOBLESS FIGHT LANDED.</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Mayor Thompson is fighting the efforts of the vicious circle in this country, who would foist upon the American people the present condition in England, through the British dole system and he is in favor of giving American working men jobs instead of charity, bread lines and soup houses.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, be it resolved that Greek-American citizens of Chicago do hereby unanimously pledge him our votes and our wholehearted support."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
