<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-04-04">Apr. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Dinner Dance</title><title level="a" type="sub">Given by Greek Division of Democratic Party</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-04-04">Apr. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">DINNER DANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Given by Greek Division of Democratic Party</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, March 31, members of the Greek Community of Chicago dined and danced in the most aristocratic setting in all America--the Bal Tabarin of the Sherman Hotel. The Greek Division of the Democratic party had Edward Kelly, the candidate for mayor, as its guest of honor at this dinner dance.....</p>
   <p>As a means of expressing its appreciation to the organization which has recognized the people of Hellenic descent more than ever before, the leaders of the Greek Democrats presented Mayor Kelly in his last appearance before the election. Bringing the present campaign to a finish, party leaders joined in the gala occasion, and gave such an election atmosphere to the affair as our people have never before witnessed.</p>
   <p>The Bal Tabarin, scene of so many of Chicago's gay social affairs, is generally accepted as being the smartest social rendezvous in the city....</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0217.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As the guests dined, they enjoyed hearing lovely organ music. The organ was so cleverly concealed that the audience found it very difficult to believe that the music which originated in the room in which they sat....</p>
   <p>The dinner was novel in many respects. A minimum number of speeches was delivered, the main speaker being Mayor Kelly. Preceded by a dinner in which the maitre d'hotel outdid himself, the address of the evening was followed by dancing. At no other time has such an occasion presented itself. At the ridiculously low price of two dollars per person the guests were given the opportunity of being present when the Greek Democrats honored the chief executive of the city, and of dining and dancing in palatial splendor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
