<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-11-02">Nov. 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Flaws in the President's Ideology</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0989</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0989.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-11-02">Nov. 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">FLAWS IN THE PRESIDENT'S IDEOLOGY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That economic struggle, which has overcome the entire civilized world, and to which we have often referred in editorials of general interest, has begun to make itself felt here in America. Not that the American nation has ever been undivided by political ideologies that are supposed to be the only means of aiding and improving social and economic conditions. Not at all! But conditions today are earmarked in such a way that signifies a new crossroad has been reached in the history of civilization. We who live in this period find it difficult to recognize significant changes, because they are too close to us. Time will reveal them to us gradually.</p>
   <p>During this crisis each nation has attempted by various and sundry methods to alleviate its economic stress. The same general procedure has been followed: an effort to facilitate the circulation of money, to encourage competitive enterprise, and to stimulate individual entrepreneurs to enlarge their busineses.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0990.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our President has evolved a new method, entitled the N.I.R.A. or N.R.A. The constantly changing situation does not permit anyone to comment as yet upon the success of this venture. However, in most of its aspects it seems to bear a marked resemblance to socialism. The multitudinous denials of such an affiliation on the part of the Administration does not eradicate the fact that its nature is definitely that of national socialism. The very fact that all who do not act in agreement with it will be punished and fined signifies that free individual enterprise is a thing of the past. This seems to indicate that the entire program of the President is inclined toward socialism.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, it would be very bold for anyone to critize the policies of Mr. Roosevelt. No one--not even his worst enemy--dares to say that his actions have any motive other than to help the great majority of the American people. He means to provide his people with the necessities of life, which have so long been denied them. In addition to that, no one can accuse him of being deaf to public opinion and ignorant of the teachings of our past history. His policy is nothing more than one of the many endeavors being made by the world <pb facs="5422062_2_0991.jpg" n="3"/>to create a society worthy of the human being.</p>
   <p>The only flaws in his policy are certain ideological impositions which are not yet acceptable to the American people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
