<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-03-14">Mar. 14, 1918</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Greeks Await Liberty Loan Call.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0768</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0768.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-03-14">Mar. 14, 1918</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">GREEKS AWAIT LIBERTY LOAN CALL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Preparations are well under way for the next Liberty Loan campaign, which opens April 6, and members of the committee representing the Greek-speaking people of Chicago are organizing and laying plans,although no official announcemen has been made from Washington as to the amount of the bond issue or other details in connection with it.</p>
   <p>One of the diligent and efficient workers on the committee is Geo. L. Matalas, president of the Greek Liberal League, who was prominent in the last campaign and is confident that the Greeks of Chicago will surpass their excellent record on that occasion in the next Liberty Loan drive.</p>
   <p>"We are more intensely anxious and determined to buy Liberty bonds next time than ever before because our dollars are going to help in establishing the liberty not only of America, of which we are a part, but also of Greece, from which we came," said Mr. Matalas several days ago. "With this twofold interest before us, we will see to it that the Greeks of Chicago shall not be laggards.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0769.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"We are going to the limit, and if necessary, we will make sacrifices to take more than our full share of Liberty bonds, so that we may make our influence felt in helping the United States directly and Greece indirectly. We are all in this war and determined to win. If the United States and its Allies lose, we shall all be lost."</p>
   <p>Aside from patriotism, which of course is the chief consideration, and for which the Greeks are distinguished, there is the idea of investment in buying Liberty bonds. They are the safest in the world. Yet, even if we were asked to give our money to the Government instead of lending it, that would still be an honorable privilege. But we are not asked to do that. We shall get every dollar back, with interest. Most important of all, the Greeks will have the priceless satisfaction of knowing that we are doing our share, by buying all the bonds that we can afford, in helping to free the world from the heel of autocracy, selfish domination, and cruelty, and in establishing the ideal of freedom and equality.</p>
   <p>(Treasury Department, Bureau of Publicity, Liberty Loan, Chicago District)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
