<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1930-02-14">Feb. 14, 1930</date><title level="a">Good News!</title><title level="a" type="sub">A.J. Vlachos Appointed Assistant States Attorney</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1930-02-14">Feb. 14, 1930</date><title level="a">GOOD NEWS!</title><title level="a" type="sub">A.J. VLACHOS APPOINTED ASSISTANT STATES ATTORNEY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1 States Attorney Swanson has announced the appointment of Andrew J. Vlachos as a member of his staff. The Greeks of Chicago rejoice over the recognition given them by this selection of one of their able lawyers and spokesmen as Assistant States Attorney.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vlachos, although still young, is one of the pioneers of the Greek community of Chicago, a master of both the English and Greek languages and well-known and well-liked amongst our people, whom he has represented at different times as a leader. He has presided at many banquets and meetings, making himself famous as a "silver tongued orator."</p>
   <p>Mr. Vlachos is a lawyer of marked ability possessing three degrees one from the University of Athens, one from the Hamilton College of Law, and one from Northwestern University, respectively.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1298.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was born in the town of Samarades, near Tripolis, Arcadia, Greece, and came to Chicago in 1902. In 1909 Mr. Vlachos returned to Greece to serve in the Greek Army, returning to Chicago in 1910. He went to Greece again in 1912 to participate in the war against Turkey and received a commission in the army as reward for distinguished service. The year 1914 saw his return to Chicago.</p>
   <p>During his many years in our city Mr. Vlachos has displayed his loyalty to the Stars and Stripes in a very effective manner. His appointment by States Attorney Swanson gives political recognition to the Greeks of Chicago, who are coming to the front as a political power.</p>
   <p>The opportunity presents itself now in which can be brought to the attention of our people and our distinguished States Attorney, a statement made before election by the Editor of the Greek Star, P. S. Lambros and which appeared in the Chicago Daily News Oct. 25th 1928.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1299.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It pointed out the loyalty of the Greeks to Judge Swanson, as follows:</p>
   <p>Peter S. Lambros, Editor and Publisher of the Greek Star, and regarded as a spokesman in Chicago for the Greeks, declared today that more than four-fifths of the voters of his race will support Judge Swanson at the polls. He issued this statement:</p>
   <p>"More than sixty five per cent of Greek voters in Chicago and Cook County will vote for Judge John A. Swanson. They are convinced, as I am, that he will give them a safe place in which to live, in which to rear their families in peace, and operate their business, without fear of "racketeers", bombers, murderers, hoodlums and other criminals, including those allied with political cliques and crooked office holders".</p>
   <p>Now that recognitions has been given to one of our countrymen we are glad to be able to make one more pledge to Judge Swanson, that we shall extend him our best support in the execution of his duties, and our efforts will always be toward law and order for the betterment and good of this great commonwealth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
