<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title><date when="1932-07-27">July 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Demetrios Passales, Founder and Manager of the Arcadia Bakery Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1485</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1485.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title><date when="1932-07-27">July 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">DEMETRIOS PASSALES, FOUNDER AND MANAGER OF THE ARCADIA BAKERY COMPANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.--One of the eminent pioneers among the Greeks of Chicago who come from Tegea is Mr. Demetrios Passales. Mr. Passales was among the earliest Greek settlers in Chicago. He comes from the village of Marikion in Tegea and migrated to America after the national disaster of 1897.</p>
   <p>Mr. Passales and Mr. Geo. Kopita are now owners of the oldest Greek bakery in Chicago, the Arcadia. Mr. Passales had numerous adventures in the first years of his life here. He founded the Arcadia Bakery in 1905 in partnership with two others, Mr. Antonios Karnetos and Mr. Emmanuel Kontoyanne, the bakery was then at Aberdeen and Polk streets. In a short time, Mr. Passales was forced to buy out his partners and operate the bakery alone. In 1912 he took Mr. Kopitas as partner and the bakery was removed to its present location on Blue Island avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1486.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Passales has always longed to visit his dear old country but on account of many adversities and obstacles in business has been unable to gratify his wish to make this journey. We heartily desire that he may take a vacation trip to Greece so that he may enjoy some rest and recreation and visit the scenes of his boyhood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
