<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-08-21">Aug. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Eleutherios Venizelos</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0889</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0889.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-08-21">Aug. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ELEUTHERIOS VENIZELOS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Venizelos' triumph indicates that Greece will enter the war. Hellas can not stand by with folded hands when practically the entire civilized world is fighting for freedom and peace. Without sacrifice and struggle nothing can be gained or accomplished.</p>
   <p>The die has been cast. No longer can the Greek people tolerate with apathy the murder of its enslaved brothers in Thrace and Asia Minor. Thirty thousand refugees fleeing from Turkish torture and tyranny, have descended upon Athens, Peraias, Thessalonike, Kavalla, and other large cities of liberated Greece.</p>
   <p>The hearts of the Greeks, in both America and Greece, are filled with pain and sorrow by the plight of their down-trodden brothers.</p>
   <p>Is there a Greek alive who does not have a feeling of hatred toward anthropomorphic Islam? Is there a Greek patriot who does not dream of the repossession of <pb facs="5422062_2_0890.jpg" n="2"/>Saint Sofia and Constantinople?</p>
   <p>For five centuries the Greek people have dreamt of such a day as this; when they would have the opportunity to even their score with the Turks, and regain for Greece her former glory. Nursing these dreams, the Greeks have braved the dangers of war, although they have been subjected to the greatest of tests and trials already.</p>
   <p>Could it be possible that Greece, who has been reborn and baptized in a river of patriotic blood, would overlook this opportunity to draw a sword and make her dreams come true?</p>
   <p>By this vote of faith in the leadership of Venizelos, the Greek nation has expressed its willingness again to spill its blood upon the battle field, in order to revenge itself upon its barbaric enemy, and to recreate the Great Greek autocracy.</p>
   <p>We do not question the patriotism of those whose thoughts are more conservative, <pb facs="5422062_2_0891.jpg" n="3"/>and advise and believe in neutrality; for, naturally, it is more pleasant to contemplate peace than it is to witness bloodshed, and the destruction of life and culture.</p>
   <p>But! If the Patriarch Gregorious and Athanasious Diakos, (priests who became heroes and martyrs in '21) and Kolokotronis, and all the other heroes of 1821, had the same ideas, then this editorial would never have been written, for there would be no Greek nation or Greek government.</p>
   <p>The Greek nation owes its very existence to bloodshed and struggle, and to the decision of Diakos, and the execution of Melas. Today the Greek people have cast aside the tools of diplomacy and all thoughts of neutrality, and demand war.</p>
   <p>Against whom they are to fight is of little consequence to them. Any nation, including Turkish, Bulgarian, and Austrian, that has desires towards Greece, will be considered an enemy.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0892.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The victory of the great Cretan has put wings of hope on the Greek spirit; and it has made the brave Greek heart dream of a battlefield of freedom and honor, where glories can be added to the great patriotic history of Greece.</p>
   <p>In the midst of the pandemonium caused by world warfare, victimized Greece will fight her ancient enemies, and re-establish herself on the throne of glory.</p>
   <p>This is the meaning of the victory of Venizelos; and the beginning of a new period in Greek history.</p>
   <p>Hurrah for the war!</p>
   <p>Hurrah for the ascendancy of Greece to her former glory!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
