<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1931-04-04">April 4, 1931</date>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0291</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-correspondence"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0291.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. A. A. Pantelis</title> 221 N. La Salle St., Chicago, Illinois
<date when="1931-04-04">April 4, 1931</date>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Citizens of Chicago:</p>
   <p>A pamphlet issued by an unnamed organization has followed the plan of a pamphlet issued by the Greek-American Division of the Democratic party. In the Republican pamphlet on one side it is stated that "Thompson recognizes the Greeks", on the other side of it "contended that Chicago has a real and true American for mayor in the person of William Hale Thompson."</p>
   <p>I wonder how these misguided Americans of Greek birth can explain Thompson's attitude towards the naturalized citizen when he says "I am a native born American citizen. My opponent is a big bohunk who came from Bohemia and ought to be returned to where he came from."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0292.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Do these misguided "Greeks" know that if one of their number was running for Mayor, Thompson would have called him a big fruit-peddling Greek who should be returned to where he came from? Do they know that most of the business men of the Greek-Americans are being daily compelled to pay "Tribute to the City Hall Machine and to the racketeers affiliated with the City Hall?"</p>
   <p>If these misguided Greeks have a selfish interest we can forgive them on the theory that self-preservation is the first law of nature, but if they were interested in the city of their adoption, the land which recognizes neither race nor creed, where all are welcome, and where Americanism bids all to prosper, their conduct is unexcusable and all we can do is ask that they be forgiven "for they know not what they are doing."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0293.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Civic pride, the good name of Chicago, the interests of its people, are crying out loud, "Do away with Thompsonism, racketeers, and all that those evils stand for and redeem Chicago, make the coming World's Fair a success, and reward efficient, conscientious, public service by electing Anton J. Cermak Mayor of Chicago."</p>
   <p>The Achaian League recommends to its friends Anton J. Cermak.</p>
   <p>The Achaian League.</p>
   <p>A. A. Pantelis</p>
   <p>President</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
