<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-08-14">Aug. 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Professionals and the Church Question.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-08-14">Aug. 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSIONALS AND THE CHURCH QUESTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For over three years, the Greek Professional Men's Club has been trying to help settle the question of the Greek Orthodox Church in America and in doing so, has called a meeting and voted the following:</p>
   <p>Because, during the last few years there has sprung up in American a small group of Greeks, who are doing their best to dissolve the Greek Orthodox Church in America;</p>
   <p>Because, the Greek Orthodox Church in America has divided itself into three groups: the first, headed by the Oikojmenikou Patriarchal Archbishop; the second, by Mr. Basileiou, first Methimnis; and the third, by the Holysynod of Greece;</p>
   <p>Because, there are various forces trying to undermine the Greek Orthodox Church in America;</p>
   <p>Because, forces are trying to make Greeks in America change their religion, so as <pb facs="5422062_2_1272.jpg" n="2"/>to break up the Greek Orthodox Church in America;</p>
   <p>Because, the three dissecting powers show no signs of weakening or compromising, an</p>
   <p>Because the younger generation has imperative need of the GreekOrthodox Church;</p>
   <p>The Greek Professional Men's Club of Chicago promises to do all in its power to bring together the three warring factions, to effect a common understanding, in order to preserve the Creek Orthodox Church in America for our children and for their children.</p>
   <p>June 17, 1927.</p>
   <p>The Greek Professional Club has been faithful to this trust and has been a powerful influence in settling the church question. It lent all available support to His Holiness Damaskinos, when he was sent from Greece to find a solution to the problem.</p>
   <p>Secretary, G. Porikos.</p>
   <p>President, P. A. Chronopoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
