<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-08-04">Aug. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[Greeks Participate in Welcome to Scotch Regiment]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0830</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0830.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-08-04">Aug. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[GREEKS PARTICIPATE IN WELCOME TO SCOTCH REGIMENT]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week, the city of Chicago had the honor of being visited by a regiment of Canadian soldiers wearing "kilties". This regiment served in France for two years, and is famous for its courage and patriotism. The Scotch band, playing the bagpipes, filled the air with the haunting Scotch marching songs.</p>
   <p>Great Britain has organized military units in most sections of the United States for the training of British citizens residing in America. In order to honor them and the Scotch-Canadian Regiment a parade was held on Michigan Boulevard. It was witnessed by thousands of spectators and was escorted by flying squadrons performing maneuvers in the air.</p>
   <p>The parade consisted of two regiments of troops from Illinois, the Canadian <pb facs="5422062_2_0831.jpg" n="2"/>regiment, naval units, war nurses, Boy Scouts, and military bands. Sousa's Band, consisting of two hundred and fifty instruments was the best in our estimation.</p>
   <p>Among the group of foreign consuls and representatives was the Consul General of Greece, Mr. Salopoulos.</p>
   <p>In the evening a great celebration was staged at the Coliseum; exhibitions of drills, marching and baton-twirling were included....For the first time in Chicago since the advent of Venizelos and Greece's declaration of war against Germany, the Greek flag was hung alongside the flags of the Allies.</p>
   <p>The blue and white waved proudly--symbolizing, as always, freedom and honor--and representing the liberty-loving spirit of the Greeks of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Before the Scotch regiment left Chicago, it visited all the foreign consulates. Last Saturday the Greek consul was honored by its presence and was thrilled</p>
   <p>when the regiment's band played the Greek national anthem and saluted the <pb facs="5422062_2_0832.jpg" n="3"/>Blue and White.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
