<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-02-11">Feb. 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Abraham Lincoln</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1078</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1078.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-02-11">Feb. 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">ABRAHAM LINCOLN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A hundred and twenty--one years ago, in a lonely corner of the state of Kentucky, an infant was born, endowed with a privileged mind which was destined to write the most beautiful page in the history of this country, the United States of America. This infant's name was Abraham Lincoln, whose birthday anniversary is tomorrow.</p>
   <p>Much has been written about Lincoln because, by abolishing slavery, he accomplished a great object and wiped away a blot of shame from the face of his country.</p>
   <p>Among these writings there are some which seek to prove that in his efforts to liberate the negroes Lincoln did not follow the dictates of his conscience--that he was rather a tool of the industrialists of the northern states who demanded the abolution of slavery because they could not compete with the Southerners who, not having to pay wages, could produce things more cheaply.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1079.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In any case, the iconoclastic writers assert that Lincoln was influenced partly, if not wholly, by these ideas.</p>
   <p>Although we recognize the force of these arguments, we believe that Abraham Lincoln was a pure idealist as are all the privileged minds of humanity, and that he was withal practical enough to take into consideration the ideas then prevailing in the Northern states regarding the work of the negroes, and to exploit it for the realization of his ideal.</p>
   <p>It is most probable that the Northern realists followed the idealist Lincoln in the campaign for the liberation of the negroes for economic reasons. But it is also evident that Lincoln, the poor man, was guided by the star of idealism and justice. This is our conviction and, therefore, we bow our head in reverence to his memory.</p>
   <p>E. Cont.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
