<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-01-15">Jan. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Women's Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-01-15">Jan. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK WOMEN'S CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are very happy to see that the Greek women of Chicago have responded to our recent editorial on philanthropic activities. They have unfurled the flag of benevolence and kindness; and they invite all Chicago Greeks to contribute to a fund for the benefit of the poor children, and the poor Greek schools.</p>
   <p>The Saloniki considered it a journalistic duty to write an article on the philanthropic activities of the other racial groups in Chicago, and to point out the absence of Greek activities. Immediately, the Greek Women's Club decided to assume the leadership of a philanthropic campaign to be conducted in Chicago. With this money they propose to aid poor and needy Greek families; to offer financial aid to the Greek schools; and to make every effort to achieve their goal so that the Greek name may have a place of honor in the next volume listing the philanthropic accomplishments of the various organizations and churches in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1174.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The organization sent the following letter to the newspaper office, and we are proud to publish it.</p>
   <p>"Dear Mr. Damascus: The Greek Women's Club of Chicago has been deeply impressed by your recent editorial, and has taken steps to correct the mistakes and deficiencies you pointed out.</p>
   <p>"Our first step in this direction will be a dance to be given in the Masonic Temple. It will be for the benefit of the Chicago Greek schools, and we entreat you to aid us in making this affair a success.</p>
   <p>"From the offices of the Greek Women's Club".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
