<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-03-27">Mar. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0523</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0523.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-03-27">Mar. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>April 6 will be election day in Chicago. It will be the first time in the history of this city that the vote will be given to women. Now we have universal suffrage. At present, there are 709,000 citizens who are registered voters. One third of this number are women.</p>
   <p>The candidates are Thompson, Republican, and Sweitzer, Democrat. Both are running for office for the first time and each is promising an era of prosperity if elected. They both promise to build subways, parks, and public works; to reorganize the police department; and to improve business conditions. The fight between the Republicans and Democrats is very heated. Those who are most active are not as interested in the fate of either party as they are in getting themselves next to some official who is handing out political plums. About 25,000 people will get high-salaried and easy jobs when the elections are over.</p>
   <p>Now the discussion turns to us--the Greeks of Chicago, who are just discovering <pb facs="5422062_2_0524.jpg" n="2"/>what the political game has to offer. Hitherto, Chicago has had a good number of Greek political clubs. However, they were organized haphazardly and un-systematically, and they have not been very successful. In an effort to achieve recognition for themselves each Greek club would spread gossip and misinformation and about the others. As a result, the American politicians lost all faith in them and no longer gave them serious consideration. Thus the Greeks have no influence in city politics, despite the fact that we now have three thousand Greek voters.</p>
   <p>Today, the situation seems to have slightly improved. A feeling of unity has begun to impress itself on Chicago's Greeks. There is a good possibility that the Greek voters will unite to form a strong political organization. Such a move will greatly increase our power and influence. After all, we control three thousand business places, most of them located in busy sections. We come in contact with thousands of voters during working hours. This puts us in a position to influence a large group of people, and to be very useful to a <pb facs="5422062_2_0525.jpg" n="3"/>political party.</p>
   <p>The Irish have achieved political strength by means of their saloons. The Greeks can become even more powerful, because a majority of people will go into a restaurant or a confectionary shop at least twice a week.</p>
   <p>Thank goodness, the Greeks have finally begun to realize their potential power. Soon, some of our men will be holding high public offices. Co-operation is necessary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
