<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-10-19">Oct. 19, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-10-19">Oct. 19, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek-American regular Democratic organization, which has been active since last June, and which has been very successful in its work, culminated its activities in a banquet given by the chairman, Mr. George Becharas, at the Sherman Hotel, on October 5.</p>
   <p>At this banquet Mr. Thomas Bowler, Mr. John Touhy and Mr. Denis A. Horan, trustees of the Sanitary District and candidates for re-election, were present. They congratulated the Greeks for forming this organization, which has been recommended to the various leaders in past years.</p>
   <p>In this organization, the Greeks of Chicago are represented by fifty representatives, one in each ward, who is to work for, and receive instructions from the Ward Committeeman. This system, recommended by the leaders of the Democratic Party, is intended to consolidate the Greek Democratic voters.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0236.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the past, it has been the custom of a few self-appointed leaders among the Greek voters to present themselves as the leaders of the Greeks a few weeks before the elections, in order to gain personal benefits, and forget about the Greek voters after the election. This has been going on until the present campaign when the Greek voters have realized that they have been mislead and forgotten after each election. For this reason they decided to form a permanent organization which is going to be a part of and affiliated with the regular Democratic Party of the City of Chicago and Cook County.</p>
   <p>The fifty Greek Ward representatives have been selected from among the most popular persons of the Greek voters, and are the proper individuals to handle the work in each Ward. They are persons of good character, and enjoy the friendship and popularity of the Greek electorate in their Wards.</p>
   <p>All these representatives have been instructed to present themselves to their Ward Committeeman, and offer their services and cooperation to all Democratic <pb facs="5422062_2_0237.jpg" n="3"/>officials in their respective Wards, in order that the Democratic Party will emerge victorious in the coming elections.</p>
   <p>The purpose of this organization is to cooperate permanently with the Democratic Party, of which it is a part, and to function continuously and permanently, even after the election.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
