<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-03-13">Mar. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Why Greece Is Restive</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0914</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0914.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-03-13">Mar. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WHY GREECE IS RESTIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not difficult to understand the restiveness of Greece as she watches the Allied fleets bombarding their way through the Dardanelles</p>
   <p>Some six hundred years before Christ the Greek city of Byzantium was founded upon the most easterly of the seven hills now occupied by Constantinople. For nearly one thousand years this city of art and luxury made Greece imperial in the Bosporus. In the year 328 A. D., Constantine the Great began his campaign of expansion, and two years later he established the new capital of the Roman Empire giving it his name. Eleven centuries later the Turks came and since then the Crescent has been in the ascendancy.</p>
   <p>However, the Greeks have never forgotten the glorious days when Byzantium belonged to them and when the oars of their triremes flashed from the water of the Golden Horn. There is a deep-rooted sentiment and a national enthusiasm <pb facs="5422062_2_0915.jpg" n="2"/>that fires the blood of this intensely patriotic people now that the fortunes of Constantinople are once more in the lap of the god of war. If it is too much that Greece should hope to reoccupy this beautiful and strategic position, then she would like at least to have a voice in shaping its destiny.</p>
   <p>And in this soil of tradition more practical considerations find root. Greece has vital interests to conserve on the Aegean. Salonika was dearly purchased in battle from Turkey and Bulgaria. Her possession of this port is eyed jealously by two powers.</p>
   <p>Austria-Hungary dreams some day of hewing a path through Serbia to the Aegean. If the fortunes of the present war are in her favor, Austria-Hungary may seek this goal as the reward for her sacrifices of blood and money. Bulgaria resents the narrow limitations of her Aegean coast and hates Greece bitterly for the part she played in restricting it.</p>
   <p>Greece fears both these nations and seeks some way to insure herself against <pb facs="5422062_2_0916.jpg" n="3"/>their designs. Were it not for Bulgaria she would have joined the Allies long before this, in order to have a share in checking the ambitions of Austria. Now, as the possibility increases that the immediate threat of Bulgarian aggression may be dissipated,the restiveness of Greece becomes more evident.</p>
   <p>Since the war began Greece has re-occupied northern Epirus which was taken away by the treaty of London. The Island of Rhodes, now held by Italy, is racially Greek, and more than a million Greeks are settled on the Western coast of Asia Minor.</p>
   <p>These are some of the facts which explain why the drums of war are beating in the breasts of the Greek people. Hellenes recall the glorious past and as the map-makers engage in their crude drafting with sword and gun, they dream again the old dream that has ever cost a price of blood and tears.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
