<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-26">June 26, 1929</date><title level="a">The Banquet Given by Greek Professionals for Graduating Students</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1308</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1308.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-26">June 26, 1929</date><title level="a">THE BANQUET GIVEN BY GREEK PROFESSIONALS FOR GRADUATING STUDENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday evening a banquet was given by the Greek Professional Men's Club of Chicago, at the Bismark Hotel, in honor of the College and University graduating Greek students.</p>
   <p>Up till now, the organization of Greek Students, Platon, gave annually a banquet for the graduates. We believe, though that this year's innovation is the largest and most distinguished. The inspiration, which the Professional Men's Club had, to give a banquet to Greek graduates is praiseworthy.</p>
   <p>In a large and magnificent hall, at the request of the Organization of Professionals, were seated sixty-five persons, of whom an equal number were of the fairer sex. It looks as if the work for the Treasurer will be plentiful because every table was filled.</p>
   <p>We are not going to spend time and space telling you about the food. That is left to your imagination. We will start at the moment when the president of the club, Dentist C. Thomas, (no one will know who we are talking about if we say Mr. Giannakopoulos) stood up and said, that the club of Professionals <pb facs="5422062_2_1309.jpg" n="2"/>is giving this evening a banquet in honor of the graduating Greek students.</p>
   <p>In order to put us in a good mood to listen to the speakers, the President considered it a good idea to start with the artistic part of the program. He presented to us Misses Katherine Miller and Olga Massias. Miss Miller delighted us with her well-chosen Greek songs which she sang beautifully and Miss Massias amazed us with her pianoforte ability.</p>
   <p>For sound and humorous advice, the president presented the first speaker of the evening, lawyer John Gekas. Mr. Gekas mentioned the time he studied at college and the small number of Greeks attending in comparison to the number attending today. He foresees the day when hundreds of Greeks boys and girls will enroll in American universities. He admonishes the new diplomats to remain true to their nation and, by their deeds, to promote the Greek name.</p>
   <p>With a gay and carefully prepared introduction, the president presented to us the second orator of the evening, Thomas Pantelis. Mr. Pantelis, a well-known speaker, started in a light vein, slowly become more serious, till finally he raised us to the heights of Parnassus and in the end, he dwelt, <pb facs="5422062_2_1310.jpg" n="3"/>at length, on his philosophy of life.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pantelis was succeeded by the publisher of the Greek Daily, Mr. Spiros Kotakis. Mr. Kotakis at the start of his speech said: "We must admit, gentlemen, that we are abandoning our mother tongue; the consecration of English in this Professional Men's Club is a fine example of this." He advised the graduates that, if they see that it concerns them more to become Americanized and find it necessary to stop using the mother tongue, by all means to do so.</p>
   <p>Then spoke the professor of natural history at Crane College, Philip Constantinides, with scientific limpidness and offered some inside information relative to the warnings and advice given by the professionals to the graduates. He told these graduates to plow their own road and not to pay much attention to the words of the older and wiser people.</p>
   <p>Again the president turned to introduce the next speaker, but this time in a different tone of voice. We realized something was in store for us. He presented to us Professor of Archeology, Mr. George Milonas. Mr. Milonas has been in Chicago only a few weeks, and will remain the entire fall in order <pb facs="5422062_2_1311.jpg" n="4"/>to give some archeological lectures at the University of Chicago. Mr. Milonas spoke inspiringly, patriotically, urging the graduates to hold high the flame of true Greek light.</p>
   <p>The last of the speakers was the poet-philosopher, Mr. P. Hronopoulos, who, for his distinguished logic and reasoning, is put in a class with Bernard Shaw and Dean Inge. He is truly a temperamental poet in that he likes nothing conventional. And so his advice to the students was different--almost revolutionary. Always, he said, face forward, doing things the way you see fit, regardless of what others will say or think.</p>
   <p>After the speakers were finished, the names of the graduates were read, in whose honor this banquet was given. They were--Christ Diabanitis, Bachelor of Law; Theodore Sarris, Bachelor of Commerce; Thomas Orphanos and Nicholas Matsokas, Bachelors of Philosophy. Mr. Ophanos, representing the graduates, was called upon to speak. Considering his youth, he surprised us with his well-prepared speech.</p>
   <p>Before the evening ended, Mrs. G. Tzivia, American by birth, sang, to a piano <pb facs="5422062_2_1312.jpg" n="5"/>accompaniment, three gay and spritely songs, the kind that keep Athenians up all hours of the morning.</p>
   <p>To all those contributing to the enjoyment of the evening and to the president and members of the organization, we extend heartiest congratulations for giving every one of us a pleasant and enjoyable evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
