<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-05-04">May 4, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A Modern Lucifer</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1007</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1007.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-05-04">May 4, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A MODERN LUCIFER</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a friend and I were walking along the street a few days ago, we passed a man whom we have both known for many years. This man is still comparatively young--at least, he is not over forty. Five years ago, he was a respected member of society and gave promise of future success and achievement.</p>
   <p>We met this man on Madison Street--a street which is frequented by the scum of society, where everything degraded and vicious can be found. The human beings in this section of the city bear a closer resemblance to chimpanzees than to men. He was a complete wreck. His clothes hung in tatters. His body was filthy and ailing. But these were relatively minor evils. "That man," said my friend, "is a dope fiend of the worst kind."</p>
   <p>I looked at him--and at the entire group that unconsciously formed a background <pb facs="5422062_2_1008.jpg" n="2"/>for him. Only a Dore, who painted the murals illustrating Milton's Paradise Lost, could reproduce what we beheld and portray its truly horrible aspects. Crime springs naturally from such polluted sources. This group of beings resembled a vicious pack of wolves. A careful study would reveal that each of these creatures was a depraved, demoralized, lustful, and shiftless character. Sin was engraved upon each face. Disease of the soul and body will be their sole companion through the years.</p>
   <p>What we witnessed here represents a great danger. The ruinous power of narcotics is great. Their wide-spread use leads most easily to the demoralization and ruin of society. In its great despair, the world is trying to commit suicide. People, it seems, do not really wish to die; but they seek alluring mental rest through the use of narcotics.</p>
   <p>The menace of narcotics dogs modern society like a wolf-pack following a herd. The wolves patiently wait for a tired or a sick or a young animal to lie down for a rest. Then they fall upon it and tear it to pieces.....As soon as an <pb facs="5422062_2_1009.jpg" n="3"/>individual falls a prey to the horrible dope evil, he is lost. He is condemned to a fate worse than death.</p>
   <p>Our society must take drastic measures against the narcotic menace if it is to retain its self-respect and the respect of the individuals who compose it.</p>
   <p>As I was speaking these thoughts to my friend, my mind was unconsciously drawing pictures of what my eyes had just seen. But no matter how dramatic or horrible my mind's pictures were, they still fell short of the gruesome reality. I could not help but compare the young Greek successful man of five short years ago with the bedraggled, vicious, and degraded man I had just passed. A complete demoralization had taken place. Even the face of Lucifer, when he was thrown out of Heaven, could not have worn such an evil expression.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
