<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-09-11">Sept. 11, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">A Greek Bank in Chicago Is Needed.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-09-11">Sept. 11, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">A GREEK BANK IN CHICAGO IS NEEDED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The arrival in Chicago of the President of the New York branch of the Bank of Athens reminds us to return to the subject of a Greek Bank in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We have always held the opinion that there are many advantages in Chicago for one of the banks of Greece to establish a bank here. We believe that with due observation and study, the bankers will decide to invest the capital needed for the purpose.</p>
   <p>The experiment, was made successfully in the case of the Atlas Exchange National Bank established by Greeks and with Greek capital. This would have remained a Greek Bank had its founders been expert in the banking business and had they not sold out to Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1622.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the reason that there are no Greek experts in this line in Chicago, an enterprising Greek community is lacking such an indispensable establishment to serve its commercial needs.</p>
   <p>An impromptu figuring of the transactions of Greek enterprises in Chicago would estimate what the number of patrons would be for a Greek banking establishment. There are, according to the most conservative estimates. Five thousand Greek business establishment enough for business for more than one bank.</p>
   <p>Besides these greek establishments, there are many buildings erected every year by Greeks financed by American banks charging high commissions. The money in savings and in bank vaults deposited by Greek workers amounts to millions. Considerable are the sums sent to Greece also.</p>
   <p>In all this handling of Greek money, it is indisputable, that a Greek bank in Chicago would share generously. Such a bank would be a powerful connecting link with the banking business in Greece.</p>
   <p>We do not know whether the banks that have expended their operations to America have given a thought to the Greek community of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1623.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We wish that Mr. Plastropoulos, who is skillfully manages the New York Bank of Athens, and possesses so much experience and insight into this particular line of business and who knows better than any one else the conditions of Hellenism in America, would take up the study of the Greek market in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We are convinced that such a study would reveal to him that there is a great field of opportunity lying latent in the Greek Community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
