<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1928-10-19">Oct. 19, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A Thousand Greek-Americans to Banquet Louis Emmerson and His Associates on the State Ticket Next Sunday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0153</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0153.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1928-10-19">Oct. 19, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A THOUSAND GREEK-AMERICANS TO BANQUET LOUIS EMMERSON AND HIS ASSOCIATES ON THE STATE TICKET NEXT SUNDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over a thousand leading Greeks of Chicago and Cook County are expected to gather in the grand ballroom of the La Salle Hotel on Sunday evening, October 21, 1928, at a banquet to be given in honor of Louis L. Emmerson, Oscar E. Carlstrom, Otis F. Glen, William J. Stratton and Ruth Hanna McCormick, by the Greek-American Republican Club of Cook County.</p>
   <p>Although there are only about 50,000 Greek votes in Illinois, ninety per cent of which are Republican, the Greeks are going to pledge in this campaign over 100,000 votes for Emmerson and his associates. It will be an easy task for them to reach this goal, taking into consideration the fact that there are about 20,000 Greek stores in Illinois, employing over 150,000 people, and coming in contact with great numbers of people daily.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0154.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A committee of leading Greek-American businessmen of this city has been organized to further the cause of Louis L. Emmerson and his associates, according to Attorney Paul Demos, president of the club, and Peter S. Lambros, editor of the Greek Star and chairman of the publicity committee; both have been authorized to take charge of the campaign. They will unite all the leading Greek-Americans in Cook County, so that all can take personal pride and interest in the support of Louis L. Emmerson and his associates on the state ticket.</p>
   <p>Mr. Emmerson has made a number of friends among the Greek people. He has been enthusiastically supported by the descendants of Pericles and Demosthenes, who believe in his integrity, his sterling character and the principles of the Republican party, with Herbert Hoover at the helm as the undisputed bearer of the Republican banner.</p>
   <p>Ruth Hanna McCormick, candidate for congressman-at-large, will be the speaker of the evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0155.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many of the candidates have been invited to attend the banquet.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
