<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-07-19">July 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A Half-Million-Dollar Lease</title><title level="a" type="sub">Negotiated through the Offices of George Tsiagouris for Raklios and Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-07-19">July 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A HALF-MILLION-DOLLAR LEASE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Negotiated Through the Offices of George Tsiagouris for Raklios and Company</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3- This is not the first time that readers of these pages have looked upon the pictures of two well-known compatriots of ours in this community, each of whom is a person of great enterprise in his field. Whenever we have a chance to publish their pictures, we have something good to report, - something which concerns not only the Greek community in Chicago but all Hellenism; for the progress of Greeks, especially of those in a foreign country, is a matter which is attributed to the entire Greek nation. By this progress people estimate the commercial ability and the enterprising nature of the whole race; by the success of Greeks in various professions, businesses, and industries their worth is reckoned as a race among other races.</p>
   <p>In America especially, where all nationalities in the world meet and struggle for ascendancy, a singular opportunity is presented to compete with many races, and this in itself tends to develop every man's natural <pb facs="5422062_2_1673.jpg" n="2"/>talents, to invigorate him, and to sharpen the ingenuity which is his racial inheritance. We must imagine at this moment that all the races of the world have assembled on Chicago's stage for one great struggle; under these circumstances it is easy to conceive how profound our emotions are while we follow their efforts, and how much profounder they become when we observe Greeks also struggling in competition with all these strangers. How intense is our desire to see them win!</p>
   <p>In these great Chicago combats, as far as restaurants are concerned, the Greeks are struggling successfully, and they always stay in the front rank. In this front rank among Greeks the leading position has been won by Mr. John Raklios, who is now competing with the strongest American organizations for leadership. Because of what we have said above the progress of Mr. Raklios and his associates is a matter of great importance to every Greek; it is to the interest of every Greek to continue to observe that progress.</p>
   <p>Little time has elapsed since we had the pleasure of recording the opening of Mr. Raklios's two latest establishments: one at the Capitol building, <pb facs="5422062_2_1674.jpg" n="3"/>in the downtown district, and the other at Jackson and Halsted Streets. Now we have the pleasure of announcing the opening of a third restaurant at Madison and Market Streets. Mr. George Tsiagouris arranged for the leasing of all three places.</p>
   <p>This last restaurant, at Madison and Market Streets, is the thirty-seventh opened by Mr. John Raklios and the thirty-first since the founding of Raklios and Company, of which he is president, Basil Kotsonis is vice-president, and Andrew Hronis is secretary. It is a matter of common knowledge that the negotations for the lease of the building which houses this restaurant have been closed, and we are able to say that large and successful leases like this one are the rule in the offices of our active and highly experienced compatriot, George Tsiagouris. The lease was made between Mr. Linn and the Raklios Company and involves the rental of the entire building at Madison and Market Streets for a short term of years. It seems that Mr. Tsiagouris did a good job in these negotiations, making both parties to the lease fast friends. Now whenever Mr. Raklios opens a new store, he leaves it to the offices of Mr. George Tsiagouris to do the leasing.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1675.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We really are not exaggerating when we say that the offices of George Tsiagouris are the ablest in Chicago for negotiating large leases for in the many years in which he has been in business Mr. Tsiagouris has made connections with the largest property-owners, and his offices are associated with the largest real estate firms in Chicago. He can therefore conduct negotiations with ease and close deals on any building or enterprise. The business of George Tsiagouris owes its success to the alertness and method with which Mr. Tsiagouris does his work and even more to his sincerity.</p>
   <p>The fact that Raklios and Company intrusts the leasing of space for its restaurants only to the offices of Mr. Tsiagouris, and that in a brief period $1,060,000 worth of leases were successfully negotiated for, demonstrates the character and the ability of Mr. George Tsiagouris.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
