<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-05-20">May 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">More about Our Labor Problems</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1022</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1022.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-05-20">May 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MORE ABOUT OUR LABOR PROBLEMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It seems that Chicago has given the impetus needed to solve many of the social problems of the Greek-Americans. Since the first article was written about the problem of the Greek bootblacks, we have received hundreds of letters from all over America, praising our efforts and promising co-operation.</p>
   <p>A short time after the formation of the Employers Protective Association, here in Chicago, we were elated to hear that a similar organization was formed in New York City. At the first New York meeting, it was decided that the shops would be closed on Sunday afternoon, and that the boys should be paid ten cents for each pair of shoes shined on Saturdays and Sundays.</p>
   <p>We have received letters from some of the New York bootblacks. In their letters they thank the Saloniki for helping them, and also extend words of <pb facs="5422062_2_1023.jpg" n="2"/>appreciation to the progressive employers of Chicago, who set such a good example for the other employers all over America to follow. In Springfield, Massachusetts--where the Saloniki has a large circulation--one hundred bootblacks went on strike and forced their employers to give them more consideration. As a result of this strike, seventeen subscriptions to the Saloniki were canceled by irate bosses who felt that we were the instigators of their labor problems.</p>
   <p>Of course, the Saloniki is not going to cease fighting for right and justice just because of a few canceled subscriptions. We will continue to raise our voices in a loud battle cry, in order that the Greek boys--who were born free, of free parents, and under a free flag--may themselves be free in this free land, and not act as slaves to the hard, cruel owners of shoe-shine parlors, who make them work seventeen to eighteen hours a day.....</p>
   <p>The job is not yet finished! Both employers and the employees must be <pb facs="5422062_2_1024.jpg" n="3"/>completely organized. The evils that have so long flourished must be abolished. The working conditions must be raised to American standards so that the American press will cease writing articles about the Greek employers. Such exposures,will, in time, ruin the business of all the Greek men, because public opinion will be aroused against them.</p>
   <p>The organization of the Chicago Greek Employers' Protective Association is going to be of benefit to the employers and the bootblacks all over America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
