<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1937-01-01">Jan. 1, 1937</date><title level="a">F. Nichols Elected President of Rogers Park Kiwanis Club.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE GREEK STAR</title>,
<date when="1937-01-01">Jan. 1, 1937</date><title level="a">F. Nichols Elected President of Rogers Park Kiwanis Club.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An example of true American sportmanship appeared last week at the Hotel Sovereign where the club has its weekly luncheon meetings. The club unanimously elected Frank Nichols as their president. Kiwanis has a membership of ninety-five thousand professional and business people in the United States and Canada, so it is indeed an honor to the Greek race and to the progressive Greeks of Chicago because it is believed that F. Nichols is the first Greek in the entire United States to hold the position of president in such an organization.</p>
   <p>Frank Nichols, whose real native name is Fotios Meltihoes Nikolopoulos, came to this country in 1912 from Vounargon, Pyrgos, Ellias, Greece, and until nine years ago had been in many parts of the country. In 1928 he opened the Hacienda at 1614 Howard Street, and even there he felt as a stranger among strangers until a neighborhood business man approached him to join the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1387.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ever since he entered the Kiwanis Club he has taken an active part in the organization. He served as director for five years during which time he served as chairman of the House Committee, chairman of the Reception Committee, chairman of the Underprivileged Child Work Committee and during the past year of 1936 he served as chairman of the Program Committee. During the chairmanship of the Underprivileged Child Work Committee, Frank promoted one of the most humanitarian objectives in the Club's membership--- the Deaf-Mute School.</p>
   <p>Mr. Nichols has belonged to the club for more than six years, has a perfect attendance record, served on all committees, and has been a director for the last four years. He is also a director of Howard District Business Association and belongs to the Institute of Human Relations; the National Confederation of Jews and Christians; the Restaurant Association; Beavers International; Masonic Order of Knight Templar; Shivers and also to the Gole Fathers' Council. Frank Nichols is a very popular and very successful business man of whom his fellow countrymen feel very proud.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
