<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1937-01-01">January 1, 1937</date><title level="a">Hitlerism &amp; Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1937-01-01">January 1, 1937</date><title level="a">HITLERISM &amp; WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a concentration of the women's organization of the National-Socialistic party in Berlin, Mr. Rudolph Es, representative for Hitler, lectured about the women of the Third Reich before Miss Gertrude Soltz-Klint and twenty-thousand other women of the organization. On this most interesting theme Mr. Es commented as follows:</p>
   <p>"A woman is honored in Germany as a mother, as a companion to her husband, and as citizen of the nation. Abroad they have erroneous ideas concerning our conception of woman. We desire women whose lives and whose works do not alter their feminine nature, that is, women that we can love! We are leaving behind us the world that wants to see only one specific kind of woman. We bear them no grudge as long as they let us choose the type of woman we consider most precious.....</p>
   <p>"The ideal woman of Germany today isn't the stereotyped "Gretchen" with her old-fashioned and narrow conceptions, but a woman who will stand by her husband, brave and uncomplaining, through the agony of life with its thousand apprehensions and joys which tend to make it more rich and full as time goes <pb facs="5422062_2_1153.jpg" n="2"/>on. This is Germany's ideal woman of today. A woman, especially that can be a mother.</p>
   <p>"That last sentence sums up one of the biggest achievements of National-Socialistic Germany. More women become mothers in Germany today than ever before and it isn't because the nation or men wish it. No, it is the mothers, they themselves are proud to bring into this world strong and healthy children. The mothers have one purpose, to preserve themselves for their country. We know, of course, that all women cannot attain that height of happiness because all women do not marry. And that is why we uphold vocations for women. They are free to choose whatever profession they wish. They can study at Universities, especially in vocations that require certain scientific knowledge where women excel over men.</p>
   <p>"On the other hand, this new Germany does not want to see its women in professions that make her seem masculine. It wants to see the German woman fulfilling her duty as a supplement to man's nature. Women of other nations will look up some day to this modern Germany. They might even envy these women contemporaries of theirs that are so far ahead of them."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
