<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-10-13">Oct. 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Liberty Loan Drive Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0811</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0811.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-10-13">Oct. 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK LIBERTY LOAN DRIVE MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday a meeting was held at 3 P. M. in the home of Mr. Constantine Salopoulos. The purpose of the meeting was to elect a chairman of the Greek committee for the Liberty Loan drive. Mr. Salopoulos, upon being elected, made the following speech.</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen,</p>
   <p>"I invited you to my home for two purposes. One was to ask all of you to bring your philanthropic and brotherly instincts to the fore in order to gain the respect and love of the American people; the other concerns the plans of this committee. I was greatly honored when the Seventh Federal Banking Division asked me to organize a committee of Greeks to encourage the purchase of Liberty Bonds by the Greek people.</p>
   <p>"We, and the various other nationalities in this country, must unite to work and <pb facs="5422062_2_0812.jpg" n="2"/>struggle for this cause which is sacred, on behalf of this adopted land in which we so happily live.</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen! My character and my way of living will testify that I did not accept this honored position for the glory it carries with it. My fifteen years spent in Chicago have never been devoted to a search for false glory or undeserved laurels.</p>
   <p>"I am a common man in the pharmacy profession. Unwillingly, I have assumed the title of journalist; this happened because I have always felt such a tremendous interest in the progress of the community. Nevertheless, I cannot help feeling a glow of pride for the honor bestowed upon me. I beseech you to aid me in this matter, in order to show that we are worthy of the trust placed in us. My acceptance was based upon my sincere belief in you.</p>
   <p>"After I present the outline of our work, and my own ideas, I desire to hear your opinions and criticisms, so as to help us in the building of a successful <pb facs="5422062_2_0813.jpg" n="3"/>program. Our nationality is going to be judged by that program, and its success or failure. If we cannot surpass them, we must at least equal the achievements of the other foreign groups of Chicago who are following similar programs. We must gain the respect of this wonderful land in which we live....</p>
   <p>"I was given the privilege of organizing a Greek committee in Chicago, to work among our fellow patriots selling Liberty Bonds. These Bonds are a guarantee against slavery, hate, fanaticism and dictatorship. The proceeds of these Bonds, will be used in both other countries and America; they will be available to all of the allied nations, including our own motherland, Greece. Therefore we are indirectly aiding our own country by supporting the drive.....</p>
   <p>"Not only will our social status be raised by our whole-heartedly aiding this drive, but our businesses will profit. When the Americans see how eager we are to show our patriotism they will repay us by patronizing our places of business. Not only will we become more successful, but we will feel quite free to ask their aid and support in any of our future problems.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0814.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Even if you ignore all of the afore-mentioned points, there is one left that is undeniable; it is, that buying Liberty Bonds is a sound business investment. These bonds pay six per cent interest and are as safe as the bank of the United States. They can be transferred....and are good forever. Everything seems to be to our advantage when we purchase these Bonds.</p>
   <p>"Acting upon the advice of the Central Committee, I made a list of one hundred people who I felt were capable of making such a program a success. You who are present here are those individuals. I wish to thank you for honoring me by being present, and I implore you to co-operate in a brotherly fashion, to make this undertaking successful. Let personal grievances be forgotten, and let us devote our minds to this patriotic cause. I place myself at your disposal, but I do require that we all abide by the wishes of the majority, and that we do so good-naturedly.</p>
   <p>"This sacred cause should firmly unite us in a more friendly spirit.</p>
   <p>"Hurrah for America! Hurrah for Greece!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
