<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-12-05">Dec. 5, 1931</date><title level="a">Pioneers of the Greek Community in Chicago by Dr. Volicos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-12-05">Dec. 5, 1931</date><title level="a">PIONEERS OF THE GREEK COMMUNITY IN CHICAGO By Dr. Volicos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- The pioneers of the present Greek Community in Chicago came much earlier than 1870. They were men of the sea. All of them spoke many languages as well as they did English, due to their work which took them everywhere. They were closely associated with Italians, as they spoke Italian. As a rule, they were mistaken for Italians. But soon other Greeks came, especially Lacedaemons and Arcadians. Following the proclivities of the pioneers, the new-comers began to sell fruit, candy and flowers in the streets of Chicago, at first using push-carts, and later on horses and buggies. The Greek community was established and was composed entirely of peddlers.</p>
   <p>The Spartans began to predominate in these three lines of business and soon, due to their shrewdness and keen observation, discovered (or stole) <pb facs="5422062_2_1493.jpg" n="2"/>a secret method of making candy. Until then, they had to purchase their candy from Jews and Italians. As soon as the method of candy-making became known, the majority of the Spartans spread all over the city and a confectionery sprang up on every busy corner. Little by little the Jews and the Italians were frozen out of the candy business. Other Spartans came, learned the trade of candy-making and, in a short time, every city in America had one or more Greek confectionery stores.</p>
   <p>Noted among the old timers was Uncle Constantine, who spent his entire fortune in helping his compatriots to be established in business, Nick Mazarakos, John Prokos, Papageorge, John Vlachandreas, Poulis from Corfu, Anast. Manousos, the old man, Poulos, who never left the saloon bar, Basil Zepos, who liked the American dances.</p>
   <p>But what a difference there is today! In my next article I will endeavor to picture the evolving stages of progress of the Greek Community in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
