<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-03-04">March 4, 1930</date><title level="a">An Opinion on the Commercial Progress of Hellenism in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-03-04">March 4, 1930</date><title level="a">AN OPINION ON THE COMMERCIAL PROGRESS OF HELLENISM IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6.- Having thought that a publisher should express not only his own thoughts but also those of others, and that the readers may benefit by a variety of opinions, I have set myself to the task and started with Mr. Christ A. Zois.</p>
   <p>I visited Mr. Zois in the office of his factory and, after I explained the purpose of my visit, he told me that I could have his opinion but not necessarily for publication. With politeness and characteristic kindness, he told me, in a serious mood, that once a purpose is fulfilled, there is no need of mentioning names.</p>
   <p>"There is a need of a modern system," Mr. Zois said, "in all lines of Greek business because Americans and other nationalities will sweep aside the Greek enterprises by their highly efficient corporations.</p>
   <p>"We must realize," he said, "that people change systems in all branches of human activity and we, too, must not be backward. We must act together <pb facs="5422062_2_1561.jpg" n="2"/>in business, honestly, and exchange ideas and opinions in public meetings and elsewhere, for our existence and development. We must listen to the opinions of others, no matter how simple and insignificant they may seem to be. Because experience is possessed by the most uneducated and illiterate individuals, and the lessons that experience teaches are needed by even the most highly educated who are trained in theory only.</p>
   <p>"We, in America must cooperate with each other. Our communities must not be divided along the interests of party lines in Greece. Our present church division is a shameful one. Our money is wasted if we put it in churches that stand divided and which tend to divide us. Wise spending of money and time will enable us to establish the perfect Greek-American. There should be educational institutions for the small communities where there are no Greek schools and from which the new Greek generation could emerge fully equipped and filled with vitality as worthy descendants of their historic ancestry."</p>
   <p>Thus Mr. Zois spoke. Mr. Zois attained most of his education from private study and social experience. He is looked upon by fellow Greeks as a capable and efficient business man.</p>
   <p>D.J. Rigas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
