<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-05-07">May 7, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A Park for Our Pcinics.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1546</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1546.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-05-07">May 7, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A PARK FOR OUR PCINICS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the coming of the summer season, all clubs, organizations, and communities, planning picnics, are confronted with the problem of a suitable park. The difficulty lies in the location of the park and in its convenience. If a park is pleasantly situated, although far from the community center, it is of little service. The same can be said if it is in the heart of the district, yet has no means of amusement or any conveniences. A solution has been found to this problem.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday, in view of the lovely weather, Charles Andrews, owner of the Grand View Gardens, 6401-6413 Grand Avenue, started remodeling the huge park and the pavilion. When finished, it will be exactly what is wanted.</p>
   <p>The park is well known to many of our countrymen, who hold their annual picnics there. Although the park was conveniently situated, it lacked space, which has now been added in addition to the remodeling.</p>
   <p>When we visited the Grand View Gardens last Sunday, we were amazed at the vast improvement <pb facs="5422062_2_1547.jpg" n="2"/>in the Gardens, to which Mr. Andrews and his partner, Mr. K. Metropoulos, escorted us. They assured us that the place will be rented very cheaply this year. Although it is not for Greeks alone, Greeks will be given preference over any other nationalistic picnic during this coming summer season, which promises many good picnic days. The Grand View Gardens are easily accessible by automobile, street cars, and buses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
