<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Hellenic Center News</title>, (Weekly)
<date when="1932-10-15">Oct. 15, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Greek-American Democratic Party Holds Meeting</title><title level="a" type="sub">Plans Strenuous Campaign between Now and Election.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0364</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0364.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Hellenic Center News</title>, (Weekly)
<date when="1932-10-15">Oct. 15, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK-AMERICAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY HOLDS MEETING</title><title level="a" type="sub">Plans Strenuous Campaign between Now and Election.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek-American Democratic Club of Chicago convened at the chambers of National Democratic Headquarters, 134 North La Salle Street, on October 10, at 5:00 p. m.,to decide upon its plans towards the coming National, State and City elections.</p>
   <p>There were more than fifty of the leaders from the various Wards of Chicago and vicinity present.</p>
   <p>The greatly esteemed chairman of the Democratic Club,Hon. Dr. Salopoulos, presided.</p>
   <p>He spoke briefly on the Democratic campaign that is going on throughout the States and stressed the duty of the Greek-American citizens towards the Government of their adopted country, America. He also elaborated on the duty of every Greek-American citizen to unite and vote for every National, State and city Democratic candidate for office.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0365.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. A. A. Pantelis, a prominent attorney of Chicago, Secretary of the Club, and active member of the Democratic party for the last quarter of a century, eloquently elaborated on a new plan whereby the Greek-American Democrats can achieve the best results on the incoming elections. Mr. Pantelis! plan is a commendable one and is certain to accomplish greater results than at first anticipated, by elevating the Greek-American Democratic Club to an enviable position among political organizations.</p>
   <p>Thereafter, many informal speeches were delivered. Some of the speakers were: Mr. Paul Kare, the fearless leader of the 27th Ward, whose enthusiasm to-wards the Greek-Democratic Club was once again displayed by his speech in this meeting, Dr. Joannides, the man of many talents, spoke lengthily on various phases of the organization and assured the Club that "successis ours."</p>
   <p>Mr. Peter Agriostathes, another aggressive leader of the 20th Ward, spoke highly of the spirit shown by the Greek-American citizens in the coming elections.</p>
   <p>Others who spoke in brief were: Mr. George Poulos, Mr. Paul Koken, Mr. Pantelis Rangos, and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0366.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Last, but not least, spoke Hon. A. T. Sabath, Congressman from Illinois, and also the chairman of the National Groups throughout the States as well as in the State of Illinois, County of Cook and City of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Hon. A. T. Sabath, the "Dean of Congress" was the guest speaker of the meeting. He mentioned the various methods used by other National Groups in achieving the best results in the coming elections. He praised very highly the Democratic candidates for office and especially Franklin Delano Roosevelt, the next President. He expressed his high regard for the Greeks and his confidence that the Greek-Democratic Club will do more than its share in electing all the Democratic candidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
