<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1931-03-30">March 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Old Greek Oath Urged as Model in Mayor Race</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editor Boosts Cermak Says City Tires of "Big Bill the Builder"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1931-03-30">March 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">OLD GREEK OATH URGED AS MODEL IN MAYOR RACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITOR BOOSTS CERMAK SAYS CITY TIRES OF "BIG BILL THE BUILDER"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The oath of the Athenians, sworn by the citizens of Athens 3,000 years ago, was taken as the model of an oath for Chicagoans today in a modern "phillipic" by Peter S. Lambros, editor of the Greek Star and active in the campaign for Anton J. Cermak, Democratic candidate for Mayor.</p>
   <p>"The Phillipics of Demosthenes stand today in universal respect by every race and every age," Mr. Lambros writes. Demosthenes exclaimed, "Oh, Athenians, remember the ruins of Athens." We exclaim today, "Oh, Chicagoans, remember the good name of Chicago."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0563.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Recalls Aristedes Incident</p>
   <p>Still further digging into the classics of his native Greece - Mr. Lambros is a Spartan but believes that today a Spartan may agree with Athenians - he recalls the campaign in which Aristides the Just was running for Mayor or something in Athens.</p>
   <p>"As Aristides was walking to the polls," Lambros recalls, "he was accosted by a citizen whom he did not know. He was handed an ostrac, or voting ballot, and was asked to vote against Aristides.</p>
   <p>"'But why should I vote against Aristides?' Aristides asked the stranger. 'Because,' the citizen replied, 'the people are tired of hearing of him as Aristides the Just.'"</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0564.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Tried of "Builder" Slogan</p>
   <p>"Perhaps," Lambros adds, "Mayor Thompson does not feel that the same terms are applicable to him. But the people of Chicago are tired of hearing of 'Big Bill the Builder.' Someone should hand him a ballot on election day and advise him to vote against himself? Here is a part of the oath of the Athenians, as dug up by Mr. Lambros:</p>
   <p>"'We will fight for the ideals and sacred things of the city, both singly and together. We will revere and obey the city's laws and do our best to incite alike respect and reverence in those above us who are prone to annul or set them at naught.</p>
   <p>"'We will strive unceasingly to quicken the public sense of civic duty. Thus in all these ways we will transmit this city....greater, better and more beautiful than it was transmitted to us.'"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
