<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1914-10-10">Oct. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our War Heroes</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-10-10">Oct. 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR WAR HEROES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek community of Chicago has taken part in many patriotic festivities and celebrations. None of them, however, are comparable to the celebration which is to be given in the Holy Trinity Church in behalf of the soldiers who fought in two victorious battles for Greece. The speaker of the day will be Mr. N. Salopoulos, the representative of King Constantine of Greece.</p>
   <p>The list of men who are to receive medals is printed below. It is not complete, however; there are many others whose names will appear on this list within a short time.</p>
   <p>Greeks of Chicago:</p>
   <p>Two years ago, two thousand Greek patriots left America and returned home to <pb facs="5422062_2_0925.jpg" n="2"/>fight for their mother country. They went through a living hell and faced death and mutilation a hundred times a day. They fought under the Sky-blue Colors: on the heights of Olympus, in Thrace, and in Avlonas. Only one hundred and forty-three returned. All of them, both the living and the dead, have been decorated with the laurel wreath of the victor.</p>
   <p>The men whose names appear below were given a Greek flag when they left two years ago. They dipped this flag in the Ionian Sea and carried it victoriously. These men are Chicagoans, and they are worthy of the highest tribute and honor that we can pay them.</p>
   <p>We must not forget the great work done by the volunteer legion of Chicago which was led by Mr. N. Salopoulos. This was the legion which inspired the Greeks of America. As a result, over thirty more volunteer legions were formed. Now these volunteers are to be decorated for their bravery and their undying patriotism. It has always been the custom to receive the conquering heroes with <pb facs="5422062_2_0926.jpg" n="3"/>joy and prayers of thanksgiving. Therefore, let us all gather in the Holy Trinity Church next Sunday and pay homage to these gallant men.</p>
   <p>The names of the honored men are as follows: officers, John Agriostathis, Constantine Collias, Andrew Alekopoulos.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
