<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-09-28">Sept. 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Why Hellenism Is Left Behind Must it Always Be Classified Among the Unorganized Foreign Groups?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0481</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0481.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-09-28">Sept. 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">WHY HELLENISM IS LEFT BEHIND MUST IT ALWAYS BE CLASSIFIED AMONG THE UNORGANIZED FOREIGN GROUPS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Proodos, right after its establishment in Chicago, tried to find out why Hellenism was so evidently left behind from a political standpoint, while showing so much activity in all other branches of social and commercial circles.</p>
   <p>According to the conception of those persons mixing in politics and the like, this is the result of our racial characteristics; lack of cooperation on account of egotistical ambitions; petty interests and other weaknesses.</p>
   <p>And because Hellenism is lacking a systematic political organization to appear united in a political body, it is classified among the foreign groups, <pb facs="5422062_2_0482.jpg" n="2"/>the unorganized, as are characterized all the unorganized groups of non-English speaking peoples, by the politicians and the parties.</p>
   <p>Another reason for this lack of systematic organization is that the various self-appointed leaders did not care, or could not organize the Greeks politically, and were satisfied with the small favors and privileges they enjoyed as individuals, leaving Hellenism to be classed among the foreign groups.</p>
   <p>The necessity of such a real and systematic organization being understood by Mr. C. Psalidas, one of the veteran Greek politicians, he and some others are now trying to reorganize the Regular Greek-American Democratic organization, along the lines of the Democratic Party organization of the Wards. We wish them the best of luck.</p>
   <p>In building up this organization they aim to have one representative in each Ward, and all these to elect a central committee to cooperate with <pb facs="5422062_2_0483.jpg" n="3"/>the Central Committee of the Democratic Party. Nothing could be more simple and in no way against the interests of the Hellenism which until now was represented by the foreign groups division.</p>
   <p>The work, so far, has been very successful, although not all the Ward representatives have been selected because it is the desire of the organizers to have harmonious cooperation with all political leaders of the Wards. The Greeks will then be represented directly instead of being left in the foreign groups and considered insignificant, although representing more than thirty-five thousand votes.</p>
   <p>Among the leaders who know and have the interest of the Greeks at heart, the consensus of opinion is to support and assist this movement, and to lay the foundation for such an organization to help the Greeks take their proper place in the political arena.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
