<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-07-06">July 6, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Beyond Tomorrow</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Graeco-Americanus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-07-06">July 6, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">BEYOND TOMORROW</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Graeco-Americanus</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In bygone days the first thing we looked for in the papers the day after the Fourth of July was an account of the fatalities resulting from fireworks. A few serious-minded people sought to read what the great of the land had said in their Fourth of July orations. Today, although the scene has changed, the background is still the same. Instead of reading about fatalities due to fireworks, we go through the papers figures to find out how many were killed in automobile accidents.</p>
   <p>Human beings continue to seek pleasure and excitement even at the risk of their lives. Man does not live by contemplation alone. That is the prerogative of the few mortals who are the guardians of civilization and the pioneers of all movements for good. Of such were the strong, resolute characters who <pb facs="5422062_2_1070.jpg" n="2"/>aroused the colonists to rebel against the unjust and selfish ruling class of England. It may be that if the Revolution had not taken place, what we today call the United States of America would have been part of the English Commonwealth of Nations....</p>
   <p>Judging from results, it was undoubtedly for the best that revolution was decided upon and that the United States of America was born. The creation of the American nation has had more to do with the liberation of the peoples of Europe from the shackles of tyranny and superstition than even the great discovery of America itself.</p>
   <p>America, by providing a refuge to the free and rebellious spirits of Europe, has done her share among nations in raising the level of the common man.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
