<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-08-23">Aug. 23, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Better to Be Barbarians Than Civilized Slaves</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-08-23">Aug. 23, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">BETTER TO BE BARBARIANS THAN CIVILIZED SLAVES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Observers of the European political and social situations are all of the opinion that the people of Europe are rapidly approaching the terrible goal set by their leaders. In other words, war seems inevitable. In other periods of history, after any great war, the peoples concerned have directed all their efforts toward future peace and to binding national wounds caused by war. For that reason, after the Napoleonic wars, there was no serious upset until 1870....Then forty years intervened before the great World War started. Of course, in the meantime, the Crimean War and the Russo-Japanese War took place; but they were both of a restricted nature, and comparatively unimportant.</p>
   <p>War has and always will be destruction and ruin to nations. The ruin, both <pb facs="5422062_2_0610.jpg" n="2"/>material and spiritual, which it leaves in its wake is often not overcome for centuries. Although every civilized person on earth is aware of the catastrophe and disaster wrought by warfare, instead of taking steps to outlaw war and to make it unknown in future generations, a peculiar thing is happening in the world. Every day news comes of still another leader of men who preaches that war is the only solution to the problem. While a spirit of liberalism should have pervaded the world after the great tragedy and anguish of the World War, instead, the opposite occurred. More brutal theories than ever are being put into practice. Millions of people have given up their liberties and personal freedom and live and are governed exactly as if this were the Feudal Age.</p>
   <p>The last twenty years have brought an actual revolution of thought in Europe. Dynasties have been destroyed only to be replaced by new systems of government, most of which are entirely opposed to the principles of democracy. We do not include Soviet Russia in this category because her program and methods <pb facs="5422062_2_0611.jpg" n="3"/>are in no way akin to the other dictator septems of Europe. There is no resemblance between Fascism--a word that is beginning to symbolize everything hateful and destructive--and Communism. There is no doubt as to the tremendous opposition the preachers of totalitarianism direct against the social precepts of Communism. For instance, they persecute minorities (as, for example, the Jews), while there is no persecution of races or groups in Russia. If there were agreement between them, then the German Communists would not be so terribly punished or killed by Hitler's Nazis.</p>
   <p>All these facts testify that back of present events and new political systems, there is a hidden spectre of oligarchy. This system will give the power into the hands of a few, and reduce the rest of humanity to beasts of burden and producers of wealth, the use of which they will never have because they will have no rights or power. Proof that these new systems are oligarchical and repressive, is that they are heartily supported by all of the conservative groups of the world. From the social unrest following the chaos of 1917, the <pb facs="5422062_2_0612.jpg" n="4"/>conservative factors molded public opinion by stressing the love for country, nationalism, and racial superiority. Only history will tell us the amount of blood which has been shed and the number of victims who have been needlessly sacrificed in the name of nationalism.</p>
   <p>The idea of loving the fatherland and being nationalistic is not, in itself, wrong. But when they only serve as a shield to hide barbarism and brutality, it is much better that they cease to exist. It is better even for a nation to die than have such an inglorious existence. It would be better if man were living in the prehistoric ages, when he feared only the dinosauer, than today, listening to the barbaric policies and manias of Hitler and his ilk on the radio.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
