<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-02-07">Feb. 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Greeks from Dodecanese to Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-02-07">Feb. 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO GREEKS FROM DODECANESE TO PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Groups of Greeks from the Dodecanese Islands are gathering in many American cities to protest the fate of their birthplace. They are trying to make the civilized world aware of the atrocities which are being committed against the Greek inhabitants of these Islands by the Italian armed forces. The most recent of these crimes and murders was their firing upon unarmed groups, composed mainly of women and children. This was done because the people preferred to close their churches entirely rather than to cut themselves off from the Ecumenical Patriarchy of Greece at the command of the Fascist tyrant.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of America will not forget these murders of their brothers by the dictator of Rome. We, in America, are in a position to hurt Mussolini by means of comparatively simple methods. We can and will reveal his true colors to the world. We can, in a peaceful way, help make him the second of the most hated men in the world. His friend Hitler unmistakably stands forth as the world's most hated man. Every protest made in America by us will be <pb facs="5422062_2_0601.jpg" n="2"/>like a nail driven in Mussolini's coffin. The Chicago Dodecanesians must use their privilege of driving hard their own spike into his coffin (they would rather drive it into his flesh).</p>
   <p>Of course the natives of these Islands are not numerous in Chicago. But are we not all Greeks? Let us fill some hall to overflowing and make formal, public, and loud protests--so that the whole world will hear. Let us make a beginning and every Greek will lend his whole-hearted support. If we speak the truth, and do so without malice we will gain the assistance of all the Americans--even the Italians. It is, of course, clearly understood that we bear no antagonism toward the Italian people; for they are just as much his victims as we are. Our hatred is directed toward the tyrant of Rome, not toward his misguided people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
