<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-29">Mar. 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Election in Chicago - the Citizens' Duty - to the Voters of the Greek Community</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-29">Mar. 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE ELECTION IN CHICAGO - THE CITIZENS' DUTY - TO THE VOTERS OF THE GREEK COMMUNITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The ever-increasing immigration to America of numerous foreign peoples and the rapid expansion of American commerce have been the principal factors in the unparalleled progress of this great cosmopolitan democratic country, which promises to subject the world to its influence.</p>
   <p>Because of the cosmopolitan spirit which prevails throughout our immense country groups of various nationalities and various creeds are co-operating in America's upward march. And here in our city of Chicago, which a few years ago was an insignificant hamlet and to-day is the metropolis of the West, we find practically all the races of the world grouped together and united to hammer out by their industry the progressive destiny of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Chicago, where three million people, natives and immigrants, have blended together and are working together to make the city prominent and universally recognized as a great commercial and intellectual center, expects its citizens to go to the polls and elect capable and conscientious leaders <pb facs="5422062_2_0451.jpg" n="2"/>to govern our municipal affairs. On April 2, 1907, Chicago will hold its municipal election. And the interests of the city and of its inhabitants will be affected by the results of this election.</p>
   <p>The Star, as guardian of the Greek element in the United States, cannot refrain from taking an interest in the election of a mayor of Chicago, for Chicago is our adopted city, the dwelling-place of thousands of Greeks. Therefore it is our imperative duty as American citizens and as persons interested in the welfare of the Greek community to dip into the political pot and to ascertain the qualifications of the opposing candidates.</p>
   <p>Careful analytical observation, coupled with common sense, reveals to us that Fred A. Busse, Republican candidate for the office of mayor, is the man better qualified to fill that office. Hence it is our honor and our duty urgently to recommend his election to the chief political office in this great cosmopolitan city. The Greek voters of Chicago will perform a service to this city if they cast their ballots for this broad-minded, progressive, fearless, and honest man. His election as mayor of Chicago will mean a great deal to us Greeks and to all progressive people of the city. If we want Chicago to advance to prosperity and greatness, Fred A. Busse is <pb facs="5422062_2_0452.jpg" n="3"/>the man who as mayor will lead the upward movement.</p>
   <p>The Star's political attitude and its support of Fred A. Busse are not based upon partisanship but upon the sincere desire to see the proper man selected to administer the affairs of the city where you and I and our fellow-Chicagoans live and move and have our being.</p>
   <p>The hopes and the expectations of the people of our city were disappointed by the present administration, which has not made a single forward step. The present mayor is a good man and an honest man, but he has proved that he lacks the ability to lead the city upward. For instance, the municipal appropriation budget for the current fiscal year is $49,447,383, $14,000,000 more than the budget for the year preceding, and no appreciable amelioration has been effected in the condition of our municipal affairs. The transportation facilities of the city are in very bad shape. Business and commerce depend upon transportation for their growth and expansion. Chicago's transportation facilities are much less adequate to the needs of a growing metropolis than those of many smaller cities.</p>
   <p>The question of transportation is the most important problem to be solved, <pb facs="5422062_2_0453.jpg" n="4"/>and it may properly be called Chicago's Gordian Knot, which only the sword of Fred A. Busse can cut.</p>
   <p>There are other things which the present administration has side-tracked, and which can be solved and accomplished if Mr. Busse is elected. The city needs more policemen to guard life and property and to maintain peace and order; we need new street-cars; and the city streets are filthy. And since we have thousands upon thousands of Americans in the making among our citizens, the rights of these future Americans must be guarded and respected irrespective of nationality or creed.</p>
   <p>Fred A. Busse, the Republican candidate for the office of mayor of Chicago, is the man to be placed at the steering-wheel to accomplish the things needed and to direct our city on its proper course. His character, his sincerity, and his demonstrated ability as merchant, as congressman, and as treasurer of the city of Chicago are his qualifications to govern. His sterling record as postmaster is a credit to him and to us.</p>
   <p>The Star can proudly say in advance that Mr. Busse will be the next mayor <pb facs="5422062_2_0454.jpg" n="5"/>of Chicago, and with the utmost confidence it adds that the hopes and the expectations of the people will not be disappointed.</p>
   <p>Under such circumstances the Greek voters of Chicago will benefit our colony and our great city if they vote the straight Republican ticket for Fred A. Busse and his colleagues.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
