<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Are Men and Women of Equal Ability</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_2_1168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_2_1168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-03-01">Mar. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ARE MEN AND WOMEN OF EQUAL ABILITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Feminism--or in other words, the women--is vociferously demanding equal rights with the men. The women wish to vote and, if they wish, to run for public office. If one examines these statements, it will be discovered that they actually point out how much more a man can do than a woman. By their demands the women mean to say that just as a man invented the aeroplane, so might they bring some great idea or creation to light.</p>
   <p>This makes us think. Many women have studied law, medicine, education, etc., and yet, they have not surpassed the men in any of these fields. This brings to mind the words of a professor who said, "Nature has created women to sew, cook, and to raise children; yet man surpasses her even there." Perhaps this professor was a misogynist, and I remember that I disagreed with him. I believed that because of her more delicate <pb facs="5422062_2_1169.jpg" n="2"/>construction, a woman did everything with a more artistic and graceful feeling than a man.</p>
   <p>Will they succeed in realizing their ambitions? They try to do so, using every means at their disposal. They work untiringly, because they know that now is the only time such a thing can be accomplished. Last week a committee of women visited Venizelos in Paris, asking his support. He gave them advice which would help their cause more than anything else. He said, "Go and become educated, study the arts and sciences, get political training, and then you will succeed."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
