<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-20">June 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Sports-Loving Public</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-20">June 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR SPORTS-LOVING PUBLIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent league match of Slavia (Slavia Soccer Football Club), which is the only Bohemian club able to compete successfully in international competition, has thrown light upon the corrupt and partisan management of the league the name of which is the "Chicago Soccer Football Association". The league consists of sixteen teams divided into two equal sections, A and B. Each team of one section plays every other team of its own section twice, and the victors of the sections play each other for the gold cup known as the "Olsen Cup". The Chicago Swedish Athletics--that is, the Swedes--were victors in Section B. The greatest number of points in Section A were made by the Slavia and by the Western Electrics, each making twenty-four points. These two, then, had to play another game, the final one for their section, which Slavia, as a result of a bribe and the partisanship of the referee, lost. Shortly before this match the league adopted a ruling by which no member of one club may "sign" for another club in the same season [sic]. The Slavia, being aware of this ruling and disinclined to violate it, <pb facs="5418478_4_1223.jpg" n="2"/>played with a regularly registered team (otherwise it would lose two points which it needed), although the team was considerably weakened. The Western Electrics played with a team in which were three players, Dicky, Herries, and Cowell, who had signed for the Hibernians. This should have caused the Western Electrics to lose two points which should have been added to Slavia's score. This was well known to the league, but was not done. The Bohemians, therefore, filed a protest in which Slavia demanded satisfaction. The protest caused a great deal of excitement in the league, because it was aware of its guilt and because--just imagine!--the Chicago championship was to be competed for by Bohemians and Swedes! The meeting which was to deal with the protest was held June 10, and Slavia was represented in it by our then president, Mr. Sieben. He demanded that the protest be dealt with exactly according to the bylaws, in which demand he was supported by the representative of the Norsemen, Campbell Rovers, and most strongly and effectively by the president of the Swedish club Fram. After he had offered his opinion, which was entirely in our favor, the president of the league got up and made the statement that we, the Slavia, also had three unregistered players, <pb facs="5418478_4_1224.jpg" n="3"/>Svarc, Varys, and Hnetkovsky, which, of course, is a colossal lie. Ex-President Sieben, however, proved this to be a lie by pointing to the fact that the president of the league had sent out to all the clubs the list of players of all the teams, and the names of the three mentioned players were on our--Slavia's--list. This proof silenced the president, as well as the rest of our "friends". What else could they do? The representative of another team in the league proved that Slavia had been sentenced to lose the protest in advance by producing from his pocket a poster printed four days prior to the meeting and announcing the cup match between the Western Electrics and the Chicago Swedish Athletics. Thereupon the representative of the Lincoln Park Football Club moved that no consideration be given to the protest and matters remain as they are. The motion was adopted by nine against four votes, and thus the matter was disposed of. Ex-President Sieben announced that this crooked action of the league makes it necessary for Slavia to resign its membership in the league, and he was joined by the representatives of four other clubs. This will explain how we have been robbed of the honest fruits of our year's endeavor. All <pb facs="5418478_4_1225.jpg" n="4"/>that, only because we are--Bohemians!</p>
   <p>For the Sportovni Klub Slavia, (Slavia Sports Club)</p>
   <p>Ant. Kudrna, president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
