<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-09">May 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Public Exhibition of the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-09">May 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A PUBLIC EXHIBITION OF THE TELOCVICNA JEDNOTA SOKOL CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although most of the projects scheduled by our organizations to take place at the end of the season are facing financial loss, it is altogether different with the public exhibitions of our sokol units. Each of these exhibitions is witnessed by great throngs of people, and the enthusiasm shown at these pageants is great and worthy only of the sokol cause. The public exhibition of the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Chicago (Sokol Chicago Gymnastic Association) was held yesterday, and although we are accustomed to seeing great throngs of people at any activity of this unit, yesterday's crowd was a surprise even for us. The program was scheduled to start at 7 P.M., but as early as 6 P.M. the people were coming in, and at the stroke of seven the hall was so crowded that those who came later had difficulty getting in. The people in the gallery and in the space reserved for the audience on the main floor formed a solid mass of humanity. Yesterday's production was under the direction of Brother Jan Matejka, well-known sokol <pb facs="5418478_4_1098.jpg" n="2"/>instructor, and a great number of members of children and junior and senior classes participated.</p>
   <p>The program opened with an address by the president of the Sokol Chicago, Brother Joseph Placek, who spoke briefly concerning the work accomplished by the Sokol Chicago during the past year. An exhibition of precision calisthenics, apparatus, and games, under the direction of Brother Jan Matejka, then followed. Brother Jan Matejka is an able and conscientious instructor, and the unit may be well satisfied with him in every respect. As an instructor he has all the necessary qualifications, and he is capable of preparing and working out drills, especially for public productions. The proof of this was shown not only in the performance of children's classes but also in the exhibitions of the junior classes. No wonder that each of the classes was rewarded with roaring applause.</p>
   <p>But generally, just like at any other public sokol exhibition, the greatest of interest was concentrated upon the men and women classes. The sokolky (Women sokols), thirty-two in number, gave an exhibition of drills with long <pb facs="5418478_4_1099.jpg" n="3"/>bars, so-called bar bells.....The sokols, thirty-six in number, gave an exhibition of precision calisthenics prepared and worked out by the well-known sokol expert, Brother Jarka Kosar.....</p>
   <p>Our report would not be complete if we did not mention the numerous gifts which Brother Matejka received from his pupils.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
