<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-17">Aug. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Plan of the Proposed Sokol Athletic Field</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Drawing, two column-fifth of a page, showing location of field and dimensions]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0968</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0968.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-17">Aug. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">PLAN OF THE PROPOSED SOKOL ATHLETIC FIELD</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Drawing, two column-fifth of a page, showing location of field and dimensions]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A short time ago we published in this newspaper an article relating to a proposed sokol athletic field to be used during the summer. That this matter interests not only the members of the sokol organizations, but the general Bohemian public, is borne out by the fact that the net proceeds, accruing from the forthcoming Narodni Pout (National Pilgrimage)....which will be attended by all of our national societies, will go toward the purchase of a sokol athletic field which will serve the Zupa Stredni (Central District [of the American Sokol union]).</p>
   <p>During a recent meeting held by the Zupa, in which many members of the sokol unions were present, it was unanimously decided to retain the idea of securing a convenient place for summer drills. The sokoldom of the Chicago area is to <pb facs="5418478_4_0969.jpg" n="2"/>unite in its efforts to make this idea a reality. In this meeting also the standing committee to secure an athletic field was augmented by the appointment of brothers Placek, Cipra, Zahrobsky, and Purer. It is generally recognized that a large athletic field is absolutely necessary during the summer. The continuation of sokol activities in America depends upon the young.</p>
   <p>But economic conditions today do not permit the sokols to own and operate such modern and well equipped gymnasiums and athletic fields as are owned and operated by many American societies. No wonder that our young people go where they are better cared for; in brief, it is no wonder that they join American athletic clubs and associations. In this way our sokoldom loses annually not tens but hundreds of our boys and girls who could otherwise be saved for the sokol idea and through it for the Bohemian nation. For this reason alone it is necessary to work with all our strength to secure the ground for an athletic field to which could be gradually added other required features such as a field house, a park, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0970.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The land which we intend to purchase is located on Crawford Avenue between 18th and 19th Streets. It is 589 by 451 feet and extends from Crawford Avenue across Komensky Avenue to Karlov Avenue. It contains almost six and one-half acres. It is easily accessible by surface line cars as well as by elevated trains, and lies in the immediate center of our Bohemian neighborhoods: Bohemian California, Takor, and Cicero.</p>
   <p>Whoever is a friend of the Sokol idea will surely work to the end that the Chicago sokols own their own athletic field as early as possible. Our first dutiful act should be our attendance at the Narodni Pout, the net proceeds of which, as already stated, will be used as a nest egg for a fund with which to purchase the necessary real estate. Also it is expected that our sokols, both men and women, will take part in the parade in imposing numbers, and that they will work most zealously toward the realization of the [newly] proposed idea!</p>
   <p>Others, who are not sokols themselves, work unstintingly for this idea; how <pb facs="5418478_4_0971.jpg" n="4"/>much more active should the sokols be! "Nazdar" (To Success!)</p>
   <p>M. Brichta.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
