<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-20">Oct. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Soccer Game</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1151</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1151.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-20">Oct. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SOCCER GAME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Olympia, Czech soccer team of Chicago, played against the Swedes last Sunday. Our club was weakened by the absence of Braun, Prchal, Ton, Stejskal and Swarckopf, who are temporarily suspended. Their places were taken by Swartz, Vlk, Beck, and Stybr. The Swedish team was physically stronger. Yet the Olympia won by three goals to one, although the wind had favored their opponents.</p>
   <p>This victory may be ascribed not only to good technique, but also the exemplary harmony, co-operation, and honest endeavor on the part of the Olympia players. They were scheduled to play against Fraur next Sunday. The game cannot take place, however, since the health authorities have forbidden playing, in view of the spreading influenza epidemic.</p>
   <p>On last Sunday's pleasant afternoon, our Cechie played its first game against Victoria on its own playground. There were no goals scored, and the game ended in a tie. The Cechie team was weaker, but held its own against the <pb facs="5418478_4_1152.jpg" n="2"/>guest team very nicely, and was even its superior.</p>
   <p>The same old drawback showed again among our players, i.e., hesitation and lack of determination in front of the goal. This fault will have to be rectified, as it is the main reason for games being lost.</p>
   <p>The Rangers should be taken as an example of how to take advantage of weak moments. They use every free moment for practice, which our players fail to do.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
