<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-30">May 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Masaryk in the Press Club Representatives of American Journalism Extend to Him a Heartfelt Welcome</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0533</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0533.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-30">May 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MASARYK IN THE PRESS CLUB Representatives of American Journalism Extend to Him a Heartfelt Welcome</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We reported yesterday on the gigantic manifestation by which the Czech settlement greeted our beloved and intrepid leader in the Czechoslovak movement beyond the borders of our motherland. He is commander in chief of the Czechoslovak Army, which is winning sympathies for the Czechoslovak people among the Allies and, most important, among the Americans. Upon these sympathies will be founded the independence of the Czechoslovak people, for they have shown, and will show, that they are worthy of liberty and independence.</p>
   <p>The Allied and the American press is of great value to our cause, but Czechoslovaks must do their part. They must make extreme sacrifices; not merely considering them to be sacrifices as such, but dictated by a sense of duty.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0534.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our political action outside the borders of the motherland is of vital importance to the cause of liberating the old homeland. The Czechoslovak Army's actions are, however, of the greatest value. This Army is our very blood, and this Czechoslovak blood has to win what our people justly demand: freedom, liberty, and independence.</p>
   <p>Masaryk has arrived here to bring this work, done by us, to the highest point of efficiency. He has organized our Czechoslovak Army from the ranks of young Czech soldiers, who preferred being taken prisoner by the Allies, to fighting under the Austro-Hungarian flag.</p>
   <p>Masaryk can accomplish invaluable work for us among influential American circles. He will do this through the medium of the American press, which, finally, has opened its columns to our cause. He will work for us in Washington by appearing before the Congress, and by contact with President Wilson. The favorable results <pb facs="5418478_4_0535.jpg" n="3"/>of all this activity cannot be measured at present.</p>
   <p>Masaryk's presence in the United States should be an incentive for further work on our part. The center of gravity in Masaryk's work lies in high, influential circles of America.</p>
   <p>It was last night that our aged leader performed a highly significant service for our cause by appearing in the Chicago Press Club which represents the foremost local American publications in the English and other languages.</p>
   <p>This visit had been arranged by Congressman Adolph J. Sabath and Mr. J. F. Stepina, treasurer of the Club. Not only all the members were invited, but also numerous prominent Czechs.</p>
   <p>A dinner preceded the lecture. Mr. Frank Commerford, presiding, introduced Professor Thomas G. Masaryk as the undaunted protagonist of truth and practical <pb facs="5418478_4_0536.jpg" n="4"/>idealism, new patriotism, and as the champion of a great, beautiful, and pure democratism. He pointed to Masaryk's determination, courage, and the scrupulousness with which he, a member of the Austrian parliament, went into the fight against Austria.</p>
   <p>Professor Masaryk spoke of our aims in this war, which are the crushing of Prussian militarism and the dismembering of Austria-Hungary. He stressed the urgent necessity of Allied help in the East, where quite a number of small nations stand alone with Russia. They must be saved unless the West also become lost. This he demonstrated with the aid of a map of Europe, warning his audience of the consequences of Germany's gaining control of those nineteen small nations. The speaker also gave an outline of the geographical and political position of Czechoslovak lands.</p>
   <p>While dwelling upon the activities of the Czechoslovak Army, now fighting against the Germans and Austrians, he appealed for help for the Czechoslovak <pb facs="5418478_4_0537.jpg" n="5"/>nation now struggling to liberate itself from German-Austrian domination. These words were directed to America, because by helping in the destruction of Prussian militarism and German-Austrian aims to expand, America itself will benefit.</p>
   <p>Masaryk's lecture received closest attention and acclaim from the journalists, who hastened, at the close, to get acquainted with their guest. The lecture surely will not fail to bring our aims nearer to the American public, who will then understand our Czechoslovak problem, which is gaining international recognition. [Translator's note: List of prominent men present is omitted in translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
