<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1881-10-08">Oct. 8, 1881</date><title level="a">Svornost Begins Volume Seven</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1881-10-08">Oct. 8, 1881</date><title level="a">SVORNOST BEGINS VOLUME SEVEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Six years have gone by since Svornost modestly began it's pilgrimage among countrymen in Chicago and throughout America. There have been found in its path, many times apparently unsurmountable obstacles, but these were overcome patiently often through great and painful want.</p>
   <p>Every reader knows, that it is constantly advancing and serving honorably, sincerely, and as quickly as possible, day by day, bringing all the news, which often, even the larger German papers, are unable to give, conscientiously and faithfully endeavors to fulfill all requirements which can be expected of it.</p>
   <p>The need for this Bohemian Daily for Chicago has been proven beyond a doubt. Especially during this past year, every reader valued the daily paper, when the entire nation, and our countrymen, were impatiently waiting and anxious about the wounded and dying President and wanted to know every day how the national martyr was progressing. How can one wait, especially in a City, until the weekly papers bring news that is from eight to ten days old; before they arrive the main daily happening is forgotten and ten new items are <pb facs="5418478_4_0258.jpg" n="2"/>interesting the public and it is necessary to bring this information to those who may not be able to read the English papers; if they are able to read the German papers, they have been forced to discontinue it for these have so often proven themselves unfriendly toward Bohemians. The latter would be humiliated to have to read that some new blame has been cast undeservedly upon them.</p>
   <p>In Bohemian business circles of Chicago Svornost serves effectively and proves to be a necessary medium of contact.</p>
   <p>With the same energy, loyalty, and conscientiousness of service to the Bohemian nationals in America and of Chicago especially, for all interests of Bohemians and their needs, Svornost will continue to endeavor to be deserving of favor and confidence of all in ever growing volume, so that it may be said that it serves all that is useful for the majority of Bohemians, and advantageous for their material and spiritual happiness.</p>
   <p>Success to Volume Seven.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
