<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-25">Mar. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">An Important National Enterprise</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-25">Mar. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AN IMPORTANT NATIONAL ENTERPRISE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One hundred years have passed since Josef Dobrovsky wrote his monumental work, a grammar of the Czech language in German, under the name Lehrgebaude Der Bohmishen Sprache. The book represents a foundation upon which the Bohemian language was further developed until a dream had come true: the re-birth of the Czech nation. Dobrovsky used good judgment in couching the work in the German language in order to reach the more educated classes of the Czech people, who had a good command of that tongue and less of the Czech language, because of the scarcity of intermediate schools and the lack of higher schools. The Czech Literary Association, which has taken upon itself the burden of supplying books and accessories to Czech classes in American high schools and universities, and also the propagation of the Czech language in such schools, is planning a great undertaking even if within a limited frame. They intend to translate into English the book by Dobrovsky, making it an extensive grammar of the Czech language destined to be a comprehensive textbook for American students. The <pb facs="5418478_4_0058.jpg" n="2"/>book will fill a long felt need in high schools and universities. It is, in fact, to be regretted that we have arrived at the thought rather late, for all the books printed in our old homeland cannot take the place of the book in English, as they are used by purely Czech pupils; the educational trend in an American book must consequently point in a different direction. Many of our adolescents have only a scant knowledge of the Czech language and they cannot be initiated into its beauties and charms simply because of the lack of a book adapted to our conditions. This reasoning appears still more valid in cases of children who hear very little of the Czech language at home, and in cases of those who have acquired only an insufficient preparatory knowledge in private schools. The book will be welcomed by pupils of other nationalities, who are ambitious to acquaint themselves with the Bohemian language.</p>
   <p>We complain about the lack of attention to our literature on the part of the American public, but where can the educated American acquire a knowledge of <pb facs="5418478_4_0059.jpg" n="3"/>our language when there are no books?</p>
   <p>The Bohemian Literary Association has indeed begun a work of still greater import since it has already published two handbooks. The outlay for the book will amount to about $1,000; the nucleus of the amount is the generous gift of the Bohemian National Cemetery. It is incumbent upon the Czech-American public to further the work by generous support.</p>
   <p>J. V. Nigrin,</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
