<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-27">Nov. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Unification of Sokol Bodies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-27">Nov. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">UNIFICATION OF SOKOL BODIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago delegates to the conference which is being held in Cleveland, [Ohio] today, and at which the unification of Bohemian-American Sokol bodies will probably be decided, left Chicago last night. The Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union) delegated Brother Jan Siman, and the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Sokol District Fuegner'-Tyrs) sent Brothers Bohus Hak and Josef Dittert. They went to Cleveland in compliance with a decision reached at the Baltimore congress of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska. That congress decided that a special conference, of representatives of Bohemian-American sokol bodies be called to Cleveland, for the purpose of working out a plan according to which the final unification of all Bohemian sokol bodies in America could be accomplished. This decision is being carried out today, and the conference is being held in the hall of Sokol Cech in Cleveland.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1291.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Each Sokolska Jednota (Sokol Union) is to have three representatives at this conference. The Narodni Jednota Sokolska is represented by Brother K. E. Hrbek of New York, the delegate from Chicago, Brother Jan Siman of Chicago and Brother Franta Filip of Cedar Rapids[Iowa]. The Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs is represented by the two brothers from Chicago and by Ptak of Cleveland. The Delnicky Americky Sokol (Sokol of American Workingmen) will be represented by Brothers V. B. Tuma of New York, J. Wagner and J. Lefner, both of Winfield, Long Island. The deliberations of the conference start this afternoon.</p>
   <p>In the best interests of the sokol movement it is desired that this conference finally bring to a satisfactory conclusion the question of the unification of all the progressive sokol movement in Bohemian America. How it is to be done is, and must remain, irrelevant; that is just a matter of form. The spirit of the agreement will tell, and from the spirit we expect a rejuvenation, a regeneration of all sokol efforts and <pb facs="5418478_4_1292.jpg" n="3"/>endeavors. Hoping that today's conference will succeed in the undertaking, we greet it with the sincere call of all sokols: Na Zdar (To Success)!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
