<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-05">Mar. 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Report of the Ceska Svobodomyslna Skola T. G. Masaryk V Cicero, Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0426</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0426.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-05">Mar. 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE CESKA SVOBODOMYSLNA SKOLA T. G. MASARYK V CICERO, ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This year marks the tenth anniversary of the Ceska Svobodomyslna Skola T. G. Masaryk (T. G. Masaryk Bohemian Free Thought School). The year 1921 was particularly characteristic of the great industry and work of the organization, for it was during that year that our Bohemian school, which bears the name of our greatest national character, the scientist, professor, and president of the Republic of Czechoslovakia, T. G. Masaryk, came into being. The zeal and indefatigable work of our societies and unions bore good fruit within a comparatively short time. The management of the school was represented by thirty societies and forty representatives; meetings took place twice a month, that is every second Monday there was a meeting of the building committee, and every last Monday of the month a meeting of the board of directors. The president for 1921 was Mr. Jan Sebek; secretary, Mr. Stanislav Schneider; financial secretary, Mr. Pole; Mr. Josef Budil was treasurer.</p>
   <p>The building of our Bohemian school proceeded at a brisk rate so that on <pb facs="5418478_4_0427.jpg" n="2"/>May 8, 1921 the cornerstone ceremony could take place. Many of our Bohemian societies, corporations, and unions, as well as outstanding persons [in our colony] took part in that ceremony. It was and unforgetable moment of which we may be justly proud; it will forever remain recorded in the annals of the Bohemian settlement of Cicero. The building was undertaken by the building contractor, Mr. Julius Kinst, after the plans which were worked out by Mr. K. Teplan. The latter gentleman gave his services gratuitously.</p>
   <p>The building was finished in August, and on September 4, 1921 it was festively declared open for its exalted use; there were a great many guests here from the Republic of Czechoslovakia on that occasion. No sooner were the doors of this Bohemian institution opened than our children themselves proved that only through industry may its progress be assured. On October 23, the children gave a theatrical performance under the guidance of their teacher, Mr. R. Kohlicek. This netted $200. Later, at the behest of the Mir Cechie (Peace of Bohemia) Lodge No. 71, of the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Benevolent Sisterhood), a meeting was called in which it was decided to invite all of <pb facs="5418478_4_0428.jpg" n="3"/>the societies of Cicero and to organize a bazaar for the benefit of the school. This plan succeeded, and with the assistance of all the organizations and societies of Cicero, a bazaar was held during the month of November, the net proceeds of which were $3,500. This shows how well our activities in the interest of our Bohemian school developed. Besides that the Delnicka Dramaticka Jednota (Bohemian Workingmen's Dramatic Association) gave a play.....which netted $87.70.</p>
   <p>If one should wish to mention every single feature in the development of our institution, such a task would present a significant effort in the history of our Cicero Bohemians. The school enjoys a good reputation among our Bohemian societies of Cicero and Chicago that use the assembly hall for their meetings and deliberations, and at the same time contributing generously to its upkeep, preserving it for our future generations, and clearing it of any debts that still encumber the school.</p>
   <p>Much may be done in this if we shall always remember our slogan: "Vse Pro <pb facs="5418478_4_0429.jpg" n="4"/>Ceskou Skolu" (all for the Bohemian school). This was ever our dream, for it we worked in a united effort; may the results of it, therefore, continue to flourish, and may the school itself serve as the best taskmaster for our children whose happiness will thus receive its foundation. The past year was a successful one, and though we regard the future with equanimity we also hope that our Bohemian-American branch will steadfastly grow and insure the success of its nation.</p>
   <p>While relinquishing my present duties of a secretary, I wish to thank all the representatives for their confidence in me. I send my good wishes to all, hoping that the current year will bring renewed successes toward which I shall continue to work.</p>
   <p>Stanislav Schneider, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
