<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-02-08">February 8, 1892</date><title level="a">Gymnastic Exhibition at World's Fair Bohemian-American Sokols (Gymnasts) Prepare for Dignified Appearance.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-02-08">February 8, 1892</date><title level="a">GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION AT WORLD'S FAIR Bohemian-American Sokols (Gymnasts) Prepare For Dignified Appearance.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held last Saturday by the Gymnastic Teachers Club of the Public Schools in which was discussed the feasibility of holding a great international gymnastic celebration in Chicago during the period of the World's Fair. German gymnasts have already taken preliminary steps in this direction and have worked up a partial program, according to which, the celebration is to be of such colossal proportions as have never before been seen here. The main purpose of this gymnastic exposition is to show Americans the results of systematic gymnastics, such as are cultivated by the German Turners, the Bohemian Sokols and gymnastic clubs of other nationalities, and thereby convert Americans to this system.</p>
   <p>In answer to the question of a member of the club, J. Cermak, in regard to the participation of other nationalities, that is, whether they are to have the opportunity to appear as independent units at the exhibition the committee replied that each nationality will have its own day. The German Turners would <pb facs="5418478_4_1373.jpg" n="2"/>have a day set aside for them, at which time they could show their physical culture exercises, marches, apparatus work and other specialties. Another day would be set apart for Bohemians to do likewise.</p>
   <p>According to the preliminary program the Exposition Directors are to be requested to allow the use of space 200 X 400 feet which would be prepared as a gymnastic field.</p>
   <p>It would be quite proper for our Sokol clubs to take an active part with the German Turners in these preliminary arrangements, in order to be assured of consideration for a special day at the exhibition. Our clubs must not pass this opportunity for if they do not attend these meetings now, they may find it impossible later to have a special day set aside for them.</p>
   <p>We feel certain that participation of Bohemian Sokols will be quite dignified and that the celebration will be attended not only by all Chicago Sokols, but by Sokols of the entire country.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1374.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It now remains for the Sokols to train actively, to energetically cultivate physical culture, so that they can prove to the public that they are not behind other nationalities, but that they actually lead them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
