<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-29">Aug. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation to Bohemian Parents</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-29">Aug. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION TO BOHEMIAN PARENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools) has received, by the good offices of Mr. Joseph A. Holpuch, the permission to use school rooms for the teaching of the Bohemian language in the following schools:</p>
   <p>In the Bohemian Pilsen district: The Jungman School at Loeffler Court and 18th Street; Throop School on Throop Street between 18th and 19th Streets; Cooper School on 19th Street near Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>In Bohemian California: Gary School on Lawndale Avenue and 30th Street.</p>
   <p>In Merigold: Bryant School on Kedzie Avenue and 14th Street.</p>
   <p>In Town of Lake: Hedges School on Winchester Avenue and 48th Street.</p>
   <p>In South Chicago: Fenger High School on Stewart Avenue and 114th Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0580.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The instruction in the Bohemian language will take place in the beautiful, and clean rooms, equipped with everything required by modern pedagogic science. It will be a pleasure both to teach and to be taught there. Classes will be from 4 to 6 P.M. The dues will be twenty-five cents a month per pupil.</p>
   <p>We do not doubt that parents will appreciate this advantage as well as the advantage of knowing the Bohemian language; and will see to it that their children enroll in these Bohemian classes. But it should not be considered that learning the Bohemian language is for practical purposes only. It is also a cultural and patriotic requirement. Let's educate our children in the spirit of our great forefathers; let's educate them so that they will be worthy of our glorious past; that they will become the hope of our future; that they will become ready to take our places in our associations and become acquainted with everything good and beautiful that our nation has created, and that they may become better Americans.</p>
   <p>Registration for classes will take place September 7 and 8.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0581.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Registration for the Saturday and Sunday classes will be September 18 and 19.</p>
   <p>There will be no Sunday afternoon classes this year.</p>
   <p>For the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodo-Myslnych Skol,</p>
   <p>Mrs. Emilie Hrisny, Mrs. Antonie Kubica,</p>
   <p>Dr. Anton Mueller, Karel Beranek, Bohumil Kral.</p>
   <p>P.S. Pupils of Bohemian schools who will take the Bohemian courses announced in this proclamation will receive credit for them in their schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
