<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-24">Aug. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Meeting of the United Czech Liberal Schools of Chicago Held on Sunday, August 20, 1911</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-24">Aug. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE MEETING OF THE UNITED CZECH LIBERAL SCHOOLS OF CHICAGO HELD ON SUNDAY, AUGUST 20, 1911</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the meeting was called to order by the president Mr. K. Kopecky and the minutes of the previous meeting were read and approved, a communication from the gymnastic society "Cechie" was read, in which the society applied for membership and chose as its delegate Mr. F. Metz. This gentleman, however, represents another body; therefore, he was notified to resign as delegate from one of the organizations because in accordance with the by-laws, a delegate can not represent two organizations at one time. An application for membership was received from "Vlasta" lodge No. 122 and this body chose as their representative Mrs. Marie Husak.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0671.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Patronage of the Czesko-Americky Svobodomyslny Skoly (Bohemian-American Liberal [Freethought]School), on Eighteenth Street, elected Mr. Joseph Budil as its delegate. The Patronage of the school in Hanson Park and the Patronage of the "Jan Neruda" School requested the members to attend their picnics. The officers of the United Schools will attend as numerously as possible.</p>
   <p>The Patronage of the "Karel Havlicek" School recommended Miss Zdenka Koler as its teacher for the coming year. The matter was taken under consideration and because she has been teaching satisfactorily for a number of years, the request of that Patronage was granted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0672.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mrs. Kubalek tendered her resignation from her teaching position and the sub-committee will provide a new teacher to fill the position.</p>
   <p>Committee Reports: It was left to the Picnic Committee and Mrs. Hrych to make arrangements for the use of the Pilsen Park on some Saturday before the end of the school term.</p>
   <p>The School Committee reported that before the school year begins it will be necessary to secure a large number of second readers. The purchase of these books was approved. The committee nominated Mrs. Weiner as teacher at the Bunker Street School. Two remaining positions were advertised and applications received from nine persons. The best qualified of these were Mr. J. Rezabek, <pb facs="5418478_4_0673.jpg" n="4"/>a former student at Prague University, who was nominated to teach on Saturday and Sunday in the Town of Lake School; the other was Mr. Bretislav Jonas, who studied at the Czech Technical School in Prague; he was selected to teach on Sunday mornings in the Irving Park School and Sunday afternoons at the Frant. Palacky School. Following this, the committee's report in regard to changes in the constitution was read, but because of insufficient time remaining and in order to consider the proposal thoroughly, the matter was postponed to a future day. A special meeting will be called for that purpose.</p>
   <p>A member of the Auditing Committee reported that it was impossible to examine <pb facs="5418478_4_0674.jpg" n="5"/>the manager's books, because one member of the committee is sick and another has left the state permanently. Mr. Hofrieter was appointed to take the place of the latter member.</p>
   <p>For the good of the organization, the question of greater agitation in favor of the periodical Svobodna Skola (Free School) so that it might be more widely read in all circles of our people was discussed. To further the purpose it was proposed that a letter be sent to all liberal-minded [freethought] organizations urging them to order at least one subscription for each of their organizations and in that way arouse interest in reading in our social circles. In addition, each delegate will receive at the November meeting several copies for free distribution.</p>
   <p>Because the needs of our liberal schools and their management continue to <pb facs="5418478_4_0675.jpg" n="6"/>increase, it is necessary to obtain the means for their upkeep, for that reason at the next meeting there will be a discussion about arranging some kind of celebration for the benefit of that purpose. If we are able to become inspired for Czech schools in the old country, where they are so indifferently dealt with by the unfriendly Austrian government, it does not mean that we should forget entirely the conditions, in which we live from day to day and which should not be unfamiliar to us.</p>
   <p>How much good could be accomplished for our children if our Czech Liberal Societies, in addition to the insignificant contribution, remembered at least once a year during the arrangement of some entertainment that there are hundreds and hundreds of Czech parents here who would be glad if their children could be <pb facs="5418478_4_0676.jpg" n="7"/>educated in their mother tongue, in addition to English. Under existing conditions it is not strange that foreigners often know more about us than our own children.</p>
   <p>How much interest is being shown on all sides for Czech schools is best proven by the enrollment in the most recently opened school in Crawford, where more than one hundred children applied. There could be many more such schools among us if financial means permitted. The officers of our societies should remember that if they wish to maintain Czech societies for any length of time, it is necessary that love for parents and all things Czech, that is, toward Czech societies also, must be cultivated from earliest childhood and the best means of doing this are the Czech schools, because the parents themselves, as a result of the fierce struggle for existence, cannot give the children the proper attention.</p>
   <p>Bohuslav Linka,</p>
   <p>Correspondent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
