<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-16">Mar. 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Soccer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-16">Mar. 16, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SOCCER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those of our countrymen who follow sport events will surely remember the time when the Sparta Athletic Club played before the public for the first time. During the second month of its existence, it had already played against several Czech clubs and scored very nicely right from the start. After the dissolution of the Conroy Coats Club,Sparta took its place in the fourth division. This qualified it to play against clubs of other nationalities, against whom it also achieved good results.</p>
   <p>After the end of that season, the clubs were classified in various divisions. Sparta was placed in the fourth division, to which it now belongs. In the last half of this season, Sparta played in seven contests, two of which it won, two were a draw, and three were lost. Sparta was given six points. The club is well prepared for the coming season, and we hope that it will continue in its defense of Czech colors.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1169.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The membership of the club has increased considerably, so that large quantities of sweaters had to be ordered. This will enable the club to put up a second team. The sweaters will bear our national colors and will be an unusual style.</p>
   <p>The Sparta playground for this season will be at Harrison Park, 19th and Wood Streets, where their club rooms are located.</p>
   <p>The club plays against Victoria I next Sunday. This will be Sparta's first league game. Victoria I is in very good condition, for only a few of its members have joined the Army--they are Germans--while other clubs have lost on the average of about one third of their regular players. The contest will mean a hard task for Sparta, which, however, expects a satisfactory result.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
