<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-14">May 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Prepartions in Progress for the Festive Unveiling of the Karel Havlicek Borousky Monument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-14">May 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARTIONS IN PROGRESS FOR THE FESTIVE UNVEILING OF THE KAREL HAVLICEK BOROUSKY MONUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten weeks still remain until the unveiling of the Karel Havlicek Borousky monument in Douglas Park. However, that is, in no way, too long a time in which to make all preparations for such a grand and great celebration as this will be. There is no doubt that this will probably be the greatest Bohemian national celebration that was ever held in America.</p>
   <p>Taking part will be, not only the Bohemians of Chicago, but surely all other Czech towns and communities throughout the United States. Therefore, it is necessary for the committee to contact all Bohemian communities, which will send delegations and representatives of <pb facs="5418478_4_1561.jpg" n="2"/>lodges and private excursions here, because preparations must be made to house the crowds of guests expected. It will be necessary to arrange with railroads for reduced fares from all parts of the country. It also will be necessary to create excursion committees throughout the country, and this cannot be accomplished in a week or two. For that purpose alone, the entire period of time which remains will be needed. In order that the success of the celebration be assured of being accomplished, it is necessary that the work of arrangements be started at once.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
