<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-26">Mar. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-26">Mar. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE SDRUZENI CESKYCH SVOBODOMYSLNYCH SKOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following is a copy of the minutes of the regular meeting of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools), held March 18, 1922:</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by the president, Mr. J. Tichava, in the presence of all officers and many delegates. The minutes of the previous meeting were read and approved, and the minutes of the subcommittee meeting were likewise approved. This was followed by the reading of correspondence.</p>
   <p>A letter was received from Mr. Vlach who reported on the textbooks for our schools and enclosed a check for $520 for books sold. Mr. Vlach also writes that it will be necessary to order diplomas, monthly report blanks for teachers, and more textbooks. The committee on economy, after conferring with the faculty, ordered these supplies. Mr. Vlach also enclosed a bond with a face value of $1,000. [Translator's note: It seems that the officer in question, because <pb facs="5418478_4_0419.jpg" n="2"/>of his frequent money transactions, had to furnish a bond.] His bond was accepted.</p>
   <p>A letter was received from Mr. Safranek in which he wished to be excused from attending the present meeting. He recommended that a bindery bill of $24.05 be paid. Payment was approved....It was also decided to increase the insurance of textbooks from $1,000 to $2,000. The fourth quaterly report was also approved in this meeting, and it was agreed that the annual report, as submitted by Mrs. Cepelak, be ordered printed. The president, Mr. J. Tichava expressed his thanks to Mrs. Cepelak who resigned as financial secretary, and to Mrs. K. Stary, who resigned as chairwoman of a subcommittee. The president requested these ladies to continue their good work for the Free Thought schools.</p>
   <p>At this time the newly elected financial secretary, Mrs. Dobias, was admonished by the president to direct her efforts to a greater development of the <pb facs="5418478_4_0420.jpg" n="3"/>Bohemian Free Thought schools. Mrs. Radesinsky gave a report on school attendance as follows: The day schools are attended by 992 pupils; the Saturday and Sunday classes have an attendance of 1,083; The Sunday socials are attended by 222; the adolescent clubs have 209 members. There are thirteen day classes, and ten Saturday and Sunday classes. There are eight classes that meet only on Saturdays, and six that meet only on Sundays. There were twenty-one teachers employed throughout the year. Mrs. Dobias, reporting as a committeewoman on curriculum, stated that thus far she was unable to examine the curricula in all of the schools [of the Federation], but that those which were examined by her were found to be conducted in good order. The delegate, Mr. Jelinek, moved that both reports be published in the periodical Vek Rozumu (Age of Reason). The motion carried. Mr. K. Stary was elected as a member of the economy committee in place of Mr. Hudecek who is unable to assume that duty.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hudecek reported on the Narodni Dan Svobomyslnych (National tax of Bohemian Freethinkers); the auditing committee found his report to be correct <pb facs="5418478_4_0421.jpg" n="4"/>in every detail, and the schools received $913 as an apportionment from that source. A letter of thanks was sent to the Svaz Svobodomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers).</p>
   <p>The proclamation by the committee on resolutions, asking Bohemians to send their children to classes in which the Bohemian language is taught at the Carter H. Harrison High School, was approved and ordered published in the local newspapers. [Translator's note: See the issue of March 23, 1922 of the Denni Hlasatel]. Another motion, entertained at this time, was that the committee on resolutions work on a proclamation against the introduction of Bible study in the public schools. This motion was carried also. The delegate from Berwyn, Illinois reported on the dramatic work of the school.....</p>
   <p>The president, Mr. J. Tichava, asked that the periodical Svobodna Skola (Free School) be better progagandized so that its circulation might increase, and the names and addresses of our free thought schools made known. It was <pb facs="5418478_4_0422.jpg" n="5"/>also argued that the printing should be less expensive. Mr. Jirak, who is business manager of the free school system, will make a report on this question in the next meeting. It was also decided that a musical and entertainment be arranged for the pupils of the Carter H. Harrison High School. After a report of income and expense was heard the meeting adjourned.</p>
   <p>Mr. Josef Tichava, president</p>
   <p>Mr. Karel Soukup, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
