<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-28">July 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Havlicek Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Entire Bohemian Group in Chicago Will Participate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-28">July 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE HAVLICEK CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Entire Bohemian Group in Chicago Will Participate</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never perhaps in the history of Bohemian Chicago was such interest shown about anything. Never was such expectation prevalent as we are now witnessing and experiencing in view of the Havlicek festivities which will take place next Saturday and Sunday. The name of Havlicek is on everyone's lips these days. There is no one among us who does not know the significance and merits of Havlicek, who does not admit that such a man is deserving of having his memory preserved forever in the hearts of a grateful posterity, and who would not endeavor to contribute as much as possible to honoring his memory.</p>
   <p>The Havlicek Monument in Douglas Park will be unveiled next Sunday. We do not want to write at length about the history of the Monument..... Here we wish only to introduce the kind of program that has been arranged by the <pb facs="5418478_4_1541.jpg" n="2"/>arrangements committee for the days of the celebration. A mass meeting of Havlicek worshippers will be held Saturday in Pilsen Park on Twenty-sixth Street at Albany Avenue. Care will be taken to provide plenty of refined entertainment and arouse a real festive mood. Mr. A. Konopasek's band will play, and a gymnastic exhibition will be held. Both Sokol Camps will work here harmoniously side by side, so as to show that the spirit of Havlicek has best been grasped by the Sokols, that in their ranks he has the largest number of most enthusiastic followers, that his principles and ideas constitute the Sokols' most precious possession. Girls from the National Sokol Unity will perform exercises with tennis rackets; girls representing all Chicago units will take part in the first exercises, while the second set of exercises will be performed by girls of Sokol Tabor. We can assure the public that these exercises will provide a beautiful as well as enjoyable treat for the spectators, so that no one who can possibly manage to do so should fail to come. It was this set of exercises which aroused the greatest enthusiasm at the last Group Congress in Cedar Rapids, Iowa.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1542.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Fuegner-Tyrs Group will appear before the public on this occasion in a most dignified manner. This group will send its pupils, women and men sokols, to demonstrate how remarkably they drill and how they endeavor so that their activities may be an honor not only to their own societies, their own groups, but an embellishment to the Havlicek celebration.</p>
   <p>The evening program will consist of musical numbers interspersed by speeches of countrymen prominent in public life. Speakers thus far announced are: Mr. Jar. R. Psenka, Dr. J. E. Salaba Vojan, Mr. Jos. Jurka, Mr. J. Tvrzicky-Kramer. It is certain that Bohemian-American country life will be represented by its best sons, who will also speak in honor of Havlicek. Mr. St. E. Vraz, our famous traveler, will transport the spectators to our native homeland. He will show interesting lantern slides picturing memorable places, primarily those which have a bearing on Havlicek.</p>
   <p>On Sunday, the societies taking part in the parade will take their places at <pb facs="5418478_4_1543.jpg" n="4"/>the pre-arranged time and place in order that the parade may start at the time set. The parade will leave from Pilsen Sokol hall, and after several turns through different streets will end in the Pilsen Park on Twenty-sixth Street.</p>
   <p>The celebration at the monument will start at 2:30 o'clock in the afternoon. The program, as is customary upon such occasions, will consist of music and speeches. Mr. Brousek's band will provide the music. The speaker of the occasion, in English, will be Professor Jar. Zmrhal, in Bohemian, Jaroslav Kosar; the unveiling of the monument will be performed by the chairman of the Monument Committee Mr. Vojt. Sedlacek; the chairman of the Park Board, Mr. W. Kolacek will present the monument to the Governor of the State of Illinois; Governor Deneen will accept the monument in a suitable speech, after which Mayor Harrison of Chicago will address those present. The Ustredni Jednota Pevecka (Central United Singing Societies) will sing Smetana's "Veno", which will surely be one of the finest numbers <pb facs="5418478_4_1544.jpg" n="5"/>of the program. All our countrymen will be greatly affected by greetings from Bohemia delivered by a representative of the Bohemian National Council, Mr. St. E. Vraz.</p>
   <p>A concert will be given in the evening in Pilsen Park. The celebration will be ended thereby, but its beneficent effects upon our entire national life will begin to appear. These we anticipate as eagerly as the celebration itself, yes, even more.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
