<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-22">Apr. 22, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-22">Apr. 22, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">SDRUZENI CESKYCH SVOBODOMYSLNYCH SKOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools) held a monthly meeting yesterday in the Klacel Lodge in which a large number of delegates gathered. The meeting, presided over by Mr. Kopecky, had on its program the reading of committee reports, which showed that the day schools, as well as Saturday and Sunday schools, are making gratifying progress and the number of their pupils shows a steady increase. Only the school in the Grand Crossing district had to be closed temporarily because no classroom is available at this time. But this difficulty will be soon overcome and a permanent home will be secured. Also the Crawford district reported that an adequate school building will soon be erected there. Following the recommendation of the guidance committee, an exhibition of the work of free thought school pupils will be arranged next fall in order to acquaint the general public with the progress of our schools. This will be the first exhibition of its kind, and our friends will have an opportunity to learn both our aims and our success in achieving them. The Grand Lodge of the Taborites has signified its full agreement with the activities of the Sdruzeni and has <pb facs="5418478_4_0629.jpg" n="2"/>promised its wholehearted support in the future. The rest of the meeting was devoted to current business, but the meeting did not adjourn until late at night because of distasteful debates which should never take place in the Sdruzeni and which certainly do not serve any useful purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
