<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-09">Feb. 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A Monument for Havlicek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-09">Feb. 9, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">A MONUMENT FOR HAVLICEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fellow country-men, compatriots! In the month of October will occur a significan celebration, full of patriotic meaning for all Bohemian-Americans, namely, the unveiling of the monument of Karel Havlicek Borovsky. The statue has been completed in Prague and is ready to be shipped to Chicago. The committee is about to contract for the accessories required and for the work involved according to the plans formulated by the architects of the park board; but alas, a great amount of the money necessary is still lacking, and so we address the Bohemian public, hoping that this will be the last time that we shall be compelled to do so.</p>
   <p>We are asking urgently for help so that we may finish a work highly important for us Bohemians! "The world is impelled by active forces, "says one <pb facs="5418478_4_1573.jpg" n="2"/>of our proverbs. Well, let us exert our strength, and the future will bring the results of honest work. Even a small nation, transplanted to foreign soil, can produce worthy fruit; if it possesses self-esteem and love for its sacred traditions and its rights, it can stand proudly side by side with other nations. We can prove that we are not merely scattered immigrants,--that Bohemians are not failen leaves but healthy, fresh off-shoots of the old stock,--that we are a nation, not only in Europe but in America as well.</p>
   <p>In looking over the list of collections for the monument of our martyred statesman, we get the impression that the greatest enthusiasm for this patriotic enterprise is registered in the American rural districts. Bohemian Chicago, that Bohemian metropolis where a third of all the Bohemian societies in this country are located, remains cool toward Havlicek! We find, true enough, several enthusiastic manifestations of enthusiasm, such as Sokol Slavsky with a hundred-dollar donation and some contributions of fifty dollars; but these few seem <pb facs="5418478_4_1574.jpg" n="3"/>to have no emulators.</p>
   <p>However, it is not yet too late. Bohemian Chicago will do its duty. In Bohemian they are completing a collection of three millions for the Central School Fund (Matice Skolska), but we in Chicago are having difficulty in collecting the $3,000 still required for the accomplishment of an aim of paramount national importance! Shall we give up like cowards? We may well complain that our system of Bohemian schools is in a pitiful condition; but of we show no interest in the monument, we demonstrate that our indifference to school problem as well; we show that we are merely a cultural fertilizer, absorbed in the mass of foreign elements!</p>
   <p>We therefore appeal to the intelligent strata of the Bohemian populace, which are always the public spokesmen of our Bohemian sentiments; we appeal to the Bohemian corporations and enterprises for donations, be they ever so small,--to Bohemian businessmen, professional men, and tradesmen, (though we know that they are not lying on any bed of roses); we appeal to Bohemian journalism for <pb facs="5418478_4_1575.jpg" n="4"/>for its loyal support, and last but not least, to Bohemian labor, whose beacon-light Havlicek has ever been.</p>
   <p>It is only by combining our forces that we can realize a long-cherished dream by unveiling the monument of Havlicek on the anniversary of his birth, October 31. By doing this the Bohemian nation will demonstrate the high level of its culture, its strength, and its undaunted spirit.x</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
