<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-09-01">Sept. 1, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Public Reading Room on Blue Island Avenue Opened</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0098</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0098.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-09-01">Sept. 1, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC READING ROOM ON BLUE ISLAND AVENUE OPENED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The goal for which the literary and book-loving public of Bohemian Chicago has been striving has at last been reached. The long-needed public [Library and] reading room in the Bohemian quarter was opened yesterday. It is located at 543-545 Blue Island Avenue, near 18th Street. The reading room was opened to the public at 8 p. m. by officials of the [Chicago] Public Library, Mr. [Frederick H.] Hild, librarian; Mr. [William B.] Wickersham, secretary; Mr. Purer, manager; and Messrs. Eckert, Tyffe,Lindstrand, Depres, and Broxeau, members of the board of directors. In addition to these, Alderman Hurt, Mr. Walleck, Mr. Souhrada, and many prominent local citizens were among those filling the spacious reading room. From the attendance it is apparent that there are many who are interested in the reading room. The large number of young people present at the opening was especially pleasing. It is surely the hope of everyone that our young people will continue to visit the reading room with as much interest as they showed yesterday.</p>
   <p>This reading room [branch of the Chicago Public Library]is so spacious, well <pb facs="5418478_4_0099.jpg" n="2"/>lighted and nicely arranged that the members of the library board make no secret of the fact that it is one of the finest reading rooms in the city. The stock of books is not complete as yet, especially in so far as Bohemian books are concerned, but they have been ordered, and everything will be arranged in the course of a few days. The selection of English books is fine, for they include such books as are to be found in the Model Library which was awarded first prize at the St. Louis World's Fair. There is a whole group of dictionaries, educational books, collections of historical writings, biographies, scientific books, books on economics, fiction, and a large selection of books for children. In addition, there will be magazines, and newspapers in English, Bohemian, Polish, German and French. Besides the books now in the reading room, an additional 1,500 volumes have been ordered. By means of the reading room it will be possible to borrow, free of charge, any kind of a book from the Public Library.</p>
   <p>The reading room will be open on week days from 12 o'clock noon to 9 o'clock in the evening, and on Sundays from 12 o'clock noon to 6 P. M. Mr. Frederic Rex <pb facs="5418478_4_0100.jpg" n="3"/>was appointed manager, and he began his duties today. We hope that this reading room will continue to draw the attendance of the local Bohemian community, and that it will have a beneficial influence throughout the neighborhood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
