<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-09">Nov. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Twenty-Five Thousand Members in the Bohemian Ladies' Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-09">Nov. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTY-FIVE THOUSAND MEMBERS IN THE BOHEMIAN LADIES' UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We had an opportunity recently to report to our readers that the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies' Union) has increased astonishingly in its membership, since it has reached the commanding total of 25,000, and has thus attained first place among our fraternal and sororal organizations.</p>
   <p>This surprising success of the Jednota must certainly fill the hearts of its members with great joy; it certainly must please everyone who appreciates the importance of our great organizations and the position they occupy in our national and social life....The credit for this unexpected increase goes, in the first place, to the untiring efforts and antlike activity of the officers and other members of the Jednota; it was these ladies who worked day and night to effect a frowth in the organization in spite of the apparent reverses which all of our organized bodies had to meet during the war.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1658.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was their effort that was responsible for the steady growth of the organization; it was their effort that led to the creation of new lodges and clubs of the Jednota and the concurrent increase in the number of its members. But it is no less the honest and correct management of the affairs of the Jednota that created a much greater confidence in the Jednota wherever its branches were organized in our Bohemian-American settlements. Thus the Jednota and its many lodges became the meeting centers for our intelligent women and girls.</p>
   <p>As is well known, the Jednota was founded more than half a century ago. During that space of time the Jednota has done much to deserve credit for its work in behalf of its members and for the good of our nation. Its unreserved support of all charitable and patriotic causes will forever remain a shining example of its activity.</p>
   <p>When it was recently announced by the central executive committee that the total membership of the Jednota is approaching its twenty-fifth thousand, the news <pb facs="5418478_4_1659.jpg" n="3"/>called forth a sincere expression of joy from its members, and it was thought proper to celebrate the occasion in a dignified way. This was recommended accordingly in the meeting of the Illinois Grand Lodge of the Jednota, and it was that lodge which commenced immediate preparations for celebrating the event. Mrs. A. Brychta is the president, and Mrs. Alzbeta Lisy the secretary, of the Grand Lodge. November 15, 1922, was chosen as the day of the celebration which will be held in the Sokol Chicago. No doubt a great number of members from all of the Chicago Lodges will attend, but there will also be out-of-town members present. Mrs. Karolina Rychlik of Cleveland, Ohio, who is the sol surviving charter member of the Jednota, will thus witness this joyous occasion of celebration. A fine program, which will fit the dignity of the great event, was prepared by the committee. The ceremonies will begin at 8 P.M. Admission is free.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
