<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-28">May 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Enormous Success of Lecture</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0851</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0851.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-28">May 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ENORMOUS SUCCESS OF LECTURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Pilsen Brewery Park pavilion was filled to its capacity in three great patriotic meetings held within the last fourteen days.</p>
   <p>One meeting was the manifestation for joint patriotic work of the Czech Catholics and the liberal [free-religionist] Czech National Alliance; the second meeting was held to stimulate enlistment for service in the Czech Branch of the American Red Cross; the third was an occasion to hear Mr. F. Pisecky, personal representative of our leader, Prof. Thomas G. Masaryk.</p>
   <p>This speaker came to the United States to acquaint our people with conditions in Russia and its revolution; also to tell of his experience on the Russian and Serbian battlefields, and finally, to give some explanations in the case of Josef Durich. The multitude which filled the pavilion listened to the <pb facs="5418478_4_0852.jpg" n="2"/>most interesting lecture ever heard in our city. Mr. Tvrzicky introduced our distinguished guest, Prof. F. Pisecky, as follows:</p>
   <p>"Our Czech community welcomes the man who is going to inform us of the results of our patriotic efforts, and of the work done by us, which, hitherto, many have thought futile. We Czechs have always been struggling for independence, first within Austria, and now on the outside, and against the Austrian monarchy. When America declared War, we joined it, renewing our national program. Now that American has declared itself, for the freedom of the small nations, it is not any more important for us to work only, we must fight also. Wherever the Czechs have battled, they did it for liberty and justice. I take great pleasure in presenting to you Professor Pisecky, who comes here to our United States, not only as a plenipotentiary of Prof. Thomas G. Masaryk, but on the expressed will of the entire Czech nation....."</p>
   <p>It is impossible for us to reproduce the address verbatim; this is what <pb facs="5418478_4_0853.jpg" n="3"/>Professor Pisecky said in essence: "I am deeply moved by your manifestation, but do not think what I am doing is anything extraordinary. It is plain, unassuming service which any other Czech would render, and which he is bound to perform. I feel that I have not accomplished what a great number of our men have already done, those who died in the Dobrudzia district, on the Russian front, and in France. Though I feel gratified by your loyalty and friendly sentiment shown me, I beg you to transfer it to those who have given their lives for our cause. I did not know before reaching this land that I would speak about Russia. I note that the Czechs are deeply affected by the fateful happenings in Russia. Everyone wants to know how Russia is faring, all are in suspense, for every sincere Czech knows that without a Russia, healthy and sound, there is no thought of an existence for us ..... The outcome of the World War depends upon Russia. I am convinced that we shall emerge victoriously, and that Germany shall be defeated, and Austria destroyed. (Thundering applause.)</p>
   <p>"I shall tell how I look upon the Russian revolution, but I ask you not to <pb facs="5418478_4_0854.jpg" n="4"/>take everything literally. That revolution is something highly intricate; its origins cannot be clearly discerned, nor can its ultimate aims be fathomed ..... Russia is a country of mysteries, of immense expanse, untouchable--a virgin land. The country of extreme contrasts, of unbearably hot and bitterly cold weather .... Great literati live there, surrounded by millions of analphabets. Public school education lasts only four years, but even this is not compulsory. As far as that goes, our own peasants in Bohemia also do not like to send their children to school; they would rather take the risk of paying a fine. Alcoholism is rampant in Russia. For more than sixty years, a fight has been waged to resist this plague, and Russia was the first country among the participants in the World War to prohibit the use of alcohol in its army. Russia also was the land of the most terrible persecutions; the best of its inhabitants, students-male or female, diligent and efficient workers, died on the gallows or in banishment in Siberia.</p>
   <p>"Close beside Tolstoj, 'the Thirteenth Apostle,' we observe such figures as <pb facs="5418478_4_0855.jpg" n="5"/>that of Rasputin, the illiterate, brutal, and fanatic monk, who succeeded in dominating the court circles, in whose sinister desires intelligent women and men acquiesced with like meekness. When seated at the Czar's table, he did not use knife and fork, but his hand, which, on the spur of the moment, he would stretch out in front of his lady neighbor and bid her to lick it clean .....</p>
   <p>"In Russia, one has to look twice to know which is which, whether it comes from Petrograd, Moscow, or whether it has been planted by Berlin .....</p>
   <p>"Who has put Russia in its present plight? Berlin, joined by Vienna and Budapest. They have sustained a super-government of aristocrats and bureaucrats in that country. The Germans did not allow the Russians to get an education. The school books for middle grades were written by Germans; those on history contained more about Germans than about Russians; other Slavonic nations had to content themselves with short notes in small <pb facs="5418478_4_0856.jpg" n="6"/>print..... The Germans kept Russia isolated from the rest of the world. All of the agricultural products of Russia had to go through Germany; that was the reason for keeping the Russians from the Dardanelles ..... The Germans incited the Russians and the Poles against one another..... The German colonies were located and spread out in such a manner that they dominated the economic life of entire Russia. .... The Germans in southeastern Russia, in Bessarabia, along the Volga, ruled the country by their wealth; even the Putilov works, Russia's biggest ammunition factory, was in German hands."</p>
   <p>The speaker then gave a survey of the World War as far as Russia was concerned, and partly France. The turmoil and disorder which prevented concerted military operations he laid to treason, perpetrated by Stuermer, and Protopopov, who was vice-president of the Duma. Hungry people, demonstrating to obtain better conditions, were shot. The great manifestation of the common people took place on the Newski Prospect in Petrograd, March 11, 1917; it was held in the form of a monster camp meeting. The terrible Sunday on <pb facs="5418478_4_0857.jpg" n="7"/>March 12 came along, when police caused wholesale bloodshed among the demonstrating crowd. The revolution was thus initiated..... All the Germanophiles, good-for-nothings, and traitors were arrested by the revolutionary authorities, headed by Kerensky, and backed by the army.....</p>
   <p>Sometime later, the former member of the Austrian parliament, Durich, arrived at Kijev (Kiev) where he was enthusiastically greeted by the Czechs and Slovaks.</p>
   <p>"It is to be regretted that he disappointed them by disparaging the achievements of such meritorious patriotic workers as Stefanik, Masaryk, Benes, Pavlu, and others, and by siding with such worthless fellows as Konicek, Stepanek and Kral. By Durich's machinations, the entire work done by the Czech National Council in Russia was compromised. Durich and his fellow-conspirators attempted to form a new, separate National Council in Russia, but as the Czarist regime went to its doom thru the rise of the revolution, <pb facs="5418478_4_0858.jpg" n="8"/>their scheme also came to naught, and Durich was forced out of the Czech National Council .....</p>
   <p>Our Sokol gymnastic societies of the old homeland have done their duty, and I hope that the American Sokols will follow the example .....</p>
   <p>It is necessary for us to unite, regardless of party or religion ..... We need the Slovaks, and the Slovaks need us. Let us stand in a united front behind our leaders, Masaryk and Stefanik ....."</p>
   <p>The address lasted until late evening. Yet every word of it was important; it is incumbent upon us to see to it that its teachings shall bear fruit.</p>
   <p>[Translator's Note.-- Professor Pisecky's lecture was translated because of its importance to the activities of the Chicago Czechs during the World War.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
