<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-14">Aug. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To Rebuild Czech School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0528</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0528.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-14">Aug. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO REBUILD CZECH SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many of our compatriots, as well as members of our societies, will be pleased to hear that the remnants of what was once the old Czech-English Free Thought School will be rebuilt probably within the next few months. The building, which was destroyed by fire, had been the gathering place for many, and the home of several, of our Czech-Chicago societies. The location is West 18th and May Streets.</p>
   <p>The board of directors of the School decided to take the first steps, after conferences with delegates from many lodges of the C.S.P.S. [Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost (Czecho-Slav Aid Society)], and also with individuals, all of whom promised to lend support to the project. The board of directors had been working on the plan for a long time, and, after due consideration of all the circumstances, it came to the conclusion that the task is feasible, and the plan can be realized if only our public will stand behind it.</p>
   <p>The desirability of starting the work early is easy to understand, for if the <pb facs="5418478_4_0529.jpg" n="2"/>board should wait until it can sell what was saved from the fire, the lodges that had put their funds into the old building would salvage very little. on the other hand, most of our organizations to whom the old building was a home and a center of recreation are longing for its speedy reconstruction. The costs of rebuilding are estimated at $30,000. Part of this is covered by fire insurance on the burned building; the rest is to come from bonds which are to be circulated at ten dollars per share and which will be payable in five years. The plans for the work are drawn up, and as soon as they are approved, the work is to begin so that our memorable building in "Czech Pilsen" will soon rise again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
