<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-30">Mar. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Gymnastic Team of the Sokol Pilsen</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Pilsen Sokol Gymnastic Team Wins Championship in American Athletic Federation; Havlicek-Tyrs Sokol and Dvorak Park Teams also Win Prizes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1031</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1031.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 3 (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-30">Mar. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE GYMNASTIC TEAM OF THE SOKOL PILSEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Pilsen Sokol Gymnastic Team Wins Championship in American Athletic Federation; Havlicek-Tyrs Sokol and Dvorak Park Teams also Win Prizes</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A tournament of the American Athletic Federation was held in the gymnasium of the Central Young Men's Christian Association yesterday. The tournament was a success, and all the more so because our young Bohemian heroes won the prizes of victory, because Bohemian prowess, power, and perservance were fully recognized by the strict judges of the Federation.</p>
   <p>The tournament yesterday was of greater importance than previous ones because there were a greater number of gymnastic associations present. Beside the Bohemian and Croatian gymnastic unions there were also the German, the Polish, the Swedish, and many others. The famous German Turnverein delegated some of its finest contestants, but they found the Czechoslovaks to be formidable rivals....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1032.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first championship of American Athletic Federation fell to Pilsen Sokol team which gained 443 1/2 points. The second prize was awarded to the Lincoln Turnverein (Lincoln German Gymnastic Association) team with 415 points; the third prize went to the team of the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs with 338 3/4 points.</p>
   <p>It is regrettable that the feats of individual contestants were not judged by the same jury; thus, for instance, the judges for the Germans were not as strict as those judging the Czechs. This explains why the Czechs were not in the first place when individual contestants were judged, though the differences in points gained were really insignificant. The first prize was awarded to Mr. J. Chech, of the Lincoln Turnverein, who gained 93 1/2 points. He obviously is a German having Czech blood as his name indicates. The second prize went to George Selos whose nationality we were unable to determine. He gained 92 3/4 points. The third prize was won by Mr. Jiri Vesely, member of the Pilsen Sokol team. Vesely gained 92 points. The fourth prize went to Mr. Jan Kristufek, of the same organization as Mr. Vesely. Kristufek gained 90 points. The fifth prize was earned by Mr. Stransky, also of the Pilsen Sokol, who gained 89 points.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1033.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The tournament was not only very interesting, but the competition was rather strong as is made evident by the slight differences in the number of points gained.</p>
   <p>Contestants of subordinate departments came out as follows: The first group prize was earned by the Eiche Turnverein with 363 points; the second by the Social Turnverein with 359 points; the third by the Dvorak Park team with 346 points; the fourth by the Lincoln Turnverein with 345 points.</p>
   <p>The individual contestants in these latter organizations who won prizes were the following: Mr. Gruenberger, German, 86 points; Mr. Khoras, a German, 76 1/2 points; Mr. A. Wendl, a Bohemian from Dvorak's Park 75 3/4 points; Mr. J. Vednik, a Bohemian from Dvorak's Park, 75 3/4 points; Mr. Werth [of the Lincoln Turnverein], 75 1/4 points.</p>
   <p>It is expected that our athletes will receive many congratulations from all friends of the art who live in the Czechoslovak colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
