<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-14">June 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Aim of the Czech Sokol Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-14">June 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE AIM OF THE CZECH SOKOL ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thousands of members, male and female, of Czech Sokol organizations will be greatly pleased by the latest issue of The Bohemian Review, official organ of the Czech National Alliance. Dr. L. J. Fisher, president of that organization, has contributed an article, "What the Sokols Stand For," wherein the origin, purposes, and the problems of the Sokol gymnastic organizations are made clear to the American public. [The Bohemian Review is a monthly printed in the English language.] It sets forth the part the Sokols are called on to play in the struggle for Czech independence. To this end some of the most salient points in modern Czech history are described, as the last great rally in Prague of all the Sokols. There is a picture of Tyrs, one of the founders of the Sokol organization.</p>
   <p>This article should be read especially by our second and third generation Czechs who will find the national efforts of their fathers and mothers well described. It should also be presented, however, to the general American public. No Czech, and particularly no Sokol family, should neglect to read <pb facs="5418478_4_0279.jpg" n="2"/>the Bohemian Review, or at least to read the one article mentioned. The price of one issue is ten cents. The offices of the monthly are located 2627 South Ridgeway Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>The above-mentioned article will no doubt be discussed in numerous English language papers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
