<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-29">Aug. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Notice from the Managing Board of the Bohemian Free Thought School Jan Neruda</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0403</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0403.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-29">Aug. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NOTICE FROM THE MANAGING BOARD OF THE BOHEMIAN FREE THOUGHT SCHOOL JAN NERUDA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>....On Saturday, September 2, 1922, the regular term of the Ceska Svobodomyslna Skola Jan Neruda (Bohemian Free Thought School Jan Neruda) will begin. The school is located at West 27th Street and Karlov Avenue. Your children will be grateful to you if you register them in a Bohemian school, where they will learn the mother tongue, the tongue of that nation which gave them their origin, and which later will be found of benefit to them. They will likewise get a correct general attitude toward life and faith, matters which surely are of utmost importance. The tuition fee for a period of ten months [school year] is $3.35--in other words, a little more than a cent a day. On registration day you will pay $1.75, and the balance within two months after registration. Every third child in each family will be taught free of charge. Registration begins Tuesday, September 5, 1922, from 9 A. M. to 7 P. M. Important! Have your children enroll on the first day of the term to make it possible for them to be placed in classes <pb facs="5418478_4_0404.jpg" n="2"/>commensurate with their abilities. The class hours will be announced by the teacher, Mr. Machek, on the day of registration.</p>
   <p>For the Patronat (managing board) of the Ceska Svobodomyslna Skola Janneruda</p>
   <p>The Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
