<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1884-08-28">Aug. 28, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">Third Gymnastic Competition; the Results Are Published, the Prizes Given; New York First; Surprising Progress of the Youth Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1884-08-28">Aug. 28, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">THIRD GYMNASTIC COMPETITION; THE RESULTS ARE PUBLISHED, THE PRIZES GIVEN; NEW YORK FIRST; SURPRISING PROGRESS OF THE YOUTH SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After two days of strenuous competitive gymnastics, results and prizes were published yesterday. Today we give the report of the results of the competition, which was conducted in a manner satisfactory to all Sokols.</p>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon the judges were busy counting the points, and as it usually happens, there were some disagreements about fencing: whether it should be regarded in the same class as the ordinary exercises on the gymnastic apparatus. Opposition was voiced by those Sokols who do not fence, but, finally, the sokols who do fence forced their motion over and fencing points were counted the same as points received on other competitive exercises on the gymnastic apparatus.</p>
   <p>While the judges perspired counting the points made by individual competitors, the Sokols employed their leisure by sightseeing the city and its parks. After the sightseers returned home, they made preparations for <pb facs="5418478_4_1386.jpg" n="2"/>a dance in the Bohemian-American Sokol Hall, at which the results would be announced and where the fencing would be held. The dance hall was filled with the participants in the festival. Our pretty young girls dressed in white attracted everybody. After 10 P. M. there started on the stage the fencing contest in which eight Sokols participated..... (Names omitted). After the fencing between the individual Sokols, the first prize was awarded to Kostlan from Milwaukee; second to Kadlec, New York, and third to Novy, Chicago. The curtain was lowered and the Sokols and their guests continued to dance. Late in the evening Sokol J. B. Belohradski, chairman of the National Sokol Union, announced the results.</p>
   <p>Three prizes for exercises in formation were granted: first to the contingent from New York Sokols; second to the Bohemian-American Sokols of Chicago; third to the Pilzen Sokols of Chicago, For individual exercises thirty-three prizes were awarded to various Sokols.....(Names omitted).</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1387.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This ended the third competitive gymnastic contest and we hope that the Bohemian Sokols will be satisfied with the results.</p>
   <p>On the prizes for exercises in formation we must congratulate the New Yorkers, because there is not a single unit which could measure in competition with them. The Bohemian-American Sokols in Chicago received the second prize and no wonder, because the formation was composed only of good seasoned Sokols. The third prize was awarded to the Pilzen Sokols, which fact must be seen as a splendid victory, because they are the youngest unit of all six participating in the competition. Will they continue to progress in the same way? Will the members stick together? This Sokol unit may be a very dangerous rival in the next competition convention. The dance entertainment continued until early in the morning and we can state positively that the excellent exercises were rewarded with complete success and attracted unexpected attention from other nationalities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
