<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-29">Nov. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Another Delay</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-29">Nov. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER DELAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have informed our readers about the Soka conference which started in Cleveland on Thanksgiving Day. The Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union), the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Sokol District Fuegner-Lyrs), and the Americky Delnicky Sokol (American Workingmen's Sokol) were each represented by three delegates, who were expected to work out a way for the unification of all sokol bodies in America. The result of their deliberations was being looked forward to by all Bohemian-Americans and, naturally, awaited with particular expectation by all sokols.</p>
   <p>It had been generally hoped that the much-talked-about, and long-attempted unification would finally come about. But a telegram received from Cleveland yesterday advises that this hope had been fulfilled in part only. The unification will affect only the Narodni Jednota Sokolska and the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs. The representatives of the Americky Delnicky Sokol did not give their agreement to a complete unification.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1288.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The wire we have received reads as follows: "Complete unification has not been achieved. The representatives of the Americky Delnicky Sokol were ready to agree to a unification on a federative basis only. Their sokol would retain its name and continue to keep its own administration, and would be represented in the central body by delegates. The Americky Delnicky Sokol could not see its way clear to relinquish this requirement; hence, further deliberations were limited to the unification of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska and the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs, and this unification was brought about. When the question of the name for the new organization came up, four delegates voted Obec Sokolska (Sokol Community) and two for Narodni Jednota Sokolska. Both suggestions will be voted upon by the whole membership of the two sokol bodies whose unification has now been agreed upon. Because of the disagreement about the name, the unification has been postponed pending the voting of the membership. A detailed report on the meeting follows by mail. B. H."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1289.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These initials indicate that the wire was sent to us by Mr. Bohus Hak, who attended the conference as one of the representatives of the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs, and who has always been one of the most ardent supporters of the idea of unification of all sokoldom in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
