<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-04-21">Apr. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Piece of Good Work</title><title level="a" type="sub">Lecture on Bohemia and the Bohemians a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0886</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0886.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-04-21">Apr. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A PIECE OF GOOD WORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">Lecture on Bohemia and the Bohemians a Great Success</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Until recently very little has been known in the United States about Bohemia and the Bohemians. The reason for this we must seek in ourselves, because, at all times and in all circumstances, we have worked only for ourselves and among our own people. Such an attitude was not helpful in making us known to the Americans of whom we expected recognition.</p>
   <p>The public has heard very little about us; has been ignorant of our brilliant past, has paid very little attention to our present existence, and has been particularly unaware of that which is really beautiful in our lives, our art. For a long time there was no one who would tell the American public about our striving for things in life which are worth while. Not until very recently have we Bohemians received any recognition from the American public. But then we began to be noticed as a cultured and mature nation, capable of competing <pb facs="5418478_4_0887.jpg" n="2"/>with the greatest nations.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's lecture by Professor Jaroslav Zmrhal was a fine piece of work. It was held in the great assembly room of the Teachers' College at 68th Street and Stewart Avenue.</p>
   <p>About five hundred students both men and women, and their teachers were assembled in the great auditorium. They followed attentively every word spoken and every picture shown by the noted speaker.</p>
   <p>Professor Zmrhal spoke very entertainingly of the Bohemian countryside and its natural beauties, of the Bohemian people, their dress, their customs; and of the nation's past. He showed slides of the Bohemian countryside, of cottages and farms, of great buildings in the cities, of castles and rural scenes. He took his audience through Bohemian cities and towns, and painted word pictures of lonely little settlements and villages. Speaking about the way of living in general, he gave a successful picture of our brothers and sisters in the old <pb facs="5418478_4_0888.jpg" n="3"/>country and their occupations which are preponderantly of an agricultural nature, but also commercial.</p>
   <p>Professor Zmrhal also spoke of the Bohemians' excellence in art, and said that the best way to demonstrate that fact is to present a Bohemian musical composition. As an example Dvorak's "Dumky" (Musings) were played by the following artists: Mr. V. A. Cerny, cello; Mr. Jiri Hrusa, violin, and Miss Mary Green, a pupil of Mr. Cerny, piano....It was a number which would have sounded well in the largest of concert halls, and we have not heard anything to equal it in recent years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hrusa and Mr. Cerny performed wonders with their playing yesterday. They were accompanied by a pianist who is really talented, and who, under the direction of her teacher, has a great future in store for her.</p>
   <p>Hardly had the last chords of the composition ceased vibrating, when the audience burst into applause, and the artists were made to give an encore--also <pb facs="5418478_4_0889.jpg" n="4"/>a trio--"Ecstasy," by Ahrensky. This well-known composition was also received with applause.</p>
   <p>After this rendition, Professor Zmrhal resumed his lecture. Its second part was entirely devoted to our "Maticka" (little mother) Praha (Prague).</p>
   <p>He spoke of Prague's glory, beauty, and old arts. The accompanying slides illustrated beautifully the professor's words, undoubtedly helping the listeners to make for themselves a fine picture of that city.</p>
   <p>The audience would have been glad to listen to the lecturer perhaps until evening, but Professor Zmrhal finally had to stop, promising to come again and tell more about Bohemia and the Bohemians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
