<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-22">Aug. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Sixth Convention of the Bohemian Sisterhood</title><title level="a" type="sub">Second and Third Sessions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-22">Aug. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SIXTH CONVENTION OF THE BOHEMIAN SISTERHOOD</title><title level="a" type="sub">Second and Third Sessions</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second session of the convention was opened yesterday at 9 A.M. by the chairman of the central committee and president of the convention, Sister Marie Hajek, of Cleveland. After the delegates repeated the slogan [of the Sisterhood], the secretary, Sister Stolf, read the roll call. It was ascertained in this manner that almost all of the delegates were present. The others arrived later. Sister Anna Churan (Lodge No. 49, Eleonora Kounic) was represented by the alternate, Sister Katerina Zahrobsky. Alternates also represented the Lodges Martha Washington No. 68 and Rozkvet Svobody (Blossoming of Freedom) No. 70, these alternates being Sisters Anna Sevcik and Frantiska Zahour [respectively]. After outlining the program for the day, the [central] committee made its recommendations. It was decided that the <pb facs="5418478_4_1752.jpg" n="2"/>convention should be in session between the hours of 9 A.M. and 12 noon, and 1 P.M. and 4 P.M. After pronouncing the slogan [of the Sisterhood], the roll call is to follow and the absentees noted. Then will come the reading of the minutes of the previous session, followed by the reading of correspondence. Amendments to the constitution will be next.</p>
   <p>The committee, whose task it was to inspect the books and records of the central committee, reported that the books were in order....The convention secretary, Sister Stolf, then read the minutes of the Saturday session which were approved as read. The secretary announced also that she had found it impossible to have the minutes published in the daily [Bohemian] press, but that she would do so on the following Monday (yesterday) so that a copy of the minutes could be in the hands of every delegate on the following morning. The press committee, which had for its duty the printing of the minutes of the convention, reported that the job was awarded to the [Bohemian] afternoon daily, and that the work shall be done as ordered.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1753.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The reading of all incoming letters followed. These were chiefly congratulatory messages. [List of societies, lodges, and individuals sending messages to the Jednota is omitted in translation.] In regard to the letter sent by the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage), we should like to add that its board of delegates, in addition to sending its best wishes to the convention, begs the Jednota to continue favoring and supporting the Utulna.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zeman, who is a well-known national worker of Cleveland, sent the following letter from the spa at Podebrady, Czechoslovakia:</p>
   <p>"To the sixth convention of the Jednota in session at Chicago, during the week of August 19, 1922:</p>
   <p>Mesadames and dear sisters: During these most significant days of your great and serious work....I hasten to send you in the name of my dear spouse, <pb facs="5418478_4_1754.jpg" n="4"/>Marie Zeman, my heartiest congratulations on your noble work already performed, wishing you the greatest possible success in your beneficent labors for the families of Bohemians, and in your philanthropic and cultural endeavors for our Bohemian colony in our new father-land [America].</p>
   <p>"Dear sisters, we feel with you and are proud of your activity, for it is the most shining example of the high degree of consciousness and comprehension which the Bohemian woman has for the noblest causes. Therefore, we hope that the Jednota will continue to prosper in its avowed ideal, and that its deliberations at the convention prove to be a blessing not only for all the dear sisters in convention assembled, but for the life of all the Czechoslovaks of America. Your work is, in its totality, appreciated by every noble heart and will surely be a mighty monument and example for future generations.</p>
   <p>"Again wishing you the best of success, though far removed from you in our <pb facs="5418478_4_1755.jpg" n="5"/>native land, we remain</p>
   <p>"Faithfully yours,</p>
   <p>Marie Zeman,</p>
   <p>"Secretary of the Central Committee of the Jednota</p>
   <p>M. Zeman."</p>
   <p>The Cechu Domov (Home of Bohemians) of Cleveland sent its best wishes, asking the convention to remember the Domov by some contribution, however small it be. This letter was laid aside to be acted on at the proper time. In response to all the congratulatory messages and at the request of the president of the convention, the delegates expressed their thanks by rising to their feet.</p>
   <p>The amendments to the constitution and bylaws were then taken up. The recommendations had already been made and ordered printed. These recommendations were now read by the second [assistant] secretary. Debates ensued as to some individual paragraphs. The liveliest discussion concerned the admission <pb facs="5418478_4_1756.jpg" n="6"/>of candidates and their national and citizenship status. The remarks made by the first secretary, Sister Anna Stolf, were very fine. She enjoined the assembled delegates not to permit, under any circumstances, the use of any language but the Czech in all the transactions of the lodges of the Jednota, and to see to it--especially as regards the junior members--that the Jednota, which admits to its membership Bohemian and Bohemian-American women and girls remain Czech as long as possible. This opinion was fully shared by the convention president who likewise insisted on the characteristically Bohemian quality of the Jednota.</p>
   <p>The question of age of applicants and the furnishing of proof of their actual ages was then debated. It was argued also that certain girls and women being of illegitimate birth would not be able to furnish a proof of their age when making applications for membership. Sister Stolf to objected to this allusion and emphasized the fact that in this day and age it is unthinkable that anyone should concern himself with such a question.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1757.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The matter of clubs was taken up. A great number of delegates spoke in favor of clubs which would admit Czech girls between the ages of fifteen and eighteen years. [These delegates] also recommended that any member of such club, upon reaching her eighteenth year, be admitted gratis into any lodge of the Jednota. This final recommendation was favorably received by the majority of the delegates; it was therefore moved and carried.</p>
   <p>Another interesting amendment was that any member who, during the first year of her membership, is found to have given any incorrect information about herself at the time of making her application for admission, shall be excluded from the Jednota and all the fees paid by her to the Jednota shall be refunded.</p>
   <p>After the noon recess, during which all the delegates had a joint luncheon to which they had been invited by the chairman of the festivities committee, Sister Marie Smrcek, the third session began at 1 P.M. The meeting was opened by the president of the sixth convention of the Jednota. There was <pb facs="5418478_4_1758.jpg" n="8"/>another roll call, and all the delegates being in their places, the work of amending the constitution and bylaws was resumed. The secretary remarked that during the noon recess, she thought about the proposed formation of [junior] clubs. She moved that these junior clubs bear no names but be designated only by numbers and the name of the state in which each is located. The clubs would then have for their common denominator the appellation of "Klub Sesterske Podporujici Jednoty" (Club of the Bohemian Sisterhood). These clubs may be established even in localities that have no lodges, and they should be under the supervision of the lodges established in the towns lying nearest to these localities. This added feature was considered correct and was approved.</p>
   <p>Several recommendations were made concerning voting on the applications of prospective members. It was maintained that rejection of a candidate for purely personal reasons, brought on by personal animosity or revenge, should not be countenanced. It may often happen that a member may dislike this or that candidate and attempt to blackball her when ballots are cast. The secretary was instructed to so reword the paragraph touching upon this point as to <pb facs="5418478_4_1759.jpg" n="9"/>be most suitable and acceptable. Likewise, it was recommended that a candidate who may be disqualified by the examining physician for reasons purely personal, may, upon the permission given by the Grand Lodge of the Jednota, be sent to another physician. This recommendation was not acted upon. On motion made by Sister Stolf, the matter concerning medical certificates was left to the conscientiousness and experience of practicing physicians.....</p>
   <p>A debate was launched concerning the support of Bohemian Free Thought schools. Sister Vlach, of Cleveland, did not object to the supporting of such schools because her own lodge takes care of them by its fund. What she did object to was the taxing of every member by a certain amount. Sister Stolf recommended that the Jednota continue the support of the Bohemian Free Thought school system, and do so by a definite quarterly tax levied on every member; it was her belief that the support of educational activities was her foremost duty. The future of the Jednota depends on the children who attend those schools. She called the attention of the Cleveland delegates to the fact that funds must be <pb facs="5418478_4_1760.jpg" n="10"/>collected by lodges for certain given causes, and that the funds collected for such causes must be used for the cause specified. The Bohemian Free Thought school system shall continue to be supported by the Jednota, and this with its whole strength.</p>
   <p>An important amendment was the one which dealt with the refusal of sick benefits of those members who willfully underwent an abortion. The committee that visits the sick shall consist of two members, and shall be appointed to serve one whole year. It shall be left to the discretion of individual lodges to pay or not to pay the expenses of the sick benefit committee; this provision also concerns the ability to pay compensation to the members of the said committee.</p>
   <p>In regard to certain beneficiary provisions, it was decided, among other things, that any sister who lives separately (away from her husband) shall continue to consider him as her beneficiary, the amount alloted to him from her policy not to be less than $5. In the case of a member not having any family or <pb facs="5418478_4_1761.jpg" n="11"/>relatives, such member must specify which of her friends is to be her beneficiary. This provision was made to forestall any possible legal disputes. The delegates were advised to instruct the members of their lodges that they must not bequeath any sums, in whole or in part, to any enterprises, but must, first of all, remember, according to law, their blood relatives, especially members of their own immediate families. After these have been remembered in their wills, other sums may be bequeathed to persons who are in turn to be instructed to use the amount of the bequest for this or that enterprise or cause. It was further emphasized that every member should allot a certain sum of the policy to burial expenses and use the balance as a bequest to be divided among such of her beneficiaries as the law permits. This particular paragraph was discussed until 4 P.M., at which time the third session was declared to have ended. The chairman of the festivities committee, sister Smrcek, then requested the assembly to repair to the rear hall for tea. The festivities committee and all of its helpers deserve much credit for caring so well for the comforts and entertainment of the convention delegates. On every day of the convention, the members of this committee <pb facs="5418478_4_1762.jpg" n="12"/>prepare tasty home cooked dinners and teas, cooked and served in the pavilion. As we were told by the out-of-town delegates especially, the cooking done by local sisters was excellent, and they were very much satisfied with it. The festivities committee may, therefore, also feel satisfied with its workers and the recognition it receives all around. We wish to augment today's report by the remark that all of the convention delegates.....are really looking forward to the splendid picnic which is to be held in honor of the Jednota in Pilsen Park, tomorrow afternoon.....It is desirable that all of our countrymen attend this picnic and thus show that we appreciate and honor the work done by the Jednota.... The picnic will begin at 2 P.M. Admission is 25 cents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
