<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-16">Sept. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The President of the Central Sokol District Admonishes Chicago Bohemians to Become Nationality Conscious</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-16">Sept. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESIDENT OF THE CENTRAL SOKOL DISTRICT ADMONISHES CHICAGO BOHEMIANS TO BECOME NATIONALITY CONSCIOUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>You often read announcements in the Bohemian daily newspapers to the effect that this or that organization opened a school for the children of Czech parents, a school in which the Czech language is taught. This happens in localities inhabited by nationality-conscious countrymen who realize the necessity of a knowledge of the Czech language and the need of acquiring such a knowledge by their progeny. There is nothing sadder than the lack of understanding of the Czech language in families where the parents are indifferent or lukewarm in this regard, and where the children, consequently, cannot understand the native tongue of their parents. As a physician, I have often had the opportunity of witnessing this. The lack of understanding and of communication <pb facs="5418478_4_0387.jpg" n="2"/>between parents and children is frequently mutual, that is, the children do not understand their parents and the parents do not understand their children. In some families this situation is somewhat better; the children understand the native speech of their parents but cannot or will not answer in Bohemian. Let us remember that it is necessary, in order to be educated, to have a knowledge of another language besides the one used as a medium of communication in the land in which you live. The Germans [of this country] have their own language [besides English], and so do other foreign-language groups retain their mother tongue. Why then should we Bohemians disdain using our tongue, or the Slovaks theirs? Both the Czechs and the Slovaks fought side by side to gain their common homeland, to effect a national union. I was present in the meetings in which this language problem was discussed by our Bohemian school organizations, and I listened to many arguments both pro and con. But those who were in favor of having Czech schools were unflinching in their attempts, a fact which resulted in our having a highly organized schools system of our own.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0388.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Of course nothing is perfect in this world, and that applies equally to the schools which are so dear to us, especially when they have to depend upon the voluntary contributions of our societies and organizations--their only source of income. Still we cannot complain. We gained recognition and considerable support [from our organizations and individuals], but with the beginning of the new school year new duties confront us which must be faced with firmness--that of successfully completing the school work begun by us.</p>
   <p>It is with that end in mind that the projected Staroceske Posviceni (old Czech country festival) was arranged to raise funds for the payment of teachers' salaries and the meeting of other expenses connected with the school administration, etc. The school officers and representatives--both men and women--are performing their duties in the best possible manner, and all we ask, therefore, is that you attend in large numbers on September 17 at the Pilsen Park [pavilion] on the occasion of the said festival.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0389.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Come one, come all; all of you who read this message may be certain that you will not be disappointed. Combine the useful with the pleasurable and come!</p>
   <p>Dr. Anton Mueller, President,</p>
   <p>Central District of the American</p>
   <p>Sokol Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
