<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-10">May 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Public Gymnastic Exhibition of the Sokol Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1013</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1013.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-10">May 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A PUBLIC GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION OF THE SOKOL CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everyone, even those giving only cursory attention to the activities of our Sokol associations, must arrive at the indisputable conviction that, besides our Czech educational efforts, it is these gymnastic associations which have contributed most noticeably to the salvaging and training of our Bohemian-American youth. There our young people not only learn to discipline themselves, but also cultivate a love for their mother tongue, thus increasing their Czech consciousness and feelings step by step. These are facts which must imbue us, who are confronted by the problem of our national survival on this side of the Atlantic, with a feeling of warmth. The perennial public exhibitions of our brave Sokol associations are of especial value in this, our national educational effort, for they serve as a sort of inventory of what we have accomplished each year. Such, for instance, was the exhibition given last Sunday by the Sokol Chicago under the management of the conscientious trainer, Jan Matejka. It was a truly beautiful sight to see the parterre of the hall filled with the members <pb facs="5418478_4_1014.jpg" n="2"/>of the various teams--three hundred and fifty members in various stages of physical development. But whether one looked at the youngest or the oldest, he could perceive in their faces and in their bearing a reflection of their health, elegance, endurance, and prowess, traits which can be produced only by systematic physical cultivation which from the time of the foundation of the Sokol organization has always been the mainstay of the rare heritage left to us by the great esthete, Dr. Miroslav Tyrs, and his brother, Fuegner.</p>
   <p>The admiration of the audience grew as the individual items on the program succeeded each other...Each was greeted by renewed thunders of applause, and we gladly acknowledge the fact that it was well deserved. The program consisted of thirteen items and it would be superfluous to mention each item separately. The team's performances were devoted to those exercises which had been rehearsed for the forthcoming convention of the central Sokol district; some of them we had witnessed before. Brother Matejka deserved full credit for the exemplary forms of the exercises; they attested to his conscientiousness <pb facs="5418478_4_1015.jpg" n="3"/>and ability as a trainer. The full success of this Sunday performance was marred only by the artificial marching steps of the majority of the pupils. It was distressing to observe that many an otherwise graceful pupil marched as though he had a nail sticking in his foot. The marching exercises still leave much to be desired, a fact not to be overlooked by those men who are in charge of training. In this respect they should be merciless in their demands and should spare no efforts to make all phases of training as complete as possible.</p>
   <p>The focal points of the....program were the exercises on the apparatuses; and those of the teams trained by Brother Jindrich Smidl deserve special mention. The music which accompanied the exercises was furnished by Brother J. A. Jurena. Apropos of Brother Matejka we may also say that last Sunday he received so many gifts from his admirers that he was literally buried under them. It was as if Santa Claus had paid him a call out of season....</p>
   <p>The attendance last Sunday was really gigantic; the throng was so great that <pb facs="5418478_4_1016.jpg" n="4"/>there was standing room only, and additional space had to be provided for the overflow on the stage. Significant also was the fact that many foreign visitors came to see the performance, among them the German turners, who were invited by Alderman Anton J. Cermak. As far as we could ascertain the following persons were included in the number of our distingushed foreign visitors: Mr. J. J. Blessing, and Dr. C. A. Wail, both of whom are officials of the Illinois district of the federation of the German turners; Mr. E. C. Klafs, the district chairman; Mr. J. Willig, member of the board of directors of the said German organization; Messrs. F. Eggers and N. Dohm, trainers of the Vorwaerts Turnverein; and Messrs. G. A. Schmidt and W. Wachtel, trainers of the Central Turnverein. These gentlemen, all of whom are experts in the field of gymnastics, were not sparing in their praises of the beauty of the exhibition and perfect training of our men, and they did not conceal their enthusiasm. While talking to Mr. Cermak they expressed their desire to have our Sokols take part in the great gymnastic carnival which the Illinois district of the German Turnvereins, otherwise known as the North American Gymnastic Union, will hold on July 4, 1922, in Riverview <pb facs="5418478_4_1017.jpg" n="5"/>Park. Our Sokol association will gladly accede to this request, and we are certain that on this occasion our men will defend our good reputation....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
