<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-23">Aug. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">An Athletic Contest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-23">Aug. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">AN ATHLETIC CONTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An athletic contest and public drill by the membership of the Sokolska Jednota Fuegner (Sokol Unit Fuegner) of Grand Crossing were held yesterday morning and afternoon respectively. These events took place partly in the Jednota's own building in Grand Crossing, and partly in Calumet Park, where the athletic contest of the Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Sokol unit called Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs) was also held. We are told that these events attracted a very large number of spectators, both from the membership of the two Sokol organizations and from the general public. Grand Crossing is a comparatively large Bohemian settlement, and yesterday was quite a holiday for its people, for in addition to meeting local and nearby friends, they had an opportunity to entertain Sokols from other parts of the country, particularly from Racine, Wisconsin, a group which proved especially popular.</p>
   <p>The Sokol drill contest was participated in by forty-four out of the fiftythree <pb facs="5418478_4_1220.jpg" n="2"/>gymnasts who had entered for it, and it proved once again the superiority of the "red" Sokols [as distinct from the "blue," Catholic organization]. This contest was in principle a heptathlon.</p>
   <p>The athletic contest was held in Calumet Park, at the corner of South Green Bay Avenue and East 108th Street. It consisted of three types of jumps, high, broad, and vault; shot put, one-hundred-yard sprint, cable climb, and lifting of a weight of 76 pounds.</p>
   <p>This contest was participated in by the following Sokol units: Havlicek-Tyrs, Slavsky, Komensky, Cesko-Narodni Pokrok (Bohemian National Progress), Slavoj, Fuegner, and Sokol Mladocech (Young Bohemians) of Racine, Wisconsin.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
