<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-10-27">Oct. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of the Committee on Preparations for the John Huss Memorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-10-27">Oct. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF THE COMMITTEE ON PREPARATIONS FOR THE JOHN HUSS MEMORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committee on preparations for the building of the John Huss Memorial held its last meeting Friday night. In that meeting all preparations were made to pass on the affairs of the undertaking to a legally constituted body of representatives of Bohemian organizations interested in the building of the John Huss Memorial and of other qualified persons according to the following principles:</p>
   <p>An organization--society, association, lodge, union, etc.--contributing ten dollars to the building fund at the time of the constitution of the group, and pledging to increase its contribution to twenty-five dollars within the year, appoints one delegate; each additional one hundred dollars entitles them to one additional representative. Individuals may become members by contributing one hundred dollars. Other regular members will be representatives of newspapers giving publicity and other help to the Memorial. According to contributions and pledges received so far, the body will have over one hundred members, one <pb facs="5418478_4_1492.jpg" n="2"/>half of whom represent Chicago organizations; the other half represent organizations in rural and other districts. Out-of-Chicago members will vote by mail.</p>
   <p>The organization meeting of the body, or board of representatives, will be held in the building of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) at 18th and May Streets, tonight at 8 P. M.</p>
   <p>As soon as the body is organized and incorporated, it will select a convenient site for the Memorial, issue a call for a competition of plans and bids for the building, etc. Its aim will be to lay the cornerstone next July so that the Memorial may be completed by July, 1915, when the five-hundredth anniversary of John Huss's martyrdom will be commemorated.</p>
   <p>The Memorial will be the property of Freet inking Bohemians of America and will serve as headquarters for all work done in the national and Free Thought realm</p>
   <p>The idea of the Memorial originated with Dr. Frantisek Iska.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
