<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-16">Apr. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Gymnastic Competition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-16">Apr. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">GYMNASTIC COMPETITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Frantisek Paul, a member of Pilsen Sokol, took part in the gymnastic competition held in the Central Y. M. C. A. gymnasium under the auspices of the Amateur Athletic Federation last Saturday. Also competing were groups from the German Societies: Vorwaerts, Einigheit, La Salle, and Aurora, the groups from the Chicago Hebrew Institute, and Seward Park.</p>
   <p>In the advanced class, the Vorwaerts squad was victorious with 343.50 points; the Einigheit squad was second with 318.50 points</p>
   <p>Individual winners in this division were the following: 1st, William Horshke, La Salle, 84.2 points; 2nd, William Herzog, Vorwaerts, 83 points; 3rd, Frant. Paul, Pilsen Sokol, 81.50 points.</p>
   <p>The opinion of all Czech participants, and of Walter Eckersall, who is <pb facs="5418478_4_1355.jpg" n="2"/>known as the best athlete of the University of Chicago, was that Frant. Paul was not given a fair deal. He should have been awarded first prize on all apparatus work. Paul also was well aware of that fact, and for that reason refused to accept third prize from the "generous" German gentlemen.</p>
   <p>To be sure, the Bohemian public will not be surprised that the honor was not bestowed upon the Bohemian gymnast by the German judges. On the advice of Walter Eckersall and Sokols Haska, Macak, and Stybl, Sokol Paul absolutely refused to accept the third prize. In this way, Sokol Paul made known best to the Germans how the Bohemians and other participants in the competition look upon their fairness, and fully agree with him for not accepting third prize when he was entitled to first.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
