<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-03">Jan. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">An Anniversary of a Bohemian School</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Free Thought School Vojta Náprstek Celebrated its Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Yesterday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-03">Jan. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AN ANNIVERSARY OF A BOHEMIAN SCHOOL</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Free Thought School Vojta Náprstek Celebrated Its Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Yesterday</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday was a significant day for the Vojta Náprstek school, its student body, its Junior Club, and its alumni. Among the latter were representatives of the earliest class, which entered the institution twenty-five years ago, as well as more recent graduates. This was a silver jubilee of that institution, and among the public that came to the Sokol Chicago yesterday afternoon and evening, there were many of our countrymen who attended the Náprstek school twenty-five years ago while it was still in its infancy. The school still enjoys great popularity today. A quarter of a century in the life of a Bohemian-American school is certainly not a minor event, when we consider how much labor and sacrifice are required for its maintenance.....The stimulus for the establishment of the Náprstek school came in the year 1896 when our "California" district was an enormous Czech settlement; and on October 16, 1896, there took place the first advisory meeting of the representatives of the <!-- 5418478_4_0433 omitted, duplicate of 5418478_4_0434 --><pb facs="5418478_4_0434.jpg" n="2"/>various societies, together with the many enthusiastic national workers, all of whom discussed the pressing need for a Czech school. Those present recognized such a need, and on November 17 of the same year, a meeting of the organizing committee was held. This committee decided to found and maintain such a school.</p>
   <p>The newly organized institution was given the name "Vojta Náprstek". The following societies were represented at the organizing meeting: Sokol Chicago, Loze Trocnov Jednoty Taboritu (Lodge Trocnov of the Taborites), Sbor Bozena Nemcova Slovanska Podpurna Jednota (Bozena Nemcova Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Association), Rad Sumavan Ceskoslovanska Bratrska Podporujici Jednota (The Order of Sumavan of the Czecho-Slavonic Brotherly and Benevolent Association), Rad Caslav Cesko-Slovansky Podpurny Spolek (Order of Caslav of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Association), Sbor Palma Jednota Ceskych Dam (The Palma Group of the Bohemian Ladies Society), Rad Vladislav Cesko-Slovanske Bratrske Podpurne Jednoty (The Order of Vladislav of the Czecho-Slavonic Fraternal and Benevolent Association). During that same year, some other <pb facs="5418478_4_0435.jpg" n="3"/>organizations joined the committee. These were the Lesnicky Dvur Jan Zizka (Court John Zizka of the Order of Bohemian Foresters), and the Loze Svatopluk Cech Jednoty Taboritu (Lodge Svatopluk Cech of the Taborites). Mr. Vaclav Roubal was elected as first president, the office of the vice-president went to Mrs. K. Pecival; Mr. F. Rek became the secretary; Mrs. J. Sinagla was the financial secretary; and Mr. A. Konvalinka was elected treasurer.</p>
   <p>The new organization started its preparatory and preliminary work immediately, and in the April meeting of the following year, the educational council announced that it had rented a school-room on Kedzie Avenue. May 8 of the same year witnessed the registration of pupils. The first instructor was Mr. J. Meduna, but shortly after that he was succeeded by Mr. K. Sima. By the end of May the schools attendance was 103 pupils. In the spring of the year 1898, it was necessary to add another grade, and one year later the whole school was moved to the Sokol Chicago building. Mr. Bohumil Hladky was at that time appointed its headmaster. This gentleman was active for about <pb facs="5418478_4_0436.jpg" n="4"/>twenty years in the Náprstek school.</p>
   <p>In March, 1901, the third grade was organized; a year after that the fourth; and the continued growth of the school convinced its representatives and its devoted workers that the time had come to think about the erection of a school building. This resulted in the purchase of a plot of ground on Homan Avenue, and on April 2, 1911, the cornerstone was laid.</p>
   <p>On July 9, the new building was ready for occupancy, and since that day it has not only sheltered the largest Bohemian-American school, but has also provided space for the numerous meetings of our many societies.</p>
   <p>This year the school is attended by 552 pupils who compose the daily, the Saturday, and the Sunday classes. The present faculty consists of the following: Mr. U. Ulach, the Misses E. Kovar, F. Hulka, L. Weiner, and M. H. Beranek, and Mr. A. Machek.</p>
   <p>One of the happy results of the enthusiastic labor of the teaching staff was <pb facs="5418478_4_0437.jpg" n="5"/>the organization of the Vojta Náprstek Junior Club, which is the largest and the most active organization of this sort in the United States. The Club was founded in 1918, and since that time has been uninterruptedly active, particularly in arranging theatrical productions and other fine entertainments. The membership of the Club is reserved for the alumni of the Náprstek school who are between the ages of 14 to 18, and it is desirable that every member of the adolescent group belong to this wonderful organization.</p>
   <p>The annual celebration to commemorate the founding of Vojta Náprstek school was held yesterday afternoon and evening in the hall of Sokol Chicago, and it was very well attended. The afternoon program began with an opening speech by Mr. Richard Dusil, who is the chairman of the council under the direction of which the Junior Club functions. He greeted the audience warmly, expressing his joy over the successes the school has had during the first twenty-five years of its unselfish labor. The next speaker on the program was Mr. H. Hruby, who....spoke about the meaning of a Bohemian school.....This was followed by <pb facs="5418478_4_0438.jpg" n="6"/>a fitting and vivid tableau presented by the pupils of the first and second daytime grades and those of the second grade in the Saturday classes under the direction of Miss F. Hulka, an instructor.....</p>
   <p>The afternoon program terminated with a two-act play for children, "Carovna Pistalka" (The Enchanted Whistle), performed by the pupils.....The program was successful, and several dance numbers added to the enjoyment of those present. The dances were performed by the pupils of Mrs. Libuska Bartusek-Brown....</p>
   <p>The evening program was managed and carried out by the Junior Club and the fourth grade pupils of the Saturday and Sunday classes; under the supervision of Mr. F. Vlach, an instructor. The poem, "Jubilejni Vzpominka" ( A Jubilee Memory), from the pen of Mr. A. J. Havranek, was the opening number.....This was followed by the ever-popular legendary play, "Strakonicky Dudak" (The Bagpiper of Strakonice), by Josef K. Tyl. Its production bore witness to the fact that it was conscientiously and diligently studied and rehearsed.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0439.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The celebration of the anniversary was highly successful, and we wish for the school, upon its entry into the second quarter-century of its life, that its unselfish efforts and the self-sacrificing labors of its patrons and the faculty may be accompanied by continued success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
