<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-03">July 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Public Gymnastic Exhibition of the Chicago Sokol Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0982</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0982.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-03">July 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION OF THE CHICAGO SOKOL UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A public gymnastic exhibition of the Sokols of Chicago and vicinity was held yesterday afternoon at the Cermak Athletic Field, West 26th Street and Kostner Avenue. All the local Sokol organizations that were organized into the Zupa Stredni (Central District [of the American Sokol Union]) have drilled diligently for weeks in preparation for this event. On this occasion the famous battle of Zborov (July 2, 1917) was commemorated. That battle was fought by the Czechoslovak brigade, the first unit of an independent Czechoslovak revolutionary army that covered itself with glory. One may compare that unit with the famous [ancient] Greek army at Thermopylae. Thus yesterday's Sokol exhibition had a double significance. The attendance was unusually large, and the field, which is said to accommodate more than four thousand people, was filled to capacity....The Sokols, who paraded from the Sokol Chicago, were not fully represented, however. Besides the four flag bearers, we counted no more than forty-six <pb facs="5418478_4_0983.jpg" n="2"/>red shirts, fifteen blue shirts, and eighteen who marched in their civilian clothes. As an attenuating circumstance, it may be mentioned that many members, instead of parading, came to the athletic field directly. Yet, the situation cannot be excused because the Central District consists of about four thousand members, and these could certainly furnish enough people to march together. The nucleus of the parade consisted of junior members who joined the procession in front of the Havlicek-Tyrs Hall on 26th Street and Lawndale Avenue.</p>
   <p>It was nearly 3 P. M. when the parade reached the athletic field. The marchers then stood at attention in front of the tribune from which festive speeches were delivered. The president of the Central District, Dr. Anton Mueller, addressed the audience in the name of the Sokols; Mr. Frana Klepal spoke for the Czechoslovak Legionnaires. Both of them spoke appreciatively about the work done by the Sokols, mentioning the great services this national organization rendered to its nation from the time of its <pb facs="5418478_4_0984.jpg" n="3"/>beginning to the day of the battle of Zborov. That battle outshown all other subsequent victories [of the Czechoslovak armies]. It is to be regretted that the beautiful words of both these men could not be heard except by those standing near the speakers' platform. After the speakers finished with their addresses, the band, directed by Vaclav Husa, played the [Bohemian] national anthem "Kde Domov Muj" (Where Is My Home?). The audience remained....standing during the playing of the anthem....An intermission followed.</p>
   <p>The main program started with the children's games. These consisted of six groups of girls and four of boys....The larger girls, of whom there were one hundred and forty-four, gave some good examples of precision drills, and were later followed by one hundred boys....The execution of both groups was excellent and astonished the onlookers by its precision. No less effective were the Indian club and wand exercises. In the former number, seventy-six girls participated, and the wand exercise was executed <pb facs="5418478_4_0985.jpg" n="4"/>by forty-five young boys.....</p>
   <p>Three top-ranking teams then drilled with the horse and the horizontal bars....It was really a pleasure to behold their exemplary work, particularly that of Jindrich Smidl and Vaclav Stransky....whose drills on the horizontal bars were the quintessence of elegance and precision, and would, no doubt, have insured many points in their favor had this been a competitive affair. On this day, however, they reaped in well-deserved acclamations for a performance that on other occasions would gain them credit in competitive points. Their horse drill was also proof of their great physical fitness.</p>
   <p>Side by side with their brother Sokols, the women members, of whom there were one hundred and thirty-two, also made a good showing. They performed an exercise with wands to the accompaiment of the "Beseda" [a Czech folk dance]; the spectators had an opportunity to evaluate their well-known work. The credit for it goes to Josef Cermak, the mere mention of whose <pb facs="5418478_4_0986.jpg" n="5"/>name is a sufficient guarantee of excellence. The drill itself was fine, marred only by the inadequate grouping of the women. In this respect they were not as good as the male members whose bearing and falling in line were perfect. A group of ninety men performed with an almost machine-like precision. These precision drills were truly admirable and did full honor to our boys.</p>
   <p>The program ended with the performance of groups consisting of sixteen men each. The first of these was performed by members of the Central District, the second by the victorious Czech and Slovak team. These numbers were examples of beauty that one does not easily forget. The women's group had been drilled for the occasion by Mrs. Milada Prchal who also instructed the adolescents and the children; the male group was under the supervision of Stanislav Matoska and Jarka Jelinek. Mr. Anton J. Cermak attended, accompanied by a group of notables, mainly outstanding leaders of the German Turnverein. They carried away a fine impression [of our Sokol efforts].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
