<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-23">Mar. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Carpenter Course at Harrison High School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-23">Mar. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CARPENTER COURSE AT HARRISON HIGH SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Harrison High school, about which we are always glad to report to our readers, several departments have been created which give the adolescent pupil a fair knowledge of things practical, useful in later life, even if he should not follow up the particular line as a means of living. One of these is the department for carpentry, where the beginners are instructed in the use of tools. The course can be completed in four years, but it is not being conducted throughout the entire school year.</p>
   <p>We are particularly interested in the large number of youths of Czech descent who take advantage of the opportunity offered. There is a weekly lecture dealing with carpentry where instruction by moving pictures plays an important part. The patterns worked out by the pupils demonstrate gratifying results.</p>
   <p>There are graduation exercises held in this department today, in which three Czech youngsters, pupils in the fourth year, are to receive diplomas, which <pb facs="5418478_4_0561.jpg" n="2"/>will serve as certificates of finished apprenticeship, and also as good references. The exercises will be concluded with a musical entertainment, and addresses by the principal of the school and his assistant. The school orchestra will be the main attraction on the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
