<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-03">Apr. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Austria, a Danger for Europe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0867</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0867.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-03">Apr. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AUSTRIA, A DANGER FOR EUROPE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A lecture was held by Professor J. J. Zmrhal before the members of the Chicago Press Club and guests publicly admitted last Thursday. The members of this influential club are in the majority recruited from writers and journalists. Professor Zmrhal is secretary for the English language section of the central committee of the Ceske Narodni Sduzeni (Czech National Association). His lecture, which made a lasting impression upon the audience, reached a climax in his ultimate conclusion that Austria is the greatest danger for Europe, and that it must, in the interest of peace, be partitioned into its prime national units. The lecture was very favorably commented on by the English language press of Chicago, particularly by the Journal, which gave it considerable space. This paper featured a big headline "Austria Called Danger of Europe," and quoted Professor Zmrhal several times. It says:</p>
   <p>"Professor Zmrhal proclaimed that the dual monarchy should be split into <pb facs="5418478_4_0868.jpg" n="2"/>small democratic states. There is no room in Europe for Austria, and as long as it exists, it will be a peril to durable peace." Professor Zmrhal was guest of honor at the luncheon. The subject of his lecture was "New Europe." Professor Zmrhal asserted that the hardest part in the conclusion of peace will be the Austrian question "It is certain that the Germans will do everything in their power to keep Austria-Hungary intact, while the Allies will seek to dismember it, for they can see the danger to peace if it were left unscathed. The Allies are also aware of the fact that Austria-Hungary is a mere vassal of Germany, and that if Austria-Hungary were left undivided, Germany would begin a new aggression against the East in which it would be successful. The United States will play an important part in the negotiations for the establishment of peace, and it should use its influence, which no doubt, will be considerable, toward the breaking up of the impossible conglomeration of nations within the borders of the dual monarchy. New democratic states should be created out of it as a guaranty for lasting peace."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0869.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Professor Zmrhal further spoke of Russia, and of Professor Milyukov, now Russian minister of Foreign Affairs. The minister is primarily interested in perfect freedom for the people. "Professor Milyukov is in complete accord with England, France, and Italy, "Professor Zmrhal declared, "as to the liberation of the oppressed nations, and will work for it in Central Europe and other parts as far as the influence of Russia can reach." Thus far was the report of the Chicago Journal.</p>
   <p>Another paper, the Evening Post, uses as a headline "Austria Must Perish, Says Czech Speaker," for its report on the lecture, and quotes Professor Zmrhal as saying that Austria-Hungary must be excluded from "New Europe" if the peace concluded at the close of the War is to be a lasting one. Whoever wishes to save Austria wishes to save despotism, serfdom, and inefficiency. If Austria is saved, then Germany has won the War, no matter what it has lost on the other hand.</p>
   <p>Several hundred men of letters, and from newspaperdom were present at the <pb facs="5418478_4_0870.jpg" n="4"/>lecture. The information given to them was thus well put into service for our cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
