<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-08">June 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Festival of the Czecho-Slavonic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1783</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1783.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-08">June 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVAL OF THE CZECHO-SLAVONIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 4, 1922, at 3 P.M., a festival held by the Americka Ruze (American Rose) Lodge No. 26 of the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Czecho-Slavonic Union). This is the fourth new lodge established by the Union this year. The festival was held in the Town of Lake where, thanks to the efforts of the members residing in that part of the city, the event was entirely successful. It was noticeable from the large attendance that the interest in the Union was great.</p>
   <p>The induction of the new members was performed by Dr. Neuman in the presence of all the chief officers of the Union. The doctor spoke in both the English and the Bohemian languages with great sincerity. Several other speakers followed him on the program; it should be said that most of them were ladies who are very active in this branch of the Jednota. The installation ceremony over, the new chairman took charge of the meeting, and by the sincerity of his speech, proved that he will be a worthy member of the new organization and fulfill the <pb facs="5418478_4_1784.jpg" n="2"/>duties of his office.</p>
   <p>The program ended with the showing of motion pictures. The machine for this being rather expensive, it was decided to use it for other lodges of the Jednota, especially for the use of the children's sections. The Jednota has over one thousand children in its children's insurance plan. The movie operator, Mr. Vales, will see to it that appropriate pictures are shown on all such occasions. We wish the best of luck to the new organization!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
