<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-01">Sept. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Again Among Own People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 a (Polish)</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-01">Sept. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">AGAIN AMONG OWN PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our dear and really rare guests, the delegation,and the model team of the Ceskoslovenska Obec Sokolska (Czechoslovak Sokol Community) of Prague, were entertained last night in accordance with a program arranged in advance, by the members of the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Slavsky (Gymnastic Union Sokol Slavsky). For this occasion the Jednota invited all its members and their guests to its gymnasium at West 18th and South May Streets. Let us say right at the beginning that the membership evidenced a great deal of understanding and appreciation of the occasion because the great hall of the building was filled to the last seat long before the beginning of the program. The guests from the old country were brought in at 9:00 P.M. by the commander of the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Slavsky, Brother Hak, and were greeted by a stormy "Na Zdar!" (To Success!) by the assembled multitude.</p>
   <p>After the guests were seated at the tables reserved for them (the hall was furnished with long dining tables and chairs) the program begam with a number <pb facs="5418478_4_1060.jpg" n="2"/>of selections played by the orchestra of Brother V. Husa. Then Brother Hak addressed the guests, remarking that the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Slavsky is the mother union of all "red-shirt" Sokols in America, and told them that the Jednota, without ever expecting anything in return but the satisfaction of a duty well done, has been working unselfishly, and serving in matters of importance to the progress of the Sokoldom, the Czechoslovak nation, and humanity in general.....</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Ceskoslovenska Obec Sokolska, and its secretary, Brother Pelikak, replied on behalf of all the guests from abroad by assuring the American hosts that they feel just as if they were at home among their own people. He said that he was speaking as the representative of the oldest Sokol unit, the Sokol Prazsky (Prague Sokol). He thanked all for their kindness and thoughtfulness, especially Brother Hak for the care and attention he has been showing to the delegation.....</p>
   <p>In the meantime,Brother A. M. Hess, with members of the Pevecky Sbor "Filaretow" <pb facs="5418478_4_1061.jpg" n="3"/>(Filarets Singing Society [a Polish organization]) entered the hall and announced that the Polish singing society had come to show their esteem to the Czechoslovak Sokols by presenting a few selections. This announcement was enthusiastically received.....</p>
   <p>Thereafter Mrs. Ruzena Svoboda recited two beautiful poems, and Mrs. Bozena Hess, a sister Sokol, and a well-known singer of national and folk songs, presented three selections.....</p>
   <p>Finally there were short addresses by a number of our Chicago Sokol members to which the guests replied in a most fitting manner.....</p>
   <p>The delegates from the old country spent the day downtown visiting the principal department stores and the Art Institute. At noontime they lunched at Palace Inn.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
