<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-01">May 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Volume Twenty-Two</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-01">May 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">VOLUME TWENTY-TWO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Denni Hlasatel has completed the twenty-first year of its activity among Bohemians of Chicago and America, and with today's issue it begins its twenty-second volume. The Hlasatel can look with pride and joy upon the work it has accomplished and at the same time look toward the future with highest hopes. If it continues to serve the interests of our people faithfully, if it continues to strive to furnish its readers with interesting reports and a rich selection of educational reading matter, and by prompt and regular deliveries to ingratiate itself, then it will continue to enjoy the favor which it has earned thus far. The publishers and all the old newspaper workers employed by the Hlasatel will endeavor in this twenty-second year to carry on in the same tradition which so endeared the Hlasatel to the Bohemian people, and at the same time they will strive for the further improvement of the paper and the increase of its circulation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0184.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the past year a night shift was instituted in our plant. This makes it possible for us to make deliveries early in the morning, at the same time the English papers are delivered. This arrangement is very much appreciated by our public, and the best proof of this is the rapidly mounting number of subscribers from the date of this innovation. Larger expenses are involved, night work has many disadvantages and hardships, but we gladly take any action so long as we receive the sweetest reward to newspapermen--recognition by our readers.</p>
   <p>We beg all of our readers and friends to continue their regard for us in undiminished measure. They will manifest their friendship for us best when they not only subscribe to our paper themselves, but also recommend it to their friends and acquaintances. Our readers also help us when they are kind enough to advise us when anything important or interesting happens in their neighborhood. Telephone contact with our plant can be made any time of the day or night by calling Canal 427.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0185.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We cherish the firm hope that even in the future we shall be able to keep and increase the regard which our readers have shown us during the past twenty-one years.</p>
   <p>We remain respectfully,</p>
   <p>The Publishers of Denni Hlasatel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
