<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-09">Sept. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Record Enrollment in Bohemian Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0574</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0574.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-09">Sept. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">RECORD ENROLLMENT IN BOHEMIAN SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This year's enrollment of children in Bohemian schools has been looked forward to with a great deal of interest on the part of our public, and--let us be frank--with some apprehension, also. This, because it was for the first time in the history of Chicago schools that the energetic efforts of our Bohemian member of the Chicago Board of Education, Mr. Joseph A. Holpuch, succeeded in obtaining the School Board's permission to use, for the teaching of the Bohemian language and home lore, the same building in which the children get instruction in other subjects, that is, permission to have the classes in these two subjects in public school buildings. This success must be fully appreciated. It must be borne in mind that this permission means an increase in the school budget of fully $33,000, and we must also remember that this permission means an important recognition of our colony in the City of Chicago, and act accordingly. Furthermore, it means that we need not be ashamed of our language, and everyone of our children has now the opportunity of learning it in his public school, and has every reason to be proud of that fact. It means that the name "Bohemian" <pb facs="5418478_4_0575.jpg" n="2"/>has a good sound in America, and that the School Board believes it is possible to be a good American and yet not forget the Bohemian language.</p>
   <p>This permission is also important in a hygienic respect. The children will be studying in large, airy, sanitary rooms, fully and properly equipped for school use--rooms with which they are well acquainted and which are close to their homes. Hence they offer every possible comfort and convenience. In saying this we are far from trying to imply that every effort has not been made to do all that could be done to offer similar conveniences in rooms where Bohemian classes were being held last year, and where all our Saturday and Sunday Schools will be held this year also.</p>
   <p>But, we shall confess, we were somewhat afraid that we should be unable to take full advantage of the affability of the School Board, and thus find ourselves in the disagreeable, embarrassing situation of having, all of a sudden, ample school rooms and of being unable to fill them with pupils. Our apprehensions were a result of our observation that, seemingly, our younger generation does <pb facs="5418478_4_0576.jpg" n="3"/>not love its mother tongue as much as was the case with our fathers. No doubt there have been many instances where our euphonious language was discounted and not fully appreciated. However, we are happy to say that our anxiety was quite unnecessary. On the very first day of enrollment it was proved that we can rely on our countrymen to do the right thing, that the love of our mother tongue has not died among our people, and that we know how to show publicly our own self-esteem. The first day proved that we are interested in the education of our youth, and that we know our own value in the international arena. All this gives us the more reason for rejoicing the more we realize that we cannot and must not rely on anybody or anything but ourselves and our own strength.</p>
   <p>The first day of enrollment was a very lively one. The parents brought their children in large numbers. But the real thing was yesterday, the second day. Yesterday, some of the enrollment offices were filled to capacity, and more. The faces of the parents and the children showed how glad they were of this opportunity, how the children are looking forward <pb facs="5418478_4_0577.jpg" n="4"/>to the beginning of the school year. The results of the enrollment are commensurable to these feelings.</p>
   <p>As far as we could ascertain yesterday, the greatest enrollment was in the Gary School on Lawndale Avenue and 30th Street. There it amounted to 325 children. Next strongest was the Jungmann School on Loefler and 18th Streets with 200 children. The Corkery School on Kildare Avenue and 25th Street had 189, the Cooper School on 19th Street near Ashland Avenue had 145 children. The Throop School had 100 children the first day, to which a number was added yesterday. The exact numbers will not be known until today, when the respective committee of the School Board meets and when the executive committee receives detailed reports on the enrollment. But even these partial results show that the work of our committee on schools, conducted by Chairman Topinka, Mrs. Hrisna, Mrs. Kubica, Dr. Miller, Mr. B. Kral, and Mr. K. Beranek, met with complete and pleasant success. It is now up to our parents to see to it that the enthusiasm we are now <pb facs="5418478_4_0578.jpg" n="5"/>witnessing does not ebb in the course of the year, and that they make sure that their children get the full benefit of the advantages given to us by the Chicago Board of Education.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
