<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-13">Nov. 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">To the Czechs of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, Chicago)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-13">Nov. 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CZECHS OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, Chicago)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friends: We deem it our duty to tell you about the work we love to perform so much--patriotic work for our people--and which we are willing to continue whole-heartedly.</p>
   <p>The early members of our organization won the Cup, the first prize, in recognition of the high standards which govern our system of physical culture. Our patriotic sentiment, on the other hand, was demonstrated when we sent thirtyfive of our sturdiest boys as volunteers into the United States Army, and we were among the first to take an action of this sort. There is no other Sokol group that gave better proof, in spirit and actual sacrifice, of their high conception of national spirit. It was our member, Nedelka, who was the first to lay down his life upon the altar of our tortured old homeland; who died <pb facs="5418478_4_1176.jpg" n="2"/>fighting with the Canadian Army upon the battlefields of France. Our foremost workers gave their time and energy to the Czech National Alliance, and the absence of the volunteers is also markedly felt in our ranks.</p>
   <p>Although we carry additional financial burdens which are growing daily, we still gladly place our hall at the disposal of various organizations such as the Czech National Alliance, the Red Cross, the Czechoslavonic committee, and others without charge.</p>
   <p>Under the circumstances, it is only natural that we saw the necessity for action which would place our financial affairs on a firm basis, enabling us to continue to support national purpose and pursue the struggle.</p>
   <p>With this in mind we have formed a theatrical group composed of amateur actors who are to give performances, the proceeds of which will be used for some necessary expenses and national enterprises of our organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1177.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We appeal to the Czech public, asking their generous support of our projects. This will encourage us toward further work for the independence of our old homeland. We shall always stand in the front ranks and make sacrifices in a joyful spirit, being guided by the slogan of Tyrs, the founder of our organizations: "We crave neither profit nor glory!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
