<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-05">May 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Sokol Tabor Will Erect a New Building</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1020</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1020.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-05">May 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SOKOL TABOR WILL ERECT A NEW BUILDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Novy Tabor district [New Tabor: a Bohemian district of Chicago] will get its new social and national center. This news was announced at the last meeting of the Sokol Tabor yesterday. The building which will house the Sokol is to be a dignified structure, modern in every respect. The meeting at which this far-reaching and important decision was made, took place last night in a humble wooden frame house, situated on 13th Street, where all the present activities of the Sokol are being conducted. It was well attended by the members of the Sokol who took active part in the deliberations, and judging from their enthusiasm the project will be a success.</p>
   <p>The Sokol Tabor which consists of the members of the old Sokol Slovanska Lipa (Sokol Slavonic Linden Tree) and the members of the Sokol Slavoj all of whom have united with the Sokol Tabor, owns three building sites at 16th Street and Karlov Avenue, measuring 75 by 108 feet. On this plot of land the new <pb facs="5418478_4_1021.jpg" n="2"/>organization will erect its building. The preliminary plans have been approved and detailed specifications will follow. The latter have been entrusted to a building committee of seven men who, later on, will supervise the building operations. The new structure will measure 68 by 69 feet; it will be thoroughly modern, and will contain a spacious gymnasium which will also accommodate large meetings and theatrical productions. The stage will be movable so that extra space might be provided when necessary. There will be two lodge halls, a dining room, etc.; in short, nothing shall be omitted that will make the building both useful and practicable. The old building which this Sokol association owns at 13th Street and Karlov Avenue, will be offered for sale. It seems that there will be no difficulty in disposing of this old building, in fact, a buyer has already been found, and his terms are acceptable.</p>
   <p>In order that all financial matters might be speedily adjusted an eight-man committee has been appointed....Its members are men of experience and energy as is the case of the men who compose the building committee. The financial <pb facs="5418478_4_1022.jpg" n="3"/>committee will work among the members of the Sokol and among other interested people. In order that subscriptions may be secured, a bond issue will be floated; the individual shares of which will have a face value of one hundred or more dollars each.</p>
   <p>A meeting of both of these committees will be called as soon as possible, and there is no doubt that the results of their work will soon become apparent and gladden not only all the Czechoslovaks residing in the New Tabor district, but all the Sokols of this new organization. As soon as the blueprints are ready a photostatic copy will be published in the newspapers, and all other details will likewise be announced.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
