<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-26">May 26, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">In Memory of Karel Havlicek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-26">May 26, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">IN MEMORY OF KAREL HAVLICEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Association for the Erection of the Karel Havlicek-Borovsky Monument has taken upon itself the task of continuing to function as the Havlicek Association and of commemorating each year the unveiling of the monument to the Brixen martyr. This year it has recognized the advisability of summoning our future generation--that is, the pupils of the Free Thought schools, the youth and pupils of the Sokol gymnastic schools, and youth clubs of many other societies to a commemoration service at the monument.</p>
   <p>All pupils of schools or gymnasiums will gather at their headquarters on Saturday afternoon, July 27, and then will proceed with their instructors to Douglas Park and march to the monument. The speakers present at the monument will explain to them in Bohemian and English who Karel Havlicek was and why a monument to him was erected in Chicago. Here our children will promise to guard it as a national bequest for future generations after we old immigrants have passed on. Following the ceremonies at the park, there will be a parade to the Pilsen Brewery Park pavilion where our <pb facs="5418478_4_1501.jpg" n="2"/>youth will hold a celebration. The net proceeds of the affair will be donated to our Free Thought schools.</p>
   <p>In order that the interest in this celebration may be as great as possible, there will be a ticket sales competition. Any boy from a school or gymnasium who sells the largest number of tickets will receive a special remembrance of the occasion, and the school or gymnasium which sells the largest number of tickets will be given an American flag with Bohemian streamers, and the pupils will be able to use it at every celebration.</p>
   <p>The Sokol Zupa Fuegner-Tyrš (Fuegner-Tyrš Gymnastic Society) in its last meeting adopted this idea and is willing to work for the good of the Free Thought schools in every way possible. The Fuegner-Tyrš group has already elected its delegates, and we hope that the same will happen in the Narodní Jednota Sokolská (National Sokol Union) so that all our Freethinking youth may be gathered together.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1502.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next meeting of the Monument Association and of all delegates from other organizations will be held at 8 P. M., May 29, in Mr. Andel's coffee shop across from the Pilsen Auditorium.</p>
   <p>F. Martinek, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
