<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-10-08">Oct. 8, 1880</date><title level="a">Bohemian English School of 8th Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0757</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0757.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-10-08">Oct. 8, 1880</date><title level="a">BOHEMIAN ENGLISH SCHOOL OF 8TH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What progress has been made in behalf of the school, formerly conducted by the St. James Lodge and now temporarily housed in the "Tel. Jed. Sokol" (Gymnastic Union Sokol) building, is known to our public, especially to the readers of Svornost. (Harmony)</p>
   <p>At the last meeting of the citizens of the 8th Ward it was resolved not only to maintain the school but to build it up, and to that end invite all Bohemian Liberal Lodges to be of the utmost assistance in this respect. There was elected a special committee and it sent a proclamation to 45 Bohemian Lodges in Chicago requesting that they take this matter under consideration and make some decision as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>May we be permitted once more to add a few remarks in behalf of this matter? We and with us, surely every cooperative, educated person must admit the importance of a Bohemian-English school in this land. Therefore, it is the duty of every Bohemian to participate in the spread of knowledge, the establishment, and the improvement of these schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0758.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It should be the concern of every Bohemian to see to it that his child can learn correctly the use of it's mother tongue so as to acquire a Bohemian foundation. He is not excused from his duty toward his nationality because he has no children. If he has a school in his own neighborhood, he should remember that be also sought the help of others in his undertaking and he should be pleased that others of this countrymen are about to follow his example, therefor he should be of assistance to them with advice and in any other way possible.</p>
   <p>As has been previously said; the committee has dispatched their requests to all of our national lodges and it is hoped that the request will not be denied. The object of our dealings is not an impossibility but can very easily be accomplished with ease through united effort. The committee is hopeful of soon receiving some encouraging reports and it should not be disappointed in its expectations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
