<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-08">Sept. 8, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">They Are Gone but Will Return</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-08">Sept. 8, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THEY ARE GONE BUT WILL RETURN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our beloved and truly honored guests, a delegation of five representatives and the model Sokol group, sent to us, from far overseas, by the Ceskoslovenska Obec Sokolska (Czechoslovak Sokol Community) of Prague, to the first Slet (Sokol mass convention) of the Americka Obec Sokolska (American Sokol Community), have left. But they have not gone for good. They will return; they will return next Monday. But that will be only for a few hours, and then we shall part definitely. It will not be an easy good-by. The hearts of many of us will be heavy. We have learned to know our guests as men of sterling character, enthusiastic Sokol workers, Czechoslovaks excelling not only by their fluent and beautiful Czech language, but also by their true Czechoslovak hearts, and, last but not least, idealists who put their ideals in practical use as good republicans and true democrats. All those of us who have had the opportunity of learning to know them as such have become firmly attached to them. That could not be helped. The boys, even though there are old-timers among them, have <pb facs="5418478_4_1051.jpg" n="2"/>succeeded in winning everybody's hearts by their ways. We are happy, therefore, that we may say that they, too, enjoyed their stay among us. They hated to leave, just as those who went to say good-by to them yesterday hated to lose them, even though it was just for a few days.</p>
   <p>But it was duty that called them. And since it was a Sokol duty they did not hesitate but went gladly, with ardent hearts, to gather new laurels for the wreath of glorious successes they will take back to Czechoslovakia. They went, to gather furthur laurels, to Cedar Rapids, Iowa, and to St. Louis, Missouri. They will then complete the wreath in the East--after another short stop in Chicago--just before giving the final farewell to America; they will take it to our liberated country, not only as a proof of their own personal success, but as a proof of the life pulsating in Czechoslovak America, which now feels better for their visit--strengthened, and ready for long years of struggle in which it will never forget the beloved Republic of Czechoslovakia.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1052.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The guests called at our office yesterday morning to say good-by both to our editorial staff and to our technical personnel. They all came. On behalf of the publishers of the Denni Hlasatel, each of them was presented with a little token of esteem, a gold fountain pen, as a souvenir of their sojourn in Chicago. The boys seemed quite moved by that little evidence of thoughtfulness. This was shown by the leader of the delegation, Brother Rudolf Bilek, when he approached the president of our publishing company, Mr. Vladimir Spatny, and thanked him for everything the Denni Hlasatel has done for the Slet in general and for the delegation from Czechslovakia in particular. His emotional mood culminated in the request that the Denni Hlasatel continue working for Sokoldom and the Czechoslovak cause with success equal to that it has achieved so far, remarking that it is primarily the work of the Czechoslovak press in America on which the future of Czechoslovak American depends.</p>
   <p>The president of our company said that no member of the delegation or the model group could fully appreciate the joy with which we had been looking.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1053.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>forward to their arrival; they could not know how glad we are, throughout Czechoslovak America, that we have met them, and how happy we are at their success; and, he said, speaking on behalf of our paper, we have only done what we considered to be our duty, and tried to do it as well as our modest means would permit. And that duty we expect to do everywhere and always in the future.</p>
   <p>Due to the kindness of Brother Jan Kostecka of the undertaking establishment of Cermak &amp; Kostecka, the delegation was given a special car in which to go to Cedar Rapids. They were accompanied by the commander of the Americka Obec Sokolska and his wife.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
