<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-02">May 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Gymnastic Exhibition and Entertainment Given by the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1026</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1026.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-02">May 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION AND ENTERTAINMENT GIVEN BY THE SOKOL HAVLICEK-TYRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs prepared a real treat for its friends. This included not only gymnastic performances, but also some very fine artistic numbers, both vocal and instrumental. That the entertainment attracted so a large number of our people was most astonishing considering the unsually beautiful weather. Thanks to the efforts of the entertainment committee, the event was a successful one both financially and socially. The hall was filled to capacity....</p>
   <p>The following were the numbers on the program: Address by the local manager of the Sokol, V. Simaner; sitting-up exercises by six young pupils; the brothers, Jiri and Louis Solar, xylophone duet; Mr. Louis Solar played Sergei Rachmaninov's "Prelude in C Sharp Minor" on the concert piano;....Miss Jane Cervenka sang an aria from Anton Dvorak's "Rusalka" (Nymph), Vymetal's popular song, "U Studanky" (At the Well), and "Bratrum Americanum" (To Our Brother Americans). <pb facs="5418478_4_1027.jpg" n="2"/>In the last number she was accompanied by the Solar brothers on the xylophone.... This group of musical numbers was followed by more gymnastic exercises performed by the young girls of the Sokol. A group of thirty boys formed a picturesque pyramid calling forth a veritable storm of applause.... The adult male groups then performed on the stationary trapeze, and some of their exercises were truly bravura in quality. Another group of musical pieces followed this. Mrs. Marie Matejcek-Ort sang an aria from Bedrich Smetana's Opera, "Prodana Nevesta" (Bartered Bride) ....being faultlessly accompanied on the piano by Miss Augusta Durchanek. Mr. Milada Prchal supervised a gymnastic exercise of a select group of her pupils....which was accompanied by songs....This performance was greatly admired because of its realism, and it may be looked upon as a new success in Mrs. Prchal's career. No less imposing was the performance of twelve male members of the local Sokol; this group was meant to symbolize certain dramatic war activities. It was worked out by Franta Erben and staged by Stanislav Matoska. It is a gymnastic feat which imposes upon its performers an almost <pb facs="5418478_4_1028.jpg" n="3"/>unbelievable task. In spite of the great difficulties, however, it was perfectly performed, and when the boys finally reached the apotheosis in this choreographic masterpiece the applause which ensued had no end. J. Turek then recited several poems touching upon Sokoldom and its ideals, and his clear and sonorous enunciation earned him well deserved approbation. The remainder of the evening was devoted to dancing to music played by our popular Tamburasi orchestra. [Translator's note: The tamburashi are players of tambouras, which are long-necked string instruments of Jugoslav origin, and not unlike our own mandolin except that the arrangement of strings are different.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
