<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-13">Sept. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To Editors of Czechoslovak Publications</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-13">Sept. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO EDITORS OF CZECHOSLOVAK PUBLICATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Czechoslovak department was established three months ago as a branch of the Committee on Public Information. This Committee is conducted by the United States Government, and was created at the request of President Wilson. The Czechoslovak department is required to keep a record of all Czechoslovak publications in America.</p>
   <p>We have requested all the Czechoslovak editors, whom we could locate, to send us their newspapers or magazines regularly. My request was, in the majority of cases, answered promptly. Many publications, however, have not yet been received in our offices. We ask our publishers most earnestly to mail the missing numbers as quickly as possible. I am making this appeal at the order of the Federal Government and have been sworn in as its agent. I am advising those publishers, whose papers I cannot produce and put on records, that they will be charged with lack of loyalty. Delay in sending his publication may place the publisher in an embarassing position.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0139.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>No publications of any kind are exempt from being recorded in our offices, be they Czech or Slovak, dailies or weeklies, and contain political, instructive, or humorous matter; be they trade papers, women's magazines, or magazines for children, etc.; they all have to be recorded. The same applies to organization papers and those appearing at long intervals.</p>
   <p>We also request that all numbers which have been published since September 1, 1918, be sent.</p>
   <p>We firmly trust that all Czechoslovak publishing concerns will co-operate with us in their own interest, and in the interest of our beloved Czechoslovak motherland, and so help to keep the good reputation which Czechoslovaks enjoy in our country.</p>
   <p>Thanking you for your good will,</p>
   <p>Anna S. Tvrzicky,</p>
   <p>director of Czechoslovak</p>
   <p>department.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
