<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-03-12">March 12, 1901</date><title level="a">Turks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-03-12">March 12, 1901</date><title level="a">Turks</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What a pity that at the Svornost they have a lawyer whom they are convinced is the most brilliant light in his sphere, that he overshadows all others, and this lawyer permits the reign of genuine Turkish justice in his paper! No person on earth, except a Turk, can appear with a request and an invitation such as Svornost gave us.</p>
   <p>She threw in our face false accusations and now shouts: "defend yourselves and prove that it is not true!" In every civilized land, by all civilized people, it is required that the accuser first furnish proof that his accusations are justified, and then only, when the proofs are convincing, is the accused required to defend himself. But the Turks at Svornost practice genuine Turkish justice. They shout: "We do not need to prove anything: it is up to you to prove that we lie, that we accuse you falsely." What if we, too, were of that kind, and, for instance, brought an accusation against Geringer, charging that he committeed robbery and fraud in Bohemia and that he was forced to flee to America. Then when he said he never did, we simply say, prove it! With that we would charge, as Svornost does, that the evidence must be impartial; that is, such as we would consider impartial. By such Turkish methods everyone <pb facs="5418478_4_0237.jpg" n="2"/>could accuse another of the gravest crimes and simply say; "It rests with you to prove that you killed no one, robbed no one, swindled no one, and so forth. That would be a nice condition to reign among us."</p>
   <p>Svornost made us a proposal, - that we name an impartial committee which would examine their books and ours, and in that manner prove that Loeffler and Novak have no interest in our business. This committee would be impartial only when Svornost would recognize it as such, and she would do this only when it was composed of her partisans. Then the findings would be just as Turkish as the proposal. Our secretary has the names of our shareholders entered in his books and he will show them to anyone interested in the truth. So long as Svornost continues to cling to Turkish justice so long as he does not furnish proof that her accusations are justifiable and substantiated, so long as she twists and calls, "prove that it's not true", so long will she be considered a shameful slanderer and unconscionable liar. Finally, we repeat once more; "We will give to Geringer and his heirs all our earthly possessions, if he proves the truthfulness of his charge." We know his rapacity, and we believe he will go <pb facs="5418478_4_0238.jpg" n="3"/>to any length in order to increase his wealth and get rid of hateful people, who, so many times, have shown him in his moral nudity and he had to be ashamed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
