<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Activities of Soccer Club</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. Cmelik (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVITIES OF SOCCER CLUB</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. Cmelik (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sokolsky Klub Cechie (Sokol Club Cechie) closed its season last Sunday. About four years ago, a small group of Chicago members of Sokol gymnastic societies formed a circle to foster the sport of soccer which they had played even in the old homeland.</p>
   <p>The beginning was by no means promising, for unemployment loomed and pressed in on all sides, so that it was impossible for the small circle to defray expenses involved in the practice of the sport. This obligation rested almost entirely upon the shoulders of the individual members, <pb facs="5418478_4_1184.jpg" n="2"/>which circumstance contributed in no small measure to the perpetuation of that group's athletic endeavor. The circle was gradually augmented by an influx of individuals, and so the will to compete with other clubs already existing was ever strengthened.</p>
   <p>There were several contests with the Czech Club Slavia, which had been an opponent of the circle for sometime; the latter played under the name of Cechie at that time.....</p>
   <p>In a meeting on August 16, 1915, the Cechie decided to join the International League. By this step it gained considerable power, and its successes in the fall season were surprising, as were those in the following spring. In its progress the circle advanced to a decisive contest, in which the Gauger Trophy was the prize; in this combat the Cechie lost to the Swedish Athletic Club.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1185.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During this season also, the Cechie achieved excellent results. It won nineteen games and lost two. Its defeat by the Chicago Hungarians, however, deprived it of the cup of the Third Division.....</p>
   <p>Today the Sokol Club Cechie stands on a high level, although it still has to contend with various difficulties, particularly on the financial side. As to the quality of the team, great hopes are placed in the newly recruited "Cechie Juniors".....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
