<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-10-10">Oct. 10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Good Luck to Svornost Volume 8</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0253</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0253.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-10-10">Oct. 10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD LUCK TO SVORNOST VOLUME 8</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We start volume eight of Svornost with today's issue; the first Bohemian daily in America. All of our readers and followers have seen the development of this paper; what efforts and struggles were required through the years before the paper could become self-supporting so that it could serve every good interest of our nationality independently and even dare to point out some personal and social evils without fear, urging good and warning against evil; in fact to conscientiously fulfill the duties charged to a newspaper by the claims of the entire community.</p>
   <p>Only through ignorance of former and present conditions can slander and suspicion be turned against our work, but we can excuse this because they know not what they do; and we do this in the name of all those who are interested in the success of a Bohemian daily paper and realize what our national life in Chicago would be without such a paper.</p>
   <p>A good newspaper should serve impartially all good citizens and all good things, and for that purpose it is unavoidable that it be independent and self-supporting; otherwise freedom of speech of the citizens would cease and they could not recognize it as their paper. According to this principle and <pb facs="5418478_4_0254.jpg" n="2"/>effort we have conscientiously guided ourselves and if perhaps we erred at times, we realized the results of such errors and continued onward so much more carefully. When every good citizen considers the importance of a newspaper he also realizes how far his opinions in opposition to the newspaper are suppressed, and to what limits the rights of others for representation in the public press extended.</p>
   <p>Progressive readers of our nationality can depend on it that they will find in us a true ally in a national effort for education, progress, liberty, and national harmony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
