<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1885-07-27">July 27, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">The Unveiling of the Monument of Professor Ladimir Klacel.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1885-07-27">July 27, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNVEILING OF THE MONUMENT OF PROFESSOR LADIMIR KLACEL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was really an impressive festival for our Bohemian metropolis. Thousands of people gathered at the unveiling of the monument of our great teacher, Ladimir Klacel. The festival committee was right in its decision not to have a procession led by bands; this removed the possibility of the disparagement of the Bohemian name in the opinion of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>As the Americans are mourning the loss of their best son, Ulysses S. Grant, the whole town is wrapped in deep sorrow. If we had marched in procession with a band, the local newspapers would again scold us, that we have no sentiment and no regard for the sentiments of our American co-citizens.</p>
   <p>The festival committee took the highest care not to give the smallest cause for complaints. Yesterday's procession was a real funeral procession. The participating societies marched quietly timed only by a drum, and all the banners were veiled. We have proved that we can respect the prominent men of this country, and <pb facs="5418478_4_1598.jpg" n="2"/>we were praised for this in the press.</p>
   <p>The trains brought huge masses of Bohemians to the cemetery, they formed a large circle around the monument, the orchestra played the national hymn, and the mixed choir of the singing society,Lumir, sang a dirge in lowered voices. After this many wreaths were placed on the base of the monument.</p>
   <p>A long memorial speech formally delivered the monument to the Administration of the National Cemetery with the words: "Here is the result of two years of effort, the monument of our glorified, honorable Professor Ladimir Klacel. I am turning it over to your hands to include it in the estate of the National Cemetery, to protect it and to keep it as a proud symbol of the Bohemian people and as an inspiration for the national spirit for many future generations."</p>
   <p>DESCRIPTION OF THE MONUMENT.</p>
   <p>It is located in the middle of the newly opened second division of the cemetery, <pb facs="5418478_4_1599.jpg" n="3"/>partly hidden among the trees, although it can be seen from all parts of the cemetery. It is thirteen feet high; the bust is carved in white marble, larger than life-size, two feet six inches high. The similarity of the features is exceptionally good and portrays the celebrity at the time that he lived in Chicago before his illness. The base of the monument is four by four feet square and one foot four inches high. The column is three feet ten inches high and supports the base of the bust. Except for the bust, the monument is of a greyish-blue granite, imported from the Hurricane Islands.</p>
   <p>The inscription on the front part of the pedestal is as follows:</p>
   <p>"Ladimir Klacel</p>
   <p>Born April the 7th, 1808 in Ceske Trebove,</p>
   <p>passed away March the 17th, 1882 in Belle Plaine, Iowa.</p>
   <p>Encourage yourselves-to be philosophers.</p>
   <p>Erected by the Bohemians of Chicago, July 26th, 1885 to their wise and great man."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
