<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-27">Sept. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Hearst Replies to Our Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-27">Sept. 27, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MR. HEARST REPLIES TO OUR PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, August 30, 1914, the Hearst papers, published in a number of the largest American cities, carried a reproduction of one of Holarek's famous etchings. "The Moloch's Victims." The accompanying text explained that the etching is the work of the "great Hungarian painter, Emil Holarek".</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) has protested on various occasions in the past to the editorial officers of the Hearst papers against representing Bohemian artists as members of other nations, as the papers have done in the cases of Krupka, Mucha, and Holarek, who have been represented as Frenchmen, Germans, and Hungarians. As a rule, the editors publish a correction, but this has not stopped the misrepresentations.</p>
   <p>For this reason, the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar decided to issue an <pb facs="5418478_4_0160.jpg" n="2"/>unusually sharp protest in this case. The protest was addressed not only to the chief editors of all Hearst papers in the country, but also to Mr. W. R. Hearst. The Tiskova Kancelar stated in its letter that if the protest of the Bohemians of America is not respected, all Slavic organizations will be notified of that fact.</p>
   <p>Two days later, the Chicago Examiner published a correction, in which the fact was stressed that Emil Holarek is a Bohemian, and not a German, Russian, or Hungarian artist. This, however, is not considered a satisfactory disposal of the case, because such corrections have appeared in the past and similar errors recurred.</p>
   <p>But the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar also received a letter from Mr. W. R. Hearst in New York in which, through his secretary, he assured the Bohemians that he has taken notice of their protest and will see to it that his papers do not credit other nations with Bohemian artists.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0161.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We hope that Mr. Hearst's assurance is meant seriously and that it will never again be necessary to protest against the tactlessness of his papers toward the Bohemian nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
