<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-11">July 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Soccer Players Enlisting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1162</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1162.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-11">July 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SOCCER PLAYERS ENLISTING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A group of American Czechoslovak soccer players will leave for France on July 20, to augment the ranks of the fighters for the liberation of our old homeland.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the declaration of war on Germany many members of Czech clubs hastened to show their loyalty to the United States by enlisting in Uncle Sam's service. Sometimes they did this in whole squads, as in the case of the Chicago Athletic Club, Praha (Prague), of which every member offered his services.</p>
   <p>After the creation of the Czechoslovak Army, members of our clubs, Slavia, Cechie, and Olympie, joined in numbers. Some of these volunteers are already in France, while others are about to follow. The lively correspondence, constantly carried on between those abroad and their relatives and friends here, invariably contains urgent requests: "Send us tobacco, as much as you <pb facs="5418478_4_1163.jpg" n="2"/>can!" Clubs and other associations used to send tobacco to individual soldiers. This was, however, only a drop in the sea.</p>
   <p>More and more tobacco is needed! And with this in mind, the volunteers about to depart have arranged for a soccer contest between Czech teams and those of other nationalities, and have fixed the date for Sunday, July 14, one week before their departure. The proceeds will be used to buy tobacco for our soldiers in France. The Bricklayers' playground, 35th Street and Went-worth Avenue, close to Comiskey Park, will be the scene of the event. The names of the players will be published next Friday. The players are only too glad to offer their services for this affair which, in spite of a low admission charge, will enable us to send greetings in the form of tobacco to our boys over there.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
