<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-06-29">June 29, 1902</date>,
<title level="a">p. 1 Masaryk's Lecture.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0941</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0941.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-06-29">June 29, 1902</date>,
<title level="a">p. 1 MASARYK'S LECTURE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friday evening there gathered in "Libuse" hall, on 12th st. boulevard a large assemblage of men and women, to listen to the lecture of the famous guest Mr. T. G. Masaryk, professor of the Bohemian University of Prague. He dealt with the present hardships and desires of the Bohemian nation. The professor, is the founder and recognized leader of the so-called people's party, and from their viewpoint he endeavored to picture the conditions in Bohemia. He showed, that the state's rights program of the other national parties is an antiquated thing, unpractical, injurious, and that for the Bohemian people cannot accept past history as a basis for present day justice but must strive to insure their natural rights under existing conditions.</p>
   <p>The professor's speech met with agreement. Many however, thought that Mr. Masaryk looks upon the struggles and desires of the Bohemian people too much from the standpoint of his party, too subjectively.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0942.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Otherwise the lecture was a complete success. The professor is a trained speaker, and complete master of the subject with which he dealt. Even to those who were not in accord with all of his doctrines, his address was a pleasure. We comfort ourselves in the thought that when he appears before the public in some large hall in Pilsen, that he will have many attentive and grateful listeners.</p>
   <p>We have been imformed that the professor's lectures at the University of Chicago did not arouse the interest among the Bohemians which they deserved. The Bohemian workingmen can not be blamed for this. They have to work at the time the lectures are given. We have however hundreds of people among us who are better off, who like to brag about their intelligence and they should endeavor to attend the lectures on Bohemian history and conditions, given at the Chicago University. These lectures should be well attended not only to become acquainted with present day conditions, but to impress the Americans and especially the University administrators with the fact that we are interested in such matters. Our rising youth should hurry "en masse" to these lectures, to acquaint themselves with the most important chapters of Bohemian History, and also that they may understand the present situation confronting the Bohemian Nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
