<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-03">Dec. 3, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Sokol Unification</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-03">Dec. 3, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">SOKOL UNIFICATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last session of the meeting of representatives of Sokol organizations was held November 29, at 11:00 A.M.</p>
   <p>The following outline of the body to be created by the unification was adopted:</p>
   <p>Article I. The name to be decided later.</p>
   <p>Article II. For the time being the body is to be composed of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska, the Delnicky Americky Sokol, and possibly the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs. Any Sokol unit may enter the body on the condition that it adopts the constitution and bylaws.</p>
   <p>Article III. The purpose of the body is the promotion of gymnastics as a means to the physical and moral uplift of the Bohemian people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1279.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Article IV. To achieve this aim, the following ways and means are to be used;</p>
   <p>Section 1. To unite Sokol and progressive units, and to establish mutual contacts between them in technical and language questions.</p>
   <p>Section 2. To conduct training courses for gymnastic teachers.</p>
   <p>Section 3. To provide gymnastic teachers for individual units.</p>
   <p>Section 4. To introduce a common system of gymnastic methods as well as a common system of ways and routines when appearing before the general public.</p>
   <p>Section 5. To secure gymnastic equipment.</p>
   <p>Section 6. To publish and acquire gymnastic and Sokol literature.</p>
   <p>Section 7. To organize public drills, contests, Slets [mass congresses], and technical educational lectures for the membership and the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1280.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Article V. The central technical committee of the body is to be composed of ten members without regard to the unit to which they may belong. An attempt should be made, however, to represent all units, or as many as possible.</p>
   <p>Article VI. The seat of the central technical committee is Chicago.</p>
   <p>Article VII. The members of this committee are to be elected as follows: Each unit nominates not more than ten candidates, either from among its own members, or from among the members of another unit of the body. From these, the groups of gymnastic teachers of all units elect the ten members of the central technical committee. The first elections to this body will be conducted by the executive committee of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska.</p>
   <p>Section 1. The central technical committee elects from among its own members a Nacelnik (commander-in-chief), two deputy commanders, a secretary, and a treasurer.</p>
   <p>Section 2. The central technical committee is always to be guided by Article IV in all its extent.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1281.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Section 3. The central technical committee has the right to suspend any one of its own members, a commander of a Zupa (Sokol district), or Obec (Sokol community), and to recommend the suspension of a commander of a Sbor (a higher Sokol unit), in case it finds that the commander does not perform his duties toward the main body.</p>
   <p>Section 4. The yearly dues are twenty-five cents for a Sokol (man) and ten cents for a Sokolka (woman Sokol). The money is to be used toward the upkeep of the main body.</p>
   <p>Section 5. Each unit turns the dues collected from its members over to the higher unit of which it is a member. The higher unit turns them over, for the time being, to the executive committee of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska, which keeps a record of all dues received, and pays bills which have been approved and submitted by the central technical committee.</p>
   <p>A Zupa, Sbor, or Obec decides by its own jurisdiction the amount <pb facs="5418478_4_1282.jpg" n="5"/>of dues to be paid by its members.</p>
   <p>This agreement becomes effective upon receipt of a notice to the effect that the unification of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska and the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs has been completed. It will remain in force for two years.</p>
   <p>In case of a dissolution of the body, its funds will be divided among the contributing units in proportion to the size of their membership.</p>
   <p>All provisions outlined above have been thoroughly discussed and approved by all members of the conference.</p>
   <p>Finally, the following recommendation proposed by Brother Hak has been approved:</p>
   <p>The conference, at which all three American Sokol unions were represented, recommends that all Sokol units join the Patronaty (patronates, boards of trustees) <pb facs="5418478_4_1283.jpg" n="6"/>of local Bohemian Free-Thought schools wherever such exist, and to establish such schools where they do not exist. The conference further recommends that such schools be maintained definitely and completely as Free-Thought schools, and proposes to introduce into these schools a common system of instruction, in order to bring about an improvement in our rather deficient schools, especially at this time, since the reformer of Bohemian schools, Benes [Vojta Benes, brother of Eduard Benes, later President of Czechoslovakia], has been invited to America. This is an aim toward which each and every Sokol should contribute by word and deed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
