<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-07">Sept. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Schools Resume Saturday and Sunday Classes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-07">Sept. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN SCHOOLS RESUME SATURDAY AND SUNDAY CLASSES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The enrollment in all schools holding Bohemian classes on Saturday or Sunday, takes place today, and next Sunday the regular work will begin on the same basis as last year. Among these are the six-grade day school run by the Patronat (Board of Trustees) Vojta Naprstek on Homan Avenue near 26th Street, and also, we believe, the school in the building of the Cesko-Anglicka Svobodomysna Skola (Bohemian-English Free Thought School) on 18th Street.</p>
   <p>The Patronat Vojta Naprstek informs us that this year the enrollment of students will take place only in September, January, and April, and no pupils will be admitted at any other time. This measure is being taken in an effort to regularize the instruction in the various classes.</p>
   <p>The schools which hold Saturday classes enrolled their students yesterday. We understand that an unusually large number of students enrolled yesterday and we hope that today's enrollment will be large enough to fulfill the highest expectations of all friends of Bohemian educational institutions. Our hopes <pb facs="5418478_4_0608.jpg" n="2"/>embrace not only schools in Chicago's Bohemian districts, such as Pilsen, California, New Tabor, Irving Park, and the Northwest Side (the Amos Komensky School in the University Settlement at Noble and Augusta Streets), and in the Town of Lake, but also the schools in our steadily growing suburban communities where our countrymen have shown a great deal of interest in Bohemian schools. Among these are the schools in Oak Park, Morton Park, Berwyn, and Hanson Park, all of which had a considerable number of pupils during the past year and should make a still better showing now.</p>
   <p>It is a sacred duty of all Bohemian parents to see to it that their children enroll in Sunday classes today. This is the only way to give them an opportunity to learn how to read and write the Bohemian language, to become familiar with Bohemian history, and to instill love of their parents' native land in their tender hearts. The best way to show our appreciation to our lodges, societies, and other groups for their support of our schools--support which is frequently possible only after sacrifices of other things have been made--is to enroll as many students as possible. Let us not forget that it is in our own and our childrens' interest to patronize Bohemian schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
