<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-06-02">June 2, 1904</date>,
<title level="a">Vraz's Lecture.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-06-02">June 2, 1904</date>,
<title level="a">VRAZ'S LECTURE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The famous traveler E. Stanislav Vraz, gave a lecture, before a large audience on Japan, Siberia, Korea and Manchuria. That this lecture was interesting need not be mentioned, because Mr. Vraz is sufficiently well known by our entire Bohemian public, for his clever presentation of facts. The lecture was particularly interesting, because of the matter with which it was concerned. The great war in the Far East interests the entire world today and the lecturer referred mainly to the countries in which this worldly war drama is being enacted. That the sympathies of the renowned traveler gravitate toward the great Slav Empire is entirely natural and was quickly proven by him. The lecturer called attention to the fact that the present great struggle in the Far East is not merely to decide the interests of Russia and Japan, but in fact the interests of the whole civilized world, which nevertheless shortsighted Americans cannot understand. Only Russia can stop the advance of the wild Asiatic hordes upon Europe and eventually upon America; and it will stop this advance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0925.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The culture of the Japanese is only superficial. In their hearts these half civilized people are really such Asiatics, as they were not long ago, hating all foreigners. There is a big difference between the well meaning, approachable Russian and the crafty, selfish, foreigner hating Japanese. For that reason, in Manchuria and Korea, for which this terrible struggle is being waged, the Russians, who live in peace with the natives, satisfying them in everything and accomodating themselves to them, are in greater favor than the Japanese, who act superior and look upon them with a certain scorn, though they are of the same race. We can not enter into a detailed account of the lecture here, because it would require too much space and time, however, we can say that no one who attended this lecture erred. Such a plastic description of the habits, morals and manner of life, of these races will not be heard again. The beautifully executed pictures, of which there were many, the work and personal property of our famous traveler, added not a little to the affair. Some of these are really rare and were obtained with great difficulty. Especially the scenes of the unknown land of Korea.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0926.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Vraz's opinion about the present was interesting. According to him there is no doubt, that the Russians were unprepared for war, because the peace-loving Czar Nicholas was confident that everything would be settled in a peaceful manner.</p>
   <p>However, the Russians will now use their entire strength to protect their honor and that of the entire Slavonic race in spite of the malicious obstructions which are being placed in their path by their eternal enemies the English and with them, alas, the continually fraternizing Americans. Japan has sent to the battlefield not only the flower of its troops, but of the entire nation, whereas Russia has sent to the battlefields only an insignificant part of it's large and excellently trained army. When its main forces arrive and especially the famous, savagely have regiments of Cossacks, the fate of the Japanese invasion of the Russian territory will be decided.</p>
   <p>The lectures pointed out with emphasis the great cultural work which the Russian nation accomplished, with small means, within the formerly unhospitable borders of eastern Asia, deducing therefrom the great consequences for the whole of Europe - and America. That, which the Russians were able to accomplish in Asia, the Japanese will never attempt. They lack both the incentive and cultural background to do so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
