<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-30">Apr. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Bohemian Ball Park Built</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1029</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1029.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-30">Apr. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A BOHEMIAN BALL PARK BUILT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Czechoslovak countrymen, who are interested in all kinds of athletics, will surely be pleased to learn that our Bohemian-American community will have its own ball park. For this we are indebted to our Czech Alderman Mr. Anton J. Cermak, who is generally known to be a friend of every kind of good, clean sport as a fan, and who is also a member of the Chicago Athletic Commission which consists of members of the city council. Mr. Cermak recently purchased an extensive plot of ground located on west 26th Street and Kostner Avenue and turned it into a ball park. The players, who will regularly play in this park, are known as the Cermak Indians, and the park itself will bear their name. It will be officially opened on May 7, 1922, although the above-named team has already played successfully in various localities.</p>
   <p>To us, the fact that most of the members of the team are of Bohemian parentage, is, of course, most interesting. The captain of the team is Mr. Albert Vanis of 2840 South Spalding Avenue; the financial secretary is Mr. F. A. Kuban <pb facs="5418478_4_1030.jpg" n="2"/>of 2532 Homan Avenue; the treasurer is Mr. James Mixan of 1922 South 63rd Avenue, Berwyn, Illinois; and the custodians of the park, Messrs. J. Konovsky and William Soper. The business manager of the team is Mr. James Kuba of 4052 West 26th Street, and his assistants are Messrs. George Kos and F. Sekosky.</p>
   <p>We were informed that the team will consist of the following players: Messrs. Charles Mazouch (pitcher), Hank Ahrendt (catcher), Joe Vit (first base), Eddie Novak (second base), Herman Suelau (shortstop), W. Kotas (third base), Jakey Chodora (center field), Bob Melichar (right field), Tubby Hornberg (left field), Al. Ludek (utility pitcher), Jimmy Stroner (utility), Joe Tyk (utility), "Lucky" Fleider (coach) and Josef Kybic (coach).</p>
   <p>We have no doubts whatsoever that our general public will not only be interested in this Czech ball park, but also in the team, and we hope that this piece of news concerning it will not be the last one.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
