<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-24">May 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Invitation to Membership in the Czech Literary Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-24">May 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">INVITATION TO MEMBERSHIP IN THE CZECH LITERARY ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Czech patriots and friends of Czech culture are being approached by the Czech Literary Association (Česká Literární Společnost) to support the aims of this organization by becoming members.</p>
   <p>Since the introduction of the Czech language into the curriculum of the Carter Harrison High School, its pupils and teachers have felt the dire need of educational supplies, especially schoolbooks. The Czech-American National Council (Česko-Americká Národní Rada) has made the first step to remove these shortcomings by publishing a Czech primer. This book was to be used for two and a half years of study, and in different grades. It did not, however, fill the purpose. It so happened that in some of the higher grades students of the Czech language were forced to discontinue their study as a result of lack of schoolbooks, and the number in some classes gradually declined, while others had to be abandoned. A similar <pb facs="5418478_4_0314.jpg" n="2"/>fate threatens Harrison High school and the High school in Berwyn. To save these and other schools, the Literary Association was created.</p>
   <p>This organization began by publishing Czech books containing selections from Czech literature. Authors such as Erben, Nĕmcová, Havlíček, Wenzig, Čelakovský, and Tille are represented. These plans received the heartiest approval on the part of Czech parents. In the forefront of demand, however, is a grammar of the Czech language, translated in the English language, which is designed for the use of the American-born pupil, and also for the many native Czechs who wish to perfect themselves in their maternal tongue. It also ought to serve ambitious pupils of other nationalities who are eager to undertake the study of Bohemian, which would aid in making foreigners better acquainted with our literature.</p>
   <p>The grammar is being prepared now, and will be ready for publication at the beginning of the next school year. This will involve considerable <pb facs="5418478_4_0315.jpg" n="3"/>expense, which is expected to be defrayed from the contributions of those interested in the plan. Help us toward the realization of our aim. God forbid that the sons of the nation which gave a Jan Amos Komenský to the world should forget their maternal tongue for lack of the necessary funds.</p>
   <p>The dues are $5 per year; life membership $10; charter membership $20. Members will receive all books published through the Association free of charge. -For the Czech Literary Society, signed: Clara M. Claus, chairman; James H. Dibelka, treasurer; Jaroslav Nigrin, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
