<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-05-30">May 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Slavonic Day at Olympic Games in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-05-30">May 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">SLAVONIC DAY AT OLYMPIC GAMES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first Sunday afternoon of the Olympic Games has been reserved for the Slavonic Gymnastic Union, which is composed of Sokols (Gymnasts) of various Slavonic nations, and for the Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Federation of Bohemian Singing Societies).</p>
   <p>The Olympic Games, a great athletic festival, will be held at a stadium specially built for this purpose on the lake front in Grant Park from June 26 to July 6. The management of the Games is composed of prominent Chicago businessmen and industrialists. We are hoping that their enterprise will surpass the Olympic Games held last year in Stockholm in scope, in the number of participants, and in attendance, and that it will be the greatest athletic event ever staged in America.</p>
   <p>The Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota decided at its recent annual meeting to <pb facs="5418478_4_1317.jpg" n="2"/>take an active part in these festivities if the management will issue an invitation to the Jednota. The secretary of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) took it upon himself to secure the invitation. Because an invitation to the Sokols was not forthcoming, suspicions had been voiced to the effect that the management did not desire the participation of the Sokols, perhaps because the former wanted to protect other organizations from Sokol competition.</p>
   <p>In order to clear up this matter and arrange for an early issuance of an invitation to the Bohemian, or rather to all Slavonic Sokols and singing societies (if the management had planned to issue such invitations), the secretary and president pro tem. of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar called on the management of the Olympic Games in the Auditorium Hotel last Monday and had a two-hour conference with the president of the Olympic Games, Mr. Lawrence Heyworth; general manager, Mr.Herbert Jorgensen; games <pb facs="5418478_4_1318.jpg" n="3"/>director, Mr. Martin A. Delaney; the chairman of the attractions committee, Mr. H. H. Lathman; and publicity director, Mr. W. H. Williams. These men held several telephone conversations with the president of the Slavonic Gymnastic Union, Mr. R. Styblo, and the president of the Ustredni Pevecka Jednota, Mr. Anton Vanek, and gave the representative of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar the assurance that the Bohemians and other Slavonic peoples will have the first Sunday afternoon of the Games reserved for their gymnastic and vocal productions. This will be Sunday, June 29. The evening of that day is reserved for the Scandinavians, and the following Sunday--the last day of the games--for the Germans.</p>
   <p>It is estimated that 300 men and women singers, 1,100 Sokols (400 men and 700 women), and 1,500 youths will take an active part in the Slavonic Day. The Slavonic Sokols will be invited to participate in the parade and contest of gymnastic organizations to be held July 4 as a part--a sensible one--of <pb facs="5418478_4_1319.jpg" n="4"/>the Independence Day celebrations. The inclusion of this event in the program of the Games had been suggested by Mr. Karel Vopicka, who is a member of the organization committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
