<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-08-02">Aug. 2, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian School in the 8th Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0749</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0749.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-08-02">Aug. 2, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN SCHOOL IN THE 8TH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reporter of this newspaper visited yesterday the Bohemian school located in the hall of the Bohemian-American Sokol. This school is supported by the women's benevolent society Calliope. The teacher, Miss Klara Rottova, who is very capable, is training the children in reading and writing Bohemian and calculating. Although the majority of the children who started to attend the school were absolutely ignorant of the Bohemian language, they are progressing very rapidly. Forty-one children are visiting the school and this is the maximum of pupils who can be harbored in the limited number of rooms of the school. What is very obstructive is the fact that the school consists of two rooms and the teacher must divide her attention between both rooms during the course of the day. At the time when the hall was built its purpose was only for meetings of various societies, and nobody had foreseen that a school would be located in it. Miss Rottova has been very satisfied <pb facs="5418478_4_0750.jpg" n="2"/>up to this time with what has been accomplished under handicap, her only sorrow is that the boys are very mischievous and very hard to discipline. We suppose the parents of the boys could be helpful in this direction. The teacher is expending all her energy for the progress of the school, to the complete satisfaction of the ladies' society Calliope, and we hope that her efforts will be suitably rewarded.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
