<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-03-26">Mar. 26, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Slovanska Gymnasticka Unie</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1333</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1333.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-03-26">Mar. 26, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">SLOVANSKA GYMNASTICKA UNIE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The powerful association of Slavonic sokol and gymnastic societies of Chicago, "Slovanska Gymnasticka Unie" (Slavonic Gymnastic Union), from which the participating groups expect so much not only in the field of gymnastics but in Slavonic reciprocal co-operation, held its first competitive meet on Sunday, March 24, in the magnificent new Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs hall located on Lawndale Avenue at 26th Street. Two hundred and eight competitors from twenty-six societies participated in the meet. This imposing figure is the best proof that the significance of this great and promising Slavonic association is fully understood and appreciated, and therefore it is not an empty phrase if we say that we can expect splendid accomplishments from the Slovanska Gymnasticka Unie in the very near future.</p>
   <p>The program for Sunday's competition was as follows: senior division: rings, parallel bars, and high jump; intermediate division: horizontal bar, vaulting horse, broad jump; junior division: horizontal bar, parallel bars, and buck.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1334.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The results in the senior division were as follows: first place, Sokol Chicago with 187.8 points; second place,Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs with 152.3 points. The individual winners were Sokol Fr. Paul of Pilsen Sokol, first place, 37.6 points; Sokol Vaclav Stransky of Pilsen Sokol, second place, 37.4 points; Sokol Jan Eiselt of Sokol Chicago, third place, 34.08 points.</p>
   <p>In the intermediate division first place went to Pilsen Sokol with 155.2 points; second place went to the Slovak Sokol with 139.1 points; third place went to Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Slavia (Sokol Slavia Gymnastic Society) with 134.2 points. Individual winners in this division were: Stepan Huska of Slovak Sokol number 39, first place with 28.3 points; second place, Joseph Rehor of Cesko Narodni Sokol Pokrok (Bohemian National Sokol Pokrok) with 28.1 points; third place went to Joseph Bagel of Sokol Slavia with 28 points.</p>
   <p>First place in the junior division went to Sokol Chicago with 170.7 points; second place was taken by Sokol Oak Park with 145.8 points; third place went to Sokol Pilsen with 144.4 points. Individual winners in this division were <pb facs="5418478_4_1335.jpg" n="3"/>Bedrich Magr of Sokol Chicago, first place with 32.2 points; Jiri Smidl of Sokol Chicago, second place with 31.7 points; Vladislav Kulicek of Sokol Tabor, third place with 30.6 points.</p>
   <p>This first competitive tournament of the Slovanska Gymnasticka Unie was supervised by Sokol Rudolph Styblo, instructor of the central group. The next competitive meet of the Slovanska Gymnasticka Unie will be held during the summer in one of our parks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
