<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-01-08">Jan. 8, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Partial Combination of Sokols</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Steps Taken Yesterday Toward the Unification of Slavonic Sokols in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1338</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1338.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-01-08">Jan. 8, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">PARTIAL COMBINATION OF SOKOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Steps Taken Yesterday Toward The Unification of Slavonic Sokols in America</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Unification along technical lines was accomplished yesterday at the meeting of representatives of various Czech and other Slavonic sokol societies of Chicago and vicinity. The advantages which would be derived from a general unification of all Slavonic sokols in America have been referred to in sokol circles for a long time. Several attempts have been made to reach this goal, but they have usually met with defeat, to the loss of all sokols.</p>
   <p>It has been chiefly the leaders who have placed obstacles in the way of unification, so that various attempts in that direction have come to naught. Of late it has been chiefly the younger sokols, that is, the active members, who have started an energetic agitation for unification, at least along technical lines, and their work was crowned with remarkable results at yesterday's meeting of representatives of various Slavonic sokol societies. The meeting was held on the <pb facs="5418478_4_1339.jpg" n="2"/>premises of Pilsen Sokol, at 18th Street and Ashland Avenue, and the unification of all Slavonic sokols along technical lines, follows the manner of the International Gymnastic Union. This new organization is an association of active members, without regard to which camp they have belonged, and it does not stand in opposition to existing sokol bodies.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by the circuit commander, Sokol [Rudolph] Styblo, who was then unanimously elected chairman of that meeting. Sokol Joseph Zitny was appointed recorder. Sokol Styblo took the floor and explained to the representatives the idea of unification along technical lines. He called attention to the inadequacies of the sokol societies, which inadequacies could be eliminated easily through this unification. Almost the same idea was expressed by Sokol Jindrich Orth, who referred to the unfriendliness of various sokol societies and presented proof that it was not among members in training, but among the leaders of the various sokol societies that class differences are promoted. The sokols should join hands, if not by having the same parade uniforms, at least by having the same kind of gymnasium apparel. Brother sokols Bedrich Kostlan, Jan Zager, Joseph L. Martinek, Jan Tesar, and many others, sincerely recommended the idea of unification <pb facs="5418478_4_1340.jpg" n="3"/>and it was finally decided to lay the foundation for this unification at this meeting. To decide upon a suitable name for this new body was the next order of business, and on the motion of Brother sokol Jan Zagar, the new organization was named "Slovansko Sokolska Gymnasticka Unie" (Slavonic Sokol Union). The meeting then proceeded to the election of temporary officers. The following were elected: Rudolph Styblo, president; Joseph Zitny, secretary; Daniel Rigan, financial secretary; Jan Tesar, treasurer. The president then appointed Brother sokols Jindrich Ort, Bedrich Kostlan, Victor Cerny, Ivan Klaric, and Joseph S. Martinek, for the purpose of drafting a constitution and bylaws. It was voted that the annual dues of each society shall be two dollars and that each society shall be represented by three members in the meetings of the Slovansko Sokolska Gymnasticka Unie, which will be held on the fourth Sunday of each month. Because some societies, such as the Polish, Serbian, and some Slovak societies were not informed about yesterday's meeting, it was resolved that each of these societies be specially requested to send their representatives to future meetings, in order that the idea of unification may be carried out to the greatest possible extent. With such interest as <pb facs="5418478_4_1341.jpg" n="4"/>was evident among the societies, we do not doubt but that the Slovansko Sokolska Gymnasticka Unie will gain remarkable success in the shortest time.</p>
   <p>The following representatives of individual societies were present at yesterday's meeting: ....</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: List of twenty-seven names omitted.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
