<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-09">Apr. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[The Immigrant Press]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0141</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0141.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-09">Apr. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[THE IMMIGRANT PRESS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If a man can pride himself on an academic education, or more, if he can boast of a diploma of some sort, that is by no means certain proof of his perseverance, practical knowledge, or high mental standing. Even among people who are, in the current concept, called "educated," there are some with a limited horizon.</p>
   <p>One of these stars of the first magnitude who is so shortsighted that he cannot see even the tips of his shoes is the Chicago lawyer, Levi Mayer. He is suggesting that only English language newspapers should be allowed to be printed. The idea is so crazy that it is hardly worth any arguments. Mr. Mayer is certainly not so ignorant that he does not know that the population of the United States, to a large degree, consists of immigrants, many of whom are unable, in spite of sincere efforts, to acquire a sufficient knowledge of the <pb facs="5418478_4_0142.jpg" n="2"/>English language to permit them to read English newspapers so that they could get information, without which modern life is unthinkable.</p>
   <p>Mr. Mayer is also not so backward as not to see that the large number of foreign language papers here are the most reliable scale for the intelligence, maturity, and accomplishments of the immigrants--characteristics of which our people are justly proud.</p>
   <p>If a newspaper is an institution necessary in normal times, it is still more important in war time. A newspaper inspired with loyalty in surely one of the best mediums of linking the people with the Government. It is the interpreter of the people's aims which must become common good in order to ward off chaos. It is the immigrant papers, particularly our Slav papers, that have rendered the best services to the Government. Everybody knows this, and the immensely valuable services performed for the patriotic cause by immigrant papers have found due recognition even by the national administration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0143.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There are, of course, exceptions--certain silly papers whose cocky spirit should be dampened and whose rights to postal delivery should be taken away. Mr. Mayer should not use them as yardsticks for his opinion of immigrant papers in general. It is, indeed, not our people's fault that Mr. Mayer reads only bolshevik or pro-German publications.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
