<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-06-15">June 15, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">A Dignified Celebration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-06-15">June 15, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">A DIGNIFIED CELEBRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saturday evening will remain impressed for a long time upon the memories of all who did not fail to come to Libuse hall on 12th Street. Ottakar Lodge #78, Knights of Pythias celebrated its twenty-fifth anniversary there. It was a dignified celebration full of meaning. Long before nine o'clock, at which time the program was to start, the tastefully decorated hall was filled with invited guests.</p>
   <p>Immediately upon arriving at the hall, everyone was presented with a beautiful flower, which was pinned on the gentlemen helter-skelter by two charming young ladies. Upon entering the hall, everyone was surprised. The stage was transformed into an exotic grove. Palms and other tropical greens were artistically arranged upon the stage. Sharply at nine o'clock the program began. Mr. Tesinsky's band opened the program by playing a march and immediately following Mr. Vaclav Kuchynka, the grand chancellor of the lodge and chairman of the arrangements committee, spoke.</p>
   <p>He said, "Honorable Ladies and Gentlemen! This lodge was organized by Germans, Czechs, <pb facs="5418478_4_0036.jpg" n="2"/>and Poles, and it began its work in the German language. The brother Purer translated the rituals into the Czech language, the grand lodge approved them and the lodge began to work in the Czech language. Those brothers of the foreign tongue withdrew, and the lodge continued further until orders were received from the grand lodge requiring all subordinate lodges to work in one language, that is in English. Therefore the lodge is now working in its third language.</p>
   <p>"At the conclusion of these twenty-five years of struggle, we have left only five old veterans. Four are members of our lodge, the fifth is brother Somansky, who is no longer a member of our lodge, however he remains a sincere brother of ours!"</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Eugene Reis spoke, recalling blessed memories of the time, when twenty-five years ago, he inducted this lodge into the organization. The presentation of the five remaining charter members was an impressive moment.</p>
   <p>After this act, those present seated themselves at richly arranged tables and certainly everyone was surprised, not only with the arrangement of the tables, which were an example of good-taste and elegance, but with the rich assortment of excellently <pb facs="5418478_4_0037.jpg" n="3"/>prepared dainties.</p>
   <p>Several more speeches and toasts were offered, all of which were for the success and welfare of Ottakar Lodge. During the banquet, the Splavcovys (husband and wife) introduced several remarkable acts.</p>
   <p>In short, as we have already said, the entire celebration was very fine and soul inspiring.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
