<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-04-26">April 26, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">Sunday School of the Pilzen Sokol (Pilzen Falcon).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-04-26">April 26, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">SUNDAY SCHOOL OF THE PILZEN SOKOL (PILZEN FALCON).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The society "Pilzensky Sokol" (Pilzen Falcon), diligent in every regard, founded a year ago a Sunday school for our youth, whose parents were watchful that their children do not denationalize but accustom themselves to the mother language, respect it and be true to the nationality from which they descend. Every nation represented in the United States is taking care to preserve its language and character and is not despairing about its future like some Bohemian cranky old people who are measuring prematurely the longevity of the Bohemian nationality.</p>
   <p>This kind of measuring of the vital national power is harmful, and helpful only to denationalization. We must be grateful that we have among ourselves the people who are not looking hopelessly in the future but are struggling to enlighten as much as possible this dark future of nationalism. Thanks to the initiative of these people there are opened and conducted special schools where the mother language is nursed and morality developed. It is true that all children don't frequent these schools, but part of them are enrolled in the public schools and part are detained with occupations <pb facs="5418478_4_0752.jpg" n="2"/>which do not allow them to frequent the school as extensively as would be right and desirable. For this reason, namely, are founded here in Chicago the Bohemian Sunday schools accessible for every child and youth to be taught to read and write Bohemian and eventually to repeat what they were taught in the Bohemian grammar school. We have had in Chicago many of this kind of Sunday schools, but they have partially disappeared not being substantially supported or on account of unsuitable locations or simply for not being sufficiently frequented.</p>
   <p>Only one Bohemian Sunday school is left at this date and it was founded a year ago by the self-sacrificing "Pilzensky Sokol" in a location granted by the Bohemian-English liberal school on 18th street. This school is maintained from the private funds of the" Pilzensky Sokol" and the children are receiving everything free, books, ink, pens, and pencils. No extraordinary charges are requested. There are lessons exclusively in the Bohemian language and history every Sunday from 9 a. m. until 12 noon. Nevertheless this school is not receiving full recognition and support, which it rightfully deserves. At present the school is frequented by a little over 100 children although there is room for twice this amount of pupils. The teachers are <pb facs="5418478_4_0753.jpg" n="3"/>Mr. Fr. Tomek and Ed. Winternitz.</p>
   <p>It is too bad that this only Bohemian Sunday school, situated in the heart of the large Bohemian community, is not granted such support which it should have by all rights. It should be carefully considered. We like to warn the Bohemian parents that it would be shameful for them, should this school not develop and grow higher. It would be disgraceful for the community which started the school and is supporting it on their own expenditure, should the school sink.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
