<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1908-08-31">Aug. 31, 1908</date><title level="a">Public Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1576</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1576.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1908-08-31">Aug. 31, 1908</date><title level="a">PUBLIC CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Approximately Eight Thousand Persons Attended Yesterday's Public Celebration Arranged By The Management For The Dedication of Karel Havlicek's Monument.</p>
   <p>Never in the past has such a crowd of people appeared in Pilsen Brewing Park, as the one that attended yesterday's celebration under the auspices of national organizations, such as Sokol Fueguer-Trys, Grand Lodge of C.S.P.S. (Czech-Slovak-Benovelent Association), the Supreme Lodge of C.S.J. (Czecho-Slovak-Unity). That gigantic participation and that cosmopolitan enthusiasm convinced us of the hearty response and the appreciative attitude of our Bohemian people in respect to the memory of so great a leader of our countrymen as Karel Havlicek, whose name is written in gold letters among other great men in history.</p>
   <p>At yesterday's celebration no mention was made of Karel Havlicek's date of birth nor death; however, this was of no importance on the occasion of such <pb facs="5418478_4_1577.jpg" n="2"/>a public celebration, since mention was made of the great deeds performed by him for his native country. The diligence on the part of the organizers brought in good financial fesults. The true feeling in every Bohemian's heart is to have a monument erected in honor of Karel Havlicek. That feeling was expressed at yesterday's celebration.</p>
   <p>A sum of nearly a thousand dollars was collected. There were a number of prominent speakers who made such an impression on the listeners that it was decided, then and there, that Douglas Park would be the proper site for the erection of the monument with permission of the Park Board of the West Park Commissioner. This permit was granted under one condition, to satisfy the board, that the monument will benefit the public.</p>
   <p>This was assured, owing to the artistically designed sketch drawn by Mr. Taft, and written explanation by Professor Jaroslav Zmrhal. The Bohemians in the Pilsen and California (Lawndale) sections, donned their festive garb on Saturday and decorated their windows with flags of Bohemian colors. There was not a home of which the windows were not adorned with some kind of a decoration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1578.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The streets were also decorated, especially those streets along which the paraders were expected to march.</p>
   <p>These streets were decorated with American flags, on poles mounted at the curb edge of the sidewalks. Early in the afternoon the paraders assembled at the Bohemian-American Hall, on West 18th Street; at the Pilsen Sokol Hall on South Ashland Avenue; near 18th Street, and also at the Bohemian-American Liberal School, on 18th Street, near May Street. At these three mentioned places the sidewalks were crowded with spectators.</p>
   <p>The parade then proceeded from the Pilsen Sokol Hall, to the Bohemian-American Hall, where this train of marchers joined the group from the Pilsen Sokol; from here they marched to the Bohemian Liberal School on West 18th street, near May street, and this group followed the group of the Bohemian-American Hall. The parade started from this point via May street, south to Nineteenth Street, west along Nineteenth Street to Blue Island Avenue, down Blue Island Avenue, back to Eighteenth Street, this time west along Eighteenth Street to Paulina Street, south along Paulina Street to Nineteenth Street, and again west along Nineteenth Street to Leavitt Street, then south along Leavitt Street to Twenty-Second <pb facs="5418478_4_1579.jpg" n="4"/>Street, west along Twenty-Second Street to Kedzie Avenue, south along Kedzie Avenue to Twenty-fourth Street, east along Twenty-fourth Street to Albany Avenue and south down Albany Avenue straight to the pilsen Brewing Park. Here the marchers disbanded in a very orderly manner, to make room for the marchers coming from the West Side.</p>
   <p>The mounted section of Fueguer-Tyrs was led by police, followed by the students of Mr. Porbe's School; these were followed by the students of Svatplub Cech, dressed in national costumes. The students of the Fuegner-Tyrs were mounted on a very beautifully decorated allegorical float, on this float was also mounted the bust of Karel Havlicek. The decorators were the firm of Svaty and Simak; they did not charge for their work, but contributed their services in honor of Karel Havlicek.</p>
   <p>There were many more beautifully decorated floats, but none to compare with this one. The gymnasts of Sokol Slovensky followed the floats. They marched on feet, <pb facs="5418478_4_1580.jpg" n="5"/>dressed in their full regalia, with color-guards carrying the American flag and their banners. The C.S.P.S. (Czecho-Slovak Benevolent Association) gymnasts followed in a like manner. The Sokol Chicago gymnasts followed with their drum and bugle corps.</p>
   <p>The Sokol Fuegner-Tyrs were dressed in their national costumes. Then a long line of six abreast of members of various lodges marched in civilian clothes, also headed by color-guards. As this section entered the Pilsen Brewing Park, they too disbanded in an orderly manner. On the program was a folk song entitled "Spy Havlicku." After the celebration was over, the spectators enjoyed themselves dancing and singing. We can truthfully say, this was a grand celebration and we hope to have many celebrations of this kind in the future.</p>
   <p>We also wish to say that the people enjoyed not only the celebration, but also the parade and did not lock tired at all. It was all in honor of the great leader that was Karel Havlicek, who is very deserving of such a celebration as was held yesterday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
