<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-20">Nov. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Management of the Vojta Naprstek Bohemian Free Thought School Insulted by Czech Periodical</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-20">Nov. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MANAGEMENT OF THE VOJTA NAPRSTEK BOHEMIAN FREE THOUGHT SCHOOL INSULTED BY CZECH PERIODICAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a meeting of the board of managers of the Ceska Svobodomyslna Skola Vojta Naprstek (Vojta Naprstek Bohemian Free Thought School), held November 6, 1922, the matter of an untimely joke made by Mr. J. J. Jelinek in the periodical Sotek (Imp) was taken up. In an article written by Mr. Jelinek for the said periodical the management of the Naprstek School was ridiculed by being compared with the city fathers of that ancient town of Gotham. After reading Jelinek's article the delegates were embittered and summarily condemned the cowardly act of the writer. It was decided in this meeting that the complaints committee publish an open letter expressing resentment at the tenor of the accusations made against the management of the School, that letter to be published in our three Chicago Czech dailies....</p>
   <p>First of all it is necessary to inform the public of the circumstances under <pb facs="5418478_4_0363.jpg" n="2"/>which the writer of the article attacked the management of the School. Following the complaints which reached the management from time to time--that the people attending the lectures given by the management are constantly annoyed by the vendors of all kinds of literature, and that the attendance at these lectures diminished as a direct result of those annoyances--the management decided to forbid without exception the vending of any kind of printed matter on the premises where these lectures are given.</p>
   <p>At a directors' meeting, held in September, 1922, a request was made by the Mistni Sdruzeni Svazu Svobodomyslnych (local branch of the Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers) for the renting of a hall for the purpose of giving a lecture therein. The request was handed in by Mr. Frantisek Stepanek, secretary of the local branch who is also a member of the board of directors of the patronat (school management). This request was granted with the proviso that the ruling of the board [concerning the vending of literature] be respected. Mr. Stepanek, together with the custodian of the hall [in which <pb facs="5418478_4_0364.jpg" n="3"/>the lectures are given], informed Mr. Jelinek about the new ruling of the board, because Mr. Jelinek is one of the vendors of literature mentioned above. Mr. Jelinek in his attack on the patronat intentionally distorted the facts as they were related to him.</p>
   <p>The patronat, which consists of the delegates of our foremost fraternities, sororities, and benevolent organizations, and which by unselfish work built this school that is now the pride of the whole Bohemian California district, feels therefore that it was unjustly attacked and subjected to public ridicule, and leaves this matter in the hands of the various organizations in order that proper action might be started to frustrate such attacks and such ridicule of their own officially chosen representatives.</p>
   <p>For the patronat of the Vojta Naprstek Bohemian Free Thought School, The complaints committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
