<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-24">Aug. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Sixth Convention of the Bohemian Sisterhood</title><title level="a" type="sub">Sixth Session</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-24">Aug. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SIXTH CONVENTION OF THE BOHEMIAN SISTERHOOD</title><title level="a" type="sub">Sixth Session</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sixth session of the sixth convention of the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Sisterhood) was called to order by the president of the convention, Sister Marie Hajek, at 9 A. M. yesterday. The slogan of the Jednota was repeated by the delegates, and the roll call revealed that all officers and delegates of the convention were present....Since printed copies of the minutes of the previous session were not yet distributed, the [secretary] read such congratulatory telegrams and letters according to the order of the day. [List of letters and telegrams sent by various lodges, societies, and individuals is omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak, alderman of the Twelfth Ward, sent a telegram congratulating the convention on its work and urging further activity of the Jednota. The convention was asked to rise and thus express its thanks for all the congratulatory messages.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1730.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The office of the Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani (Council for Higher Education) of Cedar Rapids, Iowa, sent the following letter to the convention:</p>
   <p>"Honored convention: We take the liberty of calling your attention to the Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani and recommend to your kind support this cultural institution of our Czechoslovak nationality in America. This year the Matice will celebrate its twentieth anniversary. During this period, the Matice, by aiding a great number of young men and women of Czechoslovak nationality in getting college and university education, has performed meritorious work. It also urged our young people to attain higher education by counseling them and giving them all kinds of information. This institution works quietly but persistently, and the results of its labors are noticeable among the numbers of educated men and women who have fitted themselves into the various professions, and who stand out among the American intelligentsia--a credit to our nationality. By reminding the convention of this foremost cultural institution of the American <pb facs="5418478_4_1731.jpg" n="3"/>Czechoslovaks, we wish to thank you for all the past favors and aid given us, and we believe that you will not deny such moral and material assistance to the Matice in the future. For the Matice,</p>
   <p>"Mr. B. Simek, president,</p>
   <p>"Mr. P. A. Korab, secretary."</p>
   <p>This letter was referred to the resolutions committee which, no doubt, will recommend that the convention remember the Matice by some financial aid.</p>
   <p>The work of amending the constitution and bylaws then continued. The question of fines on members and officers was discussed, and the individual articles, after some slight changes, were allowed to remain the same as in the old bylaws. It was emphasized that every member who by marriage changes her name and her domicile should in her own interest inform her lodge about these changes. [The printed copies of] the minutes, having just arrived, were read and approved.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1732.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A rather lively debate was brought about by the discussion of the status of lodges of Cicero, Berwyn, and other places lying in the immediate vicinity of Chicago. The delegates from these suburban lodges pointed out the necessity of having certificates of transfer of membership issued to the members living in the suburbs. In making this recommendation, they mentioned the great distances which one is obliged to cover by going from such suburbs to Chicago; they also mentioned the double streetcar fare and the [annoying] time schedules which exist in the Cicero-Chicago and Chicago-Cicero connections. The presiding officer, on the other hand, pointed out that the community of Cicero will some day become a part of Chicago, and that the issuance of transfer certificates would therefore be unnecessary. The Cicero lodges should admit to membership the women and girls of Cicero and not those of Chicago. Chicago lodges, on the other hand, should not admit as members the inhabitants of Cicero. After a lengthy debate, everything remained as before, and there will be no membership transfers issued. Several articles concerning the issuance of such certificates were turned over to the committee on constitution <pb facs="5418478_4_1733.jpg" n="5"/>and bylaws for further elaboration, and that committee will later submit its newly drafted changes to the convention which will act upon them.</p>
   <p>It was decided to leave Chapter VIII of the constitution and bylaws unchanged. That chapter deals with the committees of the Jednota, such as the central committee, the state executive committee, and the lodge committee. The officers of these committees are chairman, vice-chairman, secretary, financial secretary, treasurer, sergeant at arms, custodian, a two-member committee on property, and a three-member auditing committee.</p>
   <p>It was decided by vote that the auditing committee of the central committee be elected annually, the first election to be held at the next convention. The debate concerning the installation of individual lodges by the central committee, the said committee to pay all the expenses connected with that function, brought to light how little respect there is for any central and high authority among our <pb facs="5418478_4_1734.jpg" n="6"/>Bohemian organizations. An indication of that was the fact that a large number of delegates was for having the installation of lodges performed by the nearest grand lodge committee, averring that by doing so the central committee of the Jednota could save a great deal of money. It was maintained, on the other hand, that the central committee would not have too great an expense by attending to the installation ceremonies itself. On the contrary, it would profit thereby because, equipped with expert authority, it could train the officers of newly formed lodges to work properly and thus be a credit to the whole Jednota. By attending to the function of installation itself, the central committee will gain in efficient service what it has lost in expense; its gains will be manifold. This question was therefore voted on....The motion stated that new lodges are to be installed by the officers of the central committee....</p>
   <p>There were 448 votes for and 225 against the motion. The motion [as indicated above] was carried and the central committee will therefore be responsible for <pb facs="5418478_4_1735.jpg" n="7"/>the installation of all newly formed lodges.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the festivities committee announced that dinner was ready....She also remarked that if there were any delegates or any sisters who would like to visit the Bridewell they must be ready at 2 P. M.; the warden of that prison--our countryman Mr. J. Siman--agreed to show us around. The chairman also called attention to a picnic to be held by the Jednota in the afternoon and in the evening, and asked everybody to attend, and wished everybody a good time.</p>
   <p>In the afternoon visit to the Bridewell, about 125 sisters took part and among these there were a great many delegates. The visitors to the said institution were welcomed by our well-known countryman, Mr. J. Siman and his wife. He greeted the [sisters] with sincerity....and then invited them to inspect the institution. As guides assigned to the ladies were Mrs. Siman and Mr. Petrik, the latter being an assistant to Mr. Siman. Both of them went out of their way <pb facs="5418478_4_1736.jpg" n="8"/>to make the trip through the prison as interesting as possible. That the visitors were greatly interested themselves was proved by the many questions they showered upon their ciceroni. After having seen most of the institution, the ladies left with the feeling that the visit was thoroughly worth while. They assured themselves that the prison is well managed by its present warden, and that the latter is both conscientious and humane in caring for the inmates entrusted to him. He was warmly thanked for his invitation and for having his guests shown around.</p>
   <p>From the Bridewell the ladies returned to Pilsen Park which by this time began to fill up with visitors, most of whom were members of the Jednota. At this point we cannot forbear mentioning the fact that the picnic of the Jednota was successful.The members of the Jednota themselves and among themselves sold a large number of tickets; how well liked the Jednota is by our freethinking people was fully attested by the large number of visitors.</p>
   <p>It goes without saying that the picnic was also attended by many members of <pb facs="5418478_4_1737.jpg" n="9"/>other ladies' benevolent organizations, especially those of the Bohemian Ladies' Union. Mr. Brousek's excellent orchestra was engaged for the occasion.....His orchestra was especially appreciated during the evening when it accompanied the drill team of the Jednota in its allegorical evolutions and marches. These brought forth thunders of applause....The picnic committee served the visitors so well that they did not think of going home until late at night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
