<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-10">Jan. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Dissolution of the Slavonic Sokol Gymnastic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-10">Jan. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE DISSOLUTION OF THE SLAVONIC SOKOL GYMNASTIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of the fusion of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union) with the Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Fuegner-Tyrs group), the Slavonic Sokol Gymnastic Union decided on Dec. 24, 1916, to retire from the field and be absorbed by the merger formed by the two above-mentioned bodies.</p>
   <p>It was founded in 1913 in Cleveland, Ohio, for the purpose of maintaining closer contacts among the sundry Slavonic Sokol groups in Chicago and vicinity, and especially for exchanging ideas about technical management. The beginning was successful, for among its many public affairs we must mention the gymnastic tourneys and the performances in Irving Park, the public appearance in Atlas Park, the public drills of adolescent Sokols, the gymnastic course of 1914 in Dvorak Park, and the brilliant performance in Grant Park on the occasion of which the organization was awarded the silver cup for the best educational gymnastic showing among all of the competing nationalistic societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1205.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The activities thus propitiously initiated were, alas, on the decline in the later years. In the year 1916, following the urgent demands of many groups, efforts were made for a revival of the activities of the Slavonic Sokol Gymnastic Union, but in that year there were three jamborees which did not give the Union the time needed for recuperation and a comeback. Nevertheless, it kept the various Slavonic Sokol societies in contact with one another up to the time of its dissolution. After the Sokol jamborees, the question of a fusion became acute again, and this time it was enthusiastically taken up by the Union, which brought about a merger. Now that the fusion is an accomplished fact, it is agreed that the Slavonic Sokol Gymnastic Union has become superfluous, and therefore it has been dissolved. Its funds, amounting to one hundred dollars, have been transferred to the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Association) and to the Slovanska Lipa (Slavonic Linden) in proportion to the groups represented, i.e., two thirds to the Czech National Association and one third to the Slovanska Lipa. The archives and the silver cup will go to the central technical division. The committee of trustees is composed of R. Vesely and Jos. Paskovsky for the National Sokol Union; Mat. Tenjak for the Slavonic Sokol Gymnastic Union; Ant. Svlacek for <pb facs="5418478_4_1206.jpg" n="3"/>the Bohemian-American Workingmen's Sokol; and Jos. Drahny for the Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
