<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-12-27">December 27, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">"Exercises of the Pupils of the Bohemian-English School of the 8th Ward"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-12-27">December 27, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">"EXERCISES OF THE PUPILS OF THE BOHEMIAN-ENGLISH SCHOOL OF THE 8th WARD"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A public examination and exercises by the pupils of the Bohemian-English School were held last Saturday afternoon in the main hall of the "Tel. Jed. Sokol" (Gymnastic Union Sokol). To the examination was added the distribution of gifts by "Vlasta" Lodge # 1. Because of the tardiness of the arrival of the public the exercises were not started until 2:30 P.M. The Chairman of the school committee brought the gathering to order and expressed disappointment that our public is so indifferent in regards to matters of such great cultural value.</p>
   <p>The pupils, of whom there were about forty, arose and sang a Bohemian composition. The teacher Mr. Baymayer,. then had them read from the 3rd reader. It was indeed a surprise to notice with what ease and understanding the pupils were able to read. The same may be said of the 1st and 2nd reader pupils:</p>
   <p>Before English reading was begun the audience was shown many specimens of handwriting of the pupils. The artistic writing of the girls was such, that no <pb facs="5418478_4_0755.jpg" n="2"/>one would say it was performed by a girl had it not been for the signatures. Then the pupils were tested in written dictation exercises in both the Bohemian and English languages.</p>
   <p>In the meantime the ladies of "Vlasta" Lodge arrived with some of the poorer Bohemian children. For this purpose they obtained 16 complete outfits of clothing for girls and 14 complete outfits for boys. In addition there were found large whistles for the boys and other toys for the girls.</p>
   <p>Saturday's examination has proved to us that the Bohemian-English School in the 8th ward could be carried on successfully if it had just a little more support from the public. We must add that the audience at Saturday's examinations was composed mostly of women, which shows their interest in all things noble and elevating. Too bad, that we can not say the same thing about most men who seem to have once again fallen back on the saying "Oh, well, they will manage without me." However, it is high time that such indifference be cast aside and an era of beneficent work be commenced.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
