<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-09">July 9, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Further Announcement by the Arrangements Committee for the Celebration at the Unveiling of the Karel Havlicek Borovsky Monument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-09">July 9, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">FURTHER ANNOUNCEMENT BY THE ARRANGEMENTS COMMITTEE FOR THE CELEBRATION AT THE UNVEILING OF THE KAREL HAVLICEK BOROVSKY MONUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is greatly desirable that every secretary who thus far has not sent in the notification of attendance of the Borovsky Monument celebration do so within one week, for we will start with the final arrangement of the parade.</p>
   <p>However, today we can say that according to the application received, we will prove that we are a power which should always be reckoned with for such celebrations. The past has convinced us that we know how to appreciate the significance of such an occasion, and so will also the present, especially upon this occasion when we are to demonstrate that we know how to appreciate a man who sacrificed everything in order to contribute to the happiness and liberty of our people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1550.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From among various letters received, even from out of town, we publish here one from Edwardsville, Illinois, dated June 8, 1911.</p>
   <p>"Dear countrymen, the time has arrived when everyone of us Bohemian-American can be proud that a monument of such a great man as was our Karel Havlicek Borovsky will glory in its beauty. We feel as you do, and will say also that July 30 will be the greatest holiday of the American-Bohemians. We regret that we are so far away and cannot come to this celebration. However, that day will be a beautiful remembrance about which we will tell our children and our grandchildren. We will celebrate the 30th of July, though quietly, nevertheless, with dignity. We send our best wishes and wish success for your work, success for freedom, and frustration for reaction. With Taborite Greetings from Lodge Vlasta No. 35, Rosalie Vavra, president, Marie Pfeifer, Secretary."</p>
   <p>In addition to those already published, the following societies have <pb facs="5418478_4_1551.jpg" n="3"/>agreed to take part in the parade:........</p>
   <p>For the arrangements committee, Karel J. Kopecky, chairman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
