<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-23">Aug. 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[The Havlicek Monument</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-23">Aug. 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[THE HAVLICEK MONUMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sokol Cermak's proposal published in the latest issue of Sokol Americky (American Gymnast) that the Havlicek monument in Douglas Park have inscribed upon it Havlicek's fearless motto - with a translation in English - "You may promise me, You may threaten me, Still I will not be a traitor!" comes somewhat post festum or rather, a trifle late. Nevertheless it is very welcome. Those few words clearly show Havlicek's purity, honor-ableness, and his conviction that he must under all circumstances perform the duty that he took upon himself as a Czech journalist and political teacher of his people. Mr. Cermak's translation of this characteristic motto is entirely comprehendible and at the same time faithful, so that it is not necessary for anyone to worry his head with the question of whether or not it could be said in better English. We have seen two such <pb facs="5418478_4_1516.jpg" n="2"/>attempts at translation, but neither one comes anywhere near Mr. Cermak's version. It is not any rhyming of the energetic, simple words of Havlicek that is wanted, but the preservation of their original brevity and simplicity. The longer the rhyme someone makes of them, the worse it becomes, whereas in the original text there is not one unnecessary syllable and there are exactly so many words as are needed to portray in a single sentence the steely character and rock-rooted persistency of the greatest Czech publicist. Should the Havlicek monument be provided with this characteristic device of his, then the last line of the present inscription which reads "Everlasting honor to his memory!" should be removed. Such an inscription is only suitable for the monument of some manufacturer of stockings or soap, who remembered some patriotic institution; it is not suitable for the first Czech monument erected in America in honor of one of our most illustrious men, who lived only for the Czech people and worked himself to death for them!</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1517.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Andel is proof of great tactlessness and thanklessness, which virtues very often spread with strikingly bold ostentation in our so-called national or public life. People ordinarily are forgotten with the turn of a hand as soon as a new face appears upon the scene or if the old worker momentarily leaves this "Field of Glory," even though he had worked many years without gain or perhaps even with personal loss. There really are still among us people who seek glory in our aimless planning and toiling - people, trifling and unbelievably vain, who are of course terribly jealous of everyone about whom they think that by their mere presence at one of these national manifestations, they might deprive of a bit of admiration on the part of the public.</p>
   <p>Such "little giants" are not concerned about actual patriotic work for which they have neither the comprehension nor the interest. They think of the glorification of their own dear "I" and their precious insignificant person.... that is the reason for the constant lagging of our national <pb facs="5418478_4_1518.jpg" n="4"/>labors, or for their being misdirected.</p>
   <p>Sincere, experienced, and unselfish men from our midst are not given a deciding voice in our affairs; bloated figureheads, who crave publicity and who have a penchant for prestige, play the leading role. It will be well to put these brazen men in their proper places.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
