<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-02-25">Feb. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Final Preparations Have Begun for a Big Celebration at the Unveiling of the Karel Havlicek-Borovsky Monument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-02-25">Feb. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">FINAL PREPARATIONS HAVE BEGUN FOR A BIG CELEBRATION AT THE UNVEILING OF THE KAREL HAVLICEK-BOROVSKY MONUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committee for the erection of a monument to Karel Havlicek, held a meeting in Mr. Bolka's hall on Blue Island Ave. yesterday, in which the date and program for the festive unveiling of the monument was definitely decided on. On Saturday July 29, a celebration is to be held in honor of out-of-town visitors, at the Pilsen Brewery Garden. A banquet is to be held the same evening. During the afternoon celebration there will be a parade to the monument and a speaker will address the gathering in Bohemian and in English. In the evening the play "Karel Havlicek-Borovsky," will be presented in the Czech settlement.</p>
   <p>Dr. Miller's motion, that the Nar Rada Cechu Americkych (Bohemian-American National Council), which has just come into existence, be invited to <pb facs="5418478_4_1569.jpg" n="2"/>participate in the celebration, was accepted.</p>
   <p>It was also moved that the invited Americans, chiefly public, county and state officials who attend, be taken to the Bohemian Club after the unveiling and entertained there if the club is agreeable. Mr. Vopicka, the club's delegate, promised to support the motion.</p>
   <p>The appointment of committees was left to the chairman, who immediately named Messrs. Glaser and Kopecky as a committee to locate a hall in which to hold meetings; the present hall is not large enough and both of Mr. Bolka's halls are occupied already.</p>
   <p>It was decided to hold meetings semi-monthly. Since it is not known where the next meeting will be held, it will be made known by special announcement.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1570.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>With that, this significant meeting was brought to a close. It would be desirable that all the work should not be left to a few enthusiastic individuals, but that all of the more significant Czech societies should send their delegates to the meetings and that special invitations be sent to prominent countrymen urging them also to attend.</p>
   <p>The work itself is completed; it now remains only for the Czechs to make a dignified appearance before the American public and in this our Polish brothers gave us a good example at the unveiling of the Pulaski and Koszciuzsko monuments.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
