<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-17">July 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Soiree in Honor of the Catholic Sokols That Are Delegates to the Catholic Sokol Convention in Czechoslovakia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0974</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0974.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-17">July 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A SOIREE IN HONOR OF THE CATHOLIC SOKOLS THAT ARE DELEGATES TO THE CATHOLIC SOKOL CONVENTION IN CZECHOSLOVAKIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the auspices of the Straz Katolickeho Sokola (sentinel of the Bohemian Catholic Sokol) of Chicago a soiree was given last night in honor of the departing Catholic Sokol delegates who are to represent the American Catholic Sokols at a convention, which is to take place in Brno, Czechoslovakia next month [August 10-17, 1922]. The soiree was in the Cesko-Americka Sin (Bohemian-American hall), on West 18th Street near Ashland Avenue. [The names and addresses of the delegates are given.] This is to be the first delegation of its kind sent to Czechoslovakia, and it is, therefore, important that only the top-ranking members of the [Catholic] Sokol teams be sent. All of Bohemian Catholic America is interested in the team. The young men, who have been chosen as delegates, were the chief attraction at the soiree. They are a well-balanced team, consisting of individuals whose athletic accomplishments are remarkable. They gave example of precision drill, and afterwards exercised <pb facs="5418478_4_0975.jpg" n="2"/>on the horizontal bars and the trapeze. It was a thrilling performance because of the composure with which the team executed their dangerous routine. The ovation given them culminated when Mr. Dostal, the leader of the delegation, was presented with a magnificent American flag. Mr. Dostal, in his speech of acceptance, thanked the audience sincerely, and said that he would deliver it [the flag] to Mr. Sramek, who is a member of the cabinet and who will be at Brno [on the occasion of the Catholic Sokol convention]. The flag....will thus constitute the gift of the Bohemian Catholics of America and will commemorate the first Bohemian Catholic Sokol convention, which promises to be a grand affair. There were several speeches delivered at the soiree. Mr. Karel Radous, president of the Distriktni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (district federation of the Bohemian Catholics) spoke for the district federation, and Mr. Antonin V. Tesar, office manager of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Federation of Bohemian Catholics of America) spoke for the National Federation. The other items on the program were gymnastic exhibitions.....</p>
   <p>Although yesterday's heat was considerable, the soiree was well attended.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
