<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-07">Apr. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Ceskoslovensky Poplatnicky Spolek Will Help Our Countrymen Obtain Their Citizenship</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0414</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0414.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-07">Apr. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKOSLOVENSKY POPLATNICKY SPOLEK WILL HELP OUR COUNTRYMEN OBTAIN THEIR CITIZENSHIP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All meetings of the Ceskoslovensky Poplatnicky Spolek V Ciceru (Czechoslovak Taxpayers Association of Cicero, Illinois) enjoy great popularity, and the Spolek takes an unusual interest in its activities.....The last meeting which was held on Saturday in the large assembly hall of the T. G. Masaryk School, was well attended. The meeting was conducted by Mr. H. Krcek; the secretary, Mr. V. Rous, read the minutes of the previous meeting. The delegates of our various organizations reported several matters of which one at least was of great importance. It dealt with the problem of smoke and its abatement by large manufacturing concerns. Thus far no such ordinance was on the books, and the owners of factories cared little about the rest of the citizenry. Another item on the program was the zoning ordinance, and although there were some objections to it among our members, this step made by the town government was gratefully approved. The zoning commissioners will, nevertheless, be <!-- 5418478_4_0416 omitted, duplicate of 5418478_4_0415 --><pb facs="5418478_4_0415.jpg" n="2"/>invited to our meeting to give their expert opinions. The meeting also discussed the ensuing elections of school board officials, and all members were asked to vote for Mr. F. J. Petru....The question of building a hospital was postponed until the next meeting. Mr. Svoboda recommended that the taxpayers' associations organize schools for aliens where they could learn English sufficiently well to be able to make applications for citizenship. He also pointed out the dangers of non-citizenship, and that those men who oppose becoming citizens of the United States expose themselves and the members of their families to grave dangers. The immigration laws are becoming more strict from year to year, and should the recent bill requiring aliens to register under penalty of arrest become a reality, every such indifferent person would have to face many unpleasant experiences, and even deportation in some cases. Mr. Svoboda's remarks were much appreciated, and it was moved and seconded immediately to organize such a school in which our men and women could be instructed in the rudiments of the English language, and where aliens would be aided in their desire to become citizens.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0417.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Eighteen new members joined our Association at this meeting, and the secretary read many new applications for membership. During a comparatively brief period of time our Association will, therefore, have about one thousand members and thus become the largest taxpayers association of Cicero and vicinity.</p>
   <p>V. Rous, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
