<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-08-28">Aug. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Press Congress and the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-08-28">Aug. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">PRESS CONGRESS AND THE CESKO-AMERICKA TISKOVA KANCELAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Having received a decent invitation to participate in the press congress, the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) drafted a letter to the congress explaining that matters with which the congress is to deal do not fall within the scope of interest of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar, and for that reason the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar cannot participate officially. However, in order to show its good will toward the news-papermen organizing the congress, the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar collected one hundred dollars among its own individual members, which it offered to the organizing committee of the congress to help defray expenses.</p>
   <p>During the congress, however, some of its members made derogatory remarks about the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar and accused this organization of maintaining an unfriendly attitude toward the congress. Thereupon the congress agreed <pb facs="5418478_4_0179.jpg" n="2"/>not to decide on the acceptance of the contribution until after the one hundred dollars had been deposited; then it would be left to the congress either to accept or refuse.</p>
   <p>The members of the executive committee of the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar decided in a recent meeting to save the congress any discussion it might have to undertake on the question of whether or not their personal contributions to offset the congress' expenses should be accepted. The offer therefore was retracted and the amount of the contribution was sent by the members to the Ustredni Matice Skolska (Central Scholastic Union) in Prague, the most deserving and neediest of our national institutions in the old country.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: An article published in the Denni Hlasatel on September 30 would seem to indicate that the press congress discussed in this article was of Bohemian journalists.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
