<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-01">Feb. 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Czech-American Monthly Printed in English</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0291</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0291.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-01">Feb. 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A CZECH-AMERICAN MONTHLY PRINTED IN ENGLISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first number of the organ of the "Ceske Harodni Sdruzeni" (Czech National Association), printed in the English language, is due this week. Its name shall be The Bohemian Review. The program of this monthly sheet is to show the attitude of the Czech-American to the American public, to the Allies, to the Associations, to the other friendly nations and, last not least, to our adolescent boys and girls. We want all of them to know about the patriotic work performed by the Czech immigrants.</p>
   <p>All of the nations are striving for a better future, and are compelled to appeal to public opinion. Many of them have their own organs in America. Among them are: the Syrians, Armenians, Poles, Lithuanians, and others. The initial steps for the printing of the monthly were taken by a small publishing concern, willing to do its utmost in order <pb facs="5418478_4_0292.jpg" n="2"/>to give the Czechs and organ in which they would be represented in a dignified manner, and one which would interpret in the English tongue what throbs in the hearts of our people.</p>
   <p>The publishers are: Doctor Jaroslav Smetanka, secretary of the English department of the Tiskova Kancelar Ces Nar Sdruz. (Press Bureau of the Czech National Association), Josef Tvrzicky, director of the Press Bureau, and Mr. J. J. Fekl, member central committee of the Czech National Association. The latter entered into negotiations with the publishers to bring about cooperation in such a manner that the editorial branch of The Bohemian Review shall be subordinated to suggestions made by the editorial bureau of the Czech National Association. In this latter editorial bureau, Dr. L. J. Fisher, the president of the Czech National Association, Vojta Benes, organizer, and Professor Jaroslav Zmrhal, secretary of the English department of the Czech National Association, will function as directing minds. The Czech National Association has <pb facs="5418478_4_0293.jpg" n="3"/>accepted The Bohemian Review as its own organ without financial obligations of any kind.</p>
   <p>And now is the time for all good men to come to the aid of their people! One single dollar will do its bit for the sustenance of the monthly, which is acknowledged as a dire necessity. The offices of The Bohemian Review will be located at 2816 South St. Louis Avenue, Chicago.</p>
   <p>All of our fellow countrymen should devote some of their spare time to the sale of the Review. Those of the wealthier class should deem it their duty to subscribe for several copies to be sent to libraries, associations, and Americans, influential in public life. His editorial ability, as well as his devotion to the cause, have placed Doctor Smetanka in this responsible office.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
