<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-28">Mar. 28, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Public Gymnastic Exhibition of the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1112</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1112.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-28">Mar. 28, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE PUBLIC GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION OF THE TELOCVICNA JEDNOTA SOKOL HAVLICEK-TYRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some of the most important activities of the Czechoslovak community in Chicago are the public gymnastic exhibitions of our Sokol units. In these exhibitions the whole year's activity in our Sokol halls are reflected. These exhibitions are good portrayals of the results that may be achieved by following the precepts of our two great founders of Sokoldom, Jindrich Fuegner and Miroslav Tyrs. The public exhibition held yesterday was a beautiful example of physical and moral training. It was presented by the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs (Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs Gymnastic Association) at its Sokol hall, Lawndale Avenue and 26th Street. The Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs spares neither money nor effort in bringing its children and junior classes to a point of perfection, and its efforts have been crowned with success. The Association has so many active members of all classes that the program had to be divided into two parts, one in the afternoon and one in the evening. The afternoon was devoted to the exhibition of children and junior classes. There were precision drills and <pb facs="5418478_4_1113.jpg" n="2"/>exercises with dumb-bells and apparatus. The precision drills and other exercises were arranged according to the ages of the children, and various numbers of the program were done in a truly exemplary manner. The attendance was large and the children were rewarded by well-earned applause for their splendid performance.</p>
   <p>The evening program was even more attractive because it was presented by the junior boys and girls as well as by the men and women. Before the program started, the president of the Association, Mr. Simaner, spoke a few sincere words to the gathering, and among other things he mentioned the anniversary celebration of the great teacher of nations, Jan Amos Komensky (Johannus Amos Comenius), which event is being celebrated today. Jan Amos Komensky was the first one who preached the generally acknowledged doctrine recognized today, that only in a sound body is there a sound mind. It is therefore only natural that Sokol units cherish his undying memory. Following this address, the regular program started.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1114.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One of the most beautiful numbers of the program was a rhythmical drill worked out by Mr. A. Otcenasek, a member of the technical staff of the Bohemian Sokol Union of Prague, Czechoslovakia. This drill is an example of a new technique which was introduced by the Sokols in our old country. Credit for the exemplary presentation of this drill should be given to the instructor of women classes, Milada Prchal.....</p>
   <p>Generally speaking, yesterday's gymnastic exhibition of the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs was successful, and credit for it is due to its leaders. The instructor of children and junior classes is Joseph Regner, and the women Sokols are drilled under the supervision of Milada Prchal. The commander of men classes is Karel Ocelka. The spacious hall was filled to capacity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
