<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-15">May 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Public Gymnastic Exhibition of the Pilsen Sokol</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1007</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1007.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-15">May 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION OF THE PILSEN SOKOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>....The public gymnastic exhibition arranged last night by the Plzensky Sokol (Pilsen Sokol) may be numbered among the most beautiful ever presented. For the Pilsen Sokol, in particular, last night's performance may rightly be considered one of the most significant events in its history. Brother Jelinek did some very conscientious work to train his teams, and the results of his supervision and training were such as will be remembered for a long time to come. The program consisted of fifteen events, each rivaling the preceding one in beauty. The boxing engaged in by the adolescent classes was, in itself, something entirely new and extraordinary as Sokol types of exercises go. However, it served only as an introduction to the main events. The newly worked out setting-up exercises performed by the girls to the tune of a waltz....called forth admiration from all of the visitors by its light, one is almost <pb facs="5418478_4_1008.jpg" n="2"/>tempted to say, really zephyrlike nature, so that the little girls received enthusiastic applause. Sharing their laurels were groups of adult Sokol women who performed some very intricate setting-up exercises with wands according to the Cermak formula. [Translator's note: This was Josef Cermak, a well-known Sokol instructor whose work among the Chicago teams is spoken of with great respect.] The women's exercises were accompanied by the tunes of the Beseda (get-together: a Bohemian folk dance). Another item of the same kind was performed with green wreaths.</p>
   <p>....A group of twenty-five Sokols then performed on three horizontal tree trunks --the Kladina. This type of gymnastic work is not well known here, or rather known only by hear-say, so that its introduction yesterday may [also] be considered as a novelty. The public had a chance to see what beautiful [gymnastic] work may be accomplished with these [new devices]. This work was performed at Lille, France by the Sokols of Bohemia, and [hence] the act itself is called "The Lille twenty-five" [Translator's note: That is, performed by twenty five men]. The Lille exercises are really excellent, consisting of a combination of various gymnastic elements not the least of which are dancing, <pb facs="5418478_4_1009.jpg" n="3"/>setting-up exercises, jumping, etc. The execution of this complex number was good, though in places one could sense the self-consciousness of the performers, a fact, no doubt, due to the strangeness of the apparatus. Forty other men engaged in setting-up exercises; high fidelity and precision of their timing characterized their performance.</p>
   <p>What surprized us most was the participation in these exercises of some seven veterans, that is, men who spent their entire life in Sokol work. They were Brothers Kulicek, Haller, Vokral, Maly, Vinicky, Pesek, and Unger. The oldest one of these was Brother Kulicek who is now sixty-one years of age, and who won his laurels during the first Sokol tournaments organized by the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Society of America) in 1879 in New York City. These oldsters carried on with such verve and lightness that many a young man envied their bearing. Still greater was our astonishment when we saw that these old codgers vied with their young confreres in the aforementioned Lille exercises!.... The applause which followed the performance lasted long....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1010.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Pilsen Sokol teams which have been holding championships in the American Athletic Federation and the International Gymnastic Union for twelve years, and who were hard to beat even by the best Turner teams, were next on the order of the program. After having drilled on the apparatus they received the lion's share of the whole evening performance. It goes without saying that the Pilsen Sokol is proud to have these champions and justly so.....During the last Sokol convention at Prague, the young women gymnastic teams of Sweden have introduced a novelty--a free jump over a horse thus in a way characterizing the flight of birds. Brother Jelinek reproduced this novelty with a select group of young girls. The interesting characteristic of this type of gymnastic exercise consists of a free jump across the length of the horse after a rebound, the performer not being permitted to touch the horse either with her hands or her legs. The performer lands in the outspread arms of the instructor and makes a perfect handstand.</p>
   <p>Our report would be incomplete were we to omit a mention of Brother Karafiat's <pb facs="5418478_4_1011.jpg" n="5"/>excellent orchestra which accompanied the exercises and thus rendered a very valuable service to the performers.</p>
   <p>Brother V. F. Cipra, president of the Pilsen Sokol, warmly addressed the audience before the start of the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
