<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-02">Jan. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">School Progress Evident at Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-02">Jan. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL PROGRESS EVIDENT AT FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Vojta Naprstek School is one of the best of our liberal schools; its teaching staff is making honest efforts to draw the attention of the broader strata of the Czech population of Chicago to the system it follows in the education of our boys and girls. This end is served in an excellent manner by festivities, during which there is exhibited much of the work done by the pupils.</p>
   <p>The twentieth annual festivity in the history of the institute was held yesterday in the main hall of the Sokol Chicago on 24th Street and Kedzie Avenue and proved a success in every respect.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0568.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A prologue recited by Lillian Dolezal opened the evening; it was followed by poems and songs rendered by pupils of the first preparatory class under the tutorship of Mrs. Weiner; the first higher class under Mrs. Kovar, the second class, and the Saturday and Sunday classes were next. "Pohadka o Jaru" (A Spring Tale), by Herma Pilbaur, the well-known writer of plays for children, and Vzachy Kolovratev (The Precious Spinning Wheel), followed by pictures of the National festival in Kladruby, Bohemia, gave more than ample opportunity to the pupils to demonstrate that the work done by the teachers was crowned with success. It would not be fair to single out for praise some of the pupils while all of them deserve to be commended.</p>
   <p>Special mention must be made, however, of the teachers F. Vlach and <pb facs="5418478_4_0569.jpg" n="3"/>Bohumil Hladky, the latter the "daddie" of the Vojta Naprstek school. The school has reached its present high level under the guidance of Mr. Hladky, who draws for experience from actual life and takes not much stock in rigid rules or continual reforms. Not less meritorious is the activity, as concerned with the festival, of Miss Milada Krametbauer, to whom was intrusted the laborious task of training the children for the dances. The excellent orchestra under the baton of Mr. Brousek supplied the music.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
