<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-03">Sept. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Czech Child Belongs to the Czech School (Communication from Frank Veverka, Director) (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-03">Sept. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECH CHILD BELONGS TO THE CZECH SCHOOL (Communication from Frank Veverka, Director) (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"In these days we work chiefly to help the old homeland win independence. This is a sublime idea which will show to the whole world that the Czech nation shall not perish. It will show that our people are still alive, creating works of art, producing scientists in almost all branches of learning. Our Czech nation is capable of developing in both the economic field and the political field in the management of its own affairs, with these high aims in mind, we must not, dear friends, forget ourselves--the Czech branch in American. For, if we work for ourselves, it will not mean the abandonment of the movement for the liberation of the old homeland, or--God forbid--the damaging of it. We shall, on the contrary, show the Americans that we are a healthy people, strong, and full of enterprise, and that we know how to preserve our language even outside the borders of our old homeland."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0550.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>....Let us send our children to Czech schools!.....We have a sufficient number of these schools; when one is needed, it will be provided by the "Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Association for the Maintenance of Czech Freethought Schools).....</p>
   <p>Frank Veverka,</p>
   <p>Director of Czech Schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
