<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-12-10">Dec. 10, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Speculation the Share Holders of Lidovych Novin (Peoples News) Want to Benefit through Bankruptcy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0213</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0213.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-12-10">Dec. 10, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">SPECULATION THE SHARE HOLDERS OF LIDOVYCH NOVIN (PEOPLES NEWS) WANT TO BENEFIT THROUGH BANKRUPTCY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Even before it saw the light of day the shareholders of the paper, which for a little over two years has been published on Centre Ave.,producing shame for Bohemian journalism, showed what shameless speculators they are. The public still remembers the reasons they gave for leaving work at Denni Hlasatel. They wanted the publishers of this paper to divide his property with them, to accept them into their midst, and to deliver to their tender mercies everything we had been able to accumulate after long years of work and economy. It was not sufficient for these people that they had the best working conditions , that they were paid strictly union wages, and that all union working conditions were maintained. They wanted to be partners in a business for which they had never done a good thing and which they injured whenever the opportunity offered. At that time they showed themselves to be speculators and now with their bankruptcy they have proven to the public, that they have not reformed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0214.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Lidove Noviny admitted bankruptcy in order to rid itself of debts and some inconvenient people, in order to attract new people, who might have money and want to give it into their mercies. How such people would fare is best indicated by the fact that Lidovy Noviny in not quite three years made about $22,000 of debts. The firm's property is not worth $4,000.</p>
   <p>The fate of that paper is to be decided Saturday. The shareholders are spreading reports that they already have people who will provide them with money and set them up on their feet again, but that someone would put money up for such bad security is not believed by the public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
