<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-08">Nov. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian-American Press Bureau at the Threshold of its Third Year</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0189</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0189.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-08">Nov. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN PRESS BUREAU AT THE THRESHOLD OF ITS THIRD YEAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With great tasks before it, but with many accomplishments already achieved, the Cesko-Americka Tiskova Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) stands at the threshold of its third year. During the past two years, the Bureau undertook more than one enterprise which seemed to be daring and beyond the power of the small group of enthusiasts who constitute the Bureau. Even its friends and opponents did not believe success was possible, and, therefore, predicted failure. However, there has not been a single task undertaken thus far which the Bohemian-American Press Bureau has not managed successfully, and often, as for instance in the activity in opposition of Count Appony, the million-cent collection for the scholastic association in the homeland etc., surpassed all expectations.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian-American Press Bureau, organized and supported by a group of enlightened individuals, societies and unities, which approve its purpose <pb facs="5418478_4_0190.jpg" n="2"/>and accomplishments, still has many great tasks before it. Foremost of these is the carrying through to accomplishment the lecture tour, arranged for the Czech historian, Doctor Luetz, in the large American universities.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian-American Press Bureau, as is mentioned above, is supported by voluntary contributions from members, individuals, and societies.</p>
   <p>Before commencing its third year, it is necessary for the board of directors, which is composed of Messrs. Stepina, Beranek, Psenka, Skala, and Fucik, to see to the means for maintaining the Bureau for the entire next year. For that purpose, invitations were sent to a certain number of countrymen, who are known for their comprehension of the national cause and their generosity, and who are able to contribute without suffering hardship thereby. These persons were asked to become members of the Bohemian-American Press Bureau. The first to reply favorably to the invitation and to remit his membership dues to the treasurer was Mr. Karel Novak, proprietor of a paint store on Blue Island Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0191.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In its last meeting, which was held last Saturday, the Board of Directors received the report of Mr. Novak's prompt and courteous reply with pleasure, and expressed the hope that it would soon be able to announce to the Bohemian public the names of more new members of the Bohemian-American Press Bureau. Five members of the Board of Directors subscribed forty dollars for the maintenance of the office. This is indeed a promising beginning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
