<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-04-11">Apr. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Interest in Bohemian-American Literature</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-04-11">Apr. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">INTEREST IN BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN LITERATURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago a certain Chicago daily brought the news that a well-known local banker has donated a one-hundred-dollar prize for the best dramatic or other literary work by a Bohemian-American author. A contest will be conducted to determine the winner of this prize. A committee of judges will be selected especially for this purpose. The Bohemian-American public will no doubt welcome this news and show deserved appreciation to the donor for his noble act, because literature, too, is one of the component elements of Bohemian national life in America--indeed, an element of considerable importance.</p>
   <p>Certainly all of us hope and trust that the American branch of the Bohemian nation--our branch--will prosper and grow stronger; that it will not wither; and that the Bohemian element will not disappear like a drop in the immense sea of other nations. This is also the only ultimate aim and purpose of our Bohemian-American national groups. What else would they be striving for but <pb facs="5418478_4_0069.jpg" n="2"/>that we do not perish; that we do not lose the strategic positions gained so far; that these positions be enlarged and strengthened? This is also the reason why all of our associations, lodges, and societies contribute so generously to our Bohemian schools; and there is nobody who would dare to maintain that money spent on schools is money wasted. We do not want to see our youth lose its nationality entirely; forget its origin, its native tongue. The old statement of Vaclav Hanka (a Bohemian patriot of the first decades of the nineteenth century) that a nation does not die as long as its language lives, has not yet lost any of its validity. By saving our language we shall save our nationality.</p>
   <p>What then is the first and foremost means of keeping our language from drowning in the torrent of foreign streams? Without a doubt, it is literature. It is the Bohemian book which keeps us thinking and feeling Bohemian, and which will guide the vessel of our national existence through the rocky waters and keep it from foundering in America.</p>
   <p>To try to prove this is unnecessary. All we need is to look into the history <pb facs="5418478_4_0070.jpg" n="3"/>of the Bohemian nation at the beginning of the nineteenth century when it began to awaken to a new life from a sleep of almost two hundred years; when, as if by a miracle, it accomplished its resurrection; and to the astonishment of all Europe, it stood up at the side of other nations who had never believed that it would revive. Then it was the Bohemian book that performed this miracle and awakened in us the desire for a new respectable life. It was not the sword that accomplished this resurrection and brought about the renaissance of ancient Bohemia--it was the writer's pen. For this reason our countrymen in Bohemia hold their authors in high esteem and honor them as resurrectors.</p>
   <p>However, the developments in our American branch have been quite different. We did not need to be awakened from an age-long sleep. It was not necessary to prove that we are a living nation--all that we need here is to maintain, promote, and strengthen our national consciousness. And that is the duty of literature. So far, the Bohemian-American literature has been pitifully poor. This can easily be explained by the proverbial American haste and hustling, the maddening chase after material and financial success which makes it difficult <pb facs="5418478_4_0071.jpg" n="4"/>even for the most fine-feeling and idealistic people to devote their efforts to something seemingly as petty and inconsequential as literature. In this, however, we Bohemians are not alone. It is characteristic of all America, which, with all its greatness, its stirring history, can point to only a very small number of really important writers. Just a few names will cover this field.</p>
   <p>It is a great pity that Bohemian literature in America has not had an opportunity to develop and prosper. The life of Bohemians in this land of freedom differs so greatly from the life in the old country. It is so interesting and so distinctive in character that an able treatment of American life would enrich our literature to a surprisingly large degree. The life of a Bohemian in America--what a fascinating and promising theme for an author!</p>
   <p>It behooves us, therefore, to welcome gratefully and with satisfaction the news that some of our prominent men have started to show an interest in this phase of our national life--an interest which is not only academic, but,as it <pb facs="5418478_4_0072.jpg" n="5"/>should be in America, practical. Our benefactor's offer of a literary prize is a noble, cultural deed. It is the first experiment of this kind. For the first time our Bohemian-American writers have an opportunity to enter into competition and show their mettle, their literary skill. Every competition is a very valuable encouragement for new efforts, which no doubt will also prove to be true in this case.</p>
   <p>Bohemian writers are not numerous in America. But the contest will certainly show that there are among them some who can stand an honorable comparison even with authors of renown in the old country, and who will prove that the sprig of the Bohemian linden tree which has been transplanted to America can also produce attractive blossoms and bear beautiful fruit in the field of literature. It is to be hoped that many valuable and interesting manuscripts will be entered in the contest. If such contests were more frequent--we trust that this example will soon find many followers among our benefactors--a new American branch of Bohemian literature would develop before long--a branch with its own individual color, its own peculiar character and distinctiveness.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0073.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This new branch would bring us greater honor in the old country.</p>
   <p>Neither the date of the competition nor the appointment of the judges has yet been made public. It would be desirable to have judges who are literary experts, capable of indicating a correct opinion on the entered manuscripts and making a just, unprejudiced decision. However, with the small number of both authors and literary experts, the selection of the jury will certainly be difficult, because all authors will probably enter the competition and therefore be ineligible for judging the manuscripts.</p>
   <p>But for the time being, such matters cannot mar our pleasure in seeing that Bohemian-American literature has also aroused interest in nonliterary circles, and our public may look forward with a great deal of expectation to the results of the first contest of this kind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
