<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1881-11-22">Nov. 22, 1881</date><title level="a">The Bohemian Section of the City Public Library</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1881-11-22">Nov. 22, 1881</date><title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN SECTION OF THE CITY PUBLIC LIBRARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian Section of the Public Library, which has really existed only since Mr. L.W. Kadleck was appointed to the Board of Directors by Chicago's present Mayor C.H. Harrison, is now quite a separate unit, having much valuable literature from former times as well as of the present day. The Library now has more than 1,000 bound volumes of high literary value, for care is exercised in selection of material so that no trash will be accumulated.</p>
   <p>Through the efforts of Mr. Kadlec, there was received the first shipment of books, of the value of 1,100 crowns. These books are now in the Bohemian Section of the library, from where they may be borrowed by any one who has complied with the rules as set up by the Library.</p>
   <p>Shortly after the receipt of this first order of books, there was placed a larger order. This last order has been delayed some what because many of the older volumes were not in stock at the booksellers and had to be obtained from private individuals who were willing to sell. Since all the books ordered could not be obtained at one time, shipment was made of those that could be had. The shipment consisted of more than 1,373 volumes of fiction, educational and scientific works, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0107.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As soon as the shipment arrives and is checked, they will be turned over to the bindery and efforts will be made to have them available for circulation as soon as possible. Our Library will then have over 2,000 volumes of the finest Bohemian poets and authors and will be a Library of which Chicago Bohemians may justly be proud. No where in Bohemia is there a library which can boast of such a large number of the finest and richest writings.</p>
   <p>This does not mean that we need to be satisfied with these 2,000 volumes. If we just care about it, surely the Bohemian section of the library will continue to grow.</p>
   <p>The Directors of the Public Library, set aside each year various amounts for the purchase of books and it will, no doubt, provide as much as possible for Bohemian books.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kadlec will have no difficulty in securing allotments for the purchase of Bohemian Literature, if he is given support by those most interested, and this support costs no one anything. It merely means that we Bohemians should make use of the Library service now that we have been recognized and books provided for us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
