<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-22">June 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Press Club Host to Czechoslovak Army Officers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-22">June 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO PRESS CLUB HOST TO CZECHOSLOVAK ARMY OFFICERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Press Club, whose members come from circles of journalists, literati, musicians, and other artists has extended an invitation to four officers of the Czechoslovak Army in France who are sojourning in Chicago at present. This news was conveyed to us by Mr. James F. Stepina, treasurer of the Club. Professor Thomas G. Masaryk was also a guest of the Club some time ago.</p>
   <p>Second Lieutenant Miloslav Niederle, who speaks the English language well, will address the members, and present a survey of the activities of the Czechoslovak Army in France and Russia. He was in the Austrian Army when he was captured by the Russians. While a prisoner of war, he helped form the Czechoslovak Army which, under the command of General Brusilov, fought against the Austrians on the side of the Russians. This Army is now a detached unit, and is fighting under the supreme command in France.</p>
   <p>Lieutenant Niederle's comrades are First Lieutenant Ant. Holy,and second Lieutenants <pb facs="5418478_4_0056.jpg" n="2"/>Oldrich Spaniel and Jos. Horvat. They have come to Chicago to promote enlistment in the Czechoslovak Army in France and in the Allied armies in general. Professor Jar. J. Zmrhal will also be one of the speakers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
