<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-06-02">June 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol V Chicagu</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0494</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0494.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-06-02">June 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE SDRUZENI CESKYCH SVOBODOMYSLNYCH SKOL V CHICAGU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following are the minutes of the regular meeting of the Sdruzeni Svobodomyslnych Skol v Chicagu (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools of Chicago), held May 21, 1921:</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by the chairman, Mr. Joseph Tichava, in the presence of all the officers and a large number of delegates. After the delegates were welcomed by Mr. Tichava, the reading of the minutes of the previous meeting followed. The minutes were approved as read. The minutes of the past meeting of the executive committee were also approved.</p>
   <p>The reading of letters followed. A letter received from Mr. Joseph Macha, former school teacher at the Vojta Naprstek Free Thought School, was read. At the present time he is an employee at the Czechoslovak Embassy in Washington, D. C., <pb facs="5418478_4_0495.jpg" n="2"/>and in his letter he asks for a letter of recommendation. His request was acknowledged and the secretary was ordered to answer. The Bohemian California Branch of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America) sends a gift of $25 for the benefit of the Bohemian Free Thought schools. The gift was acknowledged and the secretary was ordered to send a letter of thanks. The Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Czecho-Slavonic Union), through its secretary, Mr. Adolph Hrusa, informs the Federation that twenty-five percent of the net proceeds of a picnic, which is to be given by the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota, July 31, 1921, will be donated to the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol. It was acknowledged and the secretary was ordered to send a letter of thanks. The Patronat Skoly Jan Neruda (board of trustees of the Jan Neruda Free Thought School) informs the Federation that it is repaying the sum of $300 which sum was loaned to the Patronat by the Federation some time ago for the erection of a school building. The remittance was acknowledged. The Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Fraternal Benevolent Societies sends the sum of $10 as a voluntary contribution.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0496.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The meeting continued with the reading of the quarterly report of the editor of the Svobodna Skola (Free School). The report was approved. The executive committee recommended that the school children pay the sum of one dollar for three months; fifty cents of this amount will be turned over to the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol. During the debate which followed, a motion was made to postpone the vote upon this question for one month. Mr. Hudecek's motion that the vote be taken at once, because the money is needed, was seconded by a delegate of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Unity of Bohemian Ladies). The vote was then taken and nineteen delegates voted in favor of the payment of one dollar for three months. Sixteen delegates voted for the postponement, and the rest of the delegates did not vote. It was further called to attention that only the free thought idea should be taught at the schools. Mr. Prochazka, in his speech, attacked the textbooks; he said that there is very little free thought reading, and he also complained that the schools are not free thought schools at all. Mrs. Polak then explained that the free thought ideas are taught at the schools, but that more money is needed for the maintenance of the teachers, and furthermore, <pb facs="5418478_4_0497.jpg" n="4"/>that the attendance at the school classes is not as great as it should be. The chairman, Mr. Joseph Tichava, mentioned that there is very little chance of accomplishing a great deal because, in the first place, in order to accomplish anything there must be sufficient funds to pay the teachers. In addition, the teachers must be ordered to teach along the lines of free thought. It was resolved that after vacations one of the teachers shall visit each class once every week and lecture on free thought exclusively.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Cepelak, financial secretary of the Federation, reported that she sent letters to thirty Bohemian banks and business establishments requesting contributions in behalf of the Bohemian Free Thought schools. Only two banks responded and each sent a contribution of $10. These were the Adams State Bank and the Twenty-sixth Street State Bank. Mrs. Radesinsky presented a motion that the Bohemian amateur dramatic clubs be asked to arrange a theatrical performance at least once a year for the benefit of the Bohemian Free Thought schools, The motion was carried. Mrs. Tobias then reported on the theatrical performance which was <pb facs="5418478_4_0498.jpg" n="5"/>given at the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies' Hall, and said that the proceeds will be fair. The chairman, Mr. Tichava, thanked Mrs. Tobias and Mrs. Wainer for their good will, because only through their efforts was the success of the theatrical performance attained. The chairman reported that the Chicago district committee of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe appropriated the sum of $200 to be used to cover the running expenses connected with the arrangement of the Posvicenska Slavnost (Countrywake Festival) and which will be arranged for the benefit of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol v Chicagu.</p>
   <p>As there was no other business on hand, the reading of receipts and expenditures followed.</p>
   <p>Karel Soukup, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
