<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-09">Nov. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Formation of the Sokol Tabor Slovanske Lipy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-09">Nov. 9, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FORMATION OF THE SOKOL TABOR SLOVANSKE LIPY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>January 1, 1915, has been selected as the day on which a new Sokol unit will be introduced into the Svaz Narodni Jednoty Sokolske (Federation of the National Sokol Union). It will be the strongest Sokol unit west of New York, and no doubt next to the Sokol New York, the strongest unit in the United States. It is the Sokol Tabor Slovanske Lipy (Sokol unit called Tabor Slovanske Lipy) which will unite the memberships of the Sokol Tabor and Sokol Slovanska Lipa at the beginning of the coming year.</p>
   <p>Such was the decision of the committee of eighteen members of both of these bodies, which, until now have led an independent existence. Their ladies' groups, auxiliaries, and similar bodies will also be united on January 1, 1915.....</p>
   <p>It may be well to recall some of the historical data concerning these units.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1242.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Soko Tabor was founded on December 21, 1890, in the old Pertl's hall on 40th Court and Twelfth Street. Now, after an active life of twenty-four years, it has a membership of 208 men and 225 women. It owns a building at 13th Street and Karlov Avenue which is free of any indebtedness, and its cash assets are estimated at $18,000.</p>
   <p>The Sokol Slovanska Lipa has a membership of 190 men and 60 women. Its hall is situated near Canal Street on De Koven Street. It comes close to being a historical landmark in Chicago, because it is the oldest Bohemian national clubhouse in the city. The Sokol Slovanska Lipa was formed in 1892 by a merger of the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol (Gymnastic Union Sokol) which was founded in 1871, with the Cesko-Americky Sokol (Bohemian-American Sokol), whose origin goes back to 1868.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
