<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-24">Sept. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Encouraging News from Vojta Naprstek School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-24">Sept. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">ENCOURAGING NEWS FROM VOJTA NAPRSTEK SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A bit of most gratifying news has reached us from the Ceska Svobodna Skola Vojta Naprstek (Czech Free Thought School Vojta Naprstek. In spite of the raise in tuition which the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodnych Skol (Federation of Czech Free Thought Schools) had found it necessary to introduce, there were over five hundred pupils enrolled in our largest Free Thought school, Vojta Naprstek. It seems that the Free Thought part of our public is beginning to realize the importance of educating our youth so that it may some day serve as a solid support of our national organizations; that it realizes the importance of Free Thought schools in times where sinister, reactionary influences of various churches vie in trapping young souls. The Patronat (Board of Directors) of the School appreciates this large enrollment particularly because this school will celebrate its twenty-fifth anniversary this year. It will be twenty-five years next November 17 since a handful of Free Thought men got together who have "made something out of almost nothing," <pb facs="5418478_4_0442.jpg" n="2"/>and by overcoming obstacles which were being put in their way by the hundreds, laid the foundation for the largest Czech school in the metropolis of American Czechs.</p>
   <p>The School will observe the anniversary by a fitting celebration in which its pupils, its alumni, and its friends among the public will participate, and the Patronat is hoping that the public participation will be of really large proportions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
