<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-11-22">Nov. 22, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Thirtieth Anniversary of Sokol Slavsky</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Slavsky Receives Clear Proof of Public Favor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-11-22">Nov. 22, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE THIRTIETH ANNIVERSARY OF SOKOL SLAVSKY</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Slavsky Receives Clear Proof of Public Favor</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That the activity of those organizations which are deserving of credit for the growth of our national life, which have been working unselfishly for noble causes, is carefully watched by our people, was proven at the anniversary celebration held in Pilsen Park Pavilion yesterday. The spacious Pilsen Park Pavilion was crowded with our countrymen who came to manifest their thanks for all that which Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Slavsky (Sokol Slavsky Gymnastic Association) had accomplished during the period of thirty long years, and at the same time to encourage its members to further energetic work.</p>
   <p>Sokol Slavsky, indeed, fully deserves the favors of every enlightened fellow countryman and all of its undertakings should be heartily and generously supported. It is just as the principal speaker, the beloved leader of Sokol Slavsky, Brother Jarka Kosar, rightly declared before the gathering: <pb facs="5418478_4_1134.jpg" n="2"/>that the Sokol Slavsky has demonstrated many a time, by deeds, and not by empty phrases and loud slogans, that it knows where its place is and knows how to work to the best advantage of the Sokol movement here in America. Although it was the first Sokol unit whose members began to wear the old country Sokol uniform, "cervene kosile" (red shirts), and notwithstanding the thirty years of its activities, the Sokol Slavsky had been unable to erect its own Sokolovna (Sokol Hall). The sole reason for this was that thousands of dollars in contributions had been turned toward causes which Sokol Slavsky thought to be of more importance. All efforts of Sokol Slavsky were concentrated upon persistent and unselfish work, the removal of obstacles, and the giving of help whenever it seemed necessary. The members of Sokol Slavsky are real Bohemians, real Sokols, and that large numbers of our people are recognizing this fact, was demonstrated yesterday.</p>
   <p>The entire program, presented at this festival was dignified in every respect. Various numbers of the program were loudly applauded by the audience. First, the secretary of the association, Sokol Brichta, greeted the audience.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The principal speaker, Sokol Jarka Kosar, whose reputation as a famed orator cannot be questioned, was then introduced. There are only very few speakers who can touch the hearts and souls of their listeners as he does.....</p>
   <p>Sokol Slavsky received a great number of congratulatory communications from many of our national organizations and individuals. But because of the impossibility of reading all of them, only one, from the Ceska Obec Sokolska v Americe (American Sokol Union), was selected and read.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
