<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-12-22">Dec. 22, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Festive Opening of the New Building by the Patronage of the Bohemian-English Liberal School, the "C.S.P.S". (Czechoslovak Benevolent Society)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-12-22">Dec. 22, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVE OPENING OF THE NEW BUILDING BY THE PATRONAGE OF THE BOHEMIAN-ENGLISH LIBERAL SCHOOL, THE "C.S.P.S". (CZECHOSLOVAK BENEVOLENT SOCIETY)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opening of the new building at 48th and Honore Streets was celebrated with a festive ceremonial at 2:30 P. M. yesterday afternoon, by the (Czecho-Slovak Benevolent Society) C.S.P.S. Patronage of the Bohemian-English Liberal School, in the presence of a large, enthusiastic crowd of people. The grand celebration was begun by the chairman of the celebration-committee Mr. Jan Krajicek. He made a hearty welcoming address, and introduced the chairman of the Patronage Mr. A. Komzacek.</p>
   <p>I welcome all of you to today's significant and joyful celebration.</p>
   <p>We are celebrating the opening of our national building, our headquarters of liberal-mindedness and a home for our patriotic and benevolent societies. With a feeling of pride and joy we look upon the work of our generosity and community effort.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0729.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Following this speech the President of the "C.S.P.S. "(Czecho-Slovak Benevolent Society) Grand Lodge, Mr. Orth addressed the gathering:</p>
   <p>"Esteemed Assembly! In time-honored Prague, in the mother-country, on the banks of the foam-flecked, silvery Moldau, below the historic "Vysehrad" (high Castle), a beautiful, golden building rises towards the heavens. This building, built and constructed, by and for the Bohemian nation, awakened it from its national lethargy. When the news that this seat of Czech culture and art was destroyed by a disastrous conflagration reached the Czech borders, Czech cities, and hamlets, it was not believed, doubt was expressed as to the possibility of such a great national disaster. However, when the report of the disaster was fully confirmed, young and old, men and women, boys and girls wept; the sorrow beheld on all faces was indescribable. Out of this pain there came to every Bohemian, a new alarm which was carried to all regions, which animated us anew.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0730.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Then he explained the purpose of the new building. The building is to be a temple of healthy reason, a pavilion of harmony, equality, brotherhood, and art.</p>
   <p>The speeches and declamations were brought to a close. When the Bohemian-Workers Singing Society, Volnost rendered Probuzeni (The Awakening).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
