<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-09-01">Sept. 1, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Public Reading Room at 543-545 Blue Island Ave Opened</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-09-01">Sept. 1, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC READING ROOM AT 543-545 BLUE ISLAND AVE OPENED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The literature and reading loving public of Bohemian Chicago has at last reached its goal for the long needed public reading-room was opened in the center of the Bohemian quarter yesterday, at 543-545 Blue Island Ave, not far from 18th St. The reading-room was opened to the public at 8 P.M. by the Public Library board. The opening was attended by Messrs. Hild, librarian; Wickersham, secretary; Purer, manager of the public library and Eckert, Tyffe, Lindstrand, Depres and Broxeau, members of the library commission. In addition to these, we saw Alderman Hurt, Mr. Walleck, Mr. Souhrada, and many local citizens who filled the spacious reading room.</p>
   <p>From the attendance, it is apparent that there are many, very many of those who are interested in the reading-room, and especially pleasing was the attendance of our youth. It is surely the hope of everyone that our youth should continue to visit the reading-room with the same interest that was shown by it yesterday.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0096.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our reading room is spacious, well lighted, and nicely arranged, and the members of the Library board made no secret of it, and that it is one of the finest reading rooms in the city. The stock of books is not complete as yet, especially so far as Bohemian books are concerned, because they have just been ordered; however, everything will be arranged in the course of a few days. The selection of English books is fine, for there are books here, such as are to be found in the "Model Library" at the St. Louis Worlds Fair, which was awarded first prize. There is a whole group of various dictionaries, educational books, collections of historical writings, biographies, scientific, books on economics and fiction, and a large selection of volumes for children. Further, there are here, or already ordered, many newspapers and magazines, English, Bohemian, Polish, German and French. In addition to the books now at the reading room, there have been ordered an additional 1,500 volumes. By means of the reading room it will be possible to borrow, free of charge, any kind of a book from the public library.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0097.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The reading room will be open on week days from 12 o'clock noon to 9 o'clock in the evening and on Sundays from noon to 6 P.M. Mr. Frederic Rex was appointed manager and began his duties today. We hope, that this reading room will continue to enjoy the attention of the local Bohemian community and that its beneficient influence will soon bear the desired fruit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
