<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-03">May 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Erect Monument to Karel Havlicek Borovsky</title><title level="a" type="sub">Last Act Yesterday When Statue Was Set Upon Foundation; Preparations in Progress for Unveiling Ceremony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-03">May 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ERECT MONUMENT TO KAREL HAVLICEK BOROVSKY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Last Act Yesterday When Statue Was Set Upon Foundation; Preparations in Progress For Unveiling Ceremony</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The old yearnings of the Bohemians of Chicago, and of America in general, to immortalize our national martyr, Karel Havlicek Borovsky, were fulfilled at 11:30 o'clock yesterday morning. At that time, the main construction work had been completed, and the statue of the Brixen martyr, which had been brought here from the homeland, was placed firmly upon the foundation stone.</p>
   <p>The bronze figure of our hero rises on a beautiful soot in Douglas Park today, in a pose which is suggestive of his motto:</p>
   <p>"You may continue promising me,</p>
   <p>You may persist in threatening me,</p>
   <p>Still a traitor I shall not be."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1565.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The monument is located on Ogden Avenue at Albany Avenue, near the boulevard, where, for several days, the work of building the foundation had been going on. All preparatory work was finally finished yesterday, and at ten-thirty o'clock, the box containing the statue was opened. The task of placing the statue upon its pedestal was begun immediately. This was done in the presence of a crowd of on-lookers, who encircled the site, and under the supervision of the park commissioners, with chairman Kolacek, and secretary Mungler in charge. Others present were: the committee, representing the Associated Societies: Messrs. T. G. Pilivky, F. J. Benes. V. Sedlacek; Mr. Heller, of Heller and Gregor, which firm did the mason work; superintendent Schroeder of Douglas Park and others.</p>
   <p>The foundation stone, which weighs two and one half tons, rests upon a marble plane, to which leads one step. At the rear is located a large tablet, of polished gray stone, fastened between two white marble columns. This tablet bears the following inscription:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1566.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The martyred statesman of Bohemia, beloved by his countrymen.</p>
   <p>Born October 31, 1821.</p>
   <p>Died July 29, 1856"</p>
   <p>In him Bohemia lost</p>
   <p>One of her best sons,</p>
   <p>a fearless defender of her rights and liberties,</p>
   <p>a man of sterling character ever true to his convictions</p>
   <p>for which he sacrificed his life!</p>
   <p>Undying honor to his memory!</p>
   <p>Dedicated by the American-Bohemians to the State of Illinois. Erected A.D. 1911.</p>
   <p>The festive unveiling ceremonies are to occur on Saturday and Sunday, July 29 and 30. It is to be a grand celebration, which will be participated in by more <pb facs="5418478_4_1567.jpg" n="4"/>Bohemians than have ever taken part in any previous affair. The committee has already begun making preparations so that this Bohemian monument may be unveiled in an imposing manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
