<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-10-31">Oct. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">John Huss Memorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-10-31">Oct. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN HUSS MEMORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our report on Monday's meeting of the Družstvo (board of representatives) for the building of the John Huss Memorial, we promised to bring an authentic statement concerning this undertaking as presented to the meeting by the originator of the idea, Dr. František Iška. Dr. Iška was chairman of the press and publicity subcommittee of the preparatory committee for the erection of the John Huss Memorial in Chicago, and his report is of particular interest because it gives a complete list of all organizations working on the idea, together with amounts remitted to the committee or collected and ready to be remitted on short notice. It will be noticed with special satisfaction that a very large number of our organizations from Western states are on the list. Dr. Iska's report reads:</p>
   <p>"The idea of erecting a John Huss Memorial originated in 1905. During a John Huss celebration held that year, we called attention to the fact that in ten years, in 1915, we shall be commemorating the five-hundredth anniversary of the death of our martyr. We said that we thought it was a duty of <pb facs="5418478_4_1477.jpg" n="2"/>Bohemians in America to impress upon the whole world--as it will be the whole world that will participate in the commemoration of this anniversary--that John Huss was a member of our nation. For this reason something should be done that would attract greater attention than mere speeches and an empty display of pomp. At the same time, whatever was to be done should be of definite and permanent value for us, both in respect to our national and Free Thought objectives.</p>
   <p>"For these two groups of objectives we have been working for over fifty years. Although considerable results have been achieved, we cannot help, but feel that our progress is not such as we wish it to be. The reason for this is well known. Our work is lacking the proper co-ordination and concentration. The need of systematic and educational work is generally recognized in our Free-thinking organizations. One proof of this is the fact that the appointment of educational committees has been ordered by all conventions held recently. As examples, I shall mention the conventions of the Západní Ceská Bratrská Jednota (Western Bohemian Fraternal Unity) at Omaha, and the Sokol mass <pb facs="5418478_4_1478.jpg" n="3"/>convention at Baltimore. Also the decision of the convention of the Cesko-Slovanské Podporující Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) in Milwaukee to establish 'clubs for adolescent youth' (Dorostové Kluby) is due to the recognition that there is an extreme need for educational work. There is no doubt that many other Jednoty (Unions) will follow this lead, and we shall have many educational clubs and committees, every one of which, and each by itself, will strive to achieve its end; but the aggregate of their results cannot possibly be expected to approximate results that could be achieved if the work they do each as a separate unit were by the full co-operation of all, and directed by one central institution, one headquarters.</p>
   <p>"What we need most, then, is a headquarters for our work, both Free Thought and national. The realization of this chief need gave birth to the idea of building in Chicago, the recognized Bohemian-American metropolis, a John Huss Memorial which would be the focal point of work for the benefit of all Bohemian-American communities, all our Free Thought organizations, and which would give the initiative and encouragement to serious national and Free Thought endeavors throughout Bohemian-America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1479.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"This Memorial will be dedicated to this purpose on the occasion of the five-hundredth anniversary of John Huss's death. The 1910 John Huss celebration in Pilsen Park furnished an excellent opportunity to explain this idea to the Bohemian Freethinking public. It was received with great enthusiasm, and, upon the recommendation of Mr. Fr. B. Zdrubek, the plan was approved by the two thousand men and women attending the celebration. Subsequently, it was explained by us in detail in a series of articles which Editor Zdrubek published in Svojan (Free Thought organ). In June, 1911, a call was issued to all Free Thought and other Bohemian-American organizations to express their opinion of the idea, with the result that within one month's time, fifty of them pledged their co-operation and help. By March, 1912, we had the promise of 162 societies and lodges from all parts of the United States, and even from Canada.</p>
   <p>"Thus we started with the formation of a preparatory committee for the building of the John Huss Memorial, making it clear in advance that this committee considers itself a temporary organization, the principal purpose of which is <pb facs="5418478_4_1480.jpg" n="5"/>to give proper publicity to the idea, and which will in 1913, surrender its leadership to a Družstvo composed of representatives of societies and organizations which will, by that time, have proved their serious desire to co-operate by establishing a fund for the Memorial. The preparatory committee unanimously designated the amount of twenty-five dollars as sufficient to entitle a society to be represented in the Družstvo, and each additional one hundred dollars to entitle it to one additional vote or representative."</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: There follows a list of 19 orders of the Cesko-Slovanské Podporující Spolky, (Cecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) 5 lodges of the Jednota Taboritu (Unity of Taborites), 3 lodges of the Cesko-Slovanská Jednota (Bohemian-Slavonic Unity) 5 orders of the Cesko-Slovanská Bratrská Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian-Slavonic Fraternal Benevolent Unity), 2 courts of the Cesko-Americtí Lesníci A Lesnice (Bohemian-American Foresters), 29 orders of the Cesko-Bratrská Jednota (Bohemian Fraternal Unity), 1 order of the Cesko-Americka Jednota (Bohemian American Unity), 3 units of the Sokol (Gymnastic <pb facs="5418478_4_1481.jpg" n="6"/>organization), 8 Svobodne Obce (Free Thought Communities), and 5 orders of the Zapadni Cesko-Slovenska Podporujici Jednota (Western Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Unity) of the State of Texas. All these have subscribed, have on hand, or are collecting funds for the Memorial, and have sent in their reports.]</p>
   <p>"A number of women's organizations have bought stamps, voiced their approval, or promised their support of the Memorial, but have not been included in the list because of no binding action on their part. The same applies to a number of men's organizations who are known to be working and collecting, but so far have not sent in any reports on results they may be getting.</p>
   <p>"While it is not possible at this time to make a definite statement of the amount which is now available for the Memorial--some reports are old, some incomplete--I dare say that it is over ten thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>"This, of course, is not a great deal, if we consider that the erection of the John Huss Memorial will require at least five times as much, if it is to be adequate in every respect for the requirements of the important work we are attempting. However, if we bear in mind the fact that these results <pb facs="5418478_4_1482.jpg" n="7"/>have been attained during a comparatively short time of mere preparations, what we have achieved so far is truly surprising and, in view of the conditions prevailing among our Freethinking organizations, unusual.</p>
   <p>"These results make us feel sure that the John Huss Memorial funds,wherever established, will now grow rapidly, and new ones will be starting. Over three hundred organizations have voiced their approval, and more than one hundred of them, in addition to those on our list, have promised that they will give their support as soon as the undertaking takes on a more definite form. Also, contributions from individuals are coming in steadily. It may justly be said that the John Huss Memorial has aroused a far greater interest and has been receiving much more generous support throughout America than any undertaking of Freethinkers in the past. Our hopes for complete success are therefore fully justified. We trust that the Druzstvo, which is now being organized, will show an accomplishment which will be truly magnificent and memorable--an accomplishment which will serve to increase the prestige of Bohemian-America and will prove beneficial to us and to those who will come after us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
