<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-11">July 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Vojta Naprstek School Dedicated During Simple Ceremony Last Sunday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-11">July 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE VOJTA NAPRSTEK SCHOOL DEDICATED DURING SIMPLE CEREMONY LAST SUNDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, the Vojta Naprstek School at Homan Avenue and Twenty-sixth Street was dedicated, although it has not been completed, and will require several weeks work before such is the case.</p>
   <p>A parade of school children, together with their teachers, started from the school building on Spaulding Avenue at about one o'clock. With Mr. Brousek's band in the lead, the parade moved along Kedzie Avenue, past the present school quarters in Sokol Chicago Hall to Twenty-fourth Street, there west to Homan Avenue, and south to the new school building.</p>
   <p>The many participants were very much disappointed when they saw the building without windows, without doors and not clean. At the front was hung a portrait of Vojta Naprstek, and his never-to-be-forgotten wife.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0679.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The parade came to a halt here, and the president of the trustees, Mr. Dusil, explained briefly to the gathering that as a result of the striking plumbers, the building could not be finished. The plumbers, divided into two unfriendly groups, left the work unfinished three months ago. Week after week, they promised to proceed with the work and complete it before the day set for the ceremony, but nothing was done. For that reason the committee, restrained by the continual delay, decided to hold the ceremony and deliver the building as it is to the public. Asking the pardon of the gathering for its disappointment, he announced that the festivities would be continued in the Pilsen Brewery Park. The parade then moved along Twenty-sixth Street toward the park in the same order as it had arrived. First, the band, followed by the school children, Jan Neruda lodge of C.S.P.S. (Czecho-Slovak Benevolent Society with their lodge colors, then in carriages a deputation from J.C.D. (Bohemian Women's Unity), the central committee of the C.S.P.S., and a deputation of Pilsen Dandies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0680.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The festivities were continued in the pavilion of Pilsen Park with Mr. Dusil calling upon the delegates of the several lodges belonging to the trustee, the majority of whom alas! were not present.</p>
   <p>In behalf of lodge, Jan Neruda, C. S. P. S., Mr. Valav Novak addressed a few heartfelt words to the children. Other speakers were: Mr. Ribal, Mr. Rud. Polivka, Mr. Vesely, Mrs. Stepanek, Mrs. Pech, Mrs. Brichta, Mrs. Kolar. Each of the speakers turned over a monetary contribution, for the benefit of the school, which was accepted by the committee with thanks.</p>
   <p>The rest of the program, such as festive speeches, and so forth, was dispensed with and a pleasant entertainment to the sounds of the band ensued.</p>
   <p>It is really regrettable that the celebration, which should have been taken <pb facs="5418478_4_0681.jpg" n="4"/>part in by the entire Bohemian public, and which should have been the most significant, met with so little success. We believe that the trustees of the Vojta Naprstek School, especially the old pioneers, who deserve the major portion of the credit for the school, and the good bringing up of Bohemian youth, did not deserve such disappointment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
