<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-01">Feb. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">John Huss Memorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-01">Feb. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN HUSS MEMORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The auxiliary committee, which promotes decorative improvements on the building dedicated to the memory of John Huss, is sending out an appeal to all members of the Free Thought community in Chicago to appear at a meeting in the Huss House, February 3, at 3 P. M. The auxiliary committee has made it its duty to bring the appearance of the building up to a high level, so that the edifice will serve as a dignified memorial, a monument to remind the American people of the deeds of the undaunted protagonist of truth.</p>
   <p>The Huss House should also serve as a spiritual center for our future generations and a meeting place for all sincere Freethinkers in Czech-America. We urge all of you to extend a helping hand in so noble an enterprise and to show that you know how to honor our great men.</p>
   <p>We also entreat all friends of the Huss House, in Chicago and surrounding districts, to become members of the auxiliary committee and to help make the <pb facs="5418478_4_1418.jpg" n="2"/>memorial a home, the pride of all real adherents of Free Thought. The membership fee is only one dollar per year and will be used for improvements.</p>
   <p>Let us all join and demonstrate that no matter how long we Czechs have been away from the land of our ancestors, who suffered and gave their lives for the rights and the purification of the Czech people and the Czech nation, we never forget.</p>
   <p>We hope that this appeal will not remain unheeded, and that the Huss House will become the headquarters for all Czech Free Thought organizations and liberal-thinking men in America.</p>
   <p>For the auxiliary committee,</p>
   <p>Signed: Jan Cizkovsky, President,</p>
   <p>M. Vachal, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
