<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-11">Feb. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">English Language Monthly for the Czech Cause</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-11">Feb. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ENGLISH LANGUAGE MONTHLY FOR THE CZECH CAUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first number of the Bohemian Review appeared a few days ago, and those fellow countrymen of ours who eagerly bought copies are commenting very favorably upon it. In exclusively English-speaking circles also much praise has been bestowed on the new monthly, which promotes Czech interests through the medium of the English language. As we stand at the threshold of new events, the publication can employ all its force for the benefit of our enterprise.</p>
   <p>The first issue contains an article of prime importance dealing with the work done up to the present by Professor Masaryk for the liberation of the Czechs and the Slovaks. Another article, "The Breaking Up of Austria," reviews the status of the diverse nationalities in the monarchy and elucidates this information for the reader with the assistance of a map attached. Excerpts from a book by Benes give an idea of the sufferings of the Czechs during the war up to date and show how the ranks of the Czechs were weakened by a subtle system of recruiting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0290.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The article "Czernin and Clam Martinic" refutes reports in the American press that the present Austrian government is conducted by Czechs, and it also reveals the new emperor's background and describes the policy of his three chief counsellors. The issue also gives an account of the successes achieved by the bazaars held in San Francisco, Detroit, New York, and Chicago. It gives details of the union formed by the National Sokol Association and the Group Fuegner Tyrs. It reviews a number of articles in the American press which deal with the Czech cause.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian Review is a monthly periodical not published for profit. But it is up to the public to maintain it. If our organizations have to defray the expense of publication, they will soon find themselves financially embarrassed. An organ of our own such as the Review will also make unnecessary the printing of leaflets and handbills for special announcements or as propaganda. Let us all see to it that the new organ obtain a circulation at least equal to that of "Free Poland" and other such publications.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
