<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-03-20">Mar. 20, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Educational Club Organization Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-03-20">Mar. 20, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATIONAL CLUB ORGANIZATION MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held last night in the Farragut School on Spaulding Avenue at 14th Street to organize an educational club for the promotion of literature, lectures, music, dramatic and rhetorical arts, aesthetic dancing, etc. The meeting began with a splendid lecture by our famous traveler, Mr. E. St. Vraz. The lecture was illustrated by about one hundred and fifty stereopticon slides depicting South America. He showed scenes of the region of the Orinoco River and the inhabitants, explaining their habits, conditions, etc. The audience was intensely fascinated by this classic lecture from which both young and old derived much benefit.</p>
   <p>Professor Morse, principal of the school, explained the purpose of the organization of the club, which will be given the use of the entire building with the permission of the Board of Education. He called attention to the advantages of the organization for everybody, especially our youth who can gain both pleasure and education from such a group. His speech was then translated for our <pb facs="5418478_4_0914.jpg" n="2"/>Bohemian listeners by Mr. J. B. Dibelka, a member of the Board of Education. Reverend Vaclav Vanek and Professor Bohumil Kral were elected as the committee to organize a literary club. This meeting was certainly significant for our large "California" community, and it is now up to our countrymen and their children to make the most of this remarkable opportunity. There is not the slightest doubt but that such will be the case. Our educators will do everything possible so that this new institution may be preserved and so that it will prosper, in order that our youth may be uplifted morally and that they may acquaint themselves with something better than could heretofore be provided for them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
