<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-04-20">Apr. 20, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Sponsors of Vojta Naprstek School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0718</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0718.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-04-20">Apr. 20, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE SPONSORS OF VOJTA NAPRSTEK SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.2--We print here the minutes of the meeting of the sponsors of Vojta Naprstek School, which was held on March 28, 1905. The meeting was brought to order by Chairman Alb. Lisec. The minutes of the previous meeting were read and accepted. Mr. Rys proposed Frant. Benda, 1119 Spaulding Avenue, for membership. Messrs. Roubal, Bares, and Sima were elected to the investigating committee. A new representative from Tetin Lodge 105 J.C.D.(Union of Bohemian Women), Miss Anna Silinska, was initiated. Mr. Jan Benes and Mr. Ant. Jindra did not appear for initiation, and the secretary was instructed to write to them, requesting them to be present at the next meeting. The Bohemian stone-masons sent the sum of nine dollars for the benefit of the school, the proceeds of a private entertainment; this was accepted with thanks, and the secretary will send an acknowledgement.</p>
   <p>The committee for securing school premises on West Twenty-sixth Street announced that there is nothing suitable for rent. After a lengthy debate it was resolved that the committee continue its efforts and find a suitable site <pb facs="5418478_4_0719.jpg" n="2"/>for the erection of a school building. The committee was empowered to act in the matter, and should a suitable place be found, a meeting is to be called. The exposition committee reported that it had held its first meeting and had elected as secretary for the exposition Mr. Frant. Stepanek and had appointed Messrs. Hladky and Rys as advertising committee. The other committees will be elected in future meetings. The bonds of the secretary and the treasurer were accepted and read into the record.</p>
   <p>The annual ball will not be given his year. The secretary is to acknowledge in the newspapers the donors who contributed to the ball held in February. The following named donors contributed: The Atlas Brewing Company, the Monarch Brewing Company, the Garden City Brewing Company, and the Pilsen Brewing Company, a half barrel of beer each; Messrs. Rada and Korbel, a dozen bottles of wine each; Mr. Donat, effervescent beverages; Mr. Kubat, a box of cigars; Mr. Kopecky, fifty cigars; Mr. Rusy, a hundred cigars; Mr. Placky, twenty pounds of sausage; Mr. Sekera, fifteen pounds of sausage; Mr. Treml, <pb facs="5418478_4_0720.jpg" n="3"/>twelve pounds of sausage; Mr. Pelikan, a ham; Mrs. Jirkovska, horse-radish and lunch-meats; and Mr. Kalenda, bread. Receipts recorded at this meeting were a contribution of one dollar from Mr. Pelikan, three dollars from Mr. Rusy, and nine dollars from the Bohemian stone-masons; total, thirteen dollars. There were no disbursements.</p>
   <p>Frant Stepanek, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
