<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation to the Czech People of the Town of Lake [Chicago]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0960</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0960.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION TO THE CZECH PEOPLE OF THE TOWN OF LAKE [CHICAGO]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is much truth and wisdom in some of the old sayings, and especially in the adage: "A healthy mind in a healthy body." We train our bodies in our Sokol halls, while our mind is being trained in our Bohemian schools. It is not to be denied that it is just these two organizations in America--the Sokols and the Bohemian schools--on which the future of our Bohemian-American people rests. Here, then, a stern duty confronts us to train our Bohemian-American adolescents well. Should we dodge that duty and avoid bringing up our young people, all our national aspirations will be in vain. Let us send our children to the Sokol gymnasiums; let us enroll them in Bohemian schools! We may be certain that both of these educational institutions are well established in our community.</p>
   <p>Last Tuesday, September 5, 1922, witnessed the resumption of activities of the Sokol Town of Lake, and the Bohemian Free Thought School of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) held its school <pb facs="5418478_4_0961.jpg" n="2"/>registration. The Sokol classes for girls will be held on Mondays and Thursdays, while the boys will attend classes on Tuesdays and Fridays. The [Free Thought] School will have daily classes. Under the experienced leadership of Mr. Karel Koleno, of the Sokol, and that of Mr. Honus Farsky, of the [Free Thought] School, our children will surely be well taken care of, and it only depends on Bohemian parents to take full advantage of the opportunities thus offered to them. The monthly fees of the Sokol are: ten cents a month per child for the children of members, and fifteen cents for the children of non-members. These fees are payable quarterly and in advance. The tuition fee in the Bohemian [Free Thought] School is ten cents a month.</p>
   <p>Both the Sokol gymnasium and the Bohemian School are located in the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies' Hall, West 48th and South Honore Streets. Let there not be one single child in our community who does not attend the Sokol classes and the Bohemian [Free Thought] School this year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
