<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-09-08">Sept. 8, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">"Sokol" Day.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1379</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1379.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-09-08">Sept. 8, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">"SOKOL" DAY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How the Bohemian public values the sincere gymnastic efforts and rewards their earnest unselfish work was shown yesterday. The gigantic premises of the second regiment State militia, the largest place of its kind in the city, was filled to overflowing with our public yesterday and the attendance, the enthusiasm which prevailed in the Armory, the enthusiastic shouting, which welcomed the ranks of the "Sokols," should be an incentive for our "Sokols" to further united efforts.</p>
   <p>The gymnasts, marching to the music of Mr. Kounovsky's excellent band, and with the sprightly women gymnasts in their midst, proudly strutted through the streets, loudly greeted by strangers; our women gymnasts especially were pleasing to everyone. It was unnecessary for anyone to ask what the parade represented - Bohemian Sokols are well known to the local public and who ever had time joined the parade and accompanied the Sokols to the Armory in order to witness their exercises.</p>
   <p>At three o'clock, when the building was filled (it is estimated that there were fully three thousand people present) the signal was given and the gymnasts with their instructor Karl Stulik appeared in a body; the applause which greeted these <pb facs="5418478_4_1380.jpg" n="2"/>hearty men, fairly shook the building. When the gymnasts took positions preparatory to the calisthenic exercises, Mr. J. Cermak delivered a short welcoming address, explaining to the gathering that the Sokol Societies are not merely pleasure societies, but that their gymnasiumsare teachers of a better,more sturdy generation; that in gymnastic institutions can be gained that which makes man on earth more fortunate, that is health, that it is possible through proper exercise to develop those characteristics which are the aim of every ideal man, these are strength, courage, manliness and morality. After the speech the calisthenic exercises were performed; fairly difficult combination acts were performed correctly with such apparent ease as to cause a continuous outburst of applause; the Americans present were entirely enraptured and today's papers repeat the praises of Bohemian Gymnasts and liken the Bohemian people to the Spartans who laid such great importance upon physical development.</p>
   <p>Our women gymnasts awakened justified enthusiasm by their appearance. Their exercises with wands, were performed with such elegance and perfection, that a storm of applause greeted their every movement, and there is no doubt that the ranks of our women gymnasts will grow even more from now on.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1381.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Yesterday's appearance of our Sokols and the entire performance was excellent, and all those present praised and showed their appreciation in full.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
