<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-03-25">Mar. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">John Huss Memorial</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three column-tenth of a page, showing a building, the John Huss Memorial, on which three flags are flying]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-03-25">Mar. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN HUSS MEMORIAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three column-tenth of a page, showing a building, the John Huss Memorial, on which three flags are flying]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The idea of building a John Huss Memorial in Chicago has now reached a stage where it may be safely maintained that this important undertaking of Freethinking Bohemians will soon be realized. The Vybor Pro Postaveni Husova Domu (John Huss Memorial Association) has accepted and approved the plans for this national shrine, the dedication of which is expected to be a part of the ceremonies commemorating the five hundredth anniversary of John Huss' martyr death at the stake. No doubt the building of this shrine will be started soon.</p>
   <p>The Vybor reports that the ground has been paid for, and urges all those who promised or pledged their contributions on that condition, to send them in without unnecessary delay.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1456.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to the accepted plans, the building will consist of three parts: The two-story central main building, the dimensions of which are 75 by 125 feet, will be flanked on each side by a one-story wing 30 by 70 feet. All rooms will be aired or ventilated, heated or cooled, by a special new system. There will be both gas and electric light all over. The front of the whole building, which is 135 feet in length, will be made of pressed brick and polished stone; the side and rear walls will be of ordinary brick. The roofs, which will be supported by iron trusses, will be constructed of reinforced concrete, and the same material will be used for all ceilings and floors. The whole building will be fireproof. The main hall is planned to be fully acoustic--that is, any sound uttered in one part of it will be heard throughout.</p>
   <p>The Main, or Central, Building</p>
   <p>The basement: In front, on either side, will be a room 18 by 28 feet for the heating and ventilating plants. Between these there will be a coal room of 19.4 by 35 feet. In the rear, under the speakers' platform and the dressing <pb facs="5418478_4_1457.jpg" n="3"/>rooms, will be a storage room 38 by 22.1 feet. The floor of the basement will be 4.1 feet under the street level, and the basement itself will be 8 feet high. Both the ceilings and floors will be of reinforced concrete. There will be no basement under the main hall, or auditorium, which will rest on solid ground and will have a slope of 0.1 over 1 foot.</p>
   <p>The first floor: The main entrance, which is 13.2 feet wide and consists of four doors, leads up five steps to another series of four doors which open into a lobby, 12 by 26 feet. Here will be located the box office and dressing rooms. From the lobby a hallway leads to the office of the Memorial, another hallway to the main hall, and two six-foot stairways to the second floor. From the lobby there is also access to men's washrooms on one side and ladies' rooms on the other side. All these rooms are 12 feet high.</p>
   <p>The auditorium proper is 72 by 71 feet. It seats 640 people, and the first row of seats is 10 feet from the platform. It is, on the average, 26 feet high, and has seven wide exits which prevent any possibility of panic.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1458.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the rear there is the speakers' platform, 38 by 24 feet. It is elevated 4 feet from the floor and is flanked on both sides by dressing rooms, 10 by 9.6 feet.</p>
   <p>The second floor: The center houses a lodge hall, 30 by 27.6 feet, with a reception room on each side. The side rooms open into the hallway, with doors to a ladies' room and men's room. These premises are 12 feet high.</p>
   <p>Around and above the auditorium is a gallery seating 250 people. It has four exits.</p>
   <p>The Wings</p>
   <p>One wing will be used for an advanced teachers' training school, for a library, and a small museum.</p>
   <p>The other wing will serve as premises for a Bohemian Free Thought school and <pb facs="5418478_4_1459.jpg" n="5"/>for theatrical performances for young people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
