<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-29">Apr. 29, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Frantisek B. Zdrubek School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0625</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0625.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-29">Apr. 29, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE FRANTISEK B. ZDRUBEK SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The growing Bohemian community in the neighborhood of the Bohemian National Cemetery experienced a joyful occasion in the opening of the new building of the Frantisek B. Zdrubek free-thought school. Our countrymen in Irving Park had made extensive preparations for this significant celebration, and it was regretted that circumstances prevented the more distant friends of our schools from participating. In spite of that, however, a very large number of local inhabitants, as well as numerous representatives of societies, were present to congratulate the United Societies of Irving Park upon the result of their tireless work for many years.</p>
   <p>The opening of the celebration was delayed somewhat as a result of the rain; however, the program was begun as soon as the members of local societies and the sokols, accompanied by a band, arrived. Architect Novy, together <pb facs="5418478_4_0626.jpg" n="2"/>with three little girls, appeared upon the stage. One of the girls, Victoria Kaspar, after a short speech, gave Mr. Kovy the keys to the new</p>
   <p>building, and he in turn gave them to the president of the United Societies of Irving Park, Mr. Joseph Rugel. In a lengthy and enthusiastic speech, the president described the unselfish work of his enlightened countrymen, who through extraordinary generosity had attained their goal--the erection of a beautiful building, which will be a school, as well as the gathering place, for the sokols and various Bohemian societies of Irving Park. In concluding his speech, he thanked all friends who had so generously contributed to the success of the undertaking, and expressed the hope that the new hall would become a place both of entertainment and education for his countrymen in this great Bohemian community.....</p>
   <p>The new school and hall is located at Eastwood and 40th Avenues, where it was erected at a cost of $15,000. It is a two-story brick structure, <pb facs="5418478_4_0627.jpg" n="3"/>practicably arranged. A large schoolroom, lodge room, and kitchen are located on the ground floor. A spacious hall, which will be used for entertainments and as the regular training quarters of Sokol Rozvoj, occupies the second floor.</p>
   <p>The entire building was beautifully decorated and our countrymen in the Irving Park neighborhood can be justly proud of their new school and hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
