<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-16">May 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">An Interesting Public Sokol Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-16">May 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">AN INTERESTING PUBLIC SOKOL EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Slavsky (Sokol Slavsky Gymnastic Association) which still may be considered one of the most active of our sokol units in Chicago, proved again yesterday that it is not only willing to work, but also that it is able to do the work. The unit works quietly and without publicity, but whenever it appears before our public, it performs in such a manner that the unit ingratiates itself deeper and deeper into the hearts of our people, whose admiration it gained a long time ago. The work of this sokol unit was exhibited again at its public exhibition, held yesterday at the Pilsen Park pavilion. The exhibition was attended by a large crowd of its patrons and friends . The Pilsen Park pavilion was overcrowded in the early hours of the afternoon. The members of the unit, the visiting sokols, and the people in general, were greeted by the president of the unit, Brother Bohus Hak. In his brief speech he expressed joy at the great attendance and at the success of <pb facs="5418478_4_1094.jpg" n="2"/>the sokol idea in America. He also reminded the audience of the Sokol Slet (sokol mass meeting and exhibition) which will be held in Chicago in the near future, and which will mean a number of great and really beautiful holidays for the Czechoslovak people of America in general. He remarked that it was the sokols themselves who proved their worth by participating in the struggle for Czechoslovak independence during the past few years. He also mentioned that he would like to see the same enthusiasm during the period of the Slet.</p>
   <p>Following his speech, which was rewarded by long applause, the real program started. Brother Holan, instructor of the children and junior classes, was in charge of the first five numbers of the program and he deserves a great deal of recognition for his efforts. The next number of the program was a beautiful drill presented by twelve members of the junior class, under the direction of Brother Kostlan. This was one of the best numbers of the program with the exception of the Udernicka Devitka (storm group of nine). The sokolice (members of women's classes), <pb facs="5418478_4_1095.jpg" n="3"/>thirty-six in number, presented a remarkable exhibition of precision calisthenics under the direction of Brother Tomes. The sokols, thirty in number, proved their talent and readiness by presenting difficult precision calisthenics.</p>
   <p>But the most remarkable and most beautiful number of the program was the Udernicka Devitka, presented by nine sokols. This interesting number was prepared and arranged by Brother Douda, former member of the Sokol Slavsky, and at present the commander of men's classes of the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol, Town of Lake. He conceived the idea of this number while serving in the Czechoslovak Legion. As motives for his Udernicka Devitka he used tactics practiced by our Legionnaires in their attacks and battles with Bolshevik armies. Yesterday, the Devitka was presented by Sokols Tomes, Miller, Fiser, Kosar, Kral, Petruch, Pencik, Michl, and Vanak.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's entire exhibition was an example of the progress of the classes of children, juniors, women, and men. The members of the women's classes have <pb facs="5418478_4_1096.jpg" n="4"/>been especially active. There are many members among them who are good workers. It is very significant and also interesting to know that many of the sokolice are women of advanced years for whom sokol activity in America became a pure joy in this otherwise dull everyday life. The beautiful and successful program was followed by free entertainments and many people stayed in the pavilion until late in the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
