<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-16">Sept. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Havlicek's Motto</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-16">Sept. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">HAVLICEK'S MOTTO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Toward the end of August we mentioned in these columns the proposal voiced in Sokol Americky (The American Sokol) in regard to the inscription on the Karel Havlicek monument in Douglas Park. Of course, there is an inscription upon the monument, quite a long and profound one at that, but the editor of Sokol Americky meant that it is not characteristic of the fearless journalist and undaunted protagonist of the rights of his people. He proposes that it should be replaced or supplemented with the familiar Havlicek motto: "You may promise me, you may threaten me, still I shall not become a traitor!" In the official organ of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union), there also was a very excellent English translation of this manly motto. Once again, we urge that the proposal of Sokol Americky be carried out as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>The Committee for the erection of the Havlicek monument as yet has not <pb facs="5418478_4_1514.jpg" n="2"/>finished its work, and before it renders an account of its meritorious work to the public, it should make provision for the placing of this inscription upon the monument pedestal.</p>
   <p>The present inscription upon the monument in Douglas Park also has the sad fault of being hardly legible, and for this reason we think that a bronze tablet ought to be provided for the pedestal inscribed with Havlicek's motto, which would tell the passing stranger much more about the character and merits of our immortal journalist than any excerpt from his biography. Any one reading it would understand at once why the sculptor gave Havlicek that speaker's pose. Not only were promises of reform made to Havlicek from Vienna, but the entire Czech people were often promised, and still are promised a change in political affairs. Nothing has been done, and now they have often threatened to force the people to soften their just demands in this regard. That unforgettable motto, that defiant outcry of the unyielding Czech spirit, should not be missing from the pedestal of the Darling of the Czech people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
