<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-11-25">Nov. 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">For an Intellectual Exchange.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0920</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0920.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-11-25">Nov. 25, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">FOR AN INTELLECTUAL EXCHANGE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.5--The executive committee of the Association for Higher Education has decided at its monthly meeting to create a lecture bureau which is to arrange lectures in diverse Bohemian settlements, aided by the "Svaz Osvetovy " (League for Enlightenment) in Bohemia with which the Association has come into close touch recently.</p>
   <p>The object of these future activities is to invite men from Bohemia, outstanding in their profession or in their nationalistic achievements, to undertake travels in America which would bear educational fruit for us and, at the same time, prove beneficial to their own studies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0921.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is ample hope that the initial experiments in this direction will demonstrate the sanity of the idea and the necessity of the work, and that with the support of the press and other factors much will be done for the uplift of the people and the perfecting of the education of our younger generation.</p>
   <p>The men to be invited are expected to sojourn long enough in America to become acquainted with the ways of the country, with American schools, with our institutions and organizations.</p>
   <p>Others will commensurate with their needs and inclinations, and be given the opportunity to observe American industry, commerce and various other enterprises, all of this with the purpose of practically benefiting the people of the old country by the accumulated experiences.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0922.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The usefulness of these activities should work two ways: to transmit to our new homeland what is useful or worthy of emulation in Czech science and enlightenment, and in return help responsible workers in the old country to know America. Often voiced wishes will thus be fulfilled.</p>
   <p>Every Bohemian settlement may apply for the lectures through individuals or associations, if halls, advance advertisements, and hospitality to the lecturer can be provided for.</p>
   <p>The public may be required to contribute a moderate amount for admission to the lectures, so that costs for fees and travels may be defrayed. It is of paramount importance, however, to make these lectures accessible to the greatest possible number of Bohemian-Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0923.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As far as the cost of the trip from Bohemia to the United States is concerned, they may, according to a resolution of the executive committee, be covered from the lecture fund to the amount of $300.</p>
   <p>The Lecture Bureau of the Association is up to date an experiment only. Its further progress depends upon the support which will be given to it by the public and by the press in particular.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
