<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-04">Sept. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Call of the Sokol Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1157</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1157.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-04">Sept. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE CALL OF THE SOKOL HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sokol Associations have been hard hit by the war. They have, in fact suffered more than any other organizations. The majority of the members who attended the regular drills are now in military service. Some of them enlisted in the Czechoslovak army, others in the Canadian forces, and still others were called for service by the United States. The active Sokol ranks are depleted and the gymnasiums are nearly empty. The younger generation is now the only means whereby the Sokol organizations can maintain their membership. Czech parents should take cognizance of this; not only those in Chicago and suburbs, but also those wherever any Sokol group exists. They should not hesitate, but should send their children immediately. This is desirable not only with regard to the health and physical development of the children, but also for the continued prosperous existence of the Sokol organizations.</p>
   <p>All of our Sokol halls have reopened this week and are inviting parents to send their children to attend gymnastic exercises. The Pilsen Sokols begin tomorrow <pb facs="5418478_4_1158.jpg" n="2"/>and have announced the program and classes as follows:</p>
   <p>Day classes for girls, Monday and Thursday from 4 P.M. to 8 P.M. Day classes for boys, Tuesday and Friday from 4 P.M. to 6 P.M. Evening classes for girls, Monday and Thursday from 8 P.M. to 9:30 P.M. Evening classes for boys, Tuesday and Friday from 8 P.M. to 10 P.M. The classes in the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs have also been announced. Classes for children and adults open this week at Sokol halls in Oak Park, Cicero, and Berwyn. Czech parents will certainly send their children to Czech schools, and should, therefore, send them to the Sokol halls.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
