<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-08-07">Aug. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Attention Bohemian Free Thought People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-08-07">Aug. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">ATTENTION BOHEMIAN FREE THOUGHT PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friends! The teachers of the Bohemian Free Thought schools, to whom it is of great importance that the mission of the schools be successfully accomplished, are quite concerned about the quarrel which has recently arisen regarding the Posvicenska Slavnost (Country-wake Festival). The proceeds of the festival are to be donated to the Bohemian Free Thought schools to further their activities. The teachers of the Free Thought schools are well informed and are aware of the difficult problems facing these institutions. They know very well how difficult a task it is to scrape together enough money to carry on; well known is the sentiment which accompanied the work of the teachers, that conscientious work which begins when the child is entrusted to the care of a Bohemian teacher and continues until the child leaves the school on its life's journey; when the teachers hope that the child educated in our schools will some day fill the places of our workers, the places which for various reasons may be left vacant.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0464.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>No one knows better the great joy of a teacher when his efforts have met with success; at the same time nobody else can feel the bitter disappointment of the teacher when he sees that, because of either fate or unfavorable conditions, his efforts did not bring the desired results.</p>
   <p>Joy, hope, and also grief accompany our strenuous work but, in spite of all obstacles, we do our work with love, knowing that we do not work for ourselves, but for the success of the future life of those whom fate selected to take our places when we pass on.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time we had not said anything; we were taking care of our schools only, but now we see that the unfortunate quarrel is endangering the very foundations of the Bohemian Free Thought schools. Although everybody knows and is aware of the fact that there is danger, that because of insufficient funds the Bohemian Free Thought schools may be forced to close, no one as yet has been found who would issue warnings; no one to act as an appeaser of human passions; no one to urge the embittered brothers to wake up, to think <pb facs="5418478_4_0465.jpg" n="3"/>over what they are doing; no one to tell them to stop the quarrel which brings only weakness, distrust, and hate, and which may endanger not only this project, but also our mutual undertakings in the future to the great joy of the enemies of the Bohemian Free Thought movement.</p>
   <p>At this difficult time the Bohemian teachers are aroused, and at their conference, held for the purpose of finding a way to stop this quarrel and to save whatever there is possible to save, agreed that our people must be awakened to their duty; that they must be told of the dangers of this fratricidal struggle; that it must be prevented.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we appeal to all of you, who have the success of the Bohemian Free Thought schools at heart, we beg of you: Stop! Wake up! We stand by our schools as directed by our conscience and, therefore, we have decided to give you warning. The teachers, at their conference, which was attended by the Messrs. V. Straka, F. Vlach, V. Fuks, and H. Farsky, and Mesdames E. Raeck, Z. Koller, H. Weiner, I. Walter, and M. Bartuska found that a possibility of <pb facs="5418478_4_0466.jpg" n="4"/>settling this quarrel still exists. Taking into consideration that in this quarrel we have been neutral, we present the following proposal:</p>
   <p>You, who have been engaged in this, but who, at the same time, have the interest of the schools in mind, show your good will by doing a good deed which will not be in the least humiliating. Step aside and make room for volunteers from our ranks who will take the plans of the Posvicenska Slavnost into their own hands. We offer you our name, the good name of the Bohemian Free Thought School Teachers Association, under which auspices the Posvicenska Slavnost should be arranged and with your co-operation we believe that the work, now so far advanced, will be brought to a successful end.</p>
   <p>We propose that the Posvicenska Slavnost be arranged under the auspices of the Sbor Ucitelu Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Bohemian Free Thought School Teachers Association). In that case, the cause of contention will be removed and we will be able to successfully accomplish that which was planned through difficulties.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0467.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Countrymen and countrywomen! Be of good will!</p>
   <p>It is not too late; there still is time to make amends and you are therefore invited to attend a joint meeting which will be held Wednesday, August 10, at 8 P.M. in the lower hall of the Vojta Naprstek Bohemian Free Thought School. Everyone who is interested in the planning of the Posvicenska Slavnost should come to this meeting. Throw away your prejudice, put your shoulder to the wheel and help bring the task to a successful end. You and we, then, will be rewarded in the knowledge that, in spite of all the obstacles, the work for the benefit of the Bohemian Free Thought schools was brought to a successful end. The result then will be a lesson and an example for the future, not only to us, but to, we hope, our children.</p>
   <p>The teachers of the Bohemian Free Thought Schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
