<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-23">June 23, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Adolf Heyduk Attains Three Score and Ten</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-23">June 23, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">ADOLF HEYDUK ATTAINS THREE SCORE AND TEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the closing days of this month one of the most prolific and most popular among the Bohemian poets of the nineteenth century is nearing the seventieth year of his life. His comparatively long span of life has been devoted entirely to the writing of poetry which, peacefully flowing from the southwestern Bohemian forests into our literary market, will occupy a place of honor on the shelves of Bohemian literature.</p>
   <p>This poet whose birthday is being celebrated belongs among the oldest literati of our homeland. He has managed to retain a personal brightness and buoyancy and a certain youthful enthusiasm in his work which must be called extraordinary, indeed, in our times. Though old in years and rich in experience, his spirit and his temperament are vigorous and youthful. This is the light in which Heyduk appears to us, in contrast to the unnatural and decadent writers of our times who, even in their teens, are torn already by fatigue, ennui, and mental torpor--qualities with which they infect their literary products.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0076.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Heyduk has preserved his remarkable vigor and creative enthusiasm primarily because he became fond of tranquillity and rural solitude; because he avoided the turmoil of cultural centers, which as a rule merely embitter and poison the taste for work; secondarily, because he always followed the narrow path which he had laid out for himself, unconcerned with current fads and changing fashions; and, finally, because with his temperament and with his beliefs as to the tasks of contemporary art, in his selection of subjects for poetry, and in his way of treating these subjects artistically, he has remained, to this day, a true son of the sixties and seventies of the last century, when work meant brisk activity, sincere feeling and a deep national interest. In those times the editing of poetry, educating to leadership and imparting resiliency of mood to the reading public were all inherent parts of a single whole. This is the reason why a majority of our literati of that time applied themselves to their work with much more enthusiasm and pleasure than those of today, when literary activity is merely flirted with because of the fact that by the distribution of one's books a national mission is fulfilled, and people derive pleasure from them and obtain an education at the same time.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0077.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Heyduk's literary work comprised epic and lyric poetry. Lyrics, however, play the formost part, and even in his epic there is a trace of lyricism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
