<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-29">Sept. 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">From Sokol Pilsen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1048</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1048.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-29">Sept. 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">FROM SOKOL PILSEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Czech public: No doubt Sokol Pilsen will never be accused of neglecting the principal object of Sokols, which is the physical development of children of both sexes and of men and women, and the bringing of this development to the highest possible perfection. Our past furnishes the best proofs of this endeavor. We have never spared expense to acquire the best teachers and instructors. After learning that a member of the model group of Sokols sent to us from Prague for our Slet (Sokol mass convention), a trained gymnastic instructor and expert in physical culture, Brother Jaroslav Jelinek, expects to stay in America, our body started negotiations with him, and today we are able to publish the news that our gymnastic school will be led by Brother Jelinek. Brother Jelinek will be the instructor in all our men's, women's, and youth's classes, and we hope that our gymnasium will again become an important center of <pb facs="5418478_4_1049.jpg" n="2"/>physical culture, equal to the best in the city.</p>
   <p>Men's classes will start Tuesday, October 4; women's classes Monday, October 3. Enrollment of children will take place October 1, at which time also the schedule will be made public.</p>
   <p>Dues: Children pay twenty-five cents a month, three months in advance. Nonmembers of our organization who desire to participate in the classes, men or women, are required to pay an amount equivalent to a year's membership dues at the time of enrollment. Na Zdar! (To success!)</p>
   <p>Sokol Pilsen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
