<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-10-21">Oct. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">New Building of Sokol Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Magnificent, Modern Czech Hall Nearing Completion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1342</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1342.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-10-21">Oct. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">NEW BUILDING OF SOKOL CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Magnificent, Modern Czech Hall Nearing Completion</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Drawing of Front Elevation, four column--quarter of a page, view of the new Sokol Chicago Building.]</p>
   <p>Our readers all know that a short time ago, Sokol Chicago [a gymnastic society] undertook a large and important work: to enlarge and partially rebuild its building on Kedzie Avenue so that it would better meet the requirements such as are today placed upon a modern society hall, and the needs of the largest Czech community in our city, Ceska Kalifornie, (Bohemian California) [a district of the West Side], whose societies and social life continuously and promisingly flourish. The cost of remodeling and enlarging the building will amount to around seventy to eighty thousand dollars; this figure does not include the interior arrangements.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1343.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The work on the building is progressing rapidly. Before the end of the year, or perhaps even before the Christmas holidays, Czech Chicago will be enriched by a beautiful refuge for national life, fitted out in luxuriousness, which surpasses in its proportions everything that Czech America has thus far seen. We will attempt in the following lines to somewhat illustrate for the reader the dimensions and furnishings of the various halls in this Czech society palace, which will not only be the pride of Ceska Kalifornie, but of the builders, the architectural firm of Novy and Son, to whom was entrusted the construction of this grand structure.</p>
   <p>The new building is 125 feet long and 100 feet across the front. On the ground floor, there will be a spacious dining room, a kitchen, a barroom, a boiler room, two large dressing rooms for actors, and baths consisting of four showers and two tubs for the use of Sokols [gymnasts] in training. In addition to the above, there will be a fireproof vault, and a washroom for men on the ground floor. The dining room will be eighty-two feet long and forty-six feet wide.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1344.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On the first floor will be the main room or hall which will be eighty-four feet long and seventy-two feet wide. The stage, which, of course, will be the chief attraction of this hall, will be sixty-one feet long, twenty-six feet deep and sixty feet high. It will be furnished with a movable curtain, and also with a fireproof curtain. It will have a complete electric equipment and all technical aids after the model of large theatres. This stage will be suitable for the largest productions, and the lights of the theatre can be dimmed by a special apparatus.</p>
   <p>The gallery or balcony will seat four hundred persons, and there will be seats for one thousand persons in the auditorium. The foyer will be lined with marble. The stairways will be of iron and fireproof also. On the first floor, there will also be a cloakroom for one thousand persons, quarters for a business of some kind, and the women's toilets. Against the danger of fire, the theatre is sufficiently guarded; the main hall has five exits, the gallery has four exits, and the stage has a special exit leading directly to the street.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1345.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On the second floor, there are two lodgerooms, and modern quarters for the manager or agent of the building.</p>
   <p>On the third floor, there is a large lodgeroom with an antechamber or receiving room, arranged for secret societies, such as the Free Masons, Odd Fellows, etc. The dimensions of this room are thirty-seven by forty-eight feet. There is also a smaller hall, twenty-four by thirty-nine feet, suitable for benevolent societies. In this room are boxes or safes, for lodge books etc., built into the walls.</p>
   <p>The new building is made up of two sections, the gymnasium section being only two stories in height, while the front part of the building is three stories high. The building is thirty-four feet in height with a cupola in the middle which is forty feet in height above the floor.</p>
   <p>It is no doubt unnecessary to add that not only Ceska Kalifornie, but all <pb facs="5418478_4_1346.jpg" n="5"/>of Bohemian Chicago is eagerly awaiting the day when the new building, this grand center of national and social life in the largest Bohemian-American community, is dedicated to its purpose to become the permanent headquarters of our amateur actors and singers; our educational, benevolent and humanitarian societies, in fact, of all our cultural endeavors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
