<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-12-27">Dec. 27, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Mis-Used Telegram.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-12-27">Dec. 27, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">MIS-USED TELEGRAM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Narod (Nation) served itself badly, when it made use of Kubelik's telegram to the Society of Bohemian journalists, in a clumsy attack upon the Old Peoples Home. Not only the liberal-minded, but the Roman Catholics as well, consider the Old Peoples Home a humanitarian undertaking deserving the support of denomination. All aged, forsaken, Bohemians will be given refuge in the Home without any question being raised, as to whether they belonged to a Catholic or a liberal-minded society. Bohemian Catholics know this, therefore, they charge Narod with wrong doing, in not only refusing to support the Home, but in injuring it at every opportunity. With its remarks on the occasion of Kubelik's telegram to the Bohemian journalists, Narod not only injured the Home, but the Society of Bohemian Journalists as well. From these remarks one would have to judge, that the Society of Bohemian Journalists takes upon itself the right to invite Kubelik to decide for whom he shall play, and that it is opposed to the interests of the Home. However, this is not so. The Society, of Bohemian Journalists merely offered its services to Kubelik in case he should be in need <pb facs="5418478_4_0301.jpg" n="2"/>of any information, and they, at no time, had any idea of arranging some sort of welcoming ceremony, or of advising the artist, for which Society he should play.</p>
   <p>The Society of Bohemian Journalists, together with all honorable Bohemians, supports the Home and will continue to give it support.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
