<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Gymnastic Tournament at Pilsen Sokol</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">GYMNASTIC TOURNAMENT AT PILSEN SOKOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The management of the Plzensky Sokol (Pilsen Sokol) gymnasium was taken over several months ago by Brother Jaroslav Jelinek, who was also a member of the expedition sent by the Cesko-Slovenska Sokolska Obec (Czechoslovak Sokol Community) to the Sokol festival last August. As a sort of inventory of the work done by him in this new field of activity, the Plzensky Sokol arranged a gymnastic tournament yesterday. It was not a public performance in the current meaning of that phrase, but a kind of gymnastic academy, for the program was filled with the presentation of top-ranking drill companies, that is, the most accomplished members. And to this we must add that Brother Jelinek achieved such success with the human material under his care that he must be congratulated.</p>
   <p>The exhibitions that we witnessed last night in the hall of the Plzensky Sokol very closely approached those ideals which were promulgated by our veteran Sokols. Above all, this was an example of almost ideal discipline and exemplary <pb facs="5418478_4_1043.jpg" n="2"/>drilling, even to the smallest detail. Then there was a whole set of novelty numbers which we have never seen before.. Even the first item on the program--the drill of the adolescent company--made the large audience feel that this was something extraordinary. We liked the boys because of their correct posture, their manly bearing, and their setting-up exercises which almost attained perfection. The smaller groups of boys were loudly acclaimed immediately upon their entrance; the applause increased with each one of their performances.</p>
   <p>No less effective was the performance by the adolescent girls, whose rope-skipping exercise was vigourously applauded. These girls, too, have shown by their work the firm discipline of their drill master. Another top-ranking group of adolescent girls distinguished themselves on horizontal bars; these young people exhibited remarkable self-confidence.</p>
   <p>The parade number on the program consisted of a group of setting-up exercises by the top-ranking adult drill company of eight members. Their exercises <pb facs="5418478_4_1044.jpg" n="3"/>were conceived and elaborated for the projected convention of the Stredni Zupa Sokolska (Central District of the American Sokol Union). Although these exercises were rather simple, their performance was ideal, and we may say that anything so perfect has rarely been witnessed in our gymnasiums. These men also performed on the trapeze with almost acrobatic bravado. The top-ranking company consisted of Brothers Jelinek, Matoska, Mikuta, Stransky, Kvidera, Kristufek, and Vesely. The audience was truly electrified by their elegant performance.</p>
   <p>The honors and laurels fell to both sexes, however. The girls and women, dressed in their snow-white uniforms, performed a so-called "Sikerian Sixteen"....This particular drill pattern is a veritable jewel in the field of aesthetic gymanstic exercises, and if for nothing else, Brother Jelinek should certainly be congratulated for his training of these performers within the short space of only a few months. This alone earned him the full right to be called an expert.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1045.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The closing number on the program was a group of Slovak folk dances performed by twenty pairs of Sokols of both sexes, dressed in the appropriate Tatransko costumes. The dancers expressed the various moods in these dances, without which a folk dance would be unthinkable. The performance was rewarded again and again with much applause.</p>
   <p>To provide variety in the program, the Cesko-Delnicky Pevecky Sbor Lyra (Bohemian Workingmen's Choral Society Lyre) sang several charming choral songs.....These singers, too, earned their much-deserved applause. Before the program opened, the audience was addressed by the head of the local unit, Brother V. Cipra.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, we may say that yesterday's tournament of the Plzensky Sokol was thoroughly successful, a fact which will be very stimulating to Brother Jelinek in his future work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
