<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-02">Feb. 2, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A Czech Locality Will Again Have its Library</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-02">Feb. 2, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A CZECH LOCALITY WILL AGAIN HAVE ITS LIBRARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Shedd Park, which occupies a small plot of ground between Lawndale and Millard Avenues, and between 23rd Street and the Chicago, Burlington, and Quincy Railroad, there stood a small railroad ticket office building, which was used for park purposes, and also as a branch of the public library.</p>
   <p>This branch of the public library was moved away, over a year ago, to Twelfth Street, and, as anyone can see, is entirely out of the locality where the Czechs are settled.</p>
   <p>This moving of the branch library seemed unreasonable to the Czechs living there, and immediately efforts were put forth to have the library returned to its original site.</p>
   <p>Alderman John Toman was approached by some of the citizens, and he called <pb facs="5418478_4_0081.jpg" n="2"/>on some of the board members to make inquiries regarding the discontinuance of the library.</p>
   <p>The library board, in its answer, gave reasons for the moving which seemed very satisfactory. One of the reasons given was the poor attendance and the infrequent requests for books. Another was the violence of hoodlums, which, it seemed, the police were unable to suppress. In the light of these explanations, the library board seemed to be within its rights, and it looked as though this Czech locality would have to accustom itself to the lack of a circulating library.</p>
   <p>Alderman Toman did not lose heart, but soon made an application for the return of the library. Some time ago he was informed that his request had been acted upon by the library board, and that permission would be given for the opening of new library rooms in a more favorable locality.</p>
   <p>The alderman turned to the West Park Commission for assistance. Through <pb facs="5418478_4_0082.jpg" n="3"/>his efforts the West Park Board agreed to allow the money for the building of a structure thirty-five by thirty-five feet. The first floor is to be used as a reading room and library, and the second floor as an assembly room.</p>
   <p>The building will stand at 23rd Street and Millard Avenue. The construction will begin as soon as weather conditions permit. It is expected that the new library building will be finished some time during the summer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
