<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-02-16">Feb. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Notice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0180</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0180.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-02-16">Feb. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">NOTICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beginning today, this paper will publish articles in its Sunday editions on American political science. It is needless to point to the importance of this subject. It is the duty of all our countrymen who have found a new home in America to get acquainted with the political organization of the United States, and of those who are not yet citizens, to learn how they can get their citizenship. Many of our countrymen appreciate the importance of this matter. When, a short while ago, the Denni Hlasatel announced the beginning of a political science class in the Bohemian Settlement at 1827 South Center Avenue, sixty-six men of all ages registered the first night seeking advice on how to become citizens, how to enjoy the privileges and fulfill the duties of the American citizenship. Mr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka who teaches this class, has kindly agreed to contribute to this paper a series of interesting and popularly written articles dealing with the fundamentals of American political structure. Since these articles are principally for Bohemians who grew up under the Austrian government, the differences between the American and Austrian setup will be particularly stressed. This will help in explaining some of the features which are peculiar to America, and therefore not so easily understood by an immigrant from Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0181.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Smetanka who is especially well-equipped to write these articles...plans to publish them later on in book form.</p>
   <p>The following subjects will be discussed: The fundamentals of the American political structure and its historical development; the United States Government, including its administrative, legislative, and judiciary branches; its relation to the individual States; State administration, with particular view to the State of Illinois; the composition of a State; American cities and their problems; the municipal administration of Chicago; information on how to become a citizen; excerpts from immigration and naturalization laws.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
