<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-06-26">June 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Patrons of the Vojta Naprsted Liberal School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-06-26">June 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE PATRONS OF THE VOJTA NAPRSTED LIBERAL SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.10, Col.3--The minutes of the meeting, of the Patronage of the Vojta Naprstek Liberal School, which was held on May 31, 1910. The meeting was called to order by the chairman Mr. Rich. Dusil at the regular time. All officers were present with the exception of the treasurer who was excused. Gymnastic Unity Sokol Miroslav Tyrs, sent a communication in which it announces a new delegate.--Mrs. Hrych explains how important and beneficial it is for the Vojta Naprstek school to join the Association of Patronages.--Delegate Mr. Masek then gave many reasons why we should work collectively along educational lines in schools. He added that every reasonable man must admit the advantages derived from union. Delegate Mrs. Hrych, further adds that this union should be accomplished chiefly for the purpose of doing away with the continual begging. Under present conditions, there are received at each meeting six or more requests for contributions and if all of them were granted the society would very often empty it's treasury. This begging and complaining will be done away with, for the association would take care of the needs of the various Patronages. Delegate Jind. Lednik, makes a motion, that it should be decided today, whether <pb facs="5418478_4_0701.jpg" n="2"/>the Patronage of Vojta Naprstek shall join the Association of patronages. The motion was seconded and placed before the delegates for discussion. The motion was finally voted upon and carried. A bill from the newspaper Spravidelnost for $2.50 was read--a bill from 'Sokol Chicago,' for $39 rental was ordered paid. The delegate from the Gymnastic Unity Sokol "Miroslav Tyrs," Mr. Frank Novak, was inducted. Also from "Sokol Havlicek," Mr. Vaclav Jakoubek, to replace delegate Martin Smach. Dr. J. D. Novak was made a member. The committee for arrangement of lectures reported that from the two lectures on Prague there resulted a profit of $179.80. This profit was turned over to the building fund.</p>
   <p>The auditing committee reports that from the previous audit there was shown in the treasury $544.29. Receipts from February 22, to April 26,</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$318.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$862.29</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Disbursements</cell>
     <cell>$489.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance in Treasury</cell>
     <cell>$373.19</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>This report was accepted.--A motion was made and adopted that this years <pb facs="5418478_4_0702.jpg" n="3"/>picnic be held for the benefit of the building fund. Receipts at this meeting were $5, disbursements $154. The names of all delegates present at this meeting were then read. There were thirty-three present. The meeting then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
