<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-02">June 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Svornost Lying Again</title><title level="a" type="sub">Congressman Sabath Will Show Who Recommended Melichar for Services to Him (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-02">June 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SVORNOST LYING AGAIN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Congressman Sabath Will Show Who Recommended Melichar For Services To Him (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The Chicago Herald on the first page of yesterday's issue, printed a news item from Washington, D. C., which, in essence, is nothing more than explanations to the American and the Czech-American public by Congressman A. J. Sabath in regard to his associations with A. G. Melichar. Because the article is of interest to all, we are reprinting it on another page of today's issue, as we could not get it ready for the press yesterday. It was, however, featured in the Svornost with a slur against Mr. Albert Havranek of our editorial staff.</p>
   <p>It reads as follows: 'We are publishing the [Chicago Herald] news item <pb facs="5418478_4_0151.jpg" n="2"/>translated as closely as possible. However, we wish to point out that Melichar was not recommended to Congressman Sabath by the Czech National Alliance, but by Iska [Doctor Iska] and by Mr. Albert Havranek, reporter for the Denni Hlasatel. Furthermore, the Czech National Alliance suggested and brought about the discharge of Melichar after the latter's activities had been exposed.'</p>
   <p>We do not deem it proper to dwell upon this remark, but let Mr. Havranek answer: 'I am too unassuming a man to think that I could exert any influence upon the Congressman, and I am sufficiently aware of the insignificance of my person to know that I could not urge him... My contacts with Melichar were so few they could, be counted on the fingers of my hand. I do not believe the Czech National Alliance made the recommendation as alleged in the Chicago Herald news item. However, I do know from sources directly accessible to me, who called the Congressman's attention to Melichar's <pb facs="5418478_4_0152.jpg" n="3"/>suspicious activities and caused his discharge.....'</p>
   <p>We are satisfied, for the time being, with Mr. Havranek's declaration. We hope, however, that Congressman Sabath will furnish the public with a statement which should bring clarity into the affair and brand the attack by the Svornost upon a member of our staff with the mark of a lie."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
