<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1900-03-22">March 22, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Local Notices. Standpoint of an Editor.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1900-03-22">March 22, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL NOTICES. STANDPOINT OF AN EDITOR.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the time when in Chicago cheap Bohemian newspapers appeared with cheaper contents, there was exerted a pressure on our publication, Svornost, with the demand to lower our prices. This would be impossible, should Svornost remain for the future a newspaper with carefully prepared contents, as it has until today. In the meantime while other cheap publications were filled with insignificant reprints, our readers always found in the columns of Svornost, contemporary, carefully selected information about our overworked people, the newest correspondence from our staff members from almost all parts of the United States. The decent publication of this kind of newspaper, with other necessary expenses, made the expenditure so great that the editor was absolutely unable to lower the prices. The other publications, not having such high expenses, were not able to stand the competition any other way than by being cheap. In the last few years the Svornost has almost doubled in publication and when it was more and more voiced by our enlightened workingmen that they would subscribe willingly to Svornost in preference to other pseudo-workingmen's news, were they able to pay the same price, the administration conforming with the public desire, decided to lower the price.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0243.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Starting the coming Sunday, March 25, Svornost will cost ten cents per week and its contents will not be of less value or less carefully chosen. Willing to give to the readers, always, the latest news and information and the best articles and editorials, the management of the Svornost governed themselves by the example of principal English newspapers and German workingmen's news, such as the Arbeiter Zeitung; we installed, at great expense, electrically propelled new linotypes and presses which will help extensively to lower the price of our publication.</p>
   <p>Lately the publication Denni Hlasatel which is a member of a pseudo-union, started a secret and even a public fight against Syornost for not belonging to the union. We like to explain correctly the relations of Bohemian publications with the Typographical Union. The Svornost has nothing against the union and if somebody really is a friend of workingmen, that is the editor of Svornost, Mr. August Geringer, and believe me his start in the newspaper business was much harder than of any one of those fops on Ashland avenue and 18th street, who try to be the Messiahs of Bohemian typesetters for the Bohemian workingmen.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0244.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The editor of Svornost has nothing against his employees belonging to the union, but if they are not able to become members of the union - the cause of it is again Hlasatel. We have proved already to the Bohemian citizens that there is no doubt that Hlasatel is in no way a cooperative nor a regular stock-company employing the stockholders. It is simply a case of the bosses and employers of Hlasatel being at the same time the bosses in the union of Bohemian printers where all rascals are against Svornost. Nobody has heard as yet of a union where the employers were workingmen at the same time. So long as the employers and bosses of Hlasatel can be the members of the Bohemian Printers' Union, this kind of a union can never be regarded as an honest and solid workingmen's union body.</p>
   <p>From the moment of resignation of all bosses and stockholders of the incorporated firm, Denni Hlasatel, from the union, this union will start to be an honorable workingmen's union.</p>
   <p>When Svornost installed the new linotypes and setting machinery, the personnel of Hlasatel started to gossip the news that, at least, half of our typesetters must be laid off, but nothing like that has happened and none of the setters <pb facs="5418478_4_0245.jpg" n="4"/>was dismissed. On the contrary, the editor of Svornost, a man always sympathizing with the workingmen, divided the setting personnel in two parts and gave to everyone an eight-hour a day job. In this regard our workingmen have a real advantage over the union workingmen of Hlasatel, National Press, and other printing shops where union conditions exist on paper only, and where a union man, to get along, must work hard and long into the night to obtain the exceptional pay as determined by the union. Where it happens in a union printing shop that the bosses are union members too, nobody has control of it and it is easily silenced.</p>
   <p>Should Mr. Geringer have union workingmen and abuse them the same way as Hlasatel or National Press, all the Bohemian citizens aroused by the union and its bosses would rise against him.</p>
   <p>The typesetters of Svornost are working a straight eight-hour day and their weekly payroll is absolutely higher than if they would be paid according to the union rates.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0246.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The best proof of this was when, not long ago, our manager appointed two union typesetters to help us out and gave them a salary conforming with the union scale. Neither of them, even working hard, was able to earn as much as the average wages of our typesetters. And it is a public secret that none of the so-called Bohemian Union printing shops is paying according to union scales, which are only on paper for publicity. These two boys are the best witnesses of the conditions which rule Svornost. They have assured our management that they will work willingly each time, should we need help; they stated further, that the Svornost printing shop is the best and most perfect of all they have worked in and that everything gossiped by the stock-holders about Mr. Geringer and his staff of co-workers is untrue and an un-founded lie. We must add that the said two typesetters were not any irresponsible boys but experienced workers.</p>
   <p>We are in doubt if the Bohemian Printers' Union could offer better working conditions than Svornost does, giving to its workers an eight-hour day and bigger wages than the union scale offers. In spite of this our workingmen are willing to join the union the moment the rich stockholders and proprietors of Hlasatel will resign as illegitimate members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0247.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The purchase of the machinery by Svornost is of a big advantage to our workingmen and our present and future patrons because our typesetters get a shorter day of work, the same good wages and our patrons a cheaper newspaper.</p>
   <p>We hope that the Bohemian citizens will acknowledge our position and appreciate our efforts for the benefit of the reading public and for the purpose of justice in working conditions in the Bohemian printing shops.</p>
   <p>The editor of Svornost was not the cause of our not wanting to join the union, but the real cause was the deceit of the stockholders of Denni Hlasatel, their bosses and pseudo-union-men. All the time, during this union fight against our paper, nobody else tried to rouse the prejudice and mistrust among the educated and intelligent people toward our paper, but only Hlasatel with the help of its stockholders and employers.</p>
   <p>We are asking our patrons to take everything previously said into consideration and remember that this newspaper will cost in the future ten cents only, and their desires will be fulfilled, then you will have a long-expected, widely read, excellent, and cheap Bohemian newspaper in the United States, for a <pb facs="5418478_4_0248.jpg" n="7"/>smaller prices than any insignificant paper filled with unworthy reprints from old country papers, and representing different political humbugs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
