<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Czechoslovak Review</title>,
<date when="1921-09">September 1921</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Czechoslovak Review</title>,
<date when="1921-09">September 1921</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 265... From every city of the United States where there is a Sokol organization, athletes keyed high and trained to the minute came to Chicago to take part in the first all-American Sokol competitions arranged by all groups except one. The city decked in gala attire, in which the flags of America and Czechoslovakia predominated, received the contestants, as well as the visitors, with open arms.</p>
   <p>An outstanding feature of this celebration was the presence of a team of Sokols from Czechoslovakia under the leadership of Mr. Rudolph Bilik.</p>
   <p>This is the aggregation which captured every event in which it was entered in Europe during the past year. Incidentally,it is the first visit of free Czechoslovak Sokols, which organization did such Herculean work for the freedom of Czechoslovakia.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1063.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From Washington came Dr. Bedrich Stepanek, the Czechoslovak Minister to the United States, to welcome the Sokols and their friends and to give encouragement to the competitors to display their skill.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovakian government sensed the importance of this occasion and sent an official representative in the person of Senator Vaclav Klofac, former Minister of national defense.</p>
   <p>Arrangements were in the hands of Dr. A. Mueller, chairman of the committee in charge of this year's competitions, and Mr. Josef Placek, the president of the Central Sokol Organization.</p>
   <p>On August 24th, 25th, and 26th the preliminary or elimination contests were held. On Saturday, in the Coliseum, the main events were decided. Representatives of the state and city administrations welcomed the city's guests.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1064.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Stepanek extended greetings to the assemblage. A message of felicitations and thanks to America on behalf of the Czechoslovak people was interpreted by Senator Klofac. In the contests about 3,000 athletes took part. It was the biggest aggregation of American gymnasts of Czechoslovak origin ever assembled in the United States.</p>
   <p>On August 28th, a grand parade through the Czechoslovak sections of Chicago took place. In the afternoon exhibition drills were then held in the Coliseum before a mixed audience which appreciated the efforts of the participants. This concluded the program of the most successful athletic meet ever staged . by Americans of Czechoslovak origin in the United States and it is hoped that hereafter they will be repeated annually.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
