<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-12-20">Dec. 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">School and Stage for Education</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-12-20">Dec. 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL AND STAGE FOR EDUCATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian-American Free Thought School is going to be rebuilt to meet the most modern requirements. The wealthy lodges of the school association can well afford the expenditure, and we hope that the alteration will be carried through completely this time. The building is still in good enough condition to warrant rebuilding, with the result that it will be a more suitable edifice for the center of our national activities than it formerly was. The trustees of the association should not shrink from any expense or limit the outlay to a simple patching-up of the old building. This would mean a mere waste of money, unwise for the coffers even of a prosperous organization. And the leaders should not forget that the accommodations of the school and the stage for theatrical performances are of signal importance, for school and theater complement each other.</p>
   <p>Our amateurs seem to have awakened to new life, and they should therefore be extended broadest hospitality. Under prevailing conditions, our amateur actors today have no adequate stage in the Pilsen district. The trustees <pb facs="5418478_4_0708.jpg" n="2"/>are not ignorant of the fact that the popularity of the old building is due more to the amateur actors than to any other organization, so that an empty gesture of gratitude [rather than actually providing theater facilities] would mean a loss in revenues.</p>
   <p>And the school? Let us unreservedly admit that there is no truly liberal school in the Pilsen district. Our Czech settlement in Chicago, the largest in the country, lags woefully behind others, even the smallest, in this respect. It is therefore a matter of course that the school should receive the greatest consideration, so that parents could send their children to a school where they will be taught properly. All other items, as for instance the dance hall, are not as important as the stage and the school.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
