<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-11">Dec. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Seventh Convention of the Czecho-Slavonic Union</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Fifth and Sixth (Final) Sessions]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1608</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1608.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-11">Dec. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE SEVENTH CONVENTION OF THE CZECHO-SLAVONIC UNION</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Fifth and Sixth (Final) Sessions]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The third day of the convention of the Cesko-Slavanska Jednota (Czecho-Slavonic Union) began at the usual time with roll call of the delegates. The reading of the minutes of the previous session followed. The minutes were approved after some minor corrections. At the request of the president, the second secretary of the convention, Mr. Antonin Turek, read a letter sent by the central committee for collecting funds for the aid of invalid Czechoslovak legionnaires and their families. In this letter the committee greeted the convention, asking its delegates not to forget the needy invalid legionnaires. The letter was referred to the committee on charities.</p>
   <p>The reports of committees followed. The resolutions committee presented the following resolution to the convention:</p>
   <p>"The committee on resolutions has considered the following:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1609.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"It is necessary that all those men who represent our element [Translator's note: The committee probably intended to say 'interest' instead of 'element'] in the various Bohemian free-thinking societies, fraternal unions, and lodges, drop their personal animosities and such other extraneous matters not concerning the life of these organizations, and concentrate on the idea of forming one solidly organized Bohemian Free Thought fraternal and benevolent union. When we consider the good which would come from such a union we wonder why this has not yet been attempted in this country. In our own and in the interest of all freethinking organizations, we desire that all these ideas of personal gain be banished in all lodges and orders. It is these ideas that stand in the way of unity and solidarity, that prevent a consolidation of these various smaller organizations into one mighty freethinking body, a unified body which we all so sorely need."</p>
   <p>This resolution received unanimous approval, whereupon the proceedings of the convention continued. The matter of raising the dues of the membership again come up for discussion. These dues concerned the reserve fund of the organization. The dues for this purpose which hitherto were paid by members were <pb facs="5418478_4_1610.jpg" n="3"/>found to be rather inadequate, and the committee recognized the need for its increase. The dues as paid hitherto were as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Amount of Benefit</cell>
     <cell>Amount of Dues</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>$1,000.00</cell>
     <cell>$0.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>750.00</cell>
     <cell>.08</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>500.00</cell>
     <cell>.05</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>250.00</cell>
     <cell>.03</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The proposed revision was as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Amount of Benefit</cell>
     <cell>Amount of Dues</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>For each $1,000.00</cell>
     <cell>$0.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>750.00</cell>
     <cell>.15</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>500.00</cell>
     <cell>.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>250.00</cell>
     <cell>.05</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1611.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is quite obvious that this recommendation was discussed at great length, and that it received the attention it deserved. It was recognized, and publicly declared by Mr. Hribal, that this increase would not be the last one. It is to be expected that further increases of these dues will be made at future conventions of the Jednota. Finally, after a protracted debate, this matter was put to a vote; the balloting was done by roll call. There were 48 ayes and 12 nays, the motion received, therefore, more than its required two-thirds majority and was passed.</p>
   <p>Chapter XIX, Article 2 of the constitution, dealing with the calling of conventions was likewise thoroughly discussed and analyzed in great detail. It was felt that the calling of a convention should occur only when there was an absolute need for it, since the expenses connected with it were great, and by wise legislation this could be avoided. It was ruled, consequently, that all future conventions take place during a specified season or whenever the need demands their being called. Article 4 of the same chapter was changed in the sense that all lodges appoint and announce their delegates six months prior <pb facs="5418478_4_1612.jpg" n="5"/>to any convention instead of sixty days as was the practice hitherto. Sixty days was too short a period during which the necessary preparations were to be made for the convention. This motion was unanimously approved and passed. The same approval was given all other changes recommended by the committee and relating to such preparatory work as is usual before a convention is held.</p>
   <p>Rules relating to the meetings of the Grand Lodge did not escape the scrutiny of the committee, and were changed to be more purposeful as regards certain details. A lively debate ensued following a recommendation by the committee which desired that greater leniency be shown to those members who were excluded from the Jednota because of nonpayment of dues. It was recommended that they be reinstated after having paid their arrears. This recommendation was not favorably received and finally rejected altogether.</p>
   <p>Rules and regulations dealing with the children's insurance department were likewise subjected to an analysis, and were clarified and corrected in certain <pb facs="5418478_4_1613.jpg" n="6"/>of their points, Since the noon hour approached, the session ended.</p>
   <p>The final session started promptly at 1:30 P.M. There was the usual roll call followed by the reading of the minutes of the previous session which were unanimously approved. The press and publicity committee then submitted its report recommending (1) that the proceedings of this convention be published in printed form, and then sent to all the newspapers as well as to the secretaries of all the lodges of the Jednota, these minutes were to be reprinted, of course, in the organ of the Jednota; (2) that all printing jobs be executed only by our own Czechoslovak printing establishments, and, as far as possible and practicable, by the printers who are members of the Jednota; and (3) that the constitution and bylaws be printed in both Czech and in English, and, since many members of the Jednota are Croatians, satisfactory provisions are also to be made that they receive copies of the constitution and bylaws in their own language. All of these recommendations were approved after some minor changes were effected in the wording of them. The recommendation which asked that only one copy of the official organ of the Jednota be mailed to families <pb facs="5418478_4_1614.jpg" n="7"/>where several members belong to the Jednota was rejected because it was considered impracticable. The law requires that every member of the Jednota must be informed about the financial state of his organization; it is, consequently, necessary that a copy of the official organ be sent to every member.</p>
   <p>The committee on finance then made its report, recommending that $5 be paid to every delegate for every day he or she attended the convention the total being $915; the committee also recommended that $192.58 for traveling expenses be paid to out-of-town delegates. The first secretary Mr. F. Lukes, shall receive $25 for his extra work connected with the convention, and the second secretary shall receive $15 for similar work. The rental of the convention hall for the three days was $60; the decorations cost $6.35. The bills for the printing of the new constitution and bylaws, as well as all other printed matter, shall be included in the general expenses of the convention, and the Grand Lodge is to meet them accordingly. The report of the finance committee was unanimously approved.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1615.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The committee on charities reported that its members decided not to recommend the making of any contributions to any institutions or causes except the Ceska Svobodna Skola (Bohemian Free Thought [community] School), at Cleveland, Ohio. It, however, leaves the matter of making all other contributions to the discretion of the whole convention. This report aroused much comment giving rise to a lengthy debate. Finally, when the delegate of Kralovice Lodge No. 40, Mr. Josef F. Belica, announced that he was going to contribute the sum of $100 (which amount of money he received for traveling and other expenses connected with this convention), for the benefit of the Bohemian Free Thought schools and other causes, the convention itself decided to match that amount with $150 to be used for charitable and educational institutions and causes, and asked the Grand Lodge delegates to make provisions for these gifts. The well-known fact that the Jednota always contributed to nationalistic, educational, charitable, and other and similar causes was duly considered, and it was believed that the amount mentioned was a sufficient contribution.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1616.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>After listening to the report of the organization committee and rejecting it as being out of place, the convention heard the additional report of the finance committee. The latter announced that it had divided the amount of $150 (which had just been approved by the convention), among various institutions. But, before a more detailed report of this committee could be received and approved, the delegate, Mr. Belica, announced that he would add the amount which he previously mentioned so that the allotment could thereby be increased. Despite both of these acts it was believed that the contributions were not large enough, and the whole matter had to be discussed again. The matter was put to a vote and referred back to the finance committee with a recommendation made by the delegate, Mrs. Blazek, that the contribution be increased to $200. and then reapportioned among the institutions and causes which were to benefit therefrom.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, a congratulatory letter arrived from the National Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) which was gratefully noted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1617.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>The committee on constitution and bylaws made its further report dealing with children's insurance. That report, too, was unanimously approved. Another recommendation, made by that same committee and dealing with initiatory rites to be published in the English language, was approved because of the obvious needs of certain lodges, and it was decided that these rites and ceremonies be used by all of the lodges of the Jednota. The same committee further announced that it is still faced with the task of amending and correcting the bylaws of subordinate lodges, but that this matter requires a tremendous amount of work, and that it, consequently, cannot be completed while this convention is in session. The committee was, therefore, willing to continue to function after the convention and make the results of its work known to the Grand Lodge as soon as it is finished. This report, showing such great willingness on the part of the members of the committee, was, of course, gratefully noted, and the said committee will continue to be active after the convention closes. The financial committee thereupon reported back to the convention giving all details as to how the contributed money was to be apportioned. The report follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1618.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>To the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol v Chicago (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools in Chicago), $40; the Svobodomyslna Skola in Milwaukee, $25; the Svobodomyslna Skola in Cedar Rapids, Iowa, $25; that of Cleveland, Ohio, $25; that of Baltimore, Maryland, $25; the Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) of Chicago, $35; the Neighborhood House in Gary, Indiana, $15; the Ceska Besidka a Opatrovna v Chicagu (Bohemian Kindergarten and Creche in Chicago), $10.</p>
   <p>Delegate Hribal....proposed that besides the four existing types of insurance a fifth type should be instituted. This type of insurance would make it possible for certain members to pay their premiums for twenty years only, and the policy would remain in force for the balance of their natural lives no matter how long they lived. This proposition could be studied by the board of directors, and if found suitable, could be made effective later. This proposition was favorably received and will be considered.</p>
   <p>This brought to a close the business of the convention.....The president <pb facs="5418478_4_1619.jpg" n="12"/>delivered his closing address in which he thanked all the delegates for their good will and for the work accomplished. He alluded also to the hard work of the members of the various committees who expedited it with such efficiency and thanked them for all their efforts; then turning to the representative of our daily Bohemian newspaper, the Denni Hlasatel he thanked us for the willingness with which our journal followed the deliberations of the Jednota....</p>
   <p>Thereupon the seventh convention of the Jednota was declared closed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
