<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-17">Apr. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Native American Feels with the Czechs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0865</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0865.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-17">Apr. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A NATIVE AMERICAN FEELS WITH THE CZECHS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Kenneth Miller, a native American, who is active as an assistant to the Reverend Doctor V. Pisek in New York, came to Chicago a few days ago for a short visit. He is returning from Texas where he stopped at eighteen communities of a strong Czech population. The main purpose of his travels is the formation and extension of branches of the Bohemian National Alliance. He succeeded in founding four groups in Texas. On his tours, which he finances himself, he collected up to $250 for the Alliance.</p>
   <p>Though a born New Yorker, Mr. Miller speaks and writes the Czech language perfectly. He acquired this knowledge during a sojourn in Moravia. Being financed by a scholarship there, he studied the country. While traveling in Moravia and Bohemia, he learned to know, to love, and to respect the Czechs. Mr. Miller studied at the Princeton University, where President <pb facs="5418478_4_0866.jpg" n="2"/>Woodrow Wilson was at that time active, and one of his teachers. He later continued studying theology in New York. On the strength of his particular knowledge of the Czech element, he is in a position to frequently deliver lectures on the subject, highly appreciating the interest of American audiences. He expects to hold one lecture for the general public upon his visit to Chicago next fall. He will then travel through the West where he is engaged for a considerable number of public appearances. He did not stay long in Chicago this time, having left last night for New York.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
