<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-03">May 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Two Local Sokol Associations Merge and Consider the Building of a New Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1023</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1023.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-03">May 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">TWO LOCAL SOKOL ASSOCIATIONS MERGE AND CONSIDER THE BUILDING OF A NEW HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A year has elapsed since two of our Sokol associations, the Sokol Tabor Slovanske Lipy (Sokol Tabor of the Slavonic Linden Tree) and the Sokol Slavoj, merged. The reason for this merger was the building of a new....Sokol hall where our young people could be trained in the great Sokol ideals, and where our Czech societies could find a new home for the cultivation of their national, cultural, and social aims, which have been somewhat neglected since the old hall of the Sokol Tabor burned down. Shortly after the two Sokol associations united, a building committee was appointed which endeavored to work toward an early realization of this idea. It is regrettable that until now progress has been slow. The chief stumbling block was the high cost of building, but the current hard times and the indecision of the members themselves as to where to build, also interfered. Add to this also the indifference from which our general public suffers, and you have a complete picture of the situation. What makes it more difficult still, is the rather complicated real-estate situation <pb facs="5418478_4_1024.jpg" n="2"/>facing the new Sokol association. That complication resulted from our ownership of the site where our old Sokol Slovanska Lipa stood before it was torn down, the partially rebuilt structure of the former Sokol Tabor, which today serves only as a meeting place for some of our societies, and the three building sites situated on 16th Street and Karlov Avenue, which we inherited from the Sokol Slavoj. We also have in our possession the sum of thirteen thousand dollars in ready cash. The payment of taxes and the upkeep of all these properties cause both hardship and expense, to say nothing of an absolute lack of profit. For the time being, our gymnasium is located in a former movie theater, and nobody can deny that that is most impractical. And yet, in spite of all these difficulties and hindrances, there seems to be a desire on the part of our members to erect a new building, for on such an action hinges the continuance of our activities as a Sokol organization, and the preservation of the Bohemian characteristics of the local community. If no steps are taken to introduce some radical changes in the immediate future, the characteristically Bohemian type and life of this community will suffer immeasurably. Therefore, to weigh all these matters, the Sokol Tabor has issued a call to all its members <pb facs="5418478_4_1025.jpg" n="3"/>to come to a meeting which is to be held on next Thursday, May 4, 1922, at 8 P. M., in the hall situated on Karlov Avenue and 13th Street. The building committee will report, and it will be definitely decided how our project is to proceed, and where the site of our future home is to be. It is therefore necessary to call this meeting to the attention of the members of the Sokol Tabor, and especially to inform the local Bohemian residents whom this project will concern most. It is also desirable that the voices of the many Bohemian societies be heard in this meeting, since their moral and material support is expected. Should these societies and our general public show their indifference, it would naturally be very difficult for the Sokol association alone to realize its aim. The local community needs an appropriate hall which would answer all its requirements for the present and the future. The co-operation of the community would make our own burden bearable. Let us hope that our united efforts will soon bring forth the desired realization of the project.....Na zdar! (All hail!)</p>
   <p>Jan Zachotina,</p>
   <p>2413 South Harding Avenue,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
