<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-12">Nov. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Czecho-Slavonic Union to Convene</title><title level="a" type="sub">Pre-convention Preparations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-12">Nov. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECHO-SLAVONIC UNION TO CONVENE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Pre-convention Preparations</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we have previously announced, there will be a convention of the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Czecho-Slavonic Union) in Chicago during the month of December. We may now augment this news by stating that according to the decision of the Grand Lodge of the Jednota, the convention is to open on December 8, 1922, and will, no doubt, last three days. According to the program already arranged the convention is to end on December 10 in the Plzensky Sokol (Pilsen Sokol) Hall, at Ashland Avenue and West 18th Street.</p>
   <p>There will be many important problems facing the convention, and the hard working members of the Jednota hope that their organization will be revitalized by the convention and stimulated to continued activity for its further development and peaceful prosperity.</p>
   <p>We assume that the delegates will come armed with many recommendations and propositions for the good of the Jednota. It will also be decided whether <pb facs="5418478_4_1655.jpg" n="2"/>only one officer is to be elected instead of the recording secretary and financial secretary; in this way the work done by two people would be done by one man, an arrangement, the members firmly believe, that would be more profitable for the Jednota, judging by similar decisions made by other organizations for the same reason.....</p>
   <p>This will be the seventh convention of this Union, and 68 lodges will be represented, all of which, with a few exceptions, are located in or near Chicago. According to latest reports the Jednota has 5,810 members, and the active brothers and sisters are striving to increase that number substantially.</p>
   <p>Moreover, the children's insurance department of the Jednota has a large number of children as insured members, and the central office of the Jednota has hopes that their number will increase to one thousand.</p>
   <p>December 16, was set aside by the Grand Lodge as a sort of surprise for all the <pb facs="5418478_4_1656.jpg" n="3"/>insured members of the children's department. That lodge made preparations for a Saint Nicholas party in the Pilsen Park pavilion, and to it all the children belonging to the Jednota will be invited. For every child there will be a gift waiting. We are convinced that in this way the interest in the children's department will greatly increase.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
