<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-01">June 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Ruzicka Wins Wrestling Match</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-01">June 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">RUZICKA WINS WRESTLING MATCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--Another victory has come to the Bohemian wrestler Ruzicka in his long chain of successful combats. For the interesting occasion the hall of the Pilsen Sokol was filled to capacity by a public highly satisfied with the events of the evening. Every number of the program had its charm and its interest. Muscle exhibitions perfectly executed entertained and educated the audience. The appearance of the Vesely brothers evoked a storm of applause.</p>
   <p>In the bout between Frank Rello from Baltimore and the Chicagoan John Yello the former won. Rello offers to match his strength against any Chicago wrestler in the 130-pound class. A telegram from wrestler Klank of Omaha was read, challenging Frank Ruzicka to a return match for five hundred dollars, the money to be deposited with the Chicago American. Ruzicka accepted the challenge.</p>
   <p>The last and most interesting number of the program was Ruzicka's bout with the colored strong man Childs. The contest was of comparatively short duration. <pb facs="5418478_4_1362.jpg" n="2"/>The negro has powerful muscles, it is true, but he is awkward and was defeated in the first two falls; so the third fall was omitted. The first fall was secured in 7 1/2 minutes by forcing Childs on his shoulders; the second after 4 minutes with the same result.</p>
   <p>The public gave vent to its satisfaction in bursts of applause. Ruzicka was generally admired by the experts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
