<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-01-12">Jan. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Lecture about Bohemians</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0895</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0895.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-01-12">Jan. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A LECTURE ABOUT BOHEMIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Bohemian principal, Professor J. J. Zmrhal,director of the modern exemplary school, Herzl public school in Chicago, delivered a lecture in Lincoln Center about Bohemians. This lecture was one of a series arranged for the purpose of acquainting the American public with the immigrants, their countries, traditions, and characteristics. The lectures were attended by students and teachers, and the speaker succeeded in interesting his select audience by his excellent delivery and accurate presentation of facts.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zmrhal started with an outline of the historical development of our Bohemian nation, stressing particularly our religious struggles and wars. He continued by discussing the period of our national regeneration and the cultural strife for national existence, as well as the success along these lines which we have achieved entirely by our own efforts without any outside help. He also described the Bohemian colony in Chicago, and the work which Bohemian immigrants are doing in this country. The Bohemians are the best educated <pb facs="5418478_4_0896.jpg" n="2"/>immigrants, having no illiterates among them. They are keenly interested in all public questions, and have four large dailies in Chicago alone. From modest beginnings the Bohemians have succeeded in building large industrial enterprises, banks, and other businesses.</p>
   <p>Among American educated classes that of the Bohemians stands in the forefront with respect to the sciences, arts, and politics. We are, therefore, not only producers of wealth, but also leaders in cultural endeavors, the creators of beauty and workers toward the public good. The speaker's statements were supported by carefully selected data, and they evidently impressed the audience, for many requests for additional information were made of Mr. Zmrhal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
