<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-06">July 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Third Convention of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych Second Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0588</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0588.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-06">July 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE THIRD CONVENTION OF THE SVAZ SVOBODOMYSLNYCH Second Day</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second day of the convention of the Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers of America enjoyed a still larger attendance than the first, many new delegates having arrived in Chicago. The debate about schools was resumed and the general concensus of opinion was that it would be impossible now to contemplate the unification of the Sdruzeni Svobodomyslnych Skol (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools) of Chicago and the Cesko-American Matice Skolska (Bohemian-American Scholastic Association), but that there will be a much closer co-operation between the two bodies in the nearest future.</p>
   <p>The question of cremation was discussed and the delegated from New York, Baltimore, Cleveland, and other cities reported on the progress that burial by fire has been making in their respective territories.....</p>
   <p>Further, the relation between the free thought and the partisans of various <pb facs="5418478_4_0589.jpg" n="2"/>other elementary principles was discussed, and Mr. Voska's speech on this topic was particularly noteworthy.</p>
   <p>A great deal of interest was aroused by Mr. Tvrzicky-Kramer, secretary of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance) who spoke on the topic "Freethinking Bohemians in America and the Work for the Liberation of the Bohemian Nation". He proved that it is the duty of every freethinking person to work for liberty. The liberty may be either political or cultural, since one supplements the other. Particularly now, in these days of Huss' commemorations, when it is up to us to show how far we have advanced in Bohemian-America, and when the protestant clergymen of non-Bohemian nationalities do not hesitate to favor openly the liberation of the Bohemian nation, there must not be even one freethinking Bohemian who does not understand the fatefulness of these days for the future of the Bohemian nation. In the Bohemian capital, the city of Prague, where a convention of freethinkers of the whole world was to be held in that Prague of John Huss, the site of <pb facs="5418478_4_0590.jpg" n="3"/>such strong manifestations of free thought organizations, warrants for the arrest of the most important Bohemian leaders are being issued. The speaker mentioned that just now one of the prominent participants in the first world free thought convention held in Prague in 1907, Dr. Josef Scheiner, the head of the Ceska Obec Sokolska (Bohemian Sokol Community), has been arrested and put in prison in Vienna. Instead of the free thought convention in Prague, the city has witnessed the closing of the publishing offices of the Volna Myslenka (Free Thought) and confiscation of its property. Since the free thought convention in Prague could not be held--the convention at which freethinkers from all over the world were to again make a strong plea for the freedom of conscience, and so honor the memory of John Huss--let this convention, assembled in the largest Bohemian community overseas, speak on behalf of the strongest branch of the Bohemian nation outside of the old country to all liberty-loving people. Let this convention adopt a resolution which would express our feeling in the matter of liberty and freedom, and send it in translation in the principal world languages to freethinking <pb facs="5418478_4_0591.jpg" n="4"/>organizations in all cultural countries.</p>
   <p>This lengthy speech of Mr. Tvrzicky-Kramer was followed with keen interest and attention. Its impression was strengthened by the speech of Mr. Voska who, taking up where his predecessor ended, presented a true picture of the work of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni. Under the spell of these two speeches the convention adopted a resolution urging all freethinking organizations to give substantial financial support to the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni and to co-operate with its action to their best possibilities. Both resolutions were adopted unanimously.</p>
   <p>The next discussion was devoted to the education of youth and a resolution was adopted urging all freethinking Bohemians to give their children a good education in the Bohemian language, and to spend whatever money may be necessary to give them the very best schooling they can afford. All Bohemian communities should see to it that the Bohemian language be taught in their high schools, and that a department for the study of Bohemian language and <pb facs="5418478_4_0592.jpg" n="5"/>literature be established in their state universities.</p>
   <p>A resolution was adopted thanking Mayor Thompson for his help in carrying out the resolution of Bohemian associations requesting the removal of the article about the German Kaiser from Chicago school books. It was also agreed to further urge this request by a special letter to the Chicago Board of Education. Other resolutions adopted were: A recommendation for the unification of all benevolent societies; a vote of thanks to the executive committee of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych in New York for his fine work; a vote of thanks to the New York and Chicago newspapers for reporting the convention.</p>
   <p>The chairman closed the convention with a beautiful speech. No doubt this convention will remain for many years in the vivid memory of all those who were fortunate enough to attend it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
