<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-16">Jan. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Action Taken by Bohemian Students Benefiting the Bohemian Public Library</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-16">Jan. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ACTION TAKEN BY BOHEMIAN STUDENTS BENEFITING THE BOHEMIAN PUBLIC LIBRARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The students of the Harrison Technical High School attending the third-year Bohemian classes in Bohemian literature and history have found it very difficult to find the books assigned by their teachers. They have found the Bohemian section of our library at Homan Avenue and 26th Street in a deplorable condition. This Bohemian section can boast only of a few bocks of doubtful literary value, and they are dirty and torn.</p>
   <p>Two committees were selected from the student body which are to strive to remedy this sad condition. One committee, Antonin Nemecek and Miss Anezka Basta, was sent to visit Mr. Legler, the librarian, to ask him to improve the Bohemian section. Mr. Legler greeted the committee very cordially and said that the money was there, but that conditions did not permit the buying of books just then.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0084.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee composed of Bohumil Janda and Miss M. Kaspar was directed to visit Dr. Frantisek Pokorney, a Bohemian member of the library board, to ask him to work for the betterment of the conditions existing at the Homan branch of the Public Library, and to see to it that employees shall be stationed there who understand Bohemian and can help those who seek information.</p>
   <p>The student body has not stopped with the appointment of committees but intends to use self-help. The students of the second semester are now translating into Bohemian a fine one-act play, "Peveclidu" (The People's Singer), which they expect to produce, and with the money thus earned they plan to start an auxilary Bohemian section of the library in our School.</p>
   <p>J. V. Nigrin, teacher of Bohemian</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
