<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-01">Apr. 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Art Club Sponsors Lectures</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0871</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0871.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-01">Apr. 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ART CLUB SPONSORS LECTURES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Umelecky Klub (Art Club) is going to arrange for popular lectures about art which are to comprise painting, sculpture, and architecture. The admission will be only 10 cents. A meeting of the club will be held on April 11 in Schnabl's place when the details will be discussed, one of which is the proposal to combine the lectures with outings during summertime. The dunes of Indiana, or the primeval forests near Bensonville are receiving due consideration.</p>
   <p>The first entertainments for active and contributing members was held in the studio of Mr. Sterba, the painter, last Wednesday, with the ladies' division of the society participating. The affair was an unqualified success, and the hilarious gathering did not disperse until the early morning hours.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0872.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first serious part of the program consisted of a lecture on Jan Amos Komensky, delivered by Dr. Vojan, followed by a musical in which the virtuoso, Vlaciha, and Medek, excelled. Among the diverse classic compositions rendered, there was the "Hungarian Dance No. 6" by Brahms, "Zephyr" by Hubay, Poem by Fibich, for the violin, played by Mr. Medek, with piano accompaniment played by Mr. Vlaciha. The latter offered also as a solo the "Minuet" by Paderewski, "Melody" by Friml, and the "Rhapsody No. 8" by Liszt. The charming hostess, Mrs. Messenger-Sterba, who is a virtuoso on the harp, rendered a transcription of Schubert's "Serenade."</p>
   <p>The second, a merry part of the program, featured a multicolored selection of songs, instrumental music, recitation of poems, and drawing to the tune of music. All those present including some bankers, contributed generously to the general fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
