<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Masaryk, T. C. <title>Cesky Odd Fellow</title> (The Bohemian Odd Fellow), (Monthly),
<date when="1937-09">Sept. 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Masaryk, T. C. <title>Cesky Odd Fellow (The Bohemian Odd Fellow)</title>, (Monthly),
<date when="1937-09">Sept. 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.16--At the age of almost eighty six years, a man, to whom in the full sense of the word, belongs the predicate of a creator and builder of the independent Czechoslovak state, retired from the most responsible position in the republic on the fourteenth of December 1935. He left firmly convinced that the liberated people and its older as well as its younger leaders are politically educated and experienced to-day, and that with their full development there need be no doubt as to the further successful direction of the state, and that the time has indeed arrived for the most sensitive and most difficult tasks, concentrated in the responsible office of President, to be now intrusted to a capable younger statesman.</p>
   <p>He did not abandon his work, but wished to devote himself to it in tranquility and privacy for as long as his span of life and his health permitted.</p>
   <p>Masaryk--philosopher of life--has possibly no other in world history to bear comparison with him; who as a thinker and reformer, politician and statesman of world-wide consequence, knew how to conduct his work so precisely and carry it out in so convincing a manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0305.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He pondered over the purpose of individual and social life with scientific exactness, and fate granted him sufficient strength and time to demonstrate on himself, on the historical development of his nation or else on the vicissitudes of life of mankind, what he, as a rigorous thinker, had discovered and accepted as his conviction.</p>
   <p>Masaryk went after the truth with assiduous persistence and with all the might of his extraordinary capability. Nothing could dissuade him from standing up for truth as derived from life. In his treatise "The problem of religion and modern philosophy" he says: "Modern man demands of philosophy an explanation of life, of actual life, of life in its entirety--he wants to know how to live--but instead, life is lived and philosophy is spoken. And thence the craving for a new philosophy, of life--hence the longing for a new word, and--for a new life."</p>
   <p>No wonder, therfore, that Masaryk was attracted above all by philosophical dissertation of whether man can actually reach the bottom of incontrovertible truth, and whether it is human reason alone which can fathom the truths of life.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0306.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this respect Masaryk's attention was mainly arrested by the Scotch thinker Hume, from whose doubt of the achievement and value of the action of pure reasoning he takes his start, and to whose sprightly and profound ratiocination he reverts time and again, since the beginning of his educational career.</p>
   <p>Just as by analyzing man, as to his individual values and in his physical and spiritual capabilities, Masaryk prepared for himself a store for the philosophical synthesis and for a practical program in life, he progressed in the study of family, community, state, church, Europe, the whole world and the entire mankind, for he thusly expresses himself in "Ceska otazka" (The Bohemian Question): "Unless the life of man thinking, be a chain of single episodes--and such a life is utterly unbearable for one even remotely inclined towards reasoning and veracity--all spiritual as well as practical work must be based upon a distinct and solid philosophical foundation."</p>
   <p>Along this conception Masaryk also shaped the philosophy of our people, and on November 18, 1892, he delivered a speech in the Vienna parliament, on the "Conception of Austria and the Bohemian Question" in which he declared: <pb facs="5418478_4_0307.jpg" n="4"/>"We demand the independence of the countries of the Bohemian crown, we ourselves want to decide about ourselves, we want a full and perfect national life. Everything the people can do for its political and human enlightenment, we are willing to do as well. We are not a small nation, of whom the deciding authorities in Austria have become accustomed to think, that, when the worst happens, it can be just suffered, and be granted small concessions as a sap. The position of the Czech nation has a significance in Europe and the world. Our nation does not live in the moonlight-reflex of the Germanic sun, our nation had had an independent culture and has one up to the present. And this nation, remembering its great past, now wants to live again as an independent nation and to do great, and only great deeds. This is the idealism that carries us, in spite of all the mimical powers."</p>
   <p>Thus Masaryk, the thinker as well as reformer and sociologist, enters political public life, and during the years 1895-1898 he published his studies "The Bohemian Question," "Our Present Crisis," "Jan Hus," "Karel Havlicek" and "The Social Question." In these Masaryk laid down the philosophic program, the historic significance, and the aims of our nation and in this manner established contact with the philosophy of Palacky according to whose History of the Bohemian People "there had been continual contacts and contests between the Slavonic peoples on the one and the Romans and Germans on <pb facs="5418478_4_0308.jpg" n="5"/>the other hand. In this struggle the Bohemian people saved itself by its education and morality, in the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries, indeed by the higher morality and enlightenment--by Hussitism and brotherhood."</p>
   <p>Masaryk remained loyal to the heritage of Palacky who on the 23rd of April 1876, in his last message to the nation spoke: "It is necessary for us, now, to educate ourselves and to act under the direction of the educated mind. This is my last will, which, while so to speak departing, I leave to my people."</p>
   <p>Politically Masaryk gave expression to his program in the sign of progress: "The progressive man in politics who strives for freedom and equality, shall be democratic, and will face aristocracy not only in politics and economies but in education, art and morality as well. The progressive man in politics shall not only build up the Bohemian character of the tongue but the independence of the entire culture, so that our whole character be Czech."</p>
   <p>Masaryk, with his critical realism, has not only deeply influenced our nation, but the life of all the peoples of Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
