<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-01-30">Jan. 30, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">News from the First Slet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-01-30">Jan. 30, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE FIRST SLET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the first Slet (Sokol Meet and Exhibition) of the Americka Obec Sokolska (American Union) is only in the state of preparation, nevertheless a dull contour of its outlines can be seen already. A sketch of the calisthenic exercises has been prepared, and the dates for the Slet are almost set, that is from August 26 to August 30 of this year.....</p>
   <p>The president of the Czechoslovak Republic, Thomas G. Masaryk, was invited to attend this Slet by the following letter:</p>
   <p>"Chicago, Illinois, January 17, 1921.</p>
   <p>"To the President of the Czechoslovak Republic, Thomas G. Masaryk, Prague, Hradcany.</p>
   <p>"Dear Mr. President! The Slet committee of the First Slet of the Americka Obec Skolska of Chicago is taking the liberty of inviting you, Mr. President, to the <pb facs="5418478_4_1121.jpg" n="2"/>first Slet which will be held in the month of August this year in Chicago.</p>
   <p>"The Czechoslovak Sokols and people of America gratefully recollect your last visit to Chicago, and they are ardently wishing to greet you at this opportunity as the head and the first citizen of our liberated country.</p>
   <p>"We, the Czechoslovak minority, are sending you our most devoted regards, and we hope to greet you under the unfurled banners of two free and sisterly republics.</p>
   <p>"The executive committee of the Americka Obec Sokolska; the Slet committee of the First Slet of the Americka Obec Sokolska."</p>
   <p>The presidents of the National Assembly, the Czecho-Slavonic Sokol Union of Prague, and a motherly unit of the Sokoldom, the Sokol Prazsky, were also invited.</p>
   <p>We know that our invitation will not be in vain, and that we shall be happy when <pb facs="5418478_4_1122.jpg" n="3"/>we shake hands with our guests. We know that representatives of Sokoldom and representatives of our free country will come, and if it is possible, even our Father Masaryk will be here. They shall come, light shall dawn, and the might of the Sokol shall manifest itself again!</p>
   <p>Karel M. Prchal,</p>
   <p>secretary of the Slet committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
