<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-02">June 2, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">[The Bohemian-American Press]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-02">June 2, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">[THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN PRESS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--The New York Hlas Lidu, a labor paper, has joined other units of the Bohemian-American press in righteously condemning the naughty tactics of Svornost, which has recruited scabs in the great teamsters' strike by promising rewards to traitors and stool-pigeons. In its report Hlas Lidu prints:</p>
   <p>"Mr. Geringer of Chicago is a good businessman; I will not say a cunning businessman. He knows how to extract money from those Bohemian compatriots of his. When rosaries were in fashion, he sold them; to-day rabid free-thinking is in vogue, and Mr. Geringer now promotes the ex-parson Iska, who when he became unendurable in the fold of the Catholic clergy, began in Bohemia with the 'Old Catholic Church' and subjected himself to being dragged from the altar in his red-and-white insignia by the rural police.</p>
   <p>In America Parson Iska has set out on a new road. On his arrival here his manager immediately informed him how the wind blows, and Mr. Iska is touring the country lecturing on 'Uplifting Morals' and on the 'Immorality of the Clergy'."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0206.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are going to tell briefly why we are publishing this so late. We did not want to quote Hlas Lidu on account of its attack on Dr. Iska, for we are loath to draw personalities into polemics even if the persons concerned deserve it for their prejudiced and partisan activities. Yesterday, however! Svornost, which is still smarting from the licking administered to it for its scab advertisement, attacked us because we did not, in our report on the celebration on the National Cemetery on Decoration Day, bestow praise on Iska and his twenty-five-dollar oration.</p>
   <p>We are answering Svornost merely by this clipping from Hlas Lidu and the statement that should Svornost or Dr. Iska wish us to do so, we will serve them with still more comments of the press about his liberalism, which has been properly estimated both here and in the old country. We have up to the present time ignored Dr. Iska; should we be compelled to take notice of him, it will give no pleasure either to him or to Svornost.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
