<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1899-08-18">August 18, 1899</date><title level="a">The Activity of Bohemian Benedictines in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1899-08-18">August 18, 1899</date><title level="a">THE ACTIVITY OF BOHEMIAN BENEDICTINES IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whoever will look closely into the activity of Bohemian Benedictines in Chicago will soon come to the conclusion that they are equally as shrewd speculators and clever businessmen as the honorable Jesuit Fathers. When the monks of the Order of St. Benedict settled themselves on Allport Avenue the first thing they did was to open a printing shop and to start to edit a newspaper. By this they gained in a smart way an easy advertisement for their humbug trade and a cheap means of organizing the business, because the preliminary expenses were paid by their flocks. Our newspaper was not sufficiently profitable. After the Journal Narod, (The Nation) they started to publish a new one, Katolik (The Catholic) and then Pritel Deti (The Children's Friend); the newest output of this ecclesiastical printing shop is the newspaper, Hospodarske Listy (Farming Journal).</p>
   <p>Lately the priests started to enter the field of the printing business, advertising in their news when and where they will have their holy masses or jubilees; or publishing that the Benedictine Fathers are printing and binding everything starting from nuns to the confession tickets. This hereditary zeal of the priesthood <pb facs="5418478_4_0250.jpg" n="2"/>is at present not much appreciated even by good Catholics. The newly edited liberal newspaper Jednota, published a bitter criticism to the Hospodarske Listy. Then Narod skillfully explained to the readers their object of publication, stating that the news is printed to augment the esteem of God and religion and not for any profitable reasons.</p>
   <p>Until now the Bohemian farmers have had only one economic journal. It was published by a non-Catholic Editor by the name of Geringer. It was rather an agricultural newspaper and the editor was just ready to start the farmers' newspaper when the Benedictines decided to take the Bohemian farmers fate into their own hands and not to admit non-Catholic influence to our countrymen, otherwise an eternal distinction would threaten this prosperous flock.</p>
   <p>The people have been saying that Geringer intended to start a new farmers' newspaper; it is a lie and the Narod's, Mr. Rosicki, knows as well that it was a lie, because before he started to be a manager for the Benedictines he persuaded Mr. Geringer to start the newspaper for Bohemian farmers, and <pb facs="5418478_4_0251.jpg" n="3"/>only after positive refusal did Mr. Rosicki turn his proposition to the Benedictines, promising them a gold mine in this new publication the Hospodarske Listy. Being aware of good profits the representatives of Jesus Christ decided to start the publication immediately. This illustrates clearly the aim and intention of the new publication the Bohemian Economic Journal. Money and more money were the only purpose of this new publication, and the dollars passing from the hands of Bohemian farmers to the Benedictine Fathers. This is clear and known to everybody. Mammon was the cause and not the holy faith. The honorable Fathers expended considerable capital in opening the printing shop; this capital should be withdrawn with respectable interest. They well know who helped them in this enterprise, and what kind of false and insidious ways they used to fulfill their commercial ideas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
