<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-01-31">Jan. 31, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">United Slavonic Sokols</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1336</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1336.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 3 (Croatian)</item>
     <item>II B 3 (Polish)</item>
     <item>II B 3 (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-01-31">Jan. 31, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED SLAVONIC SOKOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unification of all Slavonic sokol societies in Chicago became a reality with the organization of the Slovanska Sokolska Gymnasticka Unie (Slavonic Gymnastic Union). Societies belonging to the Narodni Sokolska Jednota (National Sokol Union), to the Fuegner-Tyrs Circuit, to the Delnicky-Americky Sokol (American Workingmen's Sokol), and to Slovak and Croatian sokols, have already joined the new organization. We do not know as yet how the Polish sokols will recieve this new movement. Besides the unification of all Slavonic sokols, the Slovanska Sokolska Gymnasticka Unie has as its purpose to increase the efficiency of the members in drills and to provide for the proper education of capable instructors. This will be accomplished by providing courses for instructors, lectures, special consultations, and occasional contests among the members of the participating societies. Any sokol society may apply for membership in the Union and each is entitled to three representatives in the central body. Dues for each society are two dollars per year. At the head of the Gymnastic Union will be a technical commission composed of nine experts, <pb facs="5418478_4_1337.jpg" n="2"/>and all nationalities participating will be represented. The organization of this important sokol institution will be completed at the next meeting of the Slovanska Sokolska Gymnasticka Unie, which will be held February 11, 1912. Friends of the sokol movement can certainly expect that the Gymnastic Union will rapidly produce fine results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
