<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-09">Apr. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Public Drill Exhibitions of the Sokols</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1200</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1200.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-09">Apr. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC DRILL EXHIBITIONS OF THE SOKOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The yearly exhibitions of our Sokol gymnastic societies belong to the list of seasonal events which we always record with great pleasure. They represent the work done during one full year. They cover a wide field of educational activities, physical and intellectual; they demonstrate how in our Sokol schools one great idea is fostered, an idea conceived and preached by the great teacher of nations, Jan Amos Komensky (Comenius): A sane mind in a healthy body. This idea was taken up as a beacon light by the founders of the Sokol societies, Jindrich Fuegner and Doctor Miroslav Tyrs.</p>
   <p>An apotheosis of Sokol activities was displayed in the appearance of the Plzensky Sokol (Pilsen district Sokol) in their hall at South Ashland Avenue. We have written repeatedly about the qualities of this group, about its technical accomplishments and its competent teachers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1201.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program was very colorful, and contained numbers of signal value. It did not fail to mightily impress the visitors who burst into reverberating applause at the appearance of every new squad of Sokols or Sokol girls. The latter appeared on the stage while the strains of Sousa's "Stars and Stripes" filled the air, to be followed by the "The Star-Spangled Banner."</p>
   <p>The performance of the drills was closed by a Sokol play. Mrs. Cejka Kazda was in charge of the girl's groups. Mr. Frank Paul directed the boys and both received tokens of gratitude and appreciation from their pupils. The attendance was large, the hall being filled to its capacity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
