<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-24">Sept. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to the Czech Schools of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0377</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0377.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-24">Sept. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO THE CZECH SCHOOLS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The school year has just begun, bringing in its wake a variety of problems and worries for the teachers and the school boards. One of these problems is securing peak enrollment of Czech children in the schools; another problem is how to keep them in school. Each school employs different methods for increasing and keeping up the attendance, but experience has taught us that the best results were obtained where a far-sighted teacher had arranged school theatricals or other public recitals. This method was found to be most fruitful in getting the interest of school children. Activities of this kind were most noticeable in those schools where a teacher who showed little interest in them was superseded by one who paid great attention to school theatricals. The school attendance in such a school increased almost immediately, the interest in school matters growing perceptibly in the neighborhood where such a school was located. It often happened, too, that a school which was more or less stagnant was thus revived and resumed its normal activity, nay, increased it as never before.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0378.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The theater also has a great educational value, and is especially important for our Bohemian schools in America. Our Bohemian-American children's opportunity to hear correct Bohemian speech is in the school. This is almost exclusively so. At home and on the street the speech which reaches their ears is either a Czech jargon corrupted by a distorted English terminology, or the so-called popular Bohemian speech which differs from the literary language a great deal. By taking part in carefully selected theatrical productions, the children are compelled to commit to memory whole passages consisting of beautiful literarily pure phrases that remain imprinted upon their minds. Also the well-managed school theaters cultivate the aesthetic feelings of the children, teaching them how to distinguish bad from good--thus ennobling the souls of the children in every way.</p>
   <p>The influence of the theater as an educative medium is tremendously important and, as such, must not be disregarded. Let us remember, for example, our Czechoslovak soldiers isolated in far-flung Siberia. It was the Czech theater and the Czech books which were able to keep up the morale of those men! Every <pb facs="5418478_4_0379.jpg" n="3"/>Czechoslovak regiment, and even every battallion had its own dramatic group. And so they gave theatrical plays at every opportunity, being fully aware of the great moral and educational force of the drama.</p>
   <p>It is most imperative that our Czech teachers and school boards recognize that great force in their own Czech schools. As it is, not a school year should go by without giving at least two public recitals in each school, recitals in which all of the children would take part. We know that many of our schools realize the importance of the theater, but do not know where to obtain the necessary books, dealing with theatrical plays. It also often happens that they have many more girls than boys, or that their total school enrollment is poor, or that they have poor stage facilities or none at all. Again, such schools may have ordered a play or two from the publishers, later realizing that for one reason or another they are unable to present the play. In all such and similar cases our Czech schools sould seek information and advice from the Cesko-Americka Matice Skolska (Bohemian-American Education Council.) The Council will be glad to give any information or advice free. It will help in the selection of plays, give <pb facs="5418478_4_0380.jpg" n="4"/>advice on how to use the school children in a theatrical production, and often too, it will procure the necessary dramatic literature needed by the schools. The Council will also gladly give any other information needed by either the teachers or the school boards.</p>
   <p>It is important to remember that the selection of plays should not be left till the last moment, but that plays should be selected at the beginning of the school year. The better the preparation, the better the results and the success of the play.</p>
   <p>Cesko-Americka Maticeskolska,</p>
   <p>Mrs. A. G. Vanek, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
