<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-03">Sept. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">In the Interest of Our Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0451</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0451.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-03">Sept. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE INTEREST OF OUR SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>These are the days in which our schools are open for enrollment, an event that should be noticed not only by some of our parents, but by all who care that their children learn the Czech language and preserve at least as much of their Czech feeling as is possible under present conditions. Here we refer not only to our Saturday and Sunday schools to which parents should be sending their children, but also to our gymnastic schools--our Sokol halls with their gymnasiums. In the former the child has an opportunity to learn the Czech language and the great history of his forebears, while the latter see to his physical development; both impart to the child the love of the country where his parents were born. It is to be hoped that the recent great Sokol festivities will act as an incentive to renewed activities in the Sokol halls, and that the Czechoslovaks will, more definitely than ever, come to the conclusion that the education which the Sokol can give to their children can be replaced by nothing else. Let us hope that our Sokol gymnasiums will be filled by our youth, that our parents will see their duty to send their <pb facs="5418478_4_0452.jpg" n="2"/>children there. If this hope should be fulfilled, and the patriotic enthusiasm of recent days should bear no other fruit than that, we may feel fully satisfied.</p>
   <p>The Czech Free Thought schools have been in no particularly favorable financial position in the past school year. Since Czech classes were eliminated from our public schools, the expenses of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Federation of Czech Free Thought Schools) have been much greater than before while its income has not grown correspondingly. Particularly during the war, the schools were badly neglected. In addition to that, the number of their pupils has shown a most gratifying growth, a circumstance that would have been most pleasing, if it had not brought with it new worries of a material character. It was no pleasure to try to find the necessary rooms, the needed teachers. It was a constant worry to find a way to pay salaries and defray other growing expenses connected with the conducting of the classes. It is no secret that at the end of the past year, conditions were so bad that the treasurer found it necessary to declare openly he did not know where to <pb facs="5418478_4_0453.jpg" n="3"/>find the money for the teachers' salaries and other necessary expenses, and the very serious statement was made that only under much more favorable circumstances than those prevailing at that time would it be possible to maintain our schools in their present number, scope, and status. Countrymen who are sincerely interested in our schools found these statements most surprising and disquieting, but the effect of these statements was beneficial. A greater degree of interest in the preservation of Czech schools was stirred up, and the last Posviceni (fall festival in Bohemia, akin to our Thanksgiving Day) has proved that fact by a very large participation, particularly if we consider that it was held at a rather unfavorable period when the whole attention of the Czechoslovak people in Chicago was turned to the great days of the Sokol Slet (mass convention). However, the outcome of the Posviceni was quite satisfactory, and just as gratifying is the fact that a renewed interest in our schools is being evidenced in our associations. This justifies the hope that the greatest danger has been averted and that the future progress of our schools will not be hampered. Of course, all depends upon our associations and individual contributors.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0454.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is up to them not to weaken in their interest and see to it that our schools can continue to function.</p>
   <p>The Sdruzeni has recently issued a proclamation which declares that it has become necessary to raise the tuition to $1.50 a year in schools where from three to four classes are held every week; to $2.50 in schools with five classes; and to $3.00 in Saturday and Sunday schools with seven classes a week. The increase is just a trifling amount which should prevent no one from sending children to a Czech school, not even those who pay $3.00 a year for every child. That is not a high price for giving the children a good knowledge of their mother tongue. The increase is a matter of necessity, and has been put in force with the approval of all represented bodies. It will make for a larger regular income of the Sdruzeni, and, considering the economics that have been introduced, the hope is justified that our schools will be spared all serious difficulties in the future.</p>
   <p>The future success of our schools depends on the support they receive and <pb facs="5418478_4_0455.jpg" n="5"/>on the amount of understanding with which they are taken advantage of by our parents. To send the children to a Czech school is a duty that nobody should shirk--in the interest of the children themselves. The parents certainly want their children to know how to speak the Czech language, and the instances are by no means rare where such knowledge is necessary in order that the children understand their parents and vice versa. As long as the child is young it prattles Czech; as soon, however, as it starts going to a public school it frequently begins forgetting what it has learned at home, and it is not long before the parents discover that it cannot or does not want to talk Czech. This, of course, is not surprising. Our children come into contact with children who do not talk anything but English, they are using that language in school and on the street, and it is therefore quite natural that they soon forget Czech if the parents neglect to provide them an opportunity to continue using the language and to learn it well. A young child learns rapidly, but it just as rapidly forgets what it has learned if it discontinues making use of it. The knowledge of the Czech language is not only a matter of national duty; it is also an accomplishment <pb facs="5418478_4_0456.jpg" n="6"/>that proves of value in practical daily life. The more languages a person knows, the wider is his horizon, the richer his life, and the greater the fund of knowledge he is able to use, particularly in his business. To give their children a thorough knowledge of the Czech language is our parents' first natural obligation toward their children, and with such opportunities as our Free Thought schools offer, there is no excuse for neglecting that obligation. Of no less importance, is their obligation to send the children to Sokol gymnasiums. The recent public performance of the Sokol youth on the occasion of the Sokol Slet must have convinced our parents of the advantages of Sokol training such as is given by all our Sokol units.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
