<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-10-02">Oct. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Cornerstone Laying Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-10-02">Oct. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CORNERSTONE LAYING CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, the gymnastic society, Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, held a significant ceremonial laying of the cornerstone of its gymnasium building located on Lawndale Avenue, between 26th and 27th Streets. Despite the fact that the weather was unfavorable, a large number of societies and friends participated. A picturesque parade of our robust men and women sokols started from the Society's headquarters on Trumbull Avenue, and marching to the music of a band, made its way to the building site on Lawndale Avenue. Upon the arrival of the parade at the site, the festive program was begun with the singing of the Czech National Hymn, "Kde domov muj" (Where is my home). The president of the society, Brother Frank Vlach, then welcomed all those present with an ardent and heartfelt speech. He discussed in detail the origin of the Havlicek-Tyrs gymnastic society, and the idea of building the society's own quarters .....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1349.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The speaker of the occasion was Mr. Stan. E. Vraz, who addressed the gathering in very hearty words .....</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. Kosar.</p>
   <p>Brother Rudolph Cermak, the secretary of the society, then read a report on the origin and organization of the Society. Sokol Havlicek was organized on August 20, 1904, and he says that in the very beginning the Society realized that it would be forced to seek a larger and more suitable gymnasium if it were to satisfactorily fulfill its mission. The idea of building its own gymnasium was thought of in 1907, and for that purpose four lots were bought for $2,175. The Society paid part cash on this amount, and for the balance issued non-interest bearing notes of five dollar denominations, which were taken up by the members and the lots paid for in full. A building committee, which was instructed to work toward the finding of means for the early realization of the building, was elected. A profit <pb facs="5418478_4_1350.jpg" n="3"/>of $1,067.34 was gained from the exhibition of 1909, and later another $500 was set aside as a reserve fund for the building. The committee collected contributions and gifts, and organized its own Building and Loan Association where the brothers deposited their savings. The plans for the building were drawn by the architects, Lud. Novy and Son, and were definitely accepted in a meeting held in April 1911. According to the estimate, the building will cost $34,000 and the lots $4,000, making a total of $38,000.....</p>
   <p>After the completion of the ceremonies, many of the participants marched to the Pilsen Brewery Park, where an informal entertainment took place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
