<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-25">Apr. 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Public Gymnastic Exhibition of the Plzensky Sokol</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-25">Apr. 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION OF THE PLZENSKY SOKOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Plzen (Sokol Pilsen Gymnastic Association), one of our oldest and most deserving Sokol units in Chicago, held the annual gymnastic exhibition of its juvenile, junior, and senior classes yesterday evening in the Pilsen Sokol Hall. As usual,the performance of this popular sokol unit met with great success. These annual public exhibitions of our sokol units have their own deep meaning, an undisputable fact that is not necessary to emphasize. These public exhibitions acquaint the people with the beneficent effect which the systematic drilling has upon the physical development of a man, upon his morals, and upon his sense for voluntary discipline and elegance. Our Sokolovny (sokol halls) are and shall always be our pride. It is in these sokol halls where, under the guidance of capable instructors, the motto of the immortal teacher of nations, Jan Amos Komensky (Johannes Amos Comenius): "A sound mind in a sound body," is practiced. A properly guided calisthenic school is a part of modern education. If a school offers education and intelligence, and prepares its pupils for practical life, then a sokol hall is an institution of no less <pb facs="5418478_4_1105.jpg" n="2"/>importance because it is also a school where a child learns to comprehend the importance of physical training--where a child learns to depend upon his own strength and energy, and where foundations are laid for the child's physical existence. All educators of progressive view agree that in sokol halls, and especially at the time when calisthenic drills are rehearsed, physiology goes hand in hand with psychology, and that the pupils acquire beautiful qualities which can be acquired nowhere else.</p>
   <p>With such results of educational work, our sokol units from time to time step before our people, and such a picture of discipline, sprightliness, and elegance was yesterday's exhibition in Pilsen Sokol Hall. It was truly a thrilling sight to watch the great sokol family--the little ones and the experienced adults who performed so excellently, deserving their reward of applause.</p>
   <p>The program gave proof of conscientious rehearsals. Twenty girls of the first class beautifully performed a calisthenic play called "Little Bo Peep"; thirty-seven boys gave an exhibition of calisthenic drills; thirty-six girls of the <pb facs="5418478_4_1106.jpg" n="3"/>second class reaped a storm of applause for their drill with wands.....The best number on the program was an exhibition given by a representative team of the Sokol Pilsen, consisting of V. Stransky, J. Vesely, J. Kristufek, B. Mikuta, O. Kvidera, and B. Lebduska. This is the same team that won the national championship at the recent contests. The boys appeared in white trousers and shirts, and their appearance immediately aroused a spontaneous storm of applause. The boys gave an exhibition on the horizontal bar, the rings, and the parallel bars; the exercises were of such nature that they bordered on acrobatics. The audience was actually electrified by their boldness and elegance, and every one of the boys reaped his share of applause. The last number on the program was a basketball game in which the juniors also participated.</p>
   <p>The drills for girls and women were worked out by Sister Helen Klaus-Mikuta; the drills for boys and men were prepared by Frank Paul, well-known Sokol instructor and champion. Both of them are very competent instructors.</p>
   <p>The exhibition held yesterday was practically the last appearance of Mr. F. Paul, <pb facs="5418478_4_1107.jpg" n="4"/>because very soon he will depart for sunny California where he intends to reside. His departure will be sincerely regretted because Mr. Paul as a sokol and instructor became one of the most distinguished factors in our sokol circles. The attendance at the exhibition was great; the hall was filled to capacity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
