<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-05-05">May 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Masonic Club Held a Social Dance for the Benefit of the Bohemian School Vojta Naprstek.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_0703</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_0703.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-05-05">May 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN MASONIC CLUB HELD A SOCIAL DANCE FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE BOHEMIAN SCHOOL VOJTA NAPRSTEK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1, col. 1 - A luxurious garden full of exotic plants, beautiful roses and many other precious flowers yesterday evening changed the entire atmosphere of the pavilion in the Pilsen Brewing Park on West 26th Street and South Albany Avenue. The Club Dobrovsky, composed of masons belonging to numerous Masonic Lodges, arranged a social dance for the benefit of the Bohemian School Vojta Naprstek.</p>
   <p>Many thanks for the nobly arranged affair and especially for the decorated place. A select group of prominent Bohemians attended this social affair. Let us without hesitation give praise to the Dobrovsky Club as an outstanding one among all social clubs.</p>
   <p>Last year's affair was arranged for the benefit of the Bohemian Orphanage Asylum and brought in many hundreds of dollars. Last night's affair was held for the benefit of the Bohemian School Vojta Naprstek. Luxurious gowns were worn by the women, and full dress clothes by the men; it was indeed a formal affair with banquet, to be remembered for a long time by those who attended. The view of the wonderfully decorated pavilion will also linger in the <pb facs="5418478_4_0704.jpg" n="2"/>memories of the participants. Last night's affair brought in a handsome amount close to a thousand dollars for the benefit of the Bohemian School. It was a pleasure to watch the dancing. The Bohemian Masons demonstrated anew their generosity; the Bohemians certainly are proud of the many Bohemians belonging to the Masonic Order.</p>
   <p>Special mention is to be made, crediting Mr. Joseph A. Mendel for his splendid decoration of the pavilion; many thanks to him for donating the plants, flowers, and his services. He too belongs to one of the Masonic Lodges and is a member of Dobrovsky Club. The orchestra was directed by Mr. Brousek.</p>
   <p>The entertainment committee also is to be complimented; it consists of Charles Koren, chairman; Richard Dusil, Joseph Mandl, Joseph Holpuch, J. M. Kralovec, James Roubal, Joseph A. Mendel, Ludwig Zavadil, Joseph Polak and Adolph Rys.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
