<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-02">Oct. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">In Unity Is Force</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_4_1245</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1245.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-02">Oct. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IN UNITY IS FORCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The idea of unifying two of the most potent Sokol units of Chicago was considered a distant dream by many of those who are best acquainted with prevailing conditions. Yesterday this unification came much closer to realization that had been thought possible. The Chicago Bohemian public, who regard our Sokols as objects of national pride, will give this possibility a warm welcome and wish that it may soon become a reality. It would give Chicago the most powerful Sokol unit, and this unit would become a Sokol fortress in the western outskirts of the city from where it would spread its useful influence, strengthen the good name of Sokol education, and help in preserving the true Bohemian ways of life in this great metropolis.</p>
   <p>One of the units in question is the Sokol Slovanska Lipa (Slavic Linden Tree), a unit of more than two hundred fine members, all of whom are known national workers, diligent and always ready to help where help is required. But the field activity which they commanded in the past is now restricted. Perhaps <pb facs="5418478_4_1246.jpg" n="2"/>every Bohemian in Chicago knows that the Sokol Slovanska Lipa is the oldest one in Chicago. Its home on De Koven Street--the center that played such an important role in the preservation of Bohemian social life in Chicago at the beginning of the period of our immigration into this city--lost its importance years ago when Chicago developed with such irresistible growth and created new districts in which the Bohemians have been the leading national element. The majority of its members have for many years sought the opportunity of resuming their past activities and assuring themselves of the prominent place in our national life to which they are entitled.</p>
   <p>Because most of the members of the Sokol Slovanska Lipa now live in the Thirty-fourth Ward--especially those parts of the Ward known as Novy Tabor (New Tabor) and Ceska Kalifornie (Bohemian California)--it is only natural that when it came to the point of selecting a site for a new home they turned their eyes toward the western section of the city, specifically to the two districts mentioned. The only abstacle, if it may be called so, was the fact that another Sokol unit has had its field of activity in that district, <pb facs="5418478_4_1247.jpg" n="3"/>a unit of admitted strength and agility--the Sokol Tabor. This unit has found that its home, new though it may be, will soon become inadequate to properly serve the ever-growing membership. Consequently, about two years ago it was decided to make a move which now could be of utmost importance to both Sokol Tabor and Sokol Slovanska Lipa.</p>
   <p>As the first step in this move, the Sokol Tabor proposed to Sokol Slovanska Lipa that they build a common home--a common hall that would be properly representative and an object of pride for all of Bohemian-Chicago.....</p>
   <p>A meeting of the representatives of these units was held yesterday. They agreed to call a general assembly of the members of both Sokols in which a committee of nine would be elected to work out definite, detailed plans for submission to the two organizations in the near future. This decision has been accepted with a great deal of satisfaction because both units are in favor of a merger.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_4_1248.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The merger would create a body of close to four hundred members with more than $50,000 in its treasury, and eager to serve not only in New Tabor and Bohemian-California but anywhere in Chicago where their co-operation would be required for the general interest of our national and Sokol life.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
