<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-04-02">April 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">As it Was Formerly.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Dr. H. H. Maurer Speaks about German-American Past. an Interesting Lecture.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0414</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0414.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-04-02">April 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AS IT WAS FORMERLY.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Dr. H. H. Maurer Speaks About German-American Past. An Interesting Lecture.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Seriousness and cheerfulness of the German-American past" could the lecture, which lasted almost two hours, be called, which Dr. H. H. Maurer held yesterday evening, before an interested audience, in the large hall of the Lincoln Club. While Dr. Maurer, in his yesterday's speech, limited it to the period of German-American history, up till the arrival of "the 48-er's", he will lecture of later events up to the present time in his second speech on April 15th.</p>
   <p>The German immigration in America, he stated, was never steady and even, but occurred so to say in waves, which were caused by drastic expressions of Imperials, across the ocean. The first such wave was caused through the invasion of the Palatinate by Louis the Fourteenth, which brought it about that 250,000 German immigrants came to the North American continent. Further mass immigrations from German domains were due to the Napoleonic wars, the spy system of Metterinch, and the events of the year 1848.</p>
   <p>Industry, honesty, and cleanliness were characteristics which the Germans brought <pb facs="5418474_11_0415.jpg" n="2"/>with them and introduced it in their new home. They combined with is a love for cheerfulness, sociability, and corporeal pleasures, which were, according to the views of their neighbors, in strong contrast with the puritan ways of England. An earlier immigrant from Germany was surprised at this contrast, and induced him to make the remark: "The Americans know no pleasures. What are they doing, when they meet? They sit around a fire and spit!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
