<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-07-08">July 8, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Old Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1364</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1364.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-07-08">July 8, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">OLD CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Heinrich von Oppen, the popular German chorus director drew from his horn of abundant memories in a chat with the representative of the Abendpost on the occasion of the celebration of his golden wedding anniversary. Mr. Von Oppen himself is a bit of German history of Chicago.</p>
   <p>In the spring of 1866, at the age of 17, young Von Oppen emigrated from Germany to America. It took him 15 days to cross the ocean from Hamburg to New York on the express steamer Germania. He came to Chicago and entered his uncle's cigar business which was located in the Hamilton Hotel at Clark and N. Water Sts. He had no difficulties in making himself understood, because the customers were mostly German. Two years later his uncle died and the young man was unemployed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1365.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He turned to music which he already had practiced in his early youth in his home town in Germany. It was there that as a boy 12 years old he played the music of the singing society, Polyhymnia, of which Cantor Hopfuer was the conductor. Cantor Hopfuer was the school teacher and the chamber musician,W. Eisenbrandt, the music teacher of young Von Oppen.</p>
   <p>At Mother Thicknan's who was the proprietress of the best German theater of Chicago, the National Theater, located on Clybourn Ave., he joined as musical director. He played every Sunday and the attendance was always satisfactory. Besides this, the young musician secured many pupils for piano and violin lessons.</p>
   <p>Time passed, the German-Franco war of 1870-71 came, the victory over the arch enemy, and the peace celebration. This was celebrated at Wright's grove, a picnic woods, which extended from Fullerton Avenue, to Diversey Parkway, west from Clark Street. The entire German population, almost <pb facs="5418474_11_1366.jpg" n="3"/>half of Chicago, were present. Emperor William of Germany, had sent the entire orchestra consisting of 20 men, of which Von Oppen was a member, complete uniforms of the German crack regiment of the guards which were worn by the musicians at the peace celebration. They caused a great sensation here.</p>
   <p>One year later, in 1872, the society Fidelia was founded by twenty young Germans. In the back room of George Blein's Tavern, at 58 Clybourne Ave., the Fidelia was born, there were held the first rehearsals and concerts and masquerades were given; later they were given at the North Side Turner Hall, and three decades later in the Lincoln Turner Hall.</p>
   <p>A mirthful German life prevailed in those times. One of the many well known German family places was that of Kronick's at Siegel and Sedgwick Streets. Here, on Sunday afternoons Wilhelm Vocke, Lorenz Brentano, the old Consul Claussenius, Herman Raster, Casper Hesing, Arthur Holinger, Dr. Storch, Dr. Bango, the prominent Swiss physician and occasionally <pb facs="5418474_11_1367.jpg" n="4"/>Governor Altgeld, could be seen.</p>
   <p>Hans Balatka was the director of the German Men's chorus of those times; Von Oppen sang under his direction and appeared as soloist at many concerts. Another excellent musical conductor was the master of the chorus of the singing society, Concordia, Mr. Grofsskurt. Besides being a director of the Fidelia, Mr. Von Oppen directed the Swiss Men's Chorus for over 40 years, from 1880 to 1920; the Harmony Singing Society of Lake View, for 35 years and the Harugari Union of Musicians, for 35 years. Mr. Von Oppen is the only chorus master in the world who directed a singing society for 50 consecutive years. Mr. Von Oppen states that his success lies in his efforts for the cultivation of German national songs in the singing societies which he founded. Von Oppen remembers Florenz Ziegfeld, Dr. Fessel, the father-in-law of Hans Balatka, Dr. Thuin of Burlington, Wis., who was a pupil of Franz Liszt, and an excellent physician as well as musician and all of whom played prominent roles in the German musical life of Chicago. <pb facs="5418474_11_1368.jpg" n="5"/>Of the many conductors Von Oppen came in contact with, he remembers Gustav Ehrhorn, who was one of his principal co-fighters in behalf of German national songs and their cultivation in all the German singing societies. Now the celebrant looks back with a clear mind and with a joyous heart upon his past activities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
