<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-23">Aug. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Accomplishment.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0980</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0980.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-23">Aug. 23, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT ACCOMPLISHMENT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4 - Mr. Karl Buenz, German Consul in Chicago, sends us the following information: The German Chancellor has empowered Dr. Paul Richard Welker, 2459 Prairie Ave., to give physical examinations to German citizens to ascertain their fitness for military service, and is authorized to issue official certificates. This affects all the Germans who are subject to military service even if they have lived in the United States for a long time.</p>
   <p>At last the German government shows some consideration for its faithful citizens, and does not send them on a long journey to New York or San Francisco when they wish to be examined for military eligibility. This <pb facs="5418474_11_0981.jpg" n="2"/>new regulation is due to constant representations by the Staats-Zeitung, which were supported by the German Consul, Mr. Buenz, and emphasized by the attraction exercised by our World's Fair. The latter undoubtedly opened the eyes of the European gentlemen and made them realize how great the Chicago German population is. Many German governmental officials crossed the ocean to see the Columbian Exposition and here gained the conviction that to expect the German citizens to sacrifice time and money for a long trip to New York was asking too much.</p>
   <p>Although the arrangement has been a protracted affair, - its final realization is nevertheless welcome. In the name of the faithful patriotic Germans of Chicago and of the Northwest, we express our thanks to the Emperor, the Chancellor, the Consul and to all those who took a hand in the matter.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
