<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1885-08-14">August 14, 1885</date><title level="a">Germans and Their Countrymen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1021</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1021.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1885-08-14">August 14, 1885</date><title level="a">GERMANS AND THEIR COUNTRYMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent festival at Bingen, arranged by the Sharp Shooters Society of New York, and the participation of several of the German-American sections at the great Turn festival in Dresden manifested a German and German-American fellowship, - which is at least something new. It would be a mistake to speak of a warm German interest toward the German-American brothers.</p>
   <p>It is a fact that the Germans in Germany know very little of the life and work of the American Germans, neither do they know how much they cling to and preserve the German language, customs and education. No, they are not interested in this... The German press brings only scant reports from America, less than from Jonkin, Kambodscha, Kimcrum and Zanzibar...The more or less official newspapers and the "voluntary government newspapers" show such an indifference towards America that it would almost be regarded as an ill-willed hatred. The belief is prevalent that Germans coming to this country almost immediately surrender themselves to the Yankees, and thus are considered a loss to the Fatherland. This accounts for the feeling against America... People considering residence in other countries, are advised to migrate either to Brazil, Argentine or other half barbaric countries, notwithstanding the fact <pb facs="5418474_11_1022.jpg" n="2"/>that there they are lost to Germany much sooner than when coming to the United States.</p>
   <p>Mr. Spielberg, the parliament member, said frankly, that "German immigration should be directed to those countries from which there is no danger of agricultural or industrial competition for Germany within a conceivable time". Not the welfare of the emigrants, but that of the people remaining at home, is considered important. The immigrant should not choose a domicile for himself where his work would be best appreciated, but where his work would not enter into competition with Germany. Is there any worse selfishness and inhumanity? In spite of this pernicious effort to send the immigrant to his ruin he still favors, as records show, this as his future home. For out of every one hundred German emigrants ninety-five come to America.</p>
   <p>It is true that the German in America eventually become less interested in their native country. Here they become free citizens of a free country, who nevertheless preserve their love for the land of their birth, although active and creative members under a different government. They are not lost to the German <pb facs="5418474_11_1023.jpg" n="3"/>people, for thousands of German schools, newspapers and societies are keeping the German language and customs alive....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
