<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-18">Mar. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Nettelhorst's Legacy to the Germans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-18">Mar. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">NETTELHORST'S LEGACY TO THE GERMANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nettelhorst is sinking into an early grave like an old Germanic hero. For this reason he - the great man - is not lost to the Germans of Chicago. Whatever he has achieved for them in this city through his persistent efforts, must by all means be maintained and preserved for his sake.</p>
   <p>He was a victorious champion of German instruction in our public schools, including the lower grades, and an eminent fellow combatant for the rights of private and parochial schools. As a member of the school board and as its president he was an invincible bulwark against Know-Nothingism.</p>
   <p>When some years ago certain nativistic elements in our high schools made a general attack upon immigration, it was Nettelhorst, as a member of the school board,who put them in their place through his strong and official protest... His real heroism, however, consisted in his untiring defense of German language and art, as well as of the German system of gymnastics.</p>
   <p>Thus he fought as a member of the School Board, and on the speaker's platform. His high position as a member of the School Board did not prevent him from taking part in the vehement battle,which the Germans of Chicago and Illinois <pb facs="5418474_11_1752.jpg" n="2"/>fought in the fall of 1890 ,to protect their private and parochial schools against the Edward Law. He did the same thing in the fall of 1892 as a private citizen.</p>
   <p>Ever since Know-nothingism received such fearful blows, because of its malicious attacks upon German private and parochial schools, and since the defeat of its beloved Edward law, it is trying to take revenge by forcing German out of all the public schools in Chicago, starting with the lower grades.</p>
   <p>Although Nettelhorst already carried the germ of death in his bosom, he, nevertheless, participated heartily in the recent battle of the German-Americans against the latest attack of the Know-Nothings. He was not privileged to see the result of the present battle.</p>
   <p>But the brave Germans, men and women, who now defend the German ideals in our schools, act entirely according to his wishes. There is a probability that they will triumphantly repulse the threatening danger for German instruction in our public schools, as Nettelhorst did formerly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
