<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-17">Sept. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">One Out of Four Is German</title><title level="a" type="sub">Better American Soldiers Are Not to Be Found (From the German Democracy Bulletin)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-17">Sept. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OUT OF FOUR IS GERMAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Better American Soldiers Are Not To Be Found (From the German Democracy Bulletin)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One out of four names is German! So writes the well-known war correspondent of the New York Times, Chas. H. Grasty, on September 5, after visiting the victorious American troops. One out of four, twenty-five per cent of America's fighting power! That is the reply to the challenge of the German militarists--"America is only a bluff."</p>
   <p>It is not only the number [of German-Americans in the American army which makes this correspondent sing the enthusiastic praises of the efficiency and loyalty of American soldiers of German extraction....."We have no better soldiers. In all my trips up and down the front, I have not found any [troops] who were imbued with a higher degree of American spirit than these splendid boys from the Middle West, almost all of whom have German names."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I came across a division," writes Grasty, "in which the German element was heavily represented. I should not like to call these young men 'German-Americans'; why, I could not even find a trace of Kultur in them. If they had ever been inoculated with it, they certainly have gotten rid of it, and that is the marvelous and great thing about our political and social system. We welcome the newcomer to our midst and make him one of us....My observations have convinced me that we can trust the descendants of the relatively new elements in our national body as completely as those whose forebears lived during the period of the War of Independence. I have been told about a company in another division in which German was the conversational language of the soldiers. And not one case of betrayal or treason, not a one!...Generally speaking, every fourth name in our army sounds German. We have no better soldiers. They are all sure of their Americanism. Europeans are often amazed at this American unity. They really expected internal disorders in America, since ten per cent of our people are of Teutonic origin. These Europeans did not take into account the fact that the elements which the Old World had given <pb facs="5418474_11_0135.jpg" n="3"/>us, could be, and have been, completely Americanized. It is true that America had to dispose of a few traitors and that these cases, which had special features, caused great excitement. But here [in France] one has come to the conclusion that the attitude of Americans of German descent, taken as a whole, is one of the most marvelous and satisfactory phenomena of the war."</p>
   <p>The praise which is paid the American of German origin in France is deserved. America, President Wilson, and the leaders of the nation have joined in this praise repeatedly. This recognition, earned on the battlefield, must not be begrudged or taken away by the "few", who, as Attorney General Becker of New York, conducting the investigation of German propaganda, recently declared, "are lying low," meaning that they are just waiting for the moment to drop the mask. Small in number, but not entirely without influence, they are attempting to retard this process of Americanization. We know them, we have often experienced their resistance in our work. In vain! This amalgamation of various elements of our people cannot be stopped; it is, as Grasty says, one of the most amazing phenomena of the war. May it continue!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
