<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-01-14">January 14, 1904</date><title level="a">Christoph Hotz Died.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1538</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1538.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-01-14">January 14, 1904</date><title level="a">CHRISTOPH HOTZ DIED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the age of 62 years Mr. Christoph Hotz died yesterday. His death makes a big gap in the circles of the public spirited, energetic Germans of the city. Being a trained technician he took, in former years, a vital interest in the private Manual Trade School which was erected on Michigan Avenue near 12th Street and which flourished successfully, but that now belongs to the University of Chicago. He was a member of the administrative board of the University before its reorganization by Dr. Harper. In the early Eighties he was a member of the Municipal Board of Education, and under Mayor Swift he was one of the ablest members of the Civil Service Board.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hotz was also a member of the administrative board of the Lewis Institute. Born in Wertheim, Baden, he received an excellent education which enabled him at the age of 17 years to enter the Technical College at Carlstruhe. After graduation he went to Switzerland to gain practical knowledge of machine construction. In Wintherthur he entered the machine factory of Gebrueder <pb facs="5418474_11_1539.jpg" n="2"/>Sulzer; several improvements in the construction of their steam engines was his work. The wanderlust brought him in 1866 to America, and in the same year to Chicago. After being for a short time a silent partner of P. W. Gates and Company, he opened his own factory in the Yates Building, corner Randolph and Canal Streets.</p>
   <p>In 1868 he married Catharine Schuettler, the daughter of the coach manufacturer, Peter Schuettler. He entered the factory of his father-in-law as technical adviser and later became his business partner. Later he also participated in bigger business enterprises and was until his death a director of the Illinois Trust and Savings Bank. His wife died four years ago. He leaves a daughter, Mrs. Wm. H. Ream and a son, Robert S. Hotz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
