<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-12-12">Dec. 12, 1928</date><title level="a">William Boeppler Conductor and Musician Is Dead</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1248</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1248.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-12-12">Dec. 12, 1928</date><title level="a">WILLIAM BOEPPLER CONDUCTOR AND MUSICIAN IS DEAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>William Boeppler, the promoter of German music and songs in Chicago, died last night after seven weeks of serious illness. The Germans of Chicago have suffered a great loss by his death. For William Boeppler's work for the preservation of German songs and music, as well as of the German language, must occupy a place of honor in the history of the local Germans.</p>
   <p>Chicago, Milwaukee, and all of America not only lose an eminent conductor, a champion of the beauty of German church music, but Germany does also. An authority of Bach, he was probably the first and only one to reveal to the Americans the forcefulness and the nobleness of this great musician.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1249.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Boeppler was 64 years old. The realization of a lifelong wish was granted to him this year. Together with his faithful wife, he undertook a long journey, which took him to the places of his youthful dreams, to Palestine, the Holy Land, to Greece, Norway, Germany, Austria, and to Switzerland. He returned a sick man. A severe kidney and bladder trouble, confined him for seven weeks until death released him yesterday evening.</p>
   <p>Boeppler's Activities</p>
   <p>His death will be deeply mourned because everybody knew William Boeppler, the conductor of the singing society, of the Bach Chorus, <pb facs="5418474_11_1250.jpg" n="3"/>of the Bethany Church Choir, and of the Lake View Ladies Chorus; the man who gave to the music-loving public many wonderful concerts. Last year, together with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, he gave a brilliant performance of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony in Orchestra Hall, also Haydn's, Bruch's oratorios, and the cantatas and psalms of Bach. Chicago not only loses a great musician, but also a great man. William Boeppler was kindness personified. Many can testify to it. Therefore, when william Boeppler is laid to rest those who will escort his body will be comforted by the remembrance, of the pleasure they had been able to give him. They honored his fortieth anniversary as conductor with a big concert in the Medinah Temple, which turned out to be an imposing celebration.</p>
   <p>Boeppler's Career</p>
   <p>William Boeppler came to America in 1894 from Krefeld, Germany, and <pb facs="5418474_11_1251.jpg" n="4"/>settled first in Milwaukee. His teachers in Germany were musicians of international repute, as Reinecke, Fiedler, and Lange in Leipzig, Ewziam in Krewznach, and Arnold Mendelsohn in Borm. For seven years prior to his departure for America, he was conductor of a large church choir in Krefeld. In Milwaukee he soon founded an a cappella choir which could now celebrate its twenty-fifth anniversary.</p>
   <p>In 1902 he followed the call of the Germania Club and moved to Chicago. Here he became the founder of the Chicago Singing Society. He also conducted the Turner Men's Chorus, and the Boeppler Symphony Orchestra. In 1907, he again took over the leadership of the Milwaukee A Cappella Choir, and a few years later became the director of the Wisconsin Musical Conservatory, however, without <pb facs="5418474_11_1252.jpg" n="5"/>relinquishing his position as leader of the Chicago Singing Society. Everywhere, William Boeppler achieved great success. The singing presentations by the Societies which were given under his direction, are especially famous.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
