<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-05-09">May 9, 1896</date><title level="a">Let's Have Proofs! (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-05-09">May 9, 1896</date><title level="a">Let's Have Proofs! (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By a Democratic newspaper, the "Chicago Chronicle", Governor Altgeld is suspected of very doubtful financial manipulations. Says this paper:</p>
   <p>"There are things of which the Governor knows the real facts. He does not possess this knowledge alone, but instead, he can talk with authority that cannot be questioned. The Treasurer of Illinois, who was elected together with Governor Altgeld, was an embezzler. He died while in office. During Ramsay's lifetime not so much administrative interest seemd to have existed as to look up the conditions of the Treasury. There were some reasons why the executive did not want to watch so closely how Ramsay, who later proved himself a thief, handled the money entrusted. But when the news came of Ramsay's death the Governor opened the safe in the presence of bondsmen who had signed the offical bond of the deceased Treasurer. The State did not lose anything, because the Chicago banks as bondsmen, replaced the missing amount immediately.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1671.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Pherhaps this is the reason that Governor Altgeld, who otherwise is so quick with his statements, did not even mention this most important and most exciting occurrence of his administration - Ramsay's thefts - when delivering his message of the year 1895. Did the robbed safe, perhaps, contain a bond of John Peter Altgeld? In one of his talkative spells the Governor could explain the entire, extraordinary affair."</p>
   <p>Here is not directly asserted but very clearly made understood, that the Governor had borrowed money of the Treasurer which belonged to the state, and that this unlawful I can was not refunded when Cashier Ramsay died. In the further progress of this essay there is indicated similar "transactions" which the Governor is said to have made with other State officals and certain rural banks. These are very severe accusations which an "honorable paper like the Chronicle should not start without the possession of convincing proffs. Not even his adversaries dared to doubt the honesty of Altgeld. If, therefore, the Governor is accused of one of the most severe <pb facs="5418474_11_1672.jpg" n="3"/>crimes that an official in his position could ever commit, it is absolutely unfair to clothe this accusation with the form of intimations or insinuations. The man to whom the Chronicle owes its knowledge of the indicated misuse of office and whose name is probably JohnRR. Walsh, cannot put up a claim for absolute credibility. But if he were personified truthfulness and trustworthiness, the Chronicle still must bring proofs for his hidden accusations. With a campaign of defamation and dirt the issue of sound money cannot gain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
