<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-20">Mar. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. F. H. Bernard Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1749</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1749.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-20">Mar. 20, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">DR. F. H. BERNARD DIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans of Chicago, especially the cultured and educated classes, suffered a severe loss through the death of Dr. F. H. Bernard, yesterday at 5 o'clock.</p>
   <p>Although Dr. Bernard had not lived in Chicago very long, he, nevertheless, had gained a splendid reputation as a man of great knowledge. He was famous as a writer and as a brilliant speaker on natural sciences. He likewise won a large number of friends through his sincere, kindly, and noble character.</p>
   <p>Dr. Bernard was born on May 20, 1833, near Treptow, Germany. After he had received a thorough college education, he went to Berlin, where he studied at the university. His special subjects were mathematics and natural sciences. After finishing his studies he received a position at the Berlin observatory. He made a special study of spectroscopy and was considered an authority in this field.</p>
   <p>Dr. Bernard came to America in 1882. For some time he was employed as a chemist by the Pennsylvania Salt Works at Natrona, Pa. Having been meat <pb facs="5418474_11_1750.jpg" n="2"/>inspector in Berlin and having gained a reputation as such, the Federal Government appointed him as one of the supervisors at the Government meat inspecting bureau of the stockyards in Chicago. This position he maintained until his death. A stomach disease caused his death.</p>
   <p>Dr. Bernard was very socially minded. He joined preferably those clubs which also cultivated sciences and literature. He was a very highly esteemed member of the German Press Club, and the Club of Technicians, where he lectured repeatedly on natural sciences. A series of public lectures on similar subjects in Brand's Hall is undoubtedly well remembered by those who attended.</p>
   <p>His widow and a married son survive him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
