<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-09-08">Sept. 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Simon W. Straus Died.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1188</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1188.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-09-08">Sept. 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">SIMON W. STRAUS DIED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The funeral of S. W. Straus, one of the most prominent bankers of the world and chairman of the board of trustees of the firm S. W. Straus &amp; Co., named for him, will be held tomorrow afternoon at the Cypress Cemetery, Brooklyn, N. Y. He died yesterday morning after a lingering illness at the age of 64 years, in his home at the Ambassador Hotel, New York City.</p>
   <p>Simon William Straus was born in Ligonier Ind., in 1866, as son of Frederick William and Madlon Goldsmith Straus. His ancestors were bankers. His father came from Rheinish-Prussia, Germany, to the United States in 1852, and soon after his arrival, settled in Ligonier, Ind., where he opened a banking firm.</p>
   <p>Young Straus attended schools in Chicago and Cincinnati and entered the business of F. W. Straus of Chicago in 1884, which had been founded by his father. Two years later, after his father's retirement, he took charge of the management of the business, which henceforth went by the name S. W. Straus &amp; Co. The business improved rapidly, and S. W. Straus was its <pb facs="5418474_11_1189.jpg" n="2"/>president until two years ago, when he became Chairman of the board of trustees. In 1915 he moved to New York, to take charge of the business named for him, which now had greatly grown. In 1911 he founded the "Franklin Trust &amp; Saving Bank" and in 1928 the "Straus National and Trust Co.," whose president he had been until his death. The erection of the Ambassador Hotel was also his work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
