<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-10">November 10, 1871</date><title level="a">To Those Who So Quickly Forgot Us.</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Emil Dietzsch. Reprint from the Chicago Union.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-10">November 10, 1871</date><title level="a">TO THOSE WHO SO QUICKLY FORGOT US.</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Emil Dietzsch. Reprint from the Chicago Union.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In July 1870 when the trans-oceanic telegraph brought the news of the declaration of war from Germany something like an electric vibration went through the hearts of all German-born citizens of the United States....before even the first German regiment had crossed the boundaries of the hereditary enemy, half a million dollars had been signed in this country for the wounded of the impending war.</p>
   <p>With more love and truly admirable faith nobody can cling to the place of this birth more than the German in America; his eternal attachment arouses the suspicions of his American fellow citizens, who are inclined to believe that our innate longing for the old country includes that for its monarchical institutions. But, God knows, that is not so!........</p>
   <p>But when the news of the disaster, which made almost 50,000 Germans shelterless paupers came to you, you brothers in Germany, you remained as mute as a grave.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1047.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>not a sound of sympathy and pity came over to us, we waited in vain...we feared, not for us, but for you. We would so gladly have seen you saving your honor before us. Alas! it was not to be. We used to boast with the magnanimity, warmth of heart and the proverbial Gemuthlichkeit of our people. Now we feel doubly sharp the sting in our hearts when the American born ask us: "Is this the generosity of your people?" We turn away, richer by a sad experience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
