<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-03-04">Mar. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Emil Hoechster</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-03-04">Mar. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">EMIL HOECHSTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have to inform our readers, of a very sad event, Emil Hoechster, undoubtedly the best known among the Germans of Chicago, and one of its most beloved representatives, is no more. With this, there is not too much said, because for decades, no other man has, upon pleasant and sad occurrences, concerning the Germans, in such a prominent way, appeared before the public, as Emil Hoechster.</p>
   <p>He fulfilled the duties, which he owed to his adopted fatherland, in an honest way. At that time, the beginning of the sixties, of the last century, during the great civil war, when he wore the uniform of a soldier, and later, in different official positions, he proved to be a true American citizen. Even then Hoechster remained a German to the core; he was one of the most important and successful champions enlisted of German ideals, German customs and manners, and it can be properly said of him:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1469.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"He lived like a German, he died like a German." He was sick only a few days, and yesterday evening, before 10 o'clock, he closed his eyes forever. He was born in Frankfort On Main in 1836, as the son of lawyer Hoechester. He came to America, and in New York was engaged as an actor by the German Theater, and for ten years he remained on the stage, amid great success.</p>
   <p>He was in St. Louis, when Lincoln issued his call for volunteers, and he enlisted immediately in the First Missouri Regiment. After three months service, he was transferred to the 24th Illinois Regiment (First Hacker Regiment) as a Lieutenant, and acted as assistant Provost Marshal under Broadhead in St. Louis, till the end of the war in 1865. He moved to Chicago and became local editor of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung for two years.</p>
   <p>President Grant appointed him in March 1869, as Consul to Barmen, Germany, which post he held till 1875.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
