<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-08-29">August 29, 1871</date><title level="a">"Schnorrerthum"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1048</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1048.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-08-29">August 29, 1871</date><title level="a">"SCHNORRERTHUM"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "Hebrew Leader" reprints an interesting article from the Hungarian Weekly regarding the Jewish Proletariat, the so-called mooch-dom (das segenannte Schnorrerthum).</p>
   <p>"The origin of the Schnorrerthum is connected with the Goluth. At the time of the Jewish persecutions of the Middle Ages, to open one's homes and to take care of exiled co-religionists was a holy duty...The persecutions have ceased, but the Schnorrerthum has remained. These moochers regard their poverty as a gift from heaven just as the rich man looks at his wealth - they don't beg for aid, but demand it with a certain self-assurance. The Schnorrer loves his poverty and makes a profession of it." The paper says further on that a flood of Schnorrers is invading Germany from the East - Germany "where otherwise the genuine Schnorrerthum no longer exists." That sounds like mockery. The specifically Jewish "schnorrethum" may no longer exist in Germany, but the Christian Germanic is genuine enough....Like its Jewish prototype it does not by far aid but "demands it with a certain self-assurance". When a committee of wealthy citizens of Frankfurt mooches contributions for the rebuilding of the burnt "Pathorn", it does not do so because it needs money, but because it wishes to give the <pb facs="5418474_11_1049.jpg" n="2"/>Frankfurters who live in far-off countries the desired chance to manifest their love for their home-town". In the same way one approaches us (man schnorst unsan") for contributions to an honorary gift for the painter of the "Germania", - not for the money, - for heaven's sake, no! - but only in order that we here in America should not feel offended, if for once we have not been so approached. The true and genuine Schnorrer always regards himself as a business friend of the Schnorree ("des Ange schnorrten").</p>
   <p>...The begging letters that have come from Germany since the end of the war have been cold shouldered in the whole German-American press, so demonstratively, that one will perhaps learn in Germany to be ashamed and will not return so soon. The Germans in America have sent exceedingly rich gifts to mitigate the sufferings of the war. But now, that Germany has brought its great victory harvest home, they would oblige us by having us "unangeschnorst" (un-mooched-on"). The German Societies here, which assist the coldly and stepmotherly dismissed German emigrants, German-American hospitals, German schools - all these institutions have far better claims to the warmest and most vigorous support from German-speaking Americans, than all projects of monuments, honorary gifts, cathedrals and what-nots in Germany. Yes, it seems to us as if now the time and had come for rich Germany to put its hand into its pocket and to do something for German-American institutions!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
