<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1918-02-27">Feb. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Ferdinand C. Schapper.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1428</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1428.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1918-02-27">Feb. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FERDINAND C. SCHAPPER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ferdinand Schapper died Feb. 24, 1918. He was born in Besselich near Coblenz, Germany, November, 1853. After receiving an excellent education, he emigrated to the United States in 1875. He settled down in Plue Island, where he and his uncle operated a drug store. In 1877 he came to Chicago where he founded a drug store at Halsted and willow Streets, his store at this time was the farthest north on the north, side. In 1885 he took over the agency of the Roessler and Haslacher Chemical Company of New York. He was the firm's first representative, who lived here permanently. He developed this business to a high degree.</p>
   <p>After having been active in this business for over thirty-two years, he retired last March. He was a member of the following associations: American Pharmaceutical Association, American Chemical Society, Verein Deutscher Chemiker, Chemical Club of New York, Geographical Society, German Club of Chicago, German University Club of Chicago, German University Club of New York, German Aid Society of Chicago, Verein of Old German Students, American Forestry Association, American Academy of Political and Social Science, American Association for the advancement of science, Illinois Pharmaceutical Association, Michigan Agricultural and Potato Association, <pb facs="5418474_11_1429.jpg" n="2"/>Constitutional Society, Art Institute of Chicago, and the Manufactures and Dealers Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
