<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-09-12">Sept. 12, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Prominent German Physician Succumbs to Heart Attack</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-09-12">Sept. 12, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">PROMINENT GERMAN PHYSICIAN SUCCUMBS TO HEART ATTACK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To all the German circles the sudden death of Dr. Gustao Schirmer brings sincere grief. Heart failure ended his life, which so exclusively was devoted to the general welfare of the people. Dr. Schirmer died at his home, 1102 S. Ashland Ave, notwithstanding his 76 years of age the physician was remarkably vigorous and active. Only few people could do as much good, alleviate much misery and want, as Dr. Schirmer.</p>
   <p>During his 45 years of practice in Chicago he had gained innumerable friends, who deeply mourn his sudden death.</p>
   <p>Dr. Schirmer was for many years on the staff of the Grant hospital and had a large practice on the Westside of Chicago.</p>
   <p>His friends considered him as a highly educated man as well as a philosopher and poet. He was one of the founders of the German medical society of Chicago and of the society of German university graduates. His charitable activities extended not only to Americans, but he also sacrificed a considerable part of his fortune to allay the terrible sufferings in Germany, during and after the <pb facs="5418474_11_1303.jpg" n="2"/>war. Just recently, his old university of the city of Erlangen bestowed honorary citizenship upon him and as such, handed to him the traditional golden Chain, in appreciation of his endowment of 25,000 dollars to the University of Erlangen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
