<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-16">Nov. 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Nationality and Language of Origin Considered in the Census</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-16">Nov. 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONALITY AND LANGUAGE OF ORIGIN CONSIDERED IN THE CENSUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Washington makes the gratifying announcement that next year's census will consider the question of language. It will be recalled that the last census overloaded its questionnaire with supposedly all-important questions, and found no space to consider the language problem. Objections to the inclusion of the latter were then resorted to with typically bureaucratic persistency. Therefore, the final official relenting in this matter deserves proper recognition. The question regarding the inhabitant's mother tongue is of profound historical significance for the United States, since it will provide definite facts about our racial foundations, give data on the nation's development and, above all, provide information about its settlers. To ignore these things would have been shortsighted indeed.</p>
   <p>It is quite evident that the question regarding nationality will in some cases <pb facs="5418474_11_0355.jpg" n="2"/>lead to misinformation given neither purposely nor maliciously, but merely because in many instances the person questioned does not know to which nationality he really belongs.</p>
   <p>This ignorance is one of the consequences of the World War. How many German-Bohemians who immigrated to America before the war and became citizens here will claim to have been Czechoslovakians? Actually they never were Czechoslovakian But since their birthplace is today a part of the newly-formed Czech republic, then insofar as statistics are concerned they have originally came from Czechoslovakia. The German who left Eupen or Malmedy thirty to forty years ago must classify himself as a Belgian if he interprets the question properly, although throughout his life such was never his intention. But today his natal hearthstone rests in Belgium, and everyone who was born and lived or died there has been officially affirmed a Belgian.</p>
   <p>The Germans would have been a small race indeed if the statistical records <pb facs="5418474_11_0356.jpg" n="3"/>were based solely upon the present boundaries, resulting from the German defeat in the World War. There would be few Germans were the birthplace the only deciding factor.</p>
   <p>However, the question which inquires about the mother tongue will, above all else, provide a true indication of one's nationality. The former German-Bohemian will never declare that his language is Czech, just as a South Tyrolean will not represent himself as Italian, or a German Pole as Polish. Likewise the emigrant from Eupen will not consider himself French or Welsh.</p>
   <p>In formulating future immigration laws it may be of utmost importance to know how many of those settlers who came to the United States in this or that decennium considered themselves of Teutonic origin.</p>
   <p>The attempt to exclude the question was tantamount to a distortion of the truth. The decision to include it again is therefore a happy circumstance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
