<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-03-11">March 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">In the German Club.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-03-11">March 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE GERMAN CLUB.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before a large audience of members of the German Club, who participated, yesterday, at the luncheon in the Sherman Hotel, the well known lawyer, George A. Mason, spoke on Americans of German descent and their position in the history of the United States. Beginning with the statistics of Germans, who immigrated to the United States and their descendants, the speaker went back to the first immigrations, after the Thirty Years War and the proof of the active participation of Germans, At all times, since the birth of the United States in every movement which would benefit the country.</p>
   <p>Already in 1688, the Germans had accepted resolutions against slavery; Jacob Leisler defended New York against the French and Peter Zenger fearlessly advocated the liberty of the press. He named Baron von Steuben, as the man who, through his talent as organizer, raised the tattered Colonial soldiers to be useful fighters for the Independence of America. Washington's letter of thanks to Baron von Steuben is the best proof of how groundless and malicious the present critics are against the German Americans; those who doubt their loyalty.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0306.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such attacks find only support in the circles of the ignorant, and others who do not know the facts. The heroine of Monmouth, Molly Pitcher, was Marie Ludwig, who was promoted to Sergeant by Washington for her bravery. So much for German-American women. The speaker referred, also to the Civil War, and praised the patriotism of the German-Americans. At present, the possibility of a war with Germany is not impossible. God forbid its coming. But even then, the German Americans would not waver in their loyalty, but would stand true to the Stars and Stripes. What the speaker said about Germany and German ways and means in international politics, was more the result of hear say, than from experience and study while his views about the coming development of democratic principles in Germany, contained more vague assertions than concrete facts.</p>
   <p>In conclusion Henry George Zander, President of the Club, in serious, deeply felt words gave expression to the woe in the hearts of the German Americans and cited a poem of a Chicagoan, Dietz, whose last line expressed the thought, that the morning sun, might dry the dew on the flowers, and the tears in the eyes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
