<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-09-02">Sept. 2, 1893</date><title level="a">Dr. Julius Ulrich</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1732</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1732.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Illinois-Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-09-02">Sept. 2, 1893</date><title level="a">DR. JULIUS ULRICH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Julius Ulrich died yesterday at his home, 202 Center Street. He was the oldest German homeopathist of Chicago. Almost his entire life was dedicated to his profession. In his chosen field, he attained eminence and success. His spirit of sacrifice and his experience, gained by years of practice, created an unceasing demand for his services. He was a man, in the genuine sense of the word, a faithful friend, a loving husband, and father, who was loved and honored by all who knew him.</p>
   <p>He was born on April 8, 1822, in Eisfeld, Germany. After finishing his studies at the Gymnasium of Schleusingen, he attended the University of Vienna, Austria, where he graduated as a Doctor of Medicine. After he had been for a time district physician in his homeland, he came to America in 1852. At first, in he settled in Wheeling, West Virginia.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1733.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During his short stay of two years there, he obtained the friendship of the community. He then came to Chicago with his family, and was successful from the very beginning. As Chicago's first German homeopathic doctor, he soon acquired a large clientele. In the fateful year 1871, in common with so many others, he lost all his possessions in Chicago's devastating fire. His relentless diligence and love for his chosen profession retrieved his fortune.</p>
   <p>The deceased was one of the founders of the Lessing Lodge, an auxiliary of the Free Masons. He also belonged to the Lincoln Park Lodge of the Odd Fellows, and the Thueringer Club. His wife died five years ago, but his children, Dr. Raymund Ulrich, Fritz Ulrich, and a daughter, Bianca Dreier, survive him. The funeral will be at 2 P. M......Interment will be at Graceland Cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
