<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-04-21">Apr. 21, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Hermann Raster's 100th Birthday to Be Celebrated Tomorrow at Hermann Raster School.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1307</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1307.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-04-21">Apr. 21, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">HERMANN RASTER'S 100TH BIRTHDAY TO BE CELEBRATED TOMORROW AT HERMANN RASTER SCHOOL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the occasion of the 100th birthday anniversary of Hermann Raster, a memorial celebration will be held tomorrow afternoon at the Hermann Raster school, 69th and Hermitage Avenue, to which all the descendants of this prominent German-American will be invited. Dr. Otto L. Schmidt will hold the memorial speech.</p>
   <p>The name of Hermann Raster is intimately interwoven with the history of the German element of Chicago, and with the Chicago English speaking as well as German press. Hermann Raster was born May 6th, 1827, in Dessau, Germany. As a young student he joined the revolutionary movement.</p>
   <p>The failure of the revolution of 1848 to which he had given his support, brought him before the court. He was set free on the condition that he would emigrate to the United States. In the year 1851 he was working for the Buffalo Democrat. In 1852 he moved to New York and worked for a New York evening paper. He remained with this paper for 15 years until in 1867 he accepted the offer of the proprietor of the Illinois Staats Zeitung, Carl <pb facs="5418474_11_1308.jpg" n="2"/>Hesing, to come to Chicago.</p>
   <p>By this time he was known as a journalist not only here but also in Germany where he was renowned as correspondent of the Berlin National Zeitung, the Augsburg Allgemeinen and the Weser Zeitung. It was he who in 1873 repulsed the first attack of the Chicago hypocrites against the open Sunday. It was also he who during the German-French war thoroughly silenced the Anglo-American press in their furious attacks against the Germans.</p>
   <p>He died in 1891, but his name has not been forgotten. He continues to live at the HermannRaster school.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
