<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-02-20">Feb. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Funeral of Ernst Hummel to Be Held Next Wednesday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1123</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1123.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-02-20">Feb. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">FUNERAL OF ERNST HUMMEL TO BE HELD NEXT WEDNESDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The funeral of the honorary president and founder of the Schwabenverein (Swabian Society), Ernst Hummel, will be held next Wednesday afternoon, in the German Evangelical St. Petri Church, 103d Street and Avenue A. After church services, the funeral, under the direction of the Keystone Lodge No. 639, of the Freemasons, will proceed to the Graceland Cemetery.</p>
   <p>The body lies till Wednesday morning in Griesel's Chapel, 10236 Ewing Ave. Hummel is also the founder and honorary president of the St. Petri Congregation. Besides being the founder of the Swabian Society, the deceased was a member of the Keystone Lodge No. 639 of the Freemasons, of the Odd Fellows, the Eagles, the Order of Harugari and a few other societies. His wife preceded him in death several years ago. He lived lately with his daughter, Mrs. H. P. McLaughlin, 10134 Avenue M.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1124.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Born April 7, 1843, in Unter Riegsingen, Wurttemberg, he came to Chicago as a young man, and he soon found employment in the building trade. In later years he was connected with the brewing industry. He was also active in politics and served, at the beginning of this century, two terms as city treasurer under Mayor Harrison. The demise of the old gentleman, who until his death enjoyed physical and spiritual alertness, is deeply mourned in wide circles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
