<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-02">Dec. 2, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Call to the Germans of Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0671</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0671.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-12-02">Dec. 2, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">CALL TO THE GERMANS OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Countrymen:</p>
   <p>For fourteen years now, our German brothers have lived apart from their own people under an alien rule, which does not serve the territories entrusted to it in faith, but is willing to obey the will of foreign potentates in the most decisive questions. These foreign potentates reach out their hands for this rich territory which lies at the gates of their own land. A long time ago, the lies about the Saar, with which French diplomats managed to bend the will of the other powers in Versailles to create a new Alsace-Lorraine, were uncovered. It has long been apparent to the whole world that the Saar has suffered great national and moral injustices. And still the League of Nations shrinks helplessly away from influential France, and does not right this injustice; France still refuses to release the Saar, which has long given clear and unanimous evidence of its unshakable will, before all the world, to reunite itself with the Reich. Verily, France has much to answer for to <pb facs="5418474_11_0672.jpg" n="2"/>the Saar region! Is it not a grave proof of moral turpitude to keep, against their will and by force, a people from its common motherland, a people which has been intimately united with Germany, its history and culture, for more than a thousand years? Is it not economically unsound to give over the home of that people to the gravest upheaval they ever went through? In spite of all that, there is cold silence over there, and adherence to the paragraphs of a treaty that was conceived in a wrong and has continued to exist in injustice.</p>
   <p>It is the task of every good German to co-operate, to the extent of all his powers, in keeping the region of the Saar German and undivided. That task is yet to be completed. The noble pro-German demonstrations at the Saar should have decided the German future of the people of the Saar in favor of that self-government which has been so highly praised by the League of Nations.</p>
   <p>"We are Germans by descent, history, language, and attitude. Now, during the deepest misfortune that beset our German brothers and sisters, we want to be united with them. A union of the Saarbruecke region with France would be <pb facs="5418474_11_0673.jpg" n="3"/>incompatible with President Wilson's principles, which were accepted, not only by Germany, but also by our enemies, as the basis for peace negotiations."</p>
   <p>So reads the proclamation which was sent, in the form of a petition, to President Wilson, at Versailles, by the citizens of Saarbruecke, in December, 1918, in an effort to prevent Frances's annexation of the Saar region. It therefore represents the will of a people of a country over which Versailles placed a regulation which did not formally deliver the Saar region, as a geographical and political entity, over to France, but which gave the economic key position of this territory--the mines of the Saar--to France. With this, they have subjected the inhabitants of the Saar, and their economic life (which directly and indirectly depends on these mines) to the will and influence of France. Can there be any greater infringement upon a people's right to self-government than a form of regulation by which a highly civilized, Christian population of more than three-quarters of a million Germans living in the heart of Europe is treated as part of the chattels of the owners of the coal mines, just as though they lived in times of human slavery?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0674.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On January 13, 1935 the people of the Saar region will decide by a plebiscite whether they want to continue bowing to the dictates of France, or whether they want to return to the mother country? All persons of either sex have a right to vote who, first, are more than twenty years old on the day of the plebiscite; second, who, on the day the Versaille treaty was signed (June 28th, 1917) had lived in the Saar. The fact of adopted citizenship in another country does not disqualify a voter, and that is why those Saarlanders who live at present in America have decided to take part in the plebiscite and will, for that purpose, go to Germany.</p>
   <p>What is our most sacred duty in this entire matter. We must enable these persons to exercise their right to vote by contributing to the expenses of the American Saarland voters who go to Germany. By expenses we do not mean traveling expenses, but costs of the support of women and children whose husbands or fathers are about to journey to Germany to exercise their suffrage rights. We must not leave these wives and children in want and <pb facs="5418474_11_0675.jpg" n="5"/>misery at a time when their husbands and fathers are about to give evidence of their unbreakable faith in their motherland.</p>
   <p>In an effort to make those contributions possible, there will be a demonstration for the Saar on Saturday, December 8th, in the Ashland auditorium. It will be a festival whose net proceeds will be turned over for the benefit of the women and children.</p>
   <p>The organizations and corporations listed below have firmly declared them-selves in favor of the Saar question and call upon all Germans to be at the forthcoming demonstration for the Saar. If, thus, every German fulfills his duty to his old homeland, then a great moral triumph resulting from the participation of the American Saarlanders in the plebiscite will be assured.</p>
   <p>German Countrymen, do your duty by your own people!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0676.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>With true German Greetings:</p>
   <p>Vereinigte Maennerchoere von Chicago (United Men's Choruses),</p>
   <p>Vereinigte Damenchoere von Chicago (United Ladies' Choruses),</p>
   <p>Illinois Turnbezirk (Illinois Turner District), Odd Fellows,</p>
   <p>Goethe Lodge,</p>
   <p>Unterstuetzungs-Verein (Mutual Aid Society),</p>
   <p>Deutsch-Amerikanischer Buergerbund (German-American Citizens' Bund),</p>
   <p>Sachsen Verein (Saxon Society of Chicago),</p>
   <p>Deutscher Krieger Bund (Bund of German World War Veterans),</p>
   <p>Saarlaender Verein (Society of Saarlanders),</p>
   <p>Vereinigte Saenger von Chicago (United Singers of Chicago),</p>
   <p>Independent German-American Woman's Club,</p>
   <p>Damenzirkel der Vereinigten Deutsche Presse (Ladies' United German Press Circle),</p>
   <p>Schutzbund Deutscher Sportsvereine (German Sporting Clubs'</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0677.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Protective Bund),</p>
   <p>Plattduetsche Grotgilde (Low German Grand Lodge),</p>
   <p>Turnverein Vorwaerte (Forward Turner Society),</p>
   <p>German Club [of Chicago],</p>
   <p>German Day Organization,</p>
   <p>Freunde des Neuen Deutschland (Friends of New Germany),</p>
   <p>Deutscher Unterstuetzungs Bund, Zentral Komite (Central Committee of the German Aid Society, Chicago District),</p>
   <p>Palatinate Organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
