<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-19">Aug. 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">State and Nation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-19">Aug. 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">STATE AND NATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>.....The Southern states seek retrogression to the states' rights of 1789.....</p>
   <p>But immigrants were never concerned with state boundaries. Indeed, a conscientious observer will conclude that immigration was a greater contributing factor than any other in shaping the nationalistic view prevailing in the Northern states.</p>
   <p>At the beginning of the century, and up to the time when the development of steam power gradually changed our economic system, one finds that the states east of the Alleghenies were just as proud of their independence as were the Southern states at a later period. Then came the large immigration from Europe. The arrivals were not particularly concerned with the rights of states and all that is implied thereby. To the immigrants, the name of a state was <pb facs="5418474_11_0608.jpg" n="2"/>of about the same importance as that of a shire in England, a department in France, or a province in Prussia; therefore the new settlers regarded the United States as a nation only, and practically obliterated state lines.</p>
   <p>Newspapers like the Chicago Times may rant ever so much that, in political attitudes, the Germans are Germans, the Irish are Irish, and the Scandinavians follow their own ideas--yet facts indicate that all these people who found a new home here are truer Americans and show greater loyalty to American nationalism than our native-born citizens who are more or less motivated by state pride.</p>
   <p>Southerners, in particular, must admit this, since they hated the "damned Dutch," especially during the Civil War, knowing fully that the nationalistic view found its greatest support among Germans who did not consider themselves as being from New York, Illinois, Missiouri, or Wisconsin, but rather as citizens of a nation--the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0609.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And this experience of twenty years ago will be repeated, if the Southerners persist in their efforts, and they will find the Germans just as stanch as ever in protecting the unity of the nation; not only the Germans, but also their related race, the Scandinavians. Since this immigration of millions of people of Germanic origin fashioned our American nation into a homogeneous unit, there is no occasion to believe that disintegration will ensue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
