<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-09-20">Sep. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Washington Hesing's Mistake</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-09-20">Sep. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">MR. WASHINGTON HESING'S MISTAKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Tribune called on Gov. Fifer this morning after his return to the capital from his stumping tour last week and questioned him in regard to what Mr. Hesing said about him in his communication to the Tribune of last Friday, and more especially as to the so-called Edwards' law, Mr. Hesing having positively denied that he helped to frame that bill, or that he visited Springfield either to have it passed or to urge the Governor to sign it. After reading Mr. Hesing's letter, the Governor slowly and deliberately made this reply:</p>
   <p>"The Democratic newspapers had a garbled report of my speech delivered at Cisma Park, Iroquois County, Wednesday last, respecting what I said on the school question. In this report, I was misrepresented. Mr. Hesing, it seems, has made this report the basis of an editorial in the Staats-Zeitung, in which he attacks me savagely.</p>
   <p>"My friend, Hesing, ought to throw open his shirt collar and cool off. In his letter, he never seems to doubt for a moment but that I was correctly reported. I never at any time or place charged that Mr. Hesing had urged me to sign the Compulsory School Bill. Neither was Judge Prendergast present, and any statement <pb facs="5418474_11_1783.jpg" n="2"/>that I ever said they were is.untrue.</p>
   <p>"In discussing the school question before the people, I have frequently said that the object of the promoters of this law was a good one. I called attention to the fact that all religions and political beliefs were represented on the committee that framed the law. I had been told this and I believed it to be true. I had been told also that Mr. Washington Hesing and Judge Prendergast were members of the committee that framed the law. Of course, I never had any personal knowledge as to this, but believed that it was true. I called attention to the fact that the German Lutherans, Catholics, and all religious beliefs were represented on the committee that framed the law, and that it was satisfactory to all of them, as I was informed; and I believe these representations were made by the committee who came down from Chicago with the bill to get it through the Legislature. I never referred to the religion of Judge Prendergast and Mr. Hesing in this connection, except to show that the different religions were represented on the committee that framed the law; and what I said in regard to these matters was rather complimentary to these gentlemen, who I said were endeavoring to improve the school system of the State.</p>
   <p>"As for myself, I have frequently said in my public speeches that I never knew of the prudency or even of the existence of the bill until after it had passed <pb facs="5418474_11_1784.jpg" n="3"/>the Lower House of the Legislature and was nearly through the Senate. In a short time after that, it passed the Senate and came to my hands for signature. A committee waited on me within thirty minutes, I think, after the bill was laid down on my desk for approval and urged me to sign it, and gave the reasons why it should have executive approval.</p>
   <p>"Neither Washington Hesing nor Judge Prendergast was of this last named committee, and I never at any time or place, said they were. It would be very foolish for me to do so, when I knew well enough that it was not true.</p>
   <p>"I will find out the names of this committee in due time and will look into the entire matter, and clear it all up in some of my speeches during the campaign. The people are not concerned whether Mr. Hesing or somebody else drew up the so-called Edwards' law. That is wholly immaterial.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Hesing, I see, takes exception to what I said in regard to his visit with Mr. Cleveland at Gray Gables. All that I ever said on that subject was that it was reported that he had been in town visiting Mr. Cleveland, and had pledged him the support of 25,000 Republican German Lutheran votes. I said this in my Pekin speech and have used the same language substantially in discussing that subject in my subsequent speeches. Of course, I do not know personally whether <pb facs="5418474_11_1785.jpg" n="4"/>"Mr. Hesing visited Mr. Cleveland or not. I was not present and did not know what was said, and I told my hearers that it was reported that he had been down; and so it was, and I feel quite sure that many are of the opinion that these reports are correct."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
