<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-09-10">Sept. 10, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">John Hetzel Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1326</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1326.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-09-10">Sept. 10, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN HETZEL DIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Another of the old German settlers of Chicago has been taken by death. John Hetzel, president for many years of the Hetzel Packing Company, died Friday night from a heart ailment.</p>
   <p>John Hetzel, who had lived for over 40 years in Chicago, died after a short illness at his home, 422 Briar Place, at the age of 62 years. He was born in Germany, and at the age of 16 years came to America, settling in Chicago. Here he started his business and from small beginnings, during the course of decades, developed it to one of the most prosperous in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1327.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since 1888, he had been president of the company. The firm today is one of the greatest packing houses of Chicago and its high grade products are well known everywhere. The Hetzel sausage machine, which was his own invention, manufactured the sausages without their having to be touched by human hands. This machine greatly contributed toward the maintenance of the firm's reputation.</p>
   <p>Many years ago, John Hetzel took his two sons into his business as partners and they also contributed their share to the firm's leadership, and undoubtedly will continue the work of the deceased on the same principles.</p>
   <p>For about 15 years the deceased has also been interested in the Western Packing Company, whose president he had been for several years.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1328.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>His sudden demise is widely mourned because of the general popularity which the he enjoyed. He was a member of the Germania club and the Germania Men's Chorus for many years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hetzel is survived by his wife and four children. Mrs. Minni Hetzel, the widow, is ill at the present time. The four children, Henry B. and John P. Hetzel, Wilma Hetzel, and Mrs. Johanna Bredemeyer, all live in Chicago and are staying at the present time at the home of their parents. Funeral services will be held at the home Monday afternoon. Burial will be in Rosehill cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
