<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-05-05">May 5, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">German Companies in Camp</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-05-05">May 5, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN COMPANIES IN CAMP</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Various rumors have been spread concerning the situation of German companies. We advise our fellow citizens to be very careful about accepting reports that German companies are badly treated or disbanded. These rumors are seldom reliable, and it is much wiser to believe the statements of honest members of the companies themselves, and form one's opinion on the basis of what they have to say. Captain Schambeck visited our office and gave us an oral report on conditions, and we have received information through the mail from good honest Captain Lippert, who is at Camp Yates, and also from our friend Eduard Bornemann, ensign in the Turner Company.</p>
   <p>All the German companies from Chicago, which are in Camp Cairo and Camp Springfield, have been accepted for service and assigned to regiments.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0243.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These companies are:</p>
   <p>At Camp Cairo (Turner) Union Cadets, Captain Kowalt Lincoln Rifles, Captain Mihaloz</p>
   <p>At Camp Yates</p>
   <p>Union Rifles, Number 1, Captain Lippert</p>
   <p>Union Rifles, Number 2, Captain Iten</p>
   <p>Washington Light Cavalry, Captain Schambeck</p>
   <p>Washington Light Infantry, Captain Mattern</p>
   <p>The troops are in good humor and are well cared for; as a rule enrollment into active service puts an end to any complaints, and everybody is satisfied. Captain Schambeck, who brought us this information, says that these conditions <pb facs="5418474_11_0244.jpg" n="3"/>are a result of the ceaseless efforts of Lieutenant Governor Hoffmann. It will be interesting to the relatives of the Chicagoans who are in camp to know that Captain Schambeck will be at Hottinger and Kastler's, on Randolph Street, today from 9 to 12 A. M. and from 1 to 3 P. M., and again tomorrow, from 9 to 12 A. M., to give anyone wishing for reliable news a true account of conditions in his camp.</p>
   <p>Genuine Turners</p>
   <p>The Union Cadets are brave boys; they do not believe in half-way methods. Not only did they ask for the honor of filling the most dangerous positions in Camp Cairo; not only did they drill so diligently and energetically that they are now able to compete with the crack Zouave Company; but they have also reorganized their Turnverein in camp, Officers elected are: A. Erbe, First Speaker; C. Bornemann, Secretary; horizontal bars were erected, and <pb facs="5418474_11_0245.jpg" n="4"/>so "Kinzie Hall" was transferred to Camp Cairo. That's the way, boys! Good luck to you!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
