<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-01-29">Jan. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">William Burkhart, Pioneer of German Musicians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1792</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1792.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-01-29">Jan. 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">WILLIAM BURKHART, PIONEER OF GERMAN MUSICIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>William Burkhart, a pioneer German musician in Chicago died Wednesday, Jan. 27th, at the age of nearly 64 years at his home in Austin.</p>
   <p>Burkhart was born on November 1, 1828 at Marolteroda, near Langensalza, Germany. He was initiated into the secrets of the art of music by his uncle, F. Burkhart, and Professor Albrecht von Bollsted. Early in 1847 he emigrated to the United States and the following year he settled down in Chicago. After directing circus bands for some time, he organized the first military band in Chicago in 1851, under the name of, "Chicago's Light Hussar Band" and from this developed, two years later, the "Chicago Light Guard Band". Burkhart was its director until 1854. Then he organized the "Garden City Band" and in 1856 the "Great Western Band". The latter was recognized as one of the outstanding military bands of the United States. In 1860, at the National Convention of the Democrats in Baltimore, it competed with the best orchestras of the country. The "Great Western Band" was the only military band which was permitted to play in the Convention Hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1793.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Famous musicians, such as A. J. Vaas, C. Bierwirth, J. Hand, C. Sehnert, W. Wiesenbach, C. Romanus, and others, who still enjoy an enviable reputation, were members of that band. In July, 1861, the band joined the 24th Hecker regiment and through its patriotic songs inspired the soldiers with courage. After returning from the war the Chicago Union of Musicians was founded, and Burkhart was its president for five years. In 1867, Burkhart consolidated the Great Western and the Light Guard Band under the name of "Great Western Light Guard Band". This band was the pride of the Garden City for many years. When the first convention of musicians was held in this country in June, 1871, in Philadelphia, Burkhart was present as the delegate of the Chicago Union of Musicians, and the then organized Musicians Protective Association elected him to the Vice-Presidency. He remained with the Great Western Light Guard Band until 1873 when he was compelled to withdraw from all musical activities because of his poor health. From then on he persued intensive gardening at Austin until 1890, when he again had to retire on account of ill health. Until his death he manifested a vital interest in the development of music in this country. With real enthusiasm he welcomed the organization of a permanent orchestra in Chicago under the direction of T. Thomas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
