<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-03-29">Mar. 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">John P. Altgeld Severely Criticizes the Present Local Administration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1552</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1552.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-03-29">Mar. 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN P. ALTGELD SEVERELY CRITICIZES THE PRESENT LOCAL ADMINISTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The faithful and loyal friend of the Germans, Ex-Governor J. P. Altgeld criticized in his speech yesterday the Mayor of our city and in his own sarcastic way scourged the latter's weaknesses and shortcomings. Altgeld's stirring speech pointed out the corrupt administration of our city and exhorted the audience to make an end to this miserable management by voting for Hanecy. We quote part of Altgeld's speech:</p>
   <p>"Although we Democrats do not owe anything to the gentlemen in the City Hall, we are under a thousandfold obligation to the city of Chicago, and owe her an honest and efficient administration. We have no right to deliver Chicago into the hands of exploiters. A few years ago, Chicago was the wonder of the world. In all parts of the world they spoke about her grandeur and beauty, and we were proud to be citizens of Chicago. We are still proud of her, but we are soon to see her in the hands of greedy robbers, and it is our duty to rescue her. Her revenues are plundered, her streets are neglected, her <pb facs="5418474_11_1553.jpg" n="2"/>bridges fall apart, and, as it were, the proud city is a picture of ruin.</p>
   <p>"It is a fact that no policeman was promoted, when he deserved it, during the last four years, unless he paid the sum of $200, to a greedy city official. Contractors were prevented from finishing their buildings, unless they filled the pockets of building inspectors. Owners of real estate have to pay twice as much for street pavings and for other public works than Indianapolis, New York or any other large city. Tammany in New York, may be corrupt, but there is no comparison with Chicago.</p>
   <p>"The mismanagement of our city and its consequences, such as thefts, embezzlements, etc., have made it necessary to increase our taxes 33%, although the tax assessors are trying hard to lower the rate.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1554.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The city's water department made a clear profit of millions under Harrison's predecessors, but now it is in debt.</p>
   <p>"The value of real estate decreases daily and if Harrison is elected again, it will become worthless, because he expects to put a debt burden of fifty millions on the city.</p>
   <p>"There can be no doubt that the Police Department and the criminals cooperate. Otherwise it would be impossible to commit forty-two thefts and robberies in a single day. This fact is taken from the records of the Police Department."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
