<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1870-09-27">Sept. 27, 1870</date>.
<title level="a">Methodist Episcopal Committee's Report on Franco-Prussian War.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1870-09-27">Sept. 27, 1870</date>.
<title level="a">METHODIST EPISCOPAL COMMITTEE'S REPORT ON FRANCO-PRUSSIAN WAR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whereas, Our beloved former fatherland has been signally victorious in a war which was forced upon her, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, We take great interest in our former fatherland, despite the fact that we are American citizens, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, This is a conflict of justice against injustice, and a conflict of national self-development against despotic tutelage, be it therefore</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we heartily deplore the horrible carnage, and herewith express our sincere sympathy for the plight of the wounded soldiers, the widows, and the orphans of the fallen warriors. Be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we hail with great joy the rise of Germany from internal <pb facs="5418474_11_0080.jpg" n="2"/>dissension to unity, from national degradation to national independence, and that we see in this gigantic struggle God's hand which makes the rage of men subservient to His purposes and is bent upon leading Germany to political and religious freedom. Be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That, although we desire that this War end soon, we are firmly convinced that it should not be terminated until certain guaranties of a permanent peace have been given. Be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we endeavor to collect money in our congregations and send it to our missionaries in Germany for distribution among the wounded soldiers and the widows and orphans. Be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That these resolutions be published in the English and German newspapers of this city.</p>
   <p>The above resolutions were unanimously adopted at a conference which the <pb facs="5418474_11_0081.jpg" n="3"/>Methodist Episcopal Church held yesterday morning.</p>
   <p>E. Wundfrlich,</p>
   <p>J. W. Roecker,</p>
   <p>R. Fiegenbaum,</p>
   <p>A. Miller,</p>
   <p>H. Boettcher.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
