<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-12-12">Dec. 12, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Wilhelm Schmidt.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Proprietor of Riverview Park, Succumbs to Heart Attack.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-12-12">Dec. 12, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">WILHELM SCHMIDT.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Proprietor of Riverview Park, Succumbs to Heart Attack.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wilhelm Schmidt, the proprietor of Riverview Park, died this morning at 9:45 o'clock of a heart attack. This news will cause great sadness among his many acquaintances. He enjoyed the reputation of being a friend and benefactor. The Germans of Chicago in particular, will mourn the passing of this brother of the same race. Because he was during his life time one of the most active, in helping the German cause. As a secret benefactor, he dried many tears and changed bitter misery into joy.</p>
   <p>Born in Ohlendorf near Goslar, Hanover, Feb. 16th, 1850, he learned the bakery trade in his home town and came to Chicago in 1872, where after a short time he opened his own shop on Clybourn Avenue and Mohawk Street. He invented, a few years later, the dough cutting machine, which even today is used in all bakeries.</p>
   <p>In 1898 he sold his bakery, and acquired Sharpshooter Park at Belmont and <pb facs="5418474_11_1374.jpg" n="2"/>Western Avenues. In 1904 the present Riverview Park was opened there, under his management. As a friend of children, he permitted them to visit the park every afternoon free of charge, and of this privilege over two million took advantage in the last four years. Mar. 18th, 1876 he married his surviving wife, Minna, nee Wagner. From the happy marriage was born a son, George A. Schmidt, whose wife presented the grandparents with a grandchild.</p>
   <p>The deceased was greatly interested in German social life in Chicago. He was for several periods, president of the Veterans Association, to which he was devoted even in after years as an honorary member, and which he always supported energetically. He also was president, for a certain length of time, of the Veterans Union of North America. He was known to all his acquaintances and friends as a true comrade. He belonged besides to the Lincoln Club, the Suabian Society, The Harmony Singing Society, and the Germania Lodge A. F. and L.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
