<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1924-10-28">Oct. 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Albert H. Loeb Dies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1924-10-28">Oct. 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ALBERT H. LOEB DIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Albert H. Loeb, vice-president of Sears, Roebuck and Company died yesterday evening at half past ten in his home at 5017 Ellis Avenue of a heart attack from which he suffered several months. He was fifty-six years old. As physicians and his relations assert, his death was not due to the trial of his son, Richard Loeb who as is known, was convicted of the fourteen year old Bobby Franks murder and given a life sentence. Sickly for two years, the symptoms of heart trouble were noticed on May 18th, three days before the kidnapping and murder of little Robert Franks. On that day Mr. Loeb had to take to his bed, and his condition became so critical that later on when Richard Loeb made a confession this fact upon advice of his physicians, was withheld from him. He saw his son for the last time on May 29th, when detectives came to his home and arrested Richard.....</p>
   <p>At his bed, when he died were his two sons, the twenty-four year old Ernest and the fourteen year old Thomas, his widow Mrs. Anna Loeb, his oldest son Allen, and his brother, Julius Loeb. Jacob Loeb, the former president of the school board and Sidney Loeb, the two other brothers, arrived a few minutes later. Mr. Loeb, one of the most successful businessmen of Chicago, was born in Rockford <pb facs="5418474_11_1376.jpg" n="2"/>Illinois. His parents Morris and Johanna Anna Loeb, who died several years ago, came to Chicago after the revolution of 1848 from Germany, and gave their son a good education. He attended the public schools and the John Hopkins University and was admitted to the bar in 1899. A few years later he was entrusted with the legal matters of Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company. Here he worked together with Julius Rosenwald, who resigned a few days ago from the presidency of the concern. The latter, it is said never made an important decision, without asking Mr. Loeb's advice, who a few years ago was made a vice-president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
