<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-08-18">August 18th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A New Speaker for the Germans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1739</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1739.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1893-08-18">August 18th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A New Speaker For The Germans.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It happens very seldom to a legislator, that be makes himself noticeable during his first term. The elder parliamentarians who understand the complicated routine of affairs, know the speaker personally and know how to use the different tricks, push the younger ones almost entirely into the back-yard. Therefore it seems a very hopeful omen when a "greenhorn" understands how to captivate public attention at the first session or with his first speech. In this the German-Democratic Congressman, Julius Goldzier, of Chicago succeeded; The Republican "Inter Ocean" published his "maiden speech" in the following telegraphic report:</p>
   <p>"Congressman Goldzier of Chicago held this morning(August 17th) his first speech before the House. It was a very serious, moderate, true and partly enthusiastic oration, for unconditional revocation of the silver purchasing law. Mr. Goldzier presented his arguments in a businesslike manner and made his points of view clear. Throughout his entire speech he kept a tactful attitude which is lacking from a number of those on his side of the House. Mr. Goldzier said, that this is the time to lift oneself above party politics abd party platforms. He seemed inclined to ignore <pb facs="5418474_11_1740.jpg" n="2"/>the National form, if it should be necessary to rxplain this platform as blocking the way of the unconditional repeal of the silver law. Mr. Goldzier's oration was earn nest, sincere and patriotic."</p>
   <p>Other speakers gave similar judgments, so that the success of Goldzier cannot be doubted. This is of great value for the Germans of Chicago and the entire country, because they had lost their best representatives in congress and were badly in need of a man who can command respect for himself and the German-Americans. It has been feared that after the retirement of Guenther and Lehlbach, the German citizens were without an able spokesman. The more pleasing it is, that in Julius Goldzier has been found a good substitute immediately. The German voters of the Northside, who helped him to a splendid victory, deemingly did not get disappointed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
