<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-15">June 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Sweitzer Fights for His Job as County Treasurer</title><title level="a" type="sub">Quo Warranto Charges Preferred against Gill in County Court</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-15">June 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">SWEITZER FIGHTS FOR HIS JOB AS COUNTY TREASURER</title><title level="a" type="sub">Quo Warranto Charges Preferred against Gill in County Court</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Monday, June 24, the first hearing on the quo warranto charges preferred by Robert M. Sweitzer, through his legal advisor, Attorney J. Harvey Levinson, against the county treasurer, Joseph L. Gill, will be held in the county court.</p>
   <p>The charges were preferred before Superior Judge Joseph Burke. The document was signed by the attorney general, Otto Kerner. It is especially emphasized that, by signing the document, the attorney general is not by any means going over to the side of Sweitzer. The law requires that the attorney general sign his name to such a motion for proceedings instituted in the name of the people, or of an administration, against any public officer.</p>
   <p>"Quo warranto" are the first two words of an interrogative question which means, <pb facs="5418474_11_1085.jpg" n="2"/>in English, "By what right, or by reason of what laws, are you in office?" The sheriff will see to it that the person so interrogated appears before the court and brings proof that he has a right to be in office.</p>
   <p>Sweitzer seeks, by this action, to recover his position as county treasurer. He could also institute a mandamus proceedings or an injunction against all of Gill's activities. But nothing is supposed to be done which might, in any way, impede the official functioning of the county administration.</p>
   <p>It is not yet certain whether Sweitzer's action will have a bearing upon the proceedings instituted against Sweitzer by the state's attorney. The state's attorney has declared that the proceedings have no interconnection. He will continue to gather the necessary evidence to bring about an indictment by the grand jury.</p>
   <p>In the quo warranto proceeding, he is going to represent the county treasurer, <pb facs="5418474_11_1086.jpg" n="3"/>Gill, because the state's attorney is also the representative of the county in all matters of court procedure.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
