<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-20">Feb. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Jakob A. Hey Dies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-20">Feb. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JAKOB A. HEY DIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After an illness of four months Jakob A. Hey died in Chicago Osteopathic Hospital. He was head of the firm of Hey Brothers and a member of the Produce Exchange. For many years the deceased played an important part in the political life of the North Side. He attained an age of fifty-two years. He was born in Otterberg, Palatinate, Germany, and immigrated to Chicago with his parents at the age of nine years. He was educated in local public schools and later graduated from a college. He gained financial independence as a grain and feed merchant. He never married. He was a member of the Masonic Order and various German societies and clubs. The funeral will very likely be held on Saturday and interment will be at Graceland Cemetery.</p>
   <p>In 1905 Jakob A. Hey was elected a member of the City Council and served the Twenty-third Ward in that capacity for ten years. He was one of the best and <pb facs="5418474_11_1414.jpg" n="2"/>ablest aldermen. He took an important part in the fight against the public utilities, and always defended the interests of the little man. In addition he championed the cause of the liberal element, opposing the encroachments of the prohibitionists with all the means at his command. He is best known as an opponent of pasteurization of milk. He made a thorough study of the problem and acquired a wide knowledge of pertinent facts. In this fight he had the support of the eminent bacteriologist, Doctor Maximilian Herzog, who preceded him in death. Alderman Hey's battle against the pasteurization of milk was in vain. In 1915 he voluntarily resigned his membership in the City Council in order to seek the nomination for mayor on the Republican ticket. His opponents were Judge Harry Olson and William Hale Thompson, the present mayor. Even after his departure from the City Council he took an active part in politics on the North Side, and was the recognized leader in the Deneen faction of his ward.</p>
   <p>Last September the deceased was taken ill with influenza. He recovered <pb facs="5418474_11_1415.jpg" n="3"/>from the attack and went to Excelsior Springs, Missouri, to recuperate. But diabetes set in, and he succumbed to it.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The final paragraph of this article contains a death notice which is irrelevant.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
