<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-05-22">May 22, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">We and Europe.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0760</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0760.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-05-22">May 22, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">WE AND EUROPE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States have few friends in this world. It is especially astonishing that particularly those European world powers who were saved from severe defeat through the entrance of our country into the war, show no gratitude whatsoever. In England we enjoy the greatest unpopularity, in France we are literally hated.</p>
   <p>This actually appeared in a crass manner on the occasion of the unsuccessful attempt of two French fliers to cross the Atlantic Ocean in an aeroplane. At the time of this incident, the French press and the Paris population permitted themselves to be carried away to use boundless absurd accusations, meaning, that America was responsible for the failure of these fliers.</p>
   <p>Some time ago, a correspondent of an American news agency - who apparently is inclined to thoroughness - had begun a systematical investigation of the frame of mind of the different European nations in relation to the United States. The inquiry did not prove anything new. In England and Italy a <pb facs="5418474_11_0761.jpg" n="2"/>strong antipathy, in France hatred, in Germany kind feelings. These facts are well-known throughout the country; even the press does not deny it.</p>
   <p>But in spite of it, many newspapers make the greatest efforts to distort the facts in some respect. This occurs not so often in the editorials of newspapers, as in the political caricatures and in those short editorial phrases of a small vest pocket format of a newspaper, which is known in the German press as the "peaked end of a sausage."</p>
   <p>There is always talk about the hatred and enmity of Europe towards the United States. Europe appears like a beggar, who comes to America with a hat in his hand to obtain loans. Europe is armed to its teeth, spends horrible sums on war preparations and refuses to repay Uncle Sam the money borrowed. Europe, indignant over imaginary injustices, and under radical mistaking of facts, holds the United States responsible for all its calamity.</p>
   <p>It therefore must be emphasized once more that such statements are wrong, and stand in violent opposition to actual facts. In this case, the term "Europe" indicates a generalization which is absolutely inadmissible. It is not Europe which shows its hostility towards the United States. Sometimes it is England, sometimes Italy, mostly France.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0762.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That such an attitude of the former allies awakes strong indignation in America is understandable. They should consider, though, that Germany makes a praiseworthy exception, because that country always displays toward the United States a just and friendly attitude. Therefore the occasional utterances of hatred of a small group of irresponsible nationalistic fanatics cannot change this sentiment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
