<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-04-28">April 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">John P. Altgeld</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1770</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1770.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-04-28">April 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN P. ALTGELD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The candidate for governor of the Democratic Party, John P. Altgeld, was born in Germany in the significant year of 1848, and as a little boy of 18 months he came with his parents to this country. He was raised upon a farm in Richland county, Ohio and had very few opportunities to attend a school. In 1864 as a youth of 16 years of age he entered the Union Army and took part in the James River campaign. After the war he was engaged as a teacher.</p>
   <p>Later he studied law and in 1872 became a lawyer. Shortly afterwards he became an attorney of Savannah, and later the state's attorney of Andrew county. He was considered as one of the best and conscientious lawyers in that section of the country. Looking for a larger field of activity, he came to Chicago in 1885 (1885 must be wrong - Trans.)....</p>
   <p>The Democratic Party nominated him in 1884 as a candidate for Congress of <pb facs="5418474_11_1771.jpg" n="2"/>the fourth district which was then predominantly German, and hopelessly Republican. Altgeld ventured a campaign which aroused much attention. and he gained for himself the reputation of being an expert politician.... In 1886 he was nominated by the Democrats to the office of judge of the Supreme Court, and was elected by a majority of 15,000 votes. Labor gave Altgeld their complete indorsement. He resigned as judge last fall.</p>
   <p>Altgeld was feared as judge, because of hismstrict impartiality, and his courage in defending the rights of the poor and oppressed against the rich and against powerful corporations. He always expressed his liberal viewpoints fearlessly, and he was always ready to fight against corruption, bigotry, and had politics.</p>
   <p>Through careful, clever and economical management of his finances he has <pb facs="5418474_11_1772.jpg" n="3"/>become quite wealthy and possesses one of the finest office buildings in Chicago, the Unity Building. However, he remains the quiet, modest, and natural man, whose urge to scientific works with genuine German thoroughness predominates. He is the author of two works which have made him famous in social-political circles, namely, Our Penal Machinery and its Victims, and Live Questions. Judge Altgeld never denied his mother tongue. He lives in the 25th ward, and always was active in German social life. He is a real American in the truest sense, but he remains a German in everything which honors the German name in this land of the stars and stripes. He is now forty-four years old.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
