<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-06-27">June 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">At Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1741</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1741.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-06-27">June 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">AT HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Neebe, Schwab and Fielden returned to their families. Governor Altgeld pardons them unconditionally.</p>
   <p>The Abendpost reported yesterday already that the three anarchists Samuel Fielden, Michael Schwab and Oscar Neebe have been pardoned.</p>
   <p>The news, although they have worked for it a number of years, struck like lightning and caused great joy and satisfaction in a large circle of the population. As known, Fielden and Schwab were sentenced to life imprisonment and Neebe to fifteen years for participation in the Haymarket riot, on May 4th, 1886. The Banker Edward S. Dreyer, a prominent member of the Amnesty Society, who was continuously active in securing their pardon, was called to Springfield by the Governor last Sunday, and received yesterday morning the full amnesty of all three condemned.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1742.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Dreyer took the train at once to Joliet, where he arrived at 3:30 PM. He was immediately conducted to the chief warden by Inspector Allen and the three prisoners were summoned. After reading the letter of pardon, the men were officially released. It was a touching moment. Tears stood in the eyes of the men and nobody could suppress his agitation. At 6:40 P. M. after the convict suits, which they wore for so long had been discarded, the pardoned men went to the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe' depot, and accompanied by Mr. Dreyer, started on the trip to Chicago. The nearer they came to their final destination, the more agitated were the pardoned men. The noise of the big city, the snorting of the engines, the clatter of the freight and passenger trains, sounded like intoxicating music in their ears. In spite of it or rather on account of it, all three felt the necessity to escape notice and welcoming scenes. Schwab, as well as the two others, declared that they preferred not be recognized. They therefore left the train at the small station at 23rd Street and continued the rest of the way on the street car. Fielden went directly to the house no. 117 Polk Street, where his wife and <pb facs="5418474_11_1743.jpg" n="3"/>children were awaiting him. Schwab hurried to his home, 637 North Washtenaw Avenue and was received at the door by his wife and two children. Neebe, has no home, his wife died, while he was in Joliet. He lives, temporarily, in his brother's house on Belmont Avenue. One hour before his arrival, his aged parents, his two daughters, Mrs. Lillie Nitschker, his son, Oscar, his brother Louis, with his family, were assembled on the veranda, in front of the house, and were looking longingly down the street. The neighbors stood in the doors and on the opposite side of the street, a large crowd congregated. At last the expected arrived; he was pale and affected, even if the signs of joy at the sight of his dear ones could be detected. It would be difficult, to describe the scenes, which followed the reunion with his beloved ones. The same took place in the homes of the other two pardoned men. Everywhere their reception was a very affectionate one. The news of the pardon spread like wild fire through the whole city, and was everywhere received with great satisfaction. At the Polk Street depot, an immense crowd was waiting to welcome them. The hope of being able to greet the pardoned men, <pb facs="5418474_11_1744.jpg" n="4"/>could not be fulfilled because, as previously stated, they left the train at another station.</p>
   <p>What Mr.Altgeld has to say:-</p>
   <p>The Governor motivated his action in a voluminous memorandum, in which judges, states attorneys, jury and police were not handled with silk gloves.</p>
   <p>Right at the beginning, he pointed out, that on the evening of May 4th, those who were present at Haymarket, started to leave after Mayor Harrison, who was also there at the beginning of the meeting left. Then came Police Commissioner Bonfield, with a strong detachment of police, to drive away those few who still remained there. The historic bomb was thrown, and although the police could never prove the guilty person, the known eight men were tried and condemned. As regards the pardoned Neebe, Schwab and Fielden, the Govenor declared, that their pardon would certainly not be justified, if it could have been proven, beyond a doubt, that they were sentenced in an impartial trial. No punishment would be too severe if the three had actually committed the <pb facs="5418474_11_1745.jpg" n="5"/>crime, of which they were accused. The soil of America is no soil, in which anarchy could blossom with success, and although our judicial institutions are by no means perfect and above the necessity of improvement, still they are the best that ever existed. Therefore they must be protected and maintained.</p>
   <p>The organization of the Jury, was made in an unusual way, a certain Henry L. Ryce, had been entrusted with the assembling of the Jury; ostensibly upon the request of the accused, in truth against the will of their defenders. "States Attorney Grinnell" said the Governor, proposed Mr. Ryce for the position, and he was accepted and appointed. But, it is immaterial upon whose proposition Ryce was chosen, as long as he could not get together an impartial jury.</p>
   <p>It was proven, that Ryce, during the summoning of the prospective jury, bragged, that in this process he was the deciding factor, and that these fellows would hang, "as sure as death." He is bringing <pb facs="5418474_11_1746.jpg" n="6"/>such men, whom the defense had to reject, and then, when the number of lawfully allowed jury candidates was exhausted, the defense would be compelled to accept people, who would be agreeable to the States Attorney.</p>
   <p>Ryce, as it seems, confined himself to certain classes of the population, clerks, business men, and manufacturers in his selection, and when the defenders asked for "men from the people," the court simply rejected their plea.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
