<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1876-12-04">December 4, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">The Emperor's Gift.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1032</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1032.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1876-12-04">December 4, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">THE EMPEROR'S GIFT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About a year ago the veterans who had served in the German Army, but are now sojourning in this city, formed a society and named it "Der Deutsche Krieger Verein" (German Soldiers' Society). The object of the society is a benevolent one to aid each other in sickness and trouble. The society prospered greatly and now has a large membership. There was but one thing wanting to make the society happy, and that was a nice silk standard or flag with which to march out in procession, and also serve to ornament their place of meeting. But how to secure it was the question. The funds for such a purpose were not at hand, all the money coming being used to aid distressed members. In this dilemma the society thought of the large-hearted German Emperor, for whom its members had battled in years gone. To him they sent a polite message, informing him of their need, and that a flag would be considered a most priceless memento. About two months afterward a package was received by the German Consul in this city, Mr. H. Clausinius, and on opening it the much-desired flag was revealed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1033.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is a beautiful emblem, of heavily corded white silk, artistically embroidered with a wreath, in the center of which is the German eagle. Over it there are the words, "William I., Emperor of Germany and King of Prussia," and below, "Kuer Den Deutschen Kriegerverein" (for the German Soldiers' Society). The presentation of the flag came off at the North Side Turner Hall last evening. The place was crowded, and the society, beside getting the much desired flag, replenished their treasury from the proceeds of the admission tickets to no small extent. The festivities opened with a grand vocal and instrumental concert, at the close of which the flag was presented by Consul H. Clausinius to Mr. Winckler, the president of the society. In presenting the flag Mr. Clausinius made a few appropriate remarks, stating that it was not a common event that a German flag presented by the German Emperor was unfurled here. He spoke of the advance Germany has made during the last two years, and how much it had gained in the eyes of other nations.</p>
   <p>Mr. Winckler in receiving the flag spoke very feelingly and referred to the sympathy of the Germans in this country with their countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
