<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-06-27">June 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">About the New Immigration Law</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-06-27">June 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE NEW IMMIGRATION LAW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new immigration law which, to be sure, does not become effective until July 1, and which has been casting its shadows for a long time now, will in all probability fulfill its purpose, which is to hinder immigration as much as possible. Ever since the interested organizations made a thorough study of its passages it turned out that, in the shape finally given it by Congress, it possesses a number of sharp edges which had never been discussed in public at the time it was debated. It will render immigration into the United States difficult.</p>
   <p>One of the clauses is, for example that only as many visas may be given as the nation in question is allotted in the number of its emigrants. Whether the receivers of the visas afterward have the intention to immigrate remains unconsidered. In such manner it may occur that American consular authorities <pb facs="5418474_11_0408.jpg" n="2"/>have given visas to the highest number of legally admissible immigrants, and yet the highest number of immigrants has not been attained. For, in place of unused visas which have lost their validity, no other visas may be issued to prospective emigrants. In this manner, the number of immigrants from all countries, it may be presumed, will remain short of the legally admissible number. Whether this cunningly devised finesse was, right from the start, designed to restrict immigration, or whether it was, in a way, manipulated into the bill as a "joker" during the last conference, it would be interesting to find out. But, be it as it may, this rule, which is not in keeping with the letter of the law, should be the topic of serious objections in Congress.</p>
   <p>Another hardship lies in the compulsion to pay ten dollars in duties for each immigration visa. Now, if the family of a German farmer of five wants to come over to be employed in agriculture, the "paterfamilias" must first deposit fifty honest dollars upon Uncle Sam's table before he and his folks are given permission to travel to the promised land. Does the immigration of a <pb facs="5418474_11_0409.jpg" n="3"/>family actually cause so much expense to our authorities, or are we dealing here with a mere scheme to lower the number of immigrants? Fifty dollars is, for most prospective immigrants who have to convert all they own into money to come here, an enormous sum. One should think that they could make better use of the money on arriving. Uncle Sam certainly does not need it half as much as they.</p>
   <p>Unjust and inconsiderate, in the long run, is the demand that all those who had before been given a visa for the price of ten dollars, should shell out another ten dollars when they apply for a new visa. These people had procured their first visas in accordance with the then existing rules and trusted in its validity, and it appears to be not quite in order that it should now be declared invalid without returning to them the duties paid.</p>
   <p>Owing to the delay in the publication of executive ordinances pertaining to the new law, considerable loss has accrued to many a prospective immigrant by having to wait for the issuance of these ordinances, because <pb facs="5418474_11_0410.jpg" n="4"/>no American consul may grant an immigration visa until he has received notice of this ordinance from the government. And all this while the emigrant sits there and eats up his money with which he intended to journey to his new homeland. That the ship companies are likewise gravely affected through the delay may here be mentioned only in passing. It is high time that an end should be made to the general uncertainty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
