<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-04-07">April 7, 1909</date><title level="a">German Art Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-04-07">April 7, 1909</date><title level="a">GERMAN ART EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night in the Art Institute the opening of modern German works of art took place with a large crowd in attendance. The exhibition has been arranged by the New York lover of art, Mr. Hugo Reisinger, with the sanction and protection of the German Emperor. It is destined to give the American public an idea of the position and progress of the present German art.</p>
   <p>The show was a great success in an artistic and social way. About five thousand invitations had been sent out and only a few of the invited were absent. From the start to the finish a great crowd of visitors pushed through the five halls of the southern wing of the Art Institute. All nations and social classes were represented. The American and German element was equally divided. The German Ambassador, Count Bernstorff, had sent a telegram with his regrets for being unable to appear personally. Also, Governor Dineen and Mayor Busse excused themselves. Consul Dr. Paul Roh acted as host, and he was assisted by General Frederic Dent Grant of the Federal Army, Mr. W. M. R.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0914.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>French, Director of the Art Institute and the Belgian Consul, Mr. Charles Henrotin. Sixty ladies of the women's clubs of the Germania Society, the Fortnightly Club and other associations, comprising some of the best known ladies of Chicago Society, assisted with the reception.</p>
   <p>President Charles L. Hutchinson, in the name of the Board of Administration of the Art Institute sent the following cable to the German Emperor, who had authorized the exhibition of numerous art works from his collections and from the Royal Art Museum of Berlin. The telegram reads:</p>
   <p>"The Board of Administration of the Art Institute in Chicago takes the liberty of announcing the successful opening of the German Art exhibition and hopes that it will strengthen the good relations which already exist between these two great nations." The collection is housed on the first floor of the south wing of the Art Institute, and fills five rooms and one hall, in which the drawings and sketches found a place. The statues and monuments are distributed in the rooms. The collection can be inspected free on all days when no admission <pb facs="5418474_11_0915.jpg" n="3"/>is charged by the Institute, Wednesdays, Saturdays, Sundays and holidays; on all other days an admission fee of twenty-five cents is charged.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
