<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-04-17">Apr. 17, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Hans Balatka, Well-Known Orchestra Leader and Musician Dies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1593</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1593.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-04-17">Apr. 17, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">HANS BALATKA, WELL-KNOWN ORCHESTRA LEADER AND MUSICIAN DIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hans Balatka, the well-known leader and musician died last night, at his home, 216 Fremont Street, as the result of apoplexy. His life was that of a pioneer who established music in the Western part of America. Hans Balatka died in his 75th year. He was born in the German section of the province Maehren and enjoyed a thorough education. During the revolution of 1848 he studied law at Vienna, Austria. He was an enthusiastic supporter of the masses during the uprising, and, when it met with defeat, he fled, for obvious reasons, to the United States.</p>
   <p>He went to Milwaukee, and in the vicinity of that city, found temporary employment as a farm-hand. However, when it became known, that the young fugitive was an excellent Cellist endowed with profound musical knowledge, then his new friends induced him to dedicate himself to his art. This he did with genuine ambition, and his labors are still bearing fruit in Milwaukee today.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1594.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Balatka had been one of the founders of the Milwaukee Music Club and functioned for decades as the leader of this capable organization. Balatka also organized the first large orchestra of German-Athenae, by starting and eventually combining small groups. The first music-festivals, of the "West" were the results of his efforts and instigation. The great Song-Festivities of the 1869 period, which were held here, in Chicago, then Cincinnati, Pittsburgh, Indianapolis, Louisville and Quincy were directed by him. As early as 1860, Balatka was elected as leader of the local Phil-harmonic Society. After he settled permanently in Chicago, he founded the "Oratoria Society", and in 1867, the Germania Maennerchor" (Male Chorus), selected him as its leader. With this Club he succeeded in producing entire Operas and his name was heralded throughout the nation, as an orchestra director, of whom Chicago can be proud, but in the following years he had to content with enemies and that class of individuals who always begrudge greatness. Thus he lost a very substantial part of the field he had cultivated. Finally, he organized a music school, on his own initiative and capital, which thrived under his guidance and that of his children who are talented musicians.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1595.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In March, 1895, the German Singing Societies honored his 70th birthday, and during these festivities, he could say...in retrospect of his life; I am justly proud, and, after all, my efforts have not been in vain. The aged musician enjoyed great physical prowess and unimpaired mentality. Even during last year's Bismarck's Festival and a few weeks ago, at the German Protest Assembly, he conducted a large orchestra. Last year he suffered with la grippe, and the effects of this attack were probably responsible for his sudden demise. No definite arrangements have been made in regard to the funeral.</p>
   <p>His family, consisting of his widow and remaining children: Christian, Anton, Richard, Hans, Jr., and Annie expressed the wish, that the German Press Club, take charge of it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
