<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1871-02-03">Feb. 3, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">German Rejoicings</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1871-02-03">Feb. 3, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN REJOICINGS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans in Chicago are making preparations to celebrate, with festivities and rejoicings, the capitulation of Paris and the probable overthrow of the French Republic.</p>
   <p>If the Germans of Chicago, or of any other city of our country, are glad that the barbarous war waged by Germany against France, in the prosecution of which indescribable misery has been inflicted upon the people of both nations, will soon be brought to a close, all good men can understand such a cause for rejoicing.</p>
   <p>What German in Chicago today, rejoicing over the capitulation of Paris, will acknowledge that his countrymen are so dastardly and mean in spirit as to be afraid of a nation their inferior in numbers and strength? Are we to be called upon to admire the prowess of Germany, and at the same time be told that the Germans are afraid of a weaker people? When a nation has manifested its ability to wrest a province from a hostile power, is the possession of that province essential to the safety of the victor?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1064.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Conceding all that ought to be conceded to the ties of blood, and home, and love for the "fatherland" leading men to rejoice over fame and victory won by their countrymen, we say that for the Germans in this country to publicly celebrate with festivities the capitulation of Paris is to offer an insult to our native-born citizens; to declare that we are insensible to the most solemn obligations of gratitude; that we are glad because of the abject misery and distress of the people whose generosity has conferred blessings upon us; and that we rejoice to see self government extinguished in the blood of a gallant people.</p>
   <p>The friends of France in this city, and all those who sympathize with the national misfortunes of a heroic people, brought about by a struggle for free government, have now an opportunity for doing great practical good, furnished by the Producers' French Aid association. The movement suggested by the Prairie Farmer a short time since has already taken shape, and it places Chicago and Illinois first in the field in the noble purpose of supplying the French people with the agricultural assistance which they will require more than anything else. The meeting of the executive commit-tee of the association on Wednesday evening showed how general the desire has become to co-operate in this movement. Offers of money, time, contributions, facilities of transportation, store-room, etc., were so generous as to show that all which is now needed is harmony of action and good executive management.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1065.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The movement has no longer any partisan complexion, but it is a call for the relief of great suffering which should not and cannot be resisted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
