<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-09-02">Sep. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Ernest J. Kruetgen.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1234</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1234.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-09-02">Sep. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">ERNEST J. KRUETGEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wherever the German element gathers, either officially or unofficially, to act for a German affair, will be found the man who can be counted among the builders of Chicago, and this is Ernst Kruetgen.</p>
   <p>Kruetgen was born March 18, 1868 in Schleswig-Holstein, Germany, the son of Ernst and Dorothea Satz-Kruetgen. He came to the United States with his parents at an early age. The family settled in Chicago. The boy was instructed in the old Franklin School. At the age of 16 he became an apprentice at the Orcutt Lithographing Co. Three years later, he accepted a position as draftsman at a similar institution in Portland, Ore. Very soon the young draftsman attracted attention in lithographing circles, and so came to the firm Gugler of Milwaukee, which in those times was regarded as the first institution of the country.</p>
   <p>In 1902, Mr. Kruetgen started his own business. In 1922 he moved to new business quarters at 917-921 Franklin Blvd. That is the business man - Kruetgen. But he is better known as honorary president of the Chicago Singverein, whose president he was for 17 years, and as a former president of the Germania <pb facs="5418474_11_1235.jpg" n="2"/>Club. Furthermore, he is the president of the German group of the World's Exposition of 1933 and the representations committee for German affairs. He also is a member of many prominent German-American societies and clubs.</p>
   <p>Himself a great admirer of music he married in 1924 Anna Louise Lauer, who is well known in musical circles. Those who know Ernest Kruetgen's home, know him in the capacity of an art connoisseur. His collection of paintings contains many valuable pieces.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
