<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-02-18">Feb. 18, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Mystery Surrounds Death of Ferdinand B. Steindel.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1280</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1280.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-02-18">Feb. 18, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">MYSTERY SURROUNDS DEATH OF FERDINAND B. STEINDEL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ferdinand B. Steindel, well known among German-Americans as a pianist and orchestra leader, is no more. His tragic death will arouse sympathy among thousands, and their thoughts will go back to the days when Ferdinand Steindel's masterful piano playing brought them many hours of enjoyment.</p>
   <p>Many will also remember the times when under his direction tunes of German marches and valses resounded in the old Bismarck Garden, and when in the North Side Turner Hall the "Steindel Trio," Ferdinand, Max and Bruno, gave their concerts. Ferdinand Steindel jumped out of the window this morning from his apartment on the seventh floor of the Algonquin Hotel. His wife struggled in vain with him to prevent it.</p>
   <p>So far the police have been unable to disvover the motive, although Police Commissioner James Mooney is personally directing the investigation. Ferdinand Steindel and his brothers came to Chicago from Chemnitz, about 15 years ago. His uncle, a cellist known beyond the borders of America, was playing at that time with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, directed by Theodore Thomas.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1281.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The three brothers played, in the beginning, in Martin Ballman's orchestra, and later became independent as the Steindel Trio. They became well known on the North Side, and among friends of the Turner Hall concerts. Ferdinand Steindel, in later years, conducted the concerts in the Bismarck Garden and also undertook extensive journeys with his orchestra.</p>
   <p>He enjoyed a great reputation as a pianist. It was the Steindel Orchestra which at one time accompanied the premiere of the Fredericus Rex films in Orchestra Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
