<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-10-22">October 22, 1902</date><title level="a">A Moral Defeat</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0932</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0932.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-10-22">October 22, 1902</date><title level="a">A MORAL DEFEAT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Probably nobody thinks today of Samoa any more, but in the spring of 1899 this group of islands stood "in the foreground of public attention". Owing to the intrigues of Great Britain to which the U. S. A. were an easy victim, a serious conflict seemed to break out between these two powers on the one side and the German Empire on the other side, and the innocent cause of all was a half naked Samoan chieftain. But because the German government kept its calmness and the American government had to perceive that it couldn't risk a clash with Germany - and the loss of the German vote - on account of such a lousy consideration, the transaction was settled peacefully. It was agreed upon the division of the islands among the three powers, who had them so far more or less "protected", and left to King Oscar of Sweden the decision of the question whether the U. S. and Great Britain were entitled to land troops in Samoa and to let destroy numerous plantations in the surroundings of Apia. This arbitrator has now made the judgement, that "the Allies" proceeded in a totally unfair way and are therefore <pb facs="5418474_11_0933.jpg" n="2"/>obliged to make compensation. The latter amounts to at most $500,000, but the so-called American diplomacy takes its defeat very painfully. It can, in fact, be not very agreeable to them, to receive in front of the whole world the tesimony, that they went into a clumsy British trap.</p>
   <p>The Samoans after long years of disorders and wars had chosen as their head chieftain a certain Mataafa who was once before banished by Germany, but whom Germany now was willing to recognize. In spite of this the Superior Judge in Apia who was appointed by the three powers, accepted the English judgement, that Mataafa could not be elected, because he was once unsympathetic to the German government. When the Samoans opposed this decision against which also Germany protested, the English maintained that anarchy had broken out that had to be crushed by the power of arms. They induced the American Admiral Kautz, who in spite of his German origin stuck to the British and American enemies of Germany, to unite with them for a "punic expedition" against the pretended rebels. This was put under the leadership of a British officer and fell into an ambush. In vengeance the Allies carried on a true incendiarism and destroyed perticulary the plantations of the Germans, who in their opinion had stirred <pb facs="5418474_11_0934.jpg" n="3"/>the rebellion. Seemingly it was the intention of the British to incite the United States to war with Germany, and the Grand Republic entered into their plans, because they thought that the German Empire wants to use Samoa only as a base from which to conquer the Philippine Islands. However German diplomacy succeeded in overcoming British intrigues and to convince the United States of the groundlessness of their fears. To the unjust and needless property destruction, Germany did not want to submit outright, and the arbitrator agreed with her.</p>
   <p>With this the incident should be fully settled. When the American Jingo Press tries now to doubt the impartiality of King Oscar, this is a meanness for which there is no excuse. The King of Sweden is of course "a monarch", but that he should decide on this account against the Republic is nonsense because Great Britain against whom the decision is also directed, has a monarchical system of government too. Evidently his judgement is just, and the United States should learn from their moral defeat, that it is not good to be too much of a friend of the faithless Albion. For the rest, they possess the recognized <pb facs="5418474_11_0935.jpg" n="4"/>best part of the entire Samoan Islands, but they don't know what to do with it, while Germany has improved in every way its assigned part and has earned the highest satisfaction of the inhabitants. Germany does not look at her colonies as being mere toys.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
