<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-11">Apr. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">To His Last Resting Place</title><title level="a" type="sub">Heinrich Hochmeister Interred in Graceland Cemetery after Impressive Ceremony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1926-04-11">Apr. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">TO HIS LAST RESTING PLACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Heinrich Hochmeister Interred in Graceland Cemetery after Impressive Ceremony</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Heinrich Hochmeister found his last resting place in Graceland Cemetery yesterday, after the funeral rites in the family home, 4512 North Robey Street. The rites testified to the popularity and the respect which the deceased had enjoyed among his friends and acquaintances.</p>
   <p>The rooms in the family home seemed not large enough to contain all the numerous mourners. The ceremony was opened by Heinrich Michelsen of the Deutscher Kriegerverein (German War Veterans' Association), who paid homage to the dead. With moving words, bearing proof of the wide gap which Hochmeister's death has made in the ranks of Chicago's German-Americans, the speaker described Hochmeister's activities in behalf of his German compatriots during his many years in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1338.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was a true friend of all who turned to him for aid. In his political career, especially, he was always mindful of the interests of his fellow Germans. Then Mr. Michelsen recalled Mr. Hochmeister's glorious deeds in the old fatherland, his heroic exploits in the war of 1870-71, in which he so distinguished himself that he received the Iron Cross. He also spoke of his services to German education, which brought him the rare reward of the cross of the Knights of the Order of the Red Eagle.</p>
   <p>Then, in the name of the Schlaraffia Chicagoana, Oscar Ruh said farewell to the dead. Members of the Schlaraffia, present in large numbers, with a last "Lulu" (Cradle song), laid red and white flowers on the breast of the departed. With this the ceremony in the home came to a close. Members of the Lessing Lodge were the pallbearers.</p>
   <p>In the chapel of the Graceland Cemetery there was later a funeral ceremony in accordance with the ritual of the Free Masons, conducted by Past Master Hermann Grau.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
