<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-02-20">Feb. 20, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">The "City Hall" Democrats and Altgeld's First Campaign Speech</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-02-20">Feb. 20, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">THE "CITY HALL" DEMOCRATS AND ALTGELD'S FIRST CAMPAIGN SPEECH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mayoralty candidate, John Peter Altgeld, opened his campaign officially, on Saturday evening. The large hall of the People's Institute was filled, not a vacant chair available, when the former Governor appeared on the rostrum to expound his program. He was greeted with jubilant acclaim and the audience followed his remarks with rapt attention. In the first part of his speech, the mayoral candidate gave detailed accounts of the present era's most obvious problems', the Trusts and Concentration of Capital, which corrupts all national, state and municipal administrations. This can be changed and the situation improved, if the people themselves own and control the monopolies for the common welfare. This has especial reference to the recently highly disputed street-car question. With that Altgeld steered very adroitly into the proper channel and now followed a tirade against his archenemy, Carter H. Harrison. He accuses him of double-crossing, in regard to the street car problem, refers to the administration of the civil-service law, <pb facs="5418474_11_1602.jpg" n="2"/>as a humbug of the first magnitude, that the money appropriated for the street cleaning department is wasted in a shameful manner and finds its way into the political coffers where its use is reserved for party purposes. For all this, he considered Harrison as being directly responsible. Under his regime we cannot expect a change, since the present members of the city hall are concerned only with their own welfare.</p>
   <p>Altgeld closed his campaign speech as follows: "I am often asked, why I do not seek the regular party nomination. How could this benefit me, since the City Hall clique still controls the nominations and proceeds in conformity to its own pleasure and choice? Besides, I am not especially desirous of occupying the mayor's office. I am fighting for the realization of great principles, for the introduction of measures, which will help the present and benefit the next generation. I do not appeal to the near-sighted party spirit of some people, nor do I expect political favors from anyone. I invoke the intelligence, patriotism, and the honesty of our population, I beseech them to <pb facs="5418474_11_1603.jpg" n="3"/>thoroughly study the important events of the day and then give a conscientious decision. I can only give assurance to the people, that all the miserable activities which heretofore have been a disgrace to our city, will cease, if I am elected as mayor."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
