<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-26">Jan. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Reverend Pister Released from His Great Suffering</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, one column-eighth of a page, front view of Reverend Pister]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-26">Jan. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">REVEREND PISTER RELEASED FROM HIS GREAT SUFFERING</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, one column-eighth of a page, front view of Reverend Pister]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Grant Hospital Reverend Jacob Pister, pastor of St. Paul's Evangelical Lutheran Church, passed away after great suffering from an inflammation of the lungs with severe complications. He succumbed to the disease only after he had made a gallant effort to recover.</p>
   <p>The funeral will take place on Monday afternoon. From four o'clock Sunday afternoon until half past one on Monday the body will lie in state in St. Paul's Church. On Monday, at one thirty, the funeral will begin. After the funeral the body will be taken to the Memorial Park Cemetery.</p>
   <p>The deceased was born November 20, 1869, in Baltimore, Ohio. His father, Jacob Pister, Sr., was a pastor and president of the Synod. Because of his father's <pb facs="5418474_11_1109.jpg" n="2"/>calling it was foreordained, from his earliest youth, that he would enter the service of the church, to which he devoted all his energy for the forty-three years of his active life as a minister.</p>
   <p>He studied for the ministry at Concordia Seminary, in Elmhurst, and at Eden Seminary, in St. Louis, Missouri, and was ordained on November 16, 1890. He devoted the first years of his life as a minister to rather small congregations in Ripley, Ohio, and Kenton, Ohio. He was then called to St. John's Church in Columbus, Ohio. Herbert, the brother of the deceased, is now pastor of the Kenton congregation.</p>
   <p>In August, 1891, Reverend Jacob Pister married Pauline Guckenberger. Their happy marriage was blessed with four children, Harold, Eugene, Theodosia, and Dorothea, all of whom are now married. The younger generation is represented by four grandchildren.</p>
   <p>In 1911 Reverend Pister became pastor of St. Paul's Church in this city, and thus <pb facs="5418474_11_1110.jpg" n="3"/>found a new field of activity in which he could exercise to the full his ability to further the Christian faith. Reverend R. John was pastor of the congregation at that time. Reverend Pister was named associate pastor, and worked for fourteen years with Reverend John in this capacity.</p>
   <p>The years in which these two pastors worked together were the golden age of St. Paul's Church, the congregation of which continually grew in numbers. The German choir and the general choir of the Church owe much of their progress to the indefatigible efforts of Reverend Pister. In the middle of the campaign for a new building for the Uhlich Orphan Home, in 1925, Reverend John suddenly resigned, and Reverend Pister attempted to resign soon afterwards. On the third Sunday in January, 1926, on the anniversary of the founding of the Church, special services were held in honor of Reverend John, upon the occasion of his departure. Reverend Pister was selected by the congregation as his successor, and entered upon his new office in February of the same year. The years that passed after he became pastor are a shining witness to his activity as a leader <pb facs="5418474_11_1111.jpg" n="4"/>of one of the most important congregations in the whole Synod. It was thanks to his tireless energy that the congregation collected more than two hundred thousand dollars for Church purposes during the first four years that he was pastor. Missions were sent to the Orient, and, after the trustees of the Church had been relieved of the responsibility of St. Paul's House, the congregation was able to devote its whole attention to furthering the interests of the Uhlich Orphan Home. In 1929 the council of the Church decided to appoint Dr. George L. Scherger associate pastor. Since that time the two have worked together with the greatest harmony and co-operation.</p>
   <p>Toward the end of last year, on November 12, 1933, the deceased had the privilege of celebrating, with his congregation, the ninetieth anniversary of St. Paul's Church, and to receive, from near and far, congratulations upon the loyalty and affection of his congregation.</p>
   <p>In Reverend Pister we have lost a man whose high qualities, both as a human being and as a minister, earned the greatest respect of all who came in contact with him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
