<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-11-14">Nov. 14, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">President of North German Lloyd Reports Increase in Capital and German Navigation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0777</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0777.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-11-14">Nov. 14, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT OF NORTH GERMAN LLOYD REPORTS INCREASE IN CAPITAL AND GERMAN NAVIGATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An interesting report about the development of German navigation in general, and of the North German Lloyd in particular, was given by its president, Dr. Phil Heineken, to a representative of the Sonntagspost, who called on him at the offices of the Lloyd. Mr. Heineken, for a number of years general manager of the company, has been for about a year, president of this great German navigation line. At first glance it can be seen, that he is one of the old Hauseatic men. He arrived in New York for a short visit on October 22nd, with the steamer "Columbus," and stopped last week in Chicago, where he was introduced to a number of prominent citizens by Mr. Ludwig Plate, manager of the general agency of the Lloyd, in Chicago. He regretted very much, that he was unable to meet Mayor Dever, personally, while in our city.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0778.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Heineken gave the representative of the Sonntagspost an outline of German navigation of today, and stated, that the prospects for next year were not unfavorable.</p>
   <p>"The North German Lloyd," he continued, "has, only lately at a meeting of the superintending committee, decided to propose at the general meeting on December 2nd, an increase in its capital of 50,000,000 marks of common shares, and 1,500,000 marks of preferred shares. Through this increase the company will have regained its pre-war capital of 125,000,000 goldmark."</p>
   <p>An increase in capital was desirable, he declared because it would make it possible to build up the Bremen-New York service still more. Dr. Heineken further said, that the company intends to build a sister ship to Germany's largest and most beautiful merchant-steamer, the "Columbus." The general popularity which the "Columbus" has enjoyed, since its launching in 1924, justifies the building of a sister ship.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0779.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Asked by our reporter, whether the rumors, which appeared a few weeks ago, of a possible merger of the North German Lloyd with the Hamburg-America line, were true, Dr. Heineken replied, that the report of the formation of a trust by the two lines, has been officially denied by Bremen as well as Hamburg. Mr. Heineken left yesterday afternoon for New York, and will return to Bremen on November 20th, on the Lloyd steamer "Stuttgart."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
