<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-23">Dec. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Do We Need Immigrants?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-23">Dec. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">DO WE NEED IMMIGRANTS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Undoubtedly there is a shortage of labor in our country, especially in the field of agriculture; and the need for labor is no less acute for the performance of the so-called "low-class" jobs, such as building roads, repair of railroads, ditch-digging--in short, ordinary day labor.</p>
   <p>Very few employers entertain the illusion that this labor shortage will cease when our boys return from Europe. Instead, the latter will probably try to get back into the same type of employment which they gave up, temporarily, when they were called to the colors. Only a very small number of them were day laborers, and military service will hardly have created any propensity to turn to this lowly work to make a living. As a matter of fact, the work which is designated as "cheap manual labor" has for decades been assigned to newly-arrived immigrants. Lumberjacks, <pb facs="5418474_11_0459.jpg" n="2"/>builders of streets and roads, have opened new paths to civilization which the natives have used to expand their industrial and commercial enterprises, to establish banks and engage in real-estate speculations. And even today the demand for "cheap labor" is just as great as ever, especially in factories, foundries, stone quarries, mines, etc., and there is no appreciable supply on hand. This is so not only because immigration came to a stop at the beginning of the war, but also--and primarily--because, as stated by the Manufacturers' Association, "The children of immigrants will not do the kind of work their parents did, and most of them are not physically capable of doing it".</p>
   <p>In view of this situation it seems strange, indeed, that all sorts of obstacles are put in the way of immigration, such as head taxes, educational tests, and so on. It is not necessary to sing a song of praise here for the things which the European accustomed to hard physical labor has done for the development of our country, by opening up and settling large areas, strengthening our industry and commerce, building highways, <pb facs="5418474_11_0460.jpg" n="3"/>and other things. The United States has become what it is today almost exclusively by means of immigrant labor. Any unjustified limitation of immigration, born of hatred for aliens or of economic rivalry, will prove to be a great hindrance for the further development and growth of this great republic. A deliberate discouragement of immigration seems all the less justified in view of the fact that the European nations will, very probably, enact laws to prohibit the emigration of their nationals. There will not be an avalanche of "greenhorns" after peace has been declared, but there will be a decided demand for them. The following statistics of immigration contain a lesson which even the most shortsighted alien-baiter would do well to heed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0461.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Yearly Immigration</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1902 - 1911 (on the average)</cell>
     <cell>918,605</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1912</cell>
     <cell>838,172</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1913</cell>
     <cell>1,197,892</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1914</cell>
     <cell>1,218,480</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1915</cell>
     <cell>326,700</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1916</cell>
     <cell>298,826</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1917</cell>
     <cell>295,403</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1918 (future estimate)</cell>
     <cell>200,000</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The war has not decreased the demand for immigrant labor. Its opponents may well be reminded of the parable of the goose that lays the golden eggs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
