<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-01-11">Jan. 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Testament of a Philanthropist.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Peter Schoenhofen bequeathes Money to Many Institutions. More than $70,000 for Charity.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1759</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1759.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-01-11">Jan. 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE TESTAMENT OF A PHILANTHROPIST.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Peter Schoenhofen bequeathes Money To Many Institutions. More than $70,000 for Charity.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge Kohlsaat passed upon the testament of the late Peter Schoenhofen, brewery owner, yesterday, in Probate Court. The fortune is estimated at $2,000,000, personal property amounts to $175,000, the remainder is in real estate. The executors are Messrs. Carl Buehl and Joseph Theurer, the sons-in-law of the deceased; their bond is $4,000,000. Schoenhofen's testament contains a wealth of detail and proves, that his well known benevolent tendencies were not founded on hear-say, since he made most liberal provisions for many charitable institutions. Mrs. Elise Schoenhofen, the widow, is given an annuity from the entire income, with the exception of the participation bonds of the deceased which are the controlling interest of his breweries. Mrs. Schoenhofen is given authority to use her money for real estate improvements, to lend it, etc. After her demise, the money is to be equally divided amongst his children.</p>
   <p>His numerous and large legacies to philanthropic institutions are further proof of Mr. Schoenhofen's humanity. We append the list.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1760.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Frauvenverein Des Deutschen Altenheim, (Ladies Association of the German Home for the Aged.)</cell>
     <cell>$10,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Alexian Brothers Hospital</cell>
     <cell>10,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Chicago Findelhaus (Foundling's Home)</cell>
     <cell>3,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>United Hebrew Charities</cell>
     <cell>3,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Old People's Home</cell>
     <cell>3,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Home For Incurables</cell>
     <cell>2,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Ephreta School For The Deaf and Dumb, 409 May St., provided that the above institution was incorporated</cell>
     <cell>3,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Newsboy's and Bootblack's Association</cell>
     <cell>2,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>American Educational Aid Association</cell>
     <cell>2,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Home for the Friendless</cell>
     <cell>2,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Chicago Orphan Asylum</cell>
     <cell>2,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>German Hospital</cell>
     <cell>8,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>German Catholic Orphanage of Rosehill</cell>
     <cell>8,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Little Sisters of the Poor</cell>
     <cell>3,000.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>From this long list of benevolent institutions which have all been remembered <pb facs="5418474_11_1761.jpg" n="3"/>by Mr. Schoenhofen, it is evident that his humaneness knows neither creed nor nationality. The testament also contains the following provision. His sons-in-law shall invest $2,000 and the interest obtained therefrom, is to be paid to the president of the Sick Benefit Association of Peter Schoenhofen's brewery employees, provided that the club is incorporated; if not, then it shall be paid to the benefit of his employees. A sum of $3,000 is also to be invested similarly by the administrators; the proceeds shall accrue to a Hospital or Orphanage in Cook County, which is dedicated to the Austrian or Bohemian born element, or their descendants. Evidently, the testator believed, that such an institution would be founded. If the above organization does not come into an incorporated existence within three years, then the provision will be void.</p>
   <p>About Schoenhofen's Brewery bonds, i. e. the shares which the deceased owned, Miss Lillie Schoenhofen, is to be given 15,740 pounds sterling, in English bonds and stocks, when she is twenty years old. The remainder of the brewery bonds shall be equally distributed amongst the widow and the children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
