<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-28">February 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Friedrich Wilhelm Schmidt</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-28">February 28, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FRIEDRICH WILHELM SCHMIDT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the ripe old age of 87 years and 6 months, one of our best known and generally esteemed German citizens, Mr. Friedrich Wilhelm Schmidt, died yesterday. He lived in the United States since December 1848, and since 1857 in Chicago. He was born in Wolfersschwenda, Schwarzburg, Souderhausen, August 13, 1826. He received a good education, and being gifted with musical talents, he, upon his own request, was thoroughly educated as a musician, so that after finishing his studies, he could always obtain a position in a good orchestra, as a violinist, clarinet or cornet player.</p>
   <p>For a short time he had to fulfill his military duties, but as a musician in the band. After that he came to America, went first to New Orleans, later to St. Louis and Cincinnati, and acquired for himself the name of an excellent clarinet, and cornet player, and also directed bands on several occasions.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1471.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the year 1857, the deceased accepted the honourable position as leader of the Great Western Band, in Chicago, with which he made successful concert tours. He, continued as a musician, but having suffered a paralytic stroke in 1864, cound not use his lips any more and therefore played only the violin. Previously he started a wine and liquor business, wholesale, in partnership with Ferdinand Crawer, a brother of his wife, under the name of Schmidt and Crawer, and later conducted under the name of Schmidt and Laves, which however was discontinued in 1896. Since then, he retired to private life.</p>
   <p>The deceased was the third oldest member of the German Freemason Lodge Germania, A. F. A. M. He would have celebrated his 50 year jubilee in May, as Master Mason. The still vivacious old gentleman had the misfortune, to fall and suffer a fractured hip, from which came pneumonia, and in spite of the most devoted nursing, recovery was impossible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
