<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-06-13">June 13, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">German Officials Guests of Sanitary Commission.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0738</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0738.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-06-13">June 13, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN OFFICIALS GUESTS OF SANITARY COMMISSION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A number of prominent German engineers and scientists arrived yesterday on an inspection journey from Indianapolis, and registered at the Bismarck Hotel. The gentlemen, all of whom occupy high positions in Germany's sanitary and drainage administrations, have as their objective the study of sanitary and drainage facilities in America.</p>
   <p>During a trip through the plants of the Chicago Sanitary district, they decided to visit also the Calumet district. Tomorrow, the Sanitary District, under its president, T. J. Crowe, will give a luncheon at the Bismarck Hotel in honor of the guests, to which representatives of the Chicago German element have been invited.</p>
   <p>Following are the names of the prominent guests: Privy Counselor Dr. Max Beninde, President of the Prussian Board of Health, Berlin, and his co-worker, Professor Bernhard Burger; Dr. Ing. h. c. Heinrich Helbing, Essen, Dr. Ing. Mix Pruss Essen, Fritz Langbein, director of canals, Berlin; Karl Fehring Moers of Rhine, Fritz Mieder Leipsic, Dr. Willy Hilland Bitterfeld, and Otto Mohr from the canalization board in Wiesbaden.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0739.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The delegation today visited the west side plants of the sanitary district, and the big factory of the Corn Products Co. in Argo, Illinois, where they were luncheon guests of the directors. Privy counselor Dr. Beninde said after inspecting the large north side plant, which had started to work last August: "This is without doubt the most modern plant of the world, and the largest one I have ever seen. I must congratulate Chicago upon its sanitary facilities."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
