<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title>,
<date when="1901-01-27">Jan. 27, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Well-Known Chicagoans</title><title level="a" type="sub">Citizens who Helped Build the Metropolis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title>,
<date when="1901-01-27">Jan. 27, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">WELL-KNOWN CHICAGOANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Citizens who Helped Build the Metropolis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Charles Gamer, foreign-born Chicagoan who figures prominently in the history of Chicago, fought for his adopted country during the Civil War. He was a valiant soldier and earned laurels in the battlefield. After the War Gamer left the army and soon after began to acquire a reputation for himself in the business world. As a Chicagoan, he never failed to show profound interest in the welfare of the rapidly developing city.</p>
   <p>Gamer left Baden, his birthplace, and came to Chicago in 1861. Soon after his arrival here he joined Hecker's forces and fought as an enthusiastic American to further the unification of his new fatherland, taking an active part in every struggle which involved his regiment.</p>
   <p>In 1867 he became a partner of Koenig in the firm of Koenig and Gamer, a furniture manufacturing concern the success of which, as well as its reputation <pb facs="5418474_11_1557.jpg" n="2"/>for fair dealing and reliability, which have reached far beyond the confines of Chicago, is due in a great measure to his business perspicacity and ability.</p>
   <p>The esteem which Mr. Gamer enjoyed among other furniture manufacturing concerns is best shown by the fact that he was elected president of the Chicago Furniture Manufacturers Association and chairman of the National Furniture Manufacturers Association. His comrades at arms elected him repeatedly as Commander of Hancock Post, of the Grand Army of the Republic.</p>
   <p>Although Mr. Gamer refused on several occasions to run as candidate for public office, he nevertheless was always willing to play a passive role in the way of giving his much sought advice to party members.</p>
   <p>Citizens from his Ward, as well as citizens from the North Side where he has been living for a long time, mentioned him repeatedly as a possible Lincoln Park Commissioner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
