<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-06-13">June 13th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Franz Amberg dead. One of Chicago's Well-Known Germans Departed.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>DIE ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1910-06-13">June 13th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Franz Amberg dead. One of Chicago's Well-Known Germans Departed.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Franz Amberg, 73 years of age died yesterday at his home, 507 Throop Street. For a half century he was a great leader in German affairs, his ambition and ability will be missed by all. He was born at Oberndorf, in the district of Aschaffenburg, where he was a cart-wright, learning the trade in his home town. He came to Chicago in 1857, where his uncle had settled previously in 1833. He proved to be a valuable addition to the German element, which at that time had a "hard row to hoe." He was a diligent, accomplished singer and became associated with the Frein Saenger Bunde ( Liberal Singing Association,) besides, the vital political questions of the day proved to be of absorbing interest to him. When the Civil War was declared he joined the first cavalry regiment, which the State of Illinois organized for the Union Army and that he was valiant indeed, need hardly be mentioned. After that fratricidal quarrel he returned to Chicago and started a feed-store. About 1875 he became the owner of a livery stable, which he operated constantly. He was a co-founder of the Orpheus Song Club and started the organization "Male Choruses" <pb facs="5418474_11_1485.jpg" n="2"/>which participated in the great song festival of the North American Song-Association in 1881. In recognition of his accomplishments his was elected honorary member by the North American Song Association at their festival in Indianapolis, an honor which has never been bestowed upon anybody heretofore. He was also active in politics. Even in this branch he acquired recognition and success. For many years he was a member of the advisory board of the State Prison at Joilet; in 1889 he was elected City Recorded and two years later. Mayor Washburn appointed him to the post of City Collector. In 1892 the Republican party nominated him to the office of State Treasurer. That year, as we know, was not auspicious for the Republicans; Mr. Amberg greatly surpassed his rivals as far as votes are concerned but even he could not quite reach the goal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
