<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-11-27">Nov. 27, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">John M. Faulhaber.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1642</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1642.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-11-27">Nov. 27, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN M. FAULHABER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The apprehension, which the Abendpost in its Wednesday number expressed, has been confirmed; the well-known wine merchant John M. Faulhaber, died in the Alexian Brothers hospital, night before last, from the effects of a self inflicted wound, which he committed in desperation over the ruin of his business. Mr. Faulhaber, was only 53 years old. That he was not able to place himself above the losses he sustained in the last few years, and to trust in a more prosperous future, finds its explanation in the fact, that he suffered reverses and became unable to with stand the hard knocks of fate. Emigrating in 1865 to the United States, he settled four years later in Chicago. He worked for a short time in several taverns, but established himself already in the fall in his own business, and for this purpose brought his brother Joseph, over from Germany to assist him in it. The enterprise became quickly successful till the big fire ruined him totally. Till the year 1875, he managed a tavern, on Halsted near Dusold Street, and later on at the corner of Van Buren and Canal Streets, in which he acquired the means to found a wine business, which made his name so well known. In the last years, owing to prevailing hard times, the business went from bad to worse, and Mr. Faulhaber decided, not to survive the inevitable bankruptcy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
