<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-04-22">April 22, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">An Inestimable, Scientific Work of a Chicagoan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1790</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1790.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-04-22">April 22, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">AN INESTIMABLE, SCIENTIFIC WORK OF A CHICAGOAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The editorial staff of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung had an opportunity recently to examine a scientific work of inestimable value. We refer to the eighty sheets containing 1005 illustrations in water color portraying all of kind of birds on the North-American continent.</p>
   <p>In order to more fully understand the scientific importance of this work we point out, that the only authentic work, recognized by science is Audubon's Birds of America. The third edition of this work appeared in 1865; it was soon sold out, and a copy recently sold for $1600.00. However, that work contains only 435 illustrations, but the one before us pictures 1005 different kinds of birds, or one picture of each kind of birds.</p>
   <p>Not long ago a similar work was published, edited by a Mr. Jasper. That volume contained nine hundred illustrations, but it was criticized as being inaccurate. Another excellent work by Nehrling is exceedingly valuable for students but it is not complete.</p>
   <p>The work submitted to us claims to be absolutely complete and exhaustive, to contain <pb facs="5418474_11_1791.jpg" n="2"/>every known bird in North-America, to picture them accurately, and to give the exact scientific terms. It is therefore indispensable for every lover of birds and every student of ornithology.</p>
   <p>The originator and author of this work is Dr. Carl Helmuth, the eminent German physician and zoologist of Chicago, who has worked at it incessantly for fourteen years. Before he studied medicine he was devoted to the study of zoology and studied under Lichtenstein in Berlin. At one time he possessed a splendid collection of North American birds in his home, but the Chicago Fire destroyed it. He started the described work in 1878 which is now complete and ready to be printed. It would cost about $40,000.00 to publish, but it is regrettable that the seventy-six year old physician and scientist is not able to finance it from his own resources.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
