<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-11-12">Nov. 12, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">John Koelling Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1292</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1292.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-11-12">Nov. 12, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN KOELLING DIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. John Koelling, former proprietor of the well known German bookstore at 206 W. Randolph Street, died suddenly in Pensacola, Florida.</p>
   <p>He had just recently retired from the management of the bookstore on account of poor health as it had become impossible for him to supervise the steadily growing business. He moved with his family to Perdido Beach, Alabama, whence he was taken to the hospital in Pensacola several days ago. The funeral will be held in Pensacola next Monday.</p>
   <p>John Koelling was born 65 years ago in Hamburg, Germany, the son of the well known musician Carl Koelling. Very early he developed a talent for music; but he was also a so-called "bookworm."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1293.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1880 he emigrated to the United States and came to Chicago where he worked first in the bookstore of Flota and Meininger and after that in several other similar stores, until about 30 years ago he founded the bookstore of Koelling and Klappenbach. Thus he made his living while promoting at the same time the cause of Germanism and furthering German culture.</p>
   <p>His spare time he devoted to gymnastics and to music. He was a member of the Chicago Turner Society for many years and also belonged to the Chicago Choral Society. Wherever Germans assembled to pay homage to their native land, Koelling was present.....</p>
   <p>He is survived and mourned by his widow, Bertha, his son, Herbert; and his two daughters, Mrs. Elsa Marie Klages and Miss Dorothea Koelling.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
