<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-04-12">April 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Words of Praise</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0307</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0307.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-04-12">April 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">WORDS OF PRAISE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The importance of Germanism in the country's development. Lecture by Professor M. D. Learned. The well-known scholar illustrated the influence of the Germans upon American civilization. Pioneering also in agriculture and industry.</p>
   <p>A comprehensive picture of the German people's influence upon the development of the American people was sketched yesterday by Professor M. D. Learned from the State University of Pennsylvania, in a lecture on the theme: "The German in the North-American civilization," at the meeting of the German Historical Association of Illinois. This influence has, as Professor Learned, who studied the German elements in the United States thoroughly explained, made itself felt on all domains, commerce and industry, particularly on intellectual grounds, in religion, education and politics. Of course, the importance of the Germans in developing the country, has never been made the object of special investigation, and therefore is not fully appreciated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0308.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The German Americans, even more so than the Americans, should never forget the fact, that America is the home of 30 million, probably 40 million people, in whose veins German blood flows," Professor Learned pointed out. The Americans point with pride to their history. " It would be far better, if nine tenths of this history had never been written, because it does not contain anything, which might help to enlighten and instruct the people."</p>
   <p>Instead, all the contributions which the German element and settler, made for the flourishing of the country's culture, should find a place in American History works. The development of a great people's culture is a very interesting field of research for the Historian, because in the start of a nation are hidden the roots of its character and its adjustment." "How would it stand with German History nowadays, if we would not possess knowledge of the culture, which the German people took over from the Romans, Gauls, Anglo-Saxons and Greeks?"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0309.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The German historian knows of no greater pleasure than to find new facts, which assisted in the foundation of German culture. In a similar way, England dates its civilization back to the cultural life of several nations. The Romans, Celts, Mormans and Germans have all contributed to thecultural development of the English people, and the aim of all of England's modern historians is directed, to open all fountains of knowledge, about the life of the original races of England, to its people. "How different is the bearing of the American historian towards our own development, and the beginning of our culture. No nation on earth has the blood of so many nations in the veins, as the Americans. The English puritan, Seigneur and felon, the Welsh,Irish, Scotch, African Negro, Swedes and Scandinavians, the Spaniard, Frenchmen Hugnenot, Portugese, German, Hungarian, Slav, Russian, Russian Jews and other Jews, Italian, Greek, Armenian, Chinese, Japanese, and whatever else they might be called have all contributed to the remarkable mixture of races...as we call the American people.</p>
   <p>These elements in our American system, are not perchance subjects of archeological inquisitiveness, but formative factors in the life and culture of our people, and they demand the attention of every historian.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0310.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The fact, that the old Hollanderism of New Holland disappeared from the everyday life, does not mean, that the cultural influence, which was exercised upon the American life by the Hollanders, has now totally subsided. On the contrary, it only begins now to bear fruits, as we may observe in our president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
