<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1875-02-02">Feb. 2, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">A Little Difficulty between a German Church and His Pastor.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1875-02-02">Feb. 2, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">A LITTLE DIFFICULTY BETWEEN A GERMAN CHURCH AND HIS PASTOR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An adjourned meeting of the Chicago presbytery was held at their rooms, in the McCormick block, yesterday afternoon. The Rev. Dr. Jacob Post, of the Holland Church, opened the meeting. The first German Church.</p>
   <p>The Rev. Mr. Trowbridge of the committee on home missions, presented a statement of the financial condition of the first German church, of which the Rev. C. Wisner is pastor.</p>
   <p>They stand by their pastor.</p>
   <p>The following series of resolutions were submitted by Elder Saalfeldt, with a request that the presbytery take some action upon the matter:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Resolved, First, that from a full knowledge of our people among whom we, as a church organization, are located, and in view of what we are constrained to believe to be for our own spiritual and religious instruction and edification as a church, we therefore hold and intend to continue as the First German Presbyterian church of Chicago, and to adhere to our present mode of divine worship, in our own German language, rather than in English, which, for such a purpose at least, we do not understand.</p>
   <p>Resolved, Second, that we are from occupying an anti-American position, nor do we harbor an anti-Anglican spirit, but rather appreciate all that is good and noble in America, and in the English language; hence we find to when circumstances change, and the state of society with us requires it, we , ourselves, are ready and willing to introduce English religious services, in wise, practical proportions. For any Christian or Christian philanthropist to ask more of us, seems to us to be asking too much.</p>
   <p>Resolved, Third, that we, led by our experience, do put such a high value upon the personal and ministerial character and labors of the Rev. Christian Wisner, our pastor, that we cannot consent to his being asked by several of the Sunday-school teachers to resign, but we, on the contrary, do heartily and unanimously desire and request his continuance with us.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0060.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Resolved, Fourth, that Mr. E. A. Saulfeldt, ruling elder in our church, together with our minister, the Rev. C. Wisner, be especially requested to present these statements and resolutions to the Presbytery of Chicago, with our hopeful prayers that these questions and issues find a candid consideration, and wise decision, so that the glory of our exalted Savior be promoted.</p>
   <p>Prof. Francis L. Patton objected to listening to the complaint of the Sunday-school teachers of the church, as a bad precedent would thus be made, which would go on record, and cause endless trouble in the future. He was opposed to placing the Sunday School on a equal footing with the members of the church, in such a matter.</p>
   <p>Rev. Mr. Wisner stated that he had laid the matter before the presbytery because he had been asked to resign by the members of the Sunday school. He was willing to abide by the decision of the presbytery, but he did not believe that preaching in the English language would successfully supplant the preaching in German.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0061.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He hoped the presbytery would not decide the matter hastily, and he spoke doubtfully of the result of an attempt to Americanize the church. He was afraid that the adoption of the report would break up the church. Dr. Mitchell dwelt in highly complementary terms on the work being done by the church, and was of opinion that the report was the best that could be made under the circumstances.</p>
   <p>Dr. Elliott said that Mr. Wisner had been of great assistance to the church and had done a good deal of work for them. He regarded this attempt to drive their pastor away as highly discreditable. The place of worship could not be maintained if he was forced to resign, and the labor of Mr. Wisner would be thrown away. No one with greater energy and ability could be found than Mr. Wisner, and the work could only be done by a German.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
