<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-07-02">July 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Recognition of the Chicago Germans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-07-02">July 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">RECOGNITION OF THE CHICAGO GERMANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Germans can be justly proud of the fact that they were permitted to play a prominent and honorable part in the founding of a National German-American Central Organization. This is not loose praise but an expression of gratitude which the actions of the leaders of the Chicago Germans, earned for them from Mr. Adolph Timm, former secretary of the National Union, who, even now, is the guiding spirit of the whole movement. Mr. Timm's letter is addressed to the editor of the Abendpost, but because it has an interest for all German speaking inhabitants of Chicago, we feel that it should be published.</p>
   <p>Philadelphia,</p>
   <p>June 30, 1931.</p>
   <p>To The Editor of the Abendpost, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>My Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>Permit us to thank the editor and publisher of the Abendpost, for the initiative <pb facs="5418474_11_0708.jpg" n="2"/>they took, in the preparation of a meeting for the establishment of a National organization on Oct. 24th &amp; 25th. This was a step in the right direction.</p>
   <p>Among the names of those who called the meeting, were many whom I do not know, but I also read the names of gallant comrades-in-arms of prewar days. I was particularly pleased that president Rixmann of the Chicago Citizens Union, whom I met in Pittsburgh, was present at the preliminary meeting and that everything works harmoniously.</p>
   <p>That the meeting is going to be held in the peasant room of the Bismarck Hotel, reminds one of the cheerful hours, which I spent with old Mr. Muller, and my dear deceased friend Ferdinand Walther, after serious deliberations in that locality. There and in the Bavarian Seppl friend Walther was a habitue.</p>
   <p>I am convinced, that the Germans of Chicago will follow the invitation to the meeting on Wednesday July 22, in a representative way, but would like to speak a few words through your newspaper to the German youth and tell them, that the Abendpost has always interceded in favor of the interests of the German-Americans. That this takes place in a quiet, solid way, free from every sensation, is the merit of the German speaking press.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0709.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I am pleased that Chicago has been selected as the foundation place of the National Organization of German-Americans, and that I was permitted to participate in the upbuilding of same.</p>
   <p>Thanking you and the Abendpost for previous and further co-operation, I remain</p>
   <p>Sincerely Yours,</p>
   <p>Adolph Timm</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
