<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-06-15">June 15, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Georg Schneider's Attacks Repulsed.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0180</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0180.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-06-15">June 15, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">MR. GEORG SCHNEIDER'S ATTACKS REPULSED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the editor of the Illinois Staats Zeitung: Kindly permit me to use your paper as a medium to repel attacks made upon me by Mr. Georg Schneider in his organ the German Abendblatt. I wish through your paper to reach my voters whom Mr. Schneider tries to persuade "I have broken my pledge to them". Mr. Georg Schneider is spreading insinuating remarks that I opposed his appointment as American charge d' affaires to Switzerland, in spite of which he received the appointment and could have assumed the office if he had chosen to. These assertions are entirely wrong. I did not lift a finger of opposition previous to his appointment, but not because I complied with his wishes sent to me by telegraph to Washington, but because I found his aspirations to join the diplomatic corps ridiculous and could not believe even in my wildest dreams, that a government which pledged itself to the reform of civil service could make the mistake of appointing a man of his caliber to become a member of the United States diplomatic embassy in Bern, and thereby submit that accredited diplomatic corps to ridicule. But when the evening papers of April the 20th brought the news that the government is about to appoint him as the successor to that very able diplomat Horace Rublee <pb facs="5418474_11_0181.jpg" n="2"/>who so excellently represented our government at Bern for eight long years, I immediately sent a wire to Mr. Evarts in Washington requesting him to withhold the appointment until a letter from me reaches him. It was too late; before my telegram reached Mr. Evarts, Mr. Schneider had been appointed to that post at a cabinet session. In said letter I warned against his appointment on the grounds of his incompetency as consul to Helsinger. This was and still is my conviction. Our government endeavours to put our civil service including the diplomatic and consular service on a a high level, and I told them of the blunder they committed. I did not break the pledge to my voters, but have performed the duty of a Republican citizen and a very special duty as a representative of the nation. I do regret that I was forced to this publication, but Mr. Georg Schneider through his unprovoked attacks on me was not satisfied otherwise. I am not conceited enough to believe that my information alone caused Mr. Schneider to resign involuntarily his appointment; other protests in this matter have been received in Washington, especially from prominent Germans of New York; the most marked effect was produced by a letter written by Dr. Schlotzer, his own brother-in-law. It would be quite misleading if Mr. Georg Schneider tries to base my information to the state department on personal hatred. Surely, he can not have forgotten that at a <pb facs="5418474_11_0182.jpg" n="3"/>meeting of the representatives of the Republican party of our state I publicly paid tribute to his political activities and, that upon my proposal he was appointed president of the German-American Republican Society.</p>
   <p>I felt it my duty to warn the Government of the propriety of Mr. Schneider's appointment to a diplomatic post, and did so in the interest of public service, and executing a patriotic duty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
