<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-08-11">Aug. 11, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">The Red Eagle.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0940</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0940.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-08-11">Aug. 11, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">THE RED EAGLE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several members of the Board of Education found it necessary to make investigations, the reason, that caused the German government to recognize by the order decoration stream following the visit of Prince Henry, also the former superintendent of German instruction, Dr. G. A. Zimmermann. How they have found out that the German consul, Dr. Walter Wever, a few months ago had paid a visit to several schools in company of Dr. Zimmermann.</p>
   <p>Of course these schools can be visited by anybody, but the consul of a foreign land is not anybody. As such it is his duty, if he wants to get acquainted with any arrangements in our state affairs, to call for the permission of the competent authorities.</p>
   <p>Consul Wever is at present in Europe on a vacation trip and Dr. Zimmermann is absent from the city and therefore these two interested parties cannot be asked. The consul in charge has no knowledge whatsoever about the affair, and says that no official report of the decoration was received by his office. He said that if a decoration was goven to Dr. Zimmermann it could be only in recognition of <pb facs="5418474_11_0941.jpg" n="2"/>his long activity at the public schools and his efforts for the cultivation of the German language and the German culture, but not for services as guide for the consul. School superintendent Cooley declared to our reporter that he has no report about any visit of the German consul and the question must stay open whether this report is only an invention or whether the violation of etiquette is a fact.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
