<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-15">May 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Turner Instructor Alfred Wild Dead after Long Illness</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, front view of Alfred Wild]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1088</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1088.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-15">May 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">TURNER INSTRUCTOR ALFRED WILD DEAD AFTER LONG ILLNESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, front view of Alfred Wild]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Alfred Wild has passed away. The news of the death of the beloved and highly esteemed turner and turner instructor of the Eiche Turnverein, the "father" of the turner camp on Fox River, which at this very time is clad in the beautiful green of spring, was not a great surprise, but caused universal sorrow....</p>
   <p>Alfred Wild was from his earliest youth a devoted adherent of the German turner movement and to the end of his life was a zealous promoter of turner ideals. Born February 11, 1870, in Idar, he came to Chicago in 1893, and at once joined the turners. He was first turner instructor of the old Westseite Turnverein (West Side turner Society), and has been in charge <pb facs="5418474_11_1089.jpg" n="2"/>of turner instruction in the Eiche Turnverein for thirty-three years. For many years he was district turner leader and member of the executive committee of Chicago, and later of the Illinois Turnbezirk (Turner District). During the last three decades there has been scarcely a single national or district convention, and even less a district, regional, or national turner festival that Alfred has not attended.</p>
   <p>As leader of the Chicago turners he took part in the German turner festival in Cologne in 1928.</p>
   <p>His special interest was youth, and it was he who, from modest beginnings, created the present model turner camp on beautiful Fox River as a playground for young people and a place of recreation for the older turners and their families. For many years, until his illness forced him to retire, he was active manager of the camp, and thousands and thousands of guests will cherish a friendly memory of the ever friendly, ever loyal, turner pioneer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
