<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-08">Nov. 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Holy Bureaucratius at the Immigration Department</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-08">Nov. 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">HOLY BUREAUCRATIUS AT THE IMMIGRATION DEPARTMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At times one experiences considerable difficulty in following the trend of thought of Saint Bureaucratius. For years the Immigration Department has declared that it is impossible to deport all aliens who entered illegally, even if their whereabouts are known, because not enough funds are available.</p>
   <p>This should lead one to the conclusion that the authorities practice a certain amount of circumspection and first of all, rid the country of undesirables. In general that may apply; but as long as bureaucracy runs rampant, it will make some blunders, which will stun our impartial citizens.</p>
   <p>Sometime ago, Uncle Sam's "catchers" apprehended a German girl who came to the United States about two years ago. The young lady had her permit renewed several times. The last time, however, a member of her immediate <pb facs="5418474_11_0358.jpg" n="2"/>family suddenly became ill. No - she did not forget to ask for an extension of the privilege - but she waited beyond the legal period. She had no intention of remaining longer in the country. All she desired was to depart peacefully without being deported.</p>
   <p>Although the local district director advocated that compulsory deportation proceedings should not be enforced under the circumstances, the Immigration Commissioner ignored it. A second appeal brought the same result; again the district director's recommendations were ignored in Washington. It had to be! The young lady, a university graduate by the way, must be deported to Germany. It must be done in a compulsory manner, and, in order to be sure, she was arrested and brought to Ellis Island.</p>
   <p>Uncle Sam obviously wants to make an example and show the world that he tolerates no fooling.</p>
   <p>How the criminals of the world who congregate in Chicago and other large <pb facs="5418474_11_0359.jpg" n="3"/>American cities, will smile when they read this! As far as this group is concerned, our strong-arm of the law and the Immigration Department seize only a small percentage.</p>
   <p>After all, so they lament, our funds are limited and we can only deport a small fraction. But a young lady, unsullied by crime, who merely overstayed her permit by a few weeks and asked for a prolongation - she must be mercilessly deported - although she has no intentions of remaining here. All she desires is to leave the country of her own accord and not "par ordre de mufti."</p>
   <p>During the interim she remains confined, at the expense of the Immigration Department, because habeas corpus proceedings were started in her behalf in New York.</p>
   <p>Why don't they act like gentlemen where a lady of irreproachable character is concerned and let her depart in peace? And why do we permit Sicilian <pb facs="5418474_11_0360.jpg" n="4"/>"gangsters" with a criminal past to remain here indefinitely? The latter case provides ample opportunities to show our rough side, but somehow we neglect it.</p>
   <p>The Immigration Department will probably declare that they have merely obeyed the law.</p>
   <p>This is always the excuse of Bureaucratius, but in reality it provides a good escape. We admit without argument that the law is on the side of the administration. But as the law is not fully applied in so many intrinsic cases - and cannot be enforced due to definite reasons, then it is certain that neither the Immigration Department nor the authorities in Washington will lose prestige if they do not always enforce the law to the letter.</p>
   <p>They are more likely to evoke esteem if it becomes apparent that one does <pb facs="5418474_11_0361.jpg" n="5"/>not deal exclusively with desiccated and dust-covered bookworms, but that one finds personalities who consider the human factor.</p>
   <p>This is the distinction between independent, thinking, ideal public employes and ossified, bureaucratic mandarins.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
