<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-08-11">Aug. 11, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Case of Dr. Gottfried A. Koehler (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-08-11">Aug. 11, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE CASE OF DR. GOTTFRIED A. KOEHLER (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The proceedings against Dr. Gottfried Koehler before the Civil Service Commission will take place Thursday. First assistant with the Board of Health, Chicago's Germans will follow his trial with especial interest, because they consider Dr. Koehler an efficient official. While the heads of the Board of Health came and went, Dr. Koehler held his office, by political influences, always doing his duty, an important cog of the department.</p>
   <p>A few weeks after this year's election for Mayor, Dr. Koehler was suspended, "in the interest of the service," so they claimed. But within the legal period of thirty days, no formal accusation was brought against him, he was reinstated in office, and granted a furlough. Now after three months, charges have been brought against him. He is accused of having falsified the <pb facs="5418474_11_1167.jpg" n="2"/>statistical records, instigating other employees of the Department to illegal acts, and of parceling out Department reports, drawn up by him, for political purposes.</p>
   <p>The charges do not appear to be very clear. The Civil Service Commission is expected to get to the bottom of these accusations. The Germans expect evidence to be heard without bias, and uninfluenced by political considerations.</p>
   <p>The Abendpost will, in consideration of the interest which the case has aroused, publish a detailed report of the proceedings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
