<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-05-15">May 15, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">People Tired of Europe.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-05-15">May 15, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLE TIRED OF EUROPE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is one of the everlasting depravities of our patriotic official speakers, to inform a more or less interested public, that the people of Europe came to the shores of this country, because of their eagerness to participate in the blessings of our democratic institutions. Anyone who is even slightly familiar with the history of immigration, realizes the nonsense of this statement.</p>
   <p>Apart from a few exceptions, the majority of immigrants came to this country only to improve their economic conditions. Formerly, the scale of economic prosperity of our country compared with that of various European countries could be easily measured by the number of immigrants from those countries. This of course was only possible as long as there were no restrictions on immigration.</p>
   <p>However, the number of applications for permission to immigrate today presents a very interesting picture of the economic conditions in the different <pb facs="5418474_11_0383.jpg" n="2"/>countries. The reports of the consuls to the State department are probably not quite correct, but in general give a reasonably credible picture of the state of affairs. The number of immigrants who can be admitted during the coming year amounts to 164,667; yet the number of those who are anxious to immigrate is ten times as large, namely: 1,619,000.</p>
   <p>The strange thing is that the requests from those countries that have the highest immigration quotas are the lowest. Those are the countries of north western Europe- Great Britain, Ireland, Scandinavia, Germany, and France. Great Britain and Scandinavia probably will fill their quotas, Germany, in all probability will remain somewhat behind its quota, which gives an interesting illustration to the claim of the distressed economic condition of Germany. Still better off is the Irish Free State, which is allowed 28,567 immigrants, and will probably only send 5,000. France, the destitute, which practically sacrificed its last sou upon the altars of the Fatherland and of revenge seems in spite of everything, quite able to support its children in a splendid manner, as only 1,500 Frenchmen desire admittance, while 3,954 can be admitted.</p>
   <p>And now the reverse side of the medal. There is Italy with a quota of only <pb facs="5418474_11_0384.jpg" n="3"/>3,815, and a half-million applications to immigrate. It is no wonder that Mussolini is seeking colonies because the necessity of finding territory in which to dispose of its tremendous surplus of population is apparent. Mr. Masaryk's empire, Czecho-Slovakia, and Poland, each submitted lists of application for admittance, reaching a total of a quarter of a million; yet only 3,077 and 5,982 immigrants respectively can be admitted from those countries. The quotas of the Balkan countries likewise amount to only a small percentage of the number of those desiring admission.</p>
   <p>If the economic conditions of Europe are indicated by these numbers, then France, the Irish Free State and Germany enjoy the greatest prosperity, with Great Britain and the Scandinavian countries close behind, in contrast with the other countries which are in terrible condition. That especially is true of the countries which were erected upon the ruins of the Double Monarchy. Apparently, they do not seem to enjoy their young freedom and national independence, since millions of their subjects have the urgent desire to exchange their glorious liberated Fatherland for the productive country of the Dollar, beyond the Atlantic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
