<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-30">Oct. 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Austria's Gift of Honor to the Cardinal Gratitude for Cardinal Mundelein's Aid in Times of Gravest Need</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0804</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0804.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-30">Oct. 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">AUSTRIA'S GIFT OF HONOR TO THE CARDINAL Gratitude for Cardinal Mundelein's Aid in Times of Gravest Need</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A simple and dignified act was staged this morning in the office of the Archbishop, 746 Cass Street, behind the cathedral. Mr. Michael Girten, the local consul from Austria, handed a gift of honor from the Austrian government to Cardinal Mundelein and read the following letter accompanying it:</p>
   <p>"Your Eminence;-</p>
   <p>"In the hours of Austria's darkest and most critical need, at a time when the very existence of the country seemed doomed, and innumerable thousands of our population looked forward to death by starvation, Your Eminence loomed high among the ranks of noble-minded human beings who came to help. By placing yourself at the head of charitable organizations, created for the purpose of alleviating the misery of the people of Austria, Your Eminence contributed much to the saving of the country. Now, when my fatherland has <pb facs="5418474_11_0805.jpg" n="2"/>fortunately come through the period of its most critical trials, and my fellow countrymen may once more look hopefully toward future security, in which they could continue following their sublime cultural mission to which they were so loyally devoted in the past, they gratefully remember those who did not forsake them when they were in need and despair, extending a helping hand to them, and assisting them to get on their feet again."</p>
   <p>"Desiring to express the gratitude of the Austrian people through a visible token, and knowing Your Eminence's reluctance to external signs of honor, my government acquired an object of considerable historical value from its national collection of rare manuscripts and books, and hopes that its possession will be a source of joy to Your Eminence. This book, a breviary entitled "Pomerium de Sanetis", and whose author was Pelibartus of Temesvar, is an original print of the year 1502; its genuineness has been established beyond any doubt by our most outstanding bibliographers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0806.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I have been especially enjoined to express to Your Eminence the innermost gratitude of the president and government of Austria for your tireless activity in behalf of Austria. It is my desire that Your Eminence deign to accept this modest gift presented to you through the Austrian consul, Mr, Girten, and receive it in the same spirit in which it is offered, as a token of highest recognition by the highest officials, people and government of Austria.</p>
   <p>"Permit me, on this occasion, to express to Your Eminence the assurance of my most esteemed honor and respect.</p>
   <p>"Edgar Prochnik,</p>
   <p>"Envoy from Austria."</p>
   <p>Cardinal Mundelein received the honor gift with cordial words of thanks and was visibly moved.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0807.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The book, an original issue of the year 1502, is a breviary having for its title "Pomerium de Sanetis", and was written by Pelibartus of Temesvar. The title page, representing the author's portrait surrounded by the four symbols of the Gospel, is in the technique of the so-called "Weiss-Linien-Schnitt" (engraving in white lines), in which the drawn lines appear upon a black background.</p>
   <p>The director of the National Library of Vienna, Hofrat (advisor to the court), and Dr. Bick, who passed upon the book, stated that they could vouch for the genuineness of the same, and for its intrinsic value for collectors. A similar favorable judgment was passed by a number of competent specialists of the state's archives, to whom the book was submitted for evaluation.</p>
   <p>According to information received from the foreign office of the chancellary, the removal of objects of great value has been forbidden by the regulations of the Treaty of St. Germainen-Laye. The book was therefore purchased by the (Austrian) federal government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
