<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-08-22">Aug. 22, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">American Farmers Study German Farming.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-08-22">Aug. 22, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN FARMERS STUDY GERMAN FARMING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For about a week, a study commission of American farmers has now been in Germany. The commission is studying the highly developed German agricultural cooperative society system and also to the management of exports of agricultural products.</p>
   <p>During its sojourn in Germany thus far, the commission has inspected experimental farms. It was somewhat surprising to the American commission to learn that no control whatsoever is exercised upon prices, by the government.</p>
   <p>The Germans submitted to the commission an exhaustive report on German export practices, which, when applied to American conditions, undoubtedly would reduce the competition of Argentina and Australian wheat.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0755.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As an example, the present existing conditions were pointed out to the Americans. While Germany in general has no export surplus of its grain harvest, just the opposite is the case at present. Right now, rye is exported from Germany to the Scandinavian countries and to France. For each quantity of exportation a receipt is issued by the German custom officials, so that in case of a bad harvest, the same quantity of rye can be imported.</p>
   <p>The Germans assume that the Americans will adopt a similar plan. The American farmers, who have so far inspected Germany's most productive territory in the vicinity of Halle and the Harz region, are at the present time, in Frankfourt on the Main.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
