<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-11-27">November 27, 1893</date><title level="a">A Dangerous Compliment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1722</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1722.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-11-27">November 27, 1893</date><title level="a">A Dangerous Compliment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What the nomination of Washington Hesing as Postmaster of Chicago has to do with the coming mayoral election, is hard to understand by the layman in politics. It is improbable that President Cleveland tried by this nomination to influence the decisions of the Democratic City Convention, but this reproach was actually made. The entire Lawler followers claim Cleveland has nominated Hesing, so Hopkins will receive the nomination as candidate for Mayor. It may be more correct to presume that the President believes that the Catholic Hesing does win him 25,000 German Lutherans, and that he expected to flatter the latter and the German voters in general, by giving an office to their pretended "leader and philosopher". In Chicago we may laught about this silliness, but what do they know in Washington of what is going on in the provinces? If one does spit here at the Democratic platform, it wouldn't be seen in Washington. And if one Calls out in the World's Fair City: "Thank the Lord I am there again where I belong, namely in the Republican Party", so the echo of it does not reach the White House.</p>
   <p>Let this be as it may, at all events it is a fact that Washington Hesing is <pb facs="5418474_11_1723.jpg" n="2"/>not in the position to deliver the "German vote" of Chicago to an Irish candidate. By his nomination to the office of Postmaster he became just as little the leader and philosopher of the Germans as he was before. At best he can now command those Germans who expect of him a position at the post office, and their number is really not large. To what extent, therefore, is the conclusion warranted, that Hopkins has to be made a candidate for Mayor because Hesing was made Postmaster? Hopkins would not be a stronger candidate because Hesing received an office.</p>
   <p>However, it is claimed that the Germans have now nothing to demand any more. Governor of the state, the Postmaster of Chicago, the Treasurer of Cook county and the States Attorney are Germans. Consequently the Mayor cannot be permitted to be of German origin. None of the mentioned offices is a municipal one. In the "City Government" the German voters are barely represented. On the other hand all departments except the judicial are headed by men of Irish blood. Shall the Mayor, also, in spite of this, be an Irishman, only because a German was favored with a federal office? That would be a pretty business for the Germans!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1724.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If the nomination of Mr. Washington Hesing is in fact the stone with which the German candidate for mayor shall be slain, so it will certainly be received with great pleasure and satisfaction by the Germans of Chicago. What sacrifice would it be too great to make for their great leader and philosopher!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
