<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-03-27">Mar. 27, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Gustav Prasse Called by Death.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1344</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1344.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-03-27">Mar. 27, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">GUSTAV PRASSE CALLED BY DEATH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Gustav Prasse, for many years local editor of the Abendpost, and one of the best known German-American journalists of the Middlewest, died yesterday evening shortly before midnight, at his home 4926 Lincoln Avenue.</p>
   <p>After a life of hard and successful work, death relieved him from severe and painful suffering.</p>
   <p>Gustav Prasse was born November 8, 1863, the son of a newspaperman, in Rostock, where he finished the gymnasium and later the University. He studied philology, and distinguished himself even in his early years, through his ingenuity and intellectuality. So it happened, that the former publisher of the Chicago Freie Presse, who was at that time, sojourning in Germany, engaged him as a tutor for his daughter and brought him to America on his return.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1345.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This was forty years ago. Very early the young tutor displayed a great inclination and qualification for a journalistic vocation, and after a short stay in Chicago, he joined the editorial staff of the Freie Presse. First he became a political editor, and later a local editor, both with tact and knowledge.</p>
   <p>In 1912 Mr. Prasse left the editorial post of the Freie Presse and for a time engaged in business. But two years afterwards, his old love for journalism awoke, and he accepted a position on the editorial staff of the Abendpost. When the local editor, A. E. Deimling, died in 1919, he assumed that position and filled it with rare ability and talent. The number of his friends increased from year to year, and his passing will be felt by them and by his journalistic colleagues as a great and painful loss.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1346.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the spiritual life of German-Americans, the deceased always took a lively interest. He was Herrlechkeit of the Schlaraffia Chicagoana and held the responsible position of treasurer, of the German Press Association. He also belonged to the Germania Club for several years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
