<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-04-12">April 12, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">Americans in Germany</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1008</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1008.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-04-12">April 12, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICANS IN GERMANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A cablegram from Germany reports that a decision regarding the legal status of the naturalized American citizens of German birth, when visiting Germany, was definitely rendered by the Supreme Court of the Reich. The decision, described in a few words, is rather difficult to interpret, but with a close scrutiny as to the matter in question, the result is as follows: On the return of a naturalized American citizen of German birth to his native land after a lapse of five years, he is to be considered a foreigner, and as such is permitted to live there provided he abides by the laws of the country. In case the German government finds his presence in that country undesirable, the government can expel such an individual without giving reasons for its action. But if a naturalized German-American chooses to reside in Germany longer than two years, the government may, if it pleases, consider such an act as a renunciation of the American <pb facs="5418474_11_1009.jpg" n="2"/>citizenship; but by no means is this individual then considered a German citizen again without further proceedings. Like any other foreigner, it would be necessary to win his citizenship. It does not seem clear to us to what extent the legal status of our German-American naturalized citizens would be changed unfavorably.</p>
   <p>The general opinion was, for a number of years, that under the Bancroft treaty the German-Americans can make use of the privilege of at least a two years' sojourn in Germany - but this was only a delusion. For years Germany has made use of its rights to deal most rigorously with the unwelcome foreigner. Every nation has rights similar to these, and may apply them as it sees fit. Thus far the United States has made use of this right only in case of an undesirable immigrant, who was in <pb facs="5418474_11_1010.jpg" n="3"/>most instances not even permitted to land. But if America would expel undersirable immigrants although they had resided in this country for a number of years (for instance, scoundrels like Grottkan, Most, etc.,) it would not mean a violation of international law, or of the treaty with Germany, inasmuch as Germany employs rigorous measures in expelling American citizens from Germany. If we understand the whole thing correctly, the naturalized American citizen will be dealt with the same as the native born citizen. That a two years sojourn in Germany is not sufficient to be again regarded as a subject of the Reich, is rather an improvement on the Bancroft Treaty. It makes it clear beyond doubt that in order to become a German subject, whether a native or a naturalized American citizen, one has to become naturalized. Although our law requires that a naturalization applicant has to be a resident of this country for five years prior to becoming a citizen, the naturalization of a foreigner in Germany is made much more difficult by requirements of the law. There they investigate the state of mind of the applicant before granting citizenship.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1011.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This is highly commendable, and it is regrettable that America does not employ the same method in this matter. The law does require such measures, as this enables the judge to pass his opinion upon the applicant's intelligence and ability to become a useful citizen of the country, or refuse the naturalization. But was there ever a case when a judge made use of his power? No, his chief concern is to naturalize any two-legged individual who at election time could aid his political party and thus aid him. This matter could be gone into much deeper, but for the present we only say: When the United States Government resents the attitude Germany takes, to act within its rights to expel any American citizen for any reason at all, our government could easily get even with Germany if it would expel from this country all the Germans (anarchists, communists and other vagabonds of this type) for being a menace to the commonwealth, and especially as these vagabonds are aliens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
