<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-07-14">July 14, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Otto L. Schmidt.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-07-14">July 14, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">DR. OTTO L. SCHMIDT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Foreign Institute of Stuttgart, ceremoniously presented to Dr. Otto L. Schmidt, through the Consul General, the greatest distinction which can be bestowed. The German Ring" now ornaments the hand of this well known man.</p>
   <p>The diploma states, that Dr. Schmidt in his profession is an example of tireless fulfillment of duty in the service of ailing mankind, and he never forgets how much he owes to his German ancestors for their spiritual gifts. "Whenever Americans of German origin needed him, he stepped into the gap willing to make a sacrifice. The services which he rendered on the other side of the ocean will not be forgotten in the history of the rooted German elements. Therefore, the gratitude of his fellow men and the laudatory remembrance of the future generation, is befitting. And so it shall be!"</p>
   <p>Dr. Schmidt was born in 1863 in Chicago, son of the well known "1848" doctor, Ernest Schmidt, called the "Red Doctor". After finishing school in Chicago, he devoted himself to medical studies and completed his studies at the universities of Wurzburg and Vienna. After his return to the United States, he <pb facs="5418474_11_1242.jpg" n="2"/>took up the practice of medicine, and also of surgery at the Alexian Brothers and Grant Hospitals.</p>
   <p>The historical societies of Chicago and Illinois, still have Dr. Schmidt as their president. He is a member of many prominent clubs and societies, such as the German and Germania Clubs. For many years he was active as a member of the Board of Education, and helped to bring some German spirit into the education of the young people. He retired from this position on account of his impaired health.</p>
   <p>His name will be connected forever with the organizations of feeding poor German children after the war.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
