<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-07-25">July 25, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Albert Ochsner Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-07-25">July 25, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">DR. ALBERT OCHSNER DIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the best known and most efficient surgeons of Chicago, Dr. Albert John Ochsuer, died today at his home, 2106 Sedgwick St. The deceased reached an age of 67 years. The physician who healed so many, fell ill last Tuesday; his condition was not considered dangerous, but suddenly grew worse and all medical skill which was administered could not prevent his death. The deceased will be buried beside his parents in Honey Creek, Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>Dr. Ochsuer was born April 3rd, 1852, in Baraboo, Wisconsin, of German parentage. He received his degree in 1886. He studied for two years at the clinics of Berlin and Vienna, returned to the United States, and settled in Chicago. He soon afterward married. In a short time his reputation as a surgeon was established and in 1896 he became chief surgeon of the Augustana and St. Mary's Hospitals. His efficiency caused a great sensation; four years later he accepted a professorship with the surgical faculty of the University of Chicago. His lectures were highly valued for their clearness of style and erudition; he was overwhelmed with honors.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1363.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Ochsuer was one of the recognized leaders of the medical profession and could be compared favorably with such prominent surgeons as the Mayo Brothers or Dr. John B. Murphy, who were outstanding authorities.</p>
   <p>Only last year he was elected, at the yearly assembly of the American Surgical Association, as their president. He also occupied honorary positions in many other medical societies.</p>
   <p>Dr. Ochsuer was one of the first physicians who acknowledged radium as a possible remedy 15 years ago; he obtained excellent results with his applications. Dr. Ochsuer is the author of various medical pamphlets. One of his writings, which caused a sensation, deals with the system of hospitals and gives highly important advice in regard to their administration and organization.</p>
   <p>Thanks to his endeavors, almost a million dollars was collected for the new annex of the Augustana Hospital. Dr. Ochsuer's reputation was international; his name was known in Europe as well as in his homeland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
