<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-03-27">Mar. 27, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Beethoven House Society Confers Honorary Degree on Mr. Boeppler.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-03-27">Mar. 27, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">BEETHOVEN HOUSE SOCIETY CONFERS HONORARY DEGREE ON MR. BOEPPLER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a time when Beethoven's name is heard in all the German circles, at a time when in the whole world the 100th anniversary of this great German master is solemnly celebrated, it is a pleasant surprise to learn that recognition is not denied to our living musicians.</p>
   <p>Two Chicago Germans, William Boeppler, the German chorus director, and William Mittelschulte, the master of the organ, have received recognition from Germany, which is indeed very gratifying. In recognition of his activity in the interest of German singing in America, William Boeppler, chorus director, has been appointed a member of the Beethoven House Society of Bonn, on the Rhine, Germany.</p>
   <p>The representative of this society, Attorney Otto Juergens, presented the honorary degree to Mr. Boeppler, signed by Professor Schmidt of the University of Bonn, president of the society. The certificate is artistically designed, with a picture of the great master, his birthplace, and the room in which he was born.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0772.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The prominent organist, William Middelschulte, is considered an authority on Johann Sebastian Bach. He also has good reason to be proud of the honors conferred upon him. He received a call to Berlin from the Prussian ministry of art, science and national education, to give a course in organ music and to lecture on the works of Bach.</p>
   <p>Mr. Middelschulte has accepted the offer and during the months of April and May will be at the State Academy of Church and School Music of Berlin-Charlottenburg, Germany. Besides that, the organist will give concerts in Berlin, Dresden, Breslau, Dortmund, Zurich, Bern and Basel. The latter three cities are in Switzerland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
