<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-05">Dec. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Impressive Funeral Rites for A.R. Seyferlich</title><title level="a" type="sub">Large Throngs in St. Paul's Church; Interment in Rosehill Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-05">Dec. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">IMPRESSIVE FUNERAL RITES FOR A.R. SEYFERLICH</title><title level="a" type="sub">Large Throngs in St. Paul's Church; Interment in Rosehill Cemetery</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Long before the funeral services for the late Fire Commissioner, Arthur R. Seyferlich, began at St. Paul's Church, Orchard Street and Kemper Place, the beautiful nave and the galleries of the church were filled to capacity. Not only was offical Chicago represented; there were also a number of elderly people, from whose conversation one could learn that they were once the playmates of the deceased; they had later grown with him to manhood, and still later in life were more than just dear acquaintances to him.</p>
   <p>In perfect discipline, a detachment of the city's fire department served as ushers. One could see plainly that these men not only were serving from a sense of duty, but also that the death of the man touched them deeply--the man who, like themselves, began his service in the ranks, and who finally was made their chief.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1098.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To the subdued strains of the organ, played by the organist of the St. James Methodist Episcopal Church, Miss Tina Mae Hames, the funeral assembly passed by the coffin of the deceased. The chords of Verdi's, "Requiem" sounded softly through the church, and wonderfully beautiful and solemn were the strains of Mendelssohn's "O rest in the Lord" and "Consolation". The coffin was then closed, and the funeral services began.</p>
   <p>First, the Oxford quartet sang a hymn, whereupon the pastor of St. Paul's parish, Dr. George Z. Scherger, stepped before the alter. After a brief prayer, he delivered the funeral sermon.</p>
   <p>In short sketches, he gave an outline of the life of the deceased.</p>
   <p>"Through all the ups and downs of his life, Seyferlich was guided by two ideals; he believed that man is here to fill the place allotted him by his Creator with all his might. He believed also that, at long last, justice is bound to conquer all wrongs. Duty and work filled his entire life. He lived the life he wanted his men to emulate, the life a fireman should lead if he <pb facs="5418474_11_1099.jpg" n="3"/>wants to be a good fireman. He gave proof that these were not merely empty words when he repeatedly expressed the wish that he wanted to die in harness.</p>
   <p>"With his smile he won the hearts of all, and with his nature he retained what he won. Kindness was characteristic of his nature. He was, however, able to drop this kindness when necessity demanded the utmost from his men in the doing of their duty. But the greatest thing about him was what is today sadly missing in so many; he learned to say "No." Even to life itself he said "No," when life as he understood it was no longer possible for him. This took him past all the many who say only "Yes," and who, for the sake of their personal comfort, are ready to do anything. Seyferlich is dead, but what was best in him is going to remain alive as a paragon every right man should emulate."</p>
   <p>After Pastor Scherger had concluded, Mayor Edward J. Kelly made a short speech.</p>
   <p>In a low voice, but no less impressive for that reason, he spoke of what the city's administration had lost by the death of Seyferlich. "No man is, of course, irreplaceable. Here, on the other hand, we are dealing with a man who was not only familiar with all branches of his important profession (so filled <pb facs="5418474_11_1100.jpg" n="4"/>with dangers), but who also enjoyed the respect of all, because he knew what he wanted, and why he did things his own way, and not otherwise. Seyferlich wrote his name into Chicago's history with large letters."</p>
   <p>Following the mayor's address, Pastor Scherger gave a solemn blessing over the remains, whereupon the members of the Ben Hur Masonic Lodge began their funeral rites. The white apron lay on the coffin and beside it was a wreath of evergreen. The ceremony was solemn indeed. With attentive devotion, the assembled company listened.</p>
   <p>Then the organ played Chopin's "March Funebre," and the coffin was carried from the church.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile the funeral cortege was formed, with four cars from the fire department richly decorated with garlands of flowers at its head. All went to Rosehill cemetery, where again the Masons took over the ceremonies after Pastor Scherger had consecreated the grave.</p>
   <p>Besides the mayor and the city council, the city's administration was represented <pb facs="5418474_11_1101.jpg" n="5"/>by the chiefs of the various departments. Many other high officials could not resist giving their colleague his last honors. Among them were Sheriff Toman; President of the County Board Smith; Chief Justice of the Municiapl Court Sonsteby; County Judge Jarecki; County Treasurer Sweitzer, and many others.</p>
   <p>Also present were Postmaster Ernst J. Kruetgen; Paul H. Mueller, editor-in-chief of the Abendpost, and former Judge Immenhausen. Many German organizations were represented, among them the German-American Citizen's Bund, the singers and the turners. The fire departments of Milwaukee, Wisconsin, and of Columbus, Ohio also sent delegations. Special groups were formed by the Retired Firemen's Association, the militia units of some of the suburbs of Chicago, and the Fire Insurance Patrol.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
