<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-08-25">August 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Washington's Policy of Love of Peace (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0898</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0898.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-08-25">August 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WASHINGTON'S POLICY OF LOVE OF PEACE (EDITORIAL)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The cannons are roaring in the far East, and hard-pressed Germany in Europe with an insignificant small military force has now to take up its defense against a powerful enemy. And while Germany, with a heroism unparalleled in history, has to fight for the defense of its own national possessions and the possession of its spiritual and cultural progress in Europe, ready to win or if necessary bleed to death, other nations whose only aim seems to be gold are engaged in hair splitting and are trying to unload upon each other the responsibility for this mass murder, and, as a result of this mass murder, the resulting killing of civilization's progress. For more than one reason, Japan's declaration of war against Germany is noteworthy, and for more than one reason, is the officially given explanation of the American Governments conduct in the newly developed Asiatic question both remarkable and lamentable. In its declaration of war, Japan seems to have laid particular stress, on the point that the world, should plainly and clearly see that it has no intention of disturbing the peace in East Asia. With a pitchfork Japan points to the fact that only by England's demand did it, as an ally, declare war upon Germany. This precaution of Japan is understandable as it belongs to the war tactics of that country. It wants to shift the blame from its own shoulders, the suspicion which has spread <pb facs="5418474_11_0899.jpg" n="2"/>abroad, that it has anything else in mind but the fulfillment of its obligation of alliance, and the observance of the territorial integrity of China. President Wilson, with Secretary of State Bryan, accepted this state of affairs immediately and officially declared that the Government in Washington, which feels itself in all ways strictly bound to neutrality does not intend to make the war declaration of Japan an object of criticism especially as Japan is not after territorial gain, and that with the return of Kiantchan, German's leased territory, to China the territorial rights of China are fully protected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
