<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-08-09">August 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Picnic of Pioneers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0547</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0547.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-08-09">August 9, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">PICNIC OF PIONEERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Willkommen" was written in large letters over the entrance to Ogden's Grove yesterday, and as the old German settlers passed in they smiled as they thought of the hearty welcome they were to receive at the hands of the Chicago Turner's society, which had charge of the picnic. The weather could not have been better, and everybody was in good humor. The crowd began to arrive at 11 o'clock and increased hourly until the early afternoon. Great preparations had been made for the comfort of the older ones, and everybody felt at ease. Old friendships were renewed and new ones made. Great onslaughts were made upon the lemonade stand, and the lively old man in charge stood in great danger at one time of being swept away by the rush of the thirsty and perspiring. As for the German national beverage it was put out of sight so rapidly that the brewer's trust will probably declare a larger dividend than usual this year. The Committee on Entertainments worked hard to make everyone happy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0548.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Louis Nettelhorst, the chairman, was omnipresent. A register was opened in which all pioneers who settled in Chicago or its suburbs previous to 1869 were entitled to put their names. Each received a silk badge inscribed with the year of settlement. Nearly every person present except the little folk wore a badge, and it took a large staff of busy clerks the entire day registering names. Over 3,000 old settlers registered. The interest of the crowd was centered in the collection of the beautiful gold medals which lay in velvet plush cases. The first gold medal was for the oldest settler present, who had continuously lived in Chicago for the greatest number of years. This was pinned upon the breast of F. Diddrich of No. 672 West Twentieth Street. He is 70 years old and was born near Kownigshofen, Bavavia. Mr. Diddrich is a carpenter by trade and works everyday. He was not impressed with Chicago when he first came. The only thing he could see was swamp, and the only reason he stayed was because of lack of funds to get back.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0549.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mrs. Solomon Haas of No. 94 Laflin street 71 years old, and who came to America September 15, 1839 won the medal of gold for the oldest woman settler present who had continuously lived in Chicago for the longest number of years. Justice I. B. Brandwell secured the medal for the oldest settler born in Germany who had continuously lived in Chicago the greatest number of years. He is 64 years old and has lived in Chicago since May 15, 1834. Mrs. Rosanna Marshall won the medal for the oldest woman settler born in Germany. She is 72 years old and came to Chicago May 14, 1837. Nicholas Schroeneck now wears the medal awarded the German-American workman who showed the longest period of continuous employment by the same firm. Mr. Schroeneck has worked for the Weber Wagon Company for 41 years. Miss Margarethe Seeger, having been general housekeeper for K. Jacob Caspar Schneider of No. 207 Indiana street since 1857, was declared the winner of the medal for the German-American woman who had been in the employ of one family the longest time. Miss Seeger is 53 years of age. As the oldest member of the Order of Chosen Friends, B. L. Ross won the medal awarded for that purpose. He joined the Order in 1856.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0550.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The oldest couple of the old settlers whose combined age gave the greatest number of years was I. S. Lindon and Lesette Lindon, whose combined ages were 150 years. They were married in Brmhsal, Baden in 1842. The oldest couple born in Germany, whose combined ages given the greatest number of years were Mr. and Mrs. John S. Kunse, whose combined ages amounted to 147 years. They were married in Berleberg, Prussia, in 1842. Here follows a list of the oldest people present with residence, age, and date of arrival in Chicago......To the music of an orchestra which contained four members of the Great Western Band, which played in 40's, the old people danced for bouquets. Louis Nettlelhorst made a speech to the settlers, in which he thanked them for the great interest they had shown in helping to bring the city into its present prosperous condition. Games were provided for the children, nearly all of whom received presents. Fireworks in the evening concluded the day's enjoyment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
