<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-24">Nov. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Vain Threats</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0882</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0882.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-24">Nov. 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">VAIN THREATS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our dear neighbors, the Germans, should finally be coming to the realization that, while they play the leading part in various large and small cities and have much influence in some states, they have no influence upon our national administration, and especially the trend of its foreign policies. Nothing can change this fact, not even the threats with which they bombard President Wilson and Secretary of State Bryan. And the pressure they are trying to exercise upon public opinion will avail them nothing either. The United States government, thank God, is not yet controlled from Berlin, and will not be for a long time to come. Mr. Wilson and Mr. Bryan are certainly men who can be driven from their chosen path by any threats, once they have decided that their path is the correct one, the only one profitable to our country, and that the threats are idle and of no importance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0883.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago Germans take good care to acquaint the English reading public with their viewpoint, which they support entirely by distorting the truth. To this end, many German newspapers publish articles daily in the English language. They have founded the weekly Fatherland which is sent free of charge to anybody whose address they can learn. We shall not waste time by telling our readers what that paper has to say about the Russians, the French, and the Englishmen. Everybody can guess that they are described there in the most revolting and vicious manner. All that we shall say is that the paper tries to influence President Wilson and his administration by misinterpretations of various happenings in America's inner political life, and tries to browbeat the Washington government into a friendly attitude toward Berlin--Vienna has become a meaningless appendage to the German capital.</p>
   <p>[Here nine paragraphs translated from The Fatherland and dealing with the alleged interference of England with our overseas trade and with an analysis of election results are omitted in translation.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0884.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The article is full of threats and accusations. But the accusations are without any foundation, and the threats are futile and vain. Our administration does not take side with either of the warring parties and it cannot help it that our trade with Germany has been made impossible, while our ships are reaching England, France, and Russia without any trouble. It is because our government endeavors to protect our overseas trade that it is trying to settle peacefully all differences arising from the interpretation of international laws concerning neutral countries in wartimes. But, after all, the Germans have no right to talk on behalf of the majority of the American nation. The majority of our nation is friendly to England and her allies in this war, at least as far as its attitude toward the misdeeds Germany has been and is committing is concerned. It cannot be bamboozled by the German press, which expresses itself here frequently in a more arrogant manner than newspapers appearing in Berlin or Vienna would dare.</p>
   <p>We consider the result of the recent election an expression of full confidence <pb facs="5418474_11_0885.jpg" n="4"/>in President Wilson and Secretary of State Bryan by a large majority of the American people. We hope that the attack by the Germans will not have the least influence upon our government, which has chosen the proper policy and is maintaining our neutrality in a way that Germany would never maintain if Germany were in our place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
