<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-02-10">Feb. 10, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">North German Lloyd Brings German Art to Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0734</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0734.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-02-10">Feb. 10, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">NORTH GERMAN LLOYD BRINGS GERMAN ART TO CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The rooms of the Chicago agency of the North German Lloyd at Randolph and LaSalle Streets have an exceptionally festive appearance in honor of a number of chosen guests, well known admirers of German art. They came to view a selection of 25 oil paintings by renowned German artists, which Ludwig Plate, the Director of the North German Lloyd has had sent over to give Chicago admirers of art an opportunity to see samples of the work of prominent German artists. This was a splendid idea and we hope it meets with great success.</p>
   <p>It is no secret that the local art dealers, like those throughout this country, are controlled by the French. Probably not because the French paintings are preferred by the Americans, but for the reason, that German artists and art dealers still lack business acumen in placing pictures on the market in the right manner, and in this way acquaint the buying public with their work. Ludwig Plate's ideas were converted into action which for this reason alone is joyfully welcomed.</p>
   <p>The paintings which the art gallery of Bremen placed at the disposal of the Lloyd agency reveal a high skill by the artists. The paintings left a thoroughly good <pb facs="5418474_11_0735.jpg" n="2"/>impression. A desire to buy became visible, and many a picture may find its buyer in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The paintings arrived January 24 in New York on the steamer "Columbus" and were immediately shipped to Chicago. They are exhibited for the time being at the Lloyd Agency and can be inspected by everyone free of charge. To further the cause of German art, the local Lloyd agency gave a good example and bought the splendid 7 x 12 foot painting by Prof. Hans Meyerkassel which represents the City Hall of Bremen.</p>
   <p>A local art dealer already declared his willingness to dispose of these paintings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
