<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-13">Jan. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Friends of German Democracy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-13">Jan. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FRIENDS OF GERMAN DEMOCRACY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the large auditorium of the building in which the Defence Council of Illinois has its headquarters, the Friends of German Democracy held a meeting yesterday afternoon in order to decide whether they should continue their activities as an association in view of the new conditions in Germany caused by the revolution and the end of the war. The final decision was in favor of continuation of the association, without an extension of their past objectives. It was resolved that although the immediate aim of the association was accomplished by the conversion of Germany into a republican form of government, the conditions there were still so unstable that one had to be prepared at any moment to resume activities on a more effective basis than ever before. For that reason the association had to be continued and the former directors were therefore kept in office.</p>
   <p>The chairman, President Otto C. Butz, reported on the past activities of the association. The meeting in March and the distribution of numerous pamphlets <pb facs="5418474_11_0844.jpg" n="2"/>comprised the main part of the work done so far. Secretary Karl Mathie called special attention to the fact that the past expenditures of the association, almost six thousand dollars, were borne exclusively by the directors. He then read a number of suggestions for the future program of the association. Most of these suggestions had to do with the starting of Americanization activities among citizens of German descent. One proposal was that the government should select some men who knew the German language well from the ranks of the association, and send them to Germany to help in the construction of the new German republic.</p>
   <p>According to a report of the representative of the National Executive-Committee of the American Friends of German Democracy in New York, Mr. Carl Collier, it was decided to continue the association in order to assist the German people in establishing a German republic on democratic principles. At the same time the association wants to continue its Americanization program here in order to bring the various national groups of America together in friendly comradeship, to serve the country, and to adhere to its ideals.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0845.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After a lively debate the above-mentioned resolution was adopted and the former directors, Otto C. Butz, Otto Schulz, O. G. Hottinger, Frank L. Roenitz and Karl Mathie were unanimously re-elected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
