<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-06-11">June 11, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Heinrich Kenkel, an Old Chicagoan, Died in Milwaukee.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-06-11">June 11, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">HEINRICH KENKEL, AN OLD CHICAGOAN, DIED IN MILWAUKEE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Heinrich Kenkel, who died after a long illness, in the home of his daughter in Milwaukee, was one of the best known of the old Chicago Germans. Mr. Kenkel was born on January 27, 1825 in Bechta, Oldenburg, the son of a teacher. Shortly after his marriage to Albertine von Voll, the pupil of the composer Spohr, he joined the ranks of the Oldenburger, who helped the Schleswig-Holsteiners in 1848, in their fight against Denmark. In Oldenburg proper he participated in a demonstration of art loving friends of liberty at the court theatre, after which he left for American. Having been a member of the stage for several years, he reported for military service at the beginning of the Civil War as a volunteer, but saw only active service, as captain of the 34th Wisconsin Infantry, whose Colonel was the former Prussian Artillery Lieutenant Fritz Annecke in the year 1863. After the war he returned to Chicago, and later became a representative of the M. L. Huck Malting Company. In 1893 he retired; five years later he celebrated with his wife their golden wedding. An excellent sense of humor, integrity and cleverness were his characteristics, which made him so popular generally. He always took part in German-American movements. Mr. Kenkel is survived by two of five children, Mrs. Schuttler and F. P. Kenkel, also one daughter in law, 13 <pb facs="5418474_11_1493.jpg" n="2"/>grandchildren and 6 great grandchildren. The grandchildren are Mrs. Captain von Kunowski in Darmstadt, Marquise Fred Spinola in Turin, Mrs. Marshall Field, Jr., in England and Henry Huck, children of his deceased older daughter Mrs. Klara Huck. After consecration of the body in the Gesu church in Milwaukee, the same will be brought to Chicago, and laid to rest beside his wife in St. Bonifacius Cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
