<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-01">December 1st, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Children of American Citizens' Foreigners.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0501</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0501.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1910-12-01">December 1st, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Children of American Citizens' Foreigners.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the immigration laws prohibited the entering of foreigners who are afflicted with contagious diseases, even the most liberal friend of immigration would agree to that. Against the principle of the law and its execution there can be no objection. These afflicted persons constitute a danger for others, if they are permitted to mingle freely.</p>
   <p>Nor can it be expected that our government will take care of these dangerous strangers, whom she did not ask to come, and to give them medical treatments at public expense. Such magnanimity would be quite expensive and would not produce the best results. No country can afford to have any other country send its dangerously sick people to her to be taken care of at her expense. This action would be just as prohibitive, as to permit the criminals, the paupers, and the tramps of other countries to enter.</p>
   <p>However, there are cases, in which the application of this law seems unjust and deplorable. We refer here to the rejection of children, whose parents live in this country and have become citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0502.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are many of these cases on record lately. This is not, because there are more children coming with contagious diseases or otherwise, but because they are not permitted to enter under certain conditions, which at previous occassions constituted no barriers. The Commissioner of Immigration, Mr. Williams, enforces the law in this as well as in other respects with unusual, and previously unknown severity. Just now there is a boy on Ellis Island, whose father lives in Oregon and has been an American citizen for several years and who had him come to the United States from Sweden. This boy was not permitted to enter, because it was discovered that he was affected with a certain inflammation of the eyes called "trachoma".</p>
   <p>Commissioner Williams demands in such cases of the Steamship company not only a free return trip for the "undersirable" immigrants, but also the payment of $100.00 as a penalty, which the law inflicts for its violation. The Cunard Steamship Company has been recently hit several times and therefore appealled to the Secretary of Commerce at Washington. In his reply he pointed out, that their protest could not be considered, in as much as the decisions of the federal courts had been definite and clear in such cases. The Cunard Line wanted to know if children, whose parents had become nationalized, likewise became American citizens, if they come to this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0503.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>where their parents had previously come, and expect to stay with them. This inquiry was answered in the negative, based on decisions of the Courts. If an immigrant obtains citizenship here, all his children under age become likewise citizens, according to the immigration laws, provided the respective children live in the United States at the time when the citizenship papers are obtained. The law does not mention anything about children, who still live in a foreign country. These remain foreigners in spite of their fathers naturalization. And as such they are subject to all the regulations of the immigration laws, if they later enter the United States.</p>
   <p>All this is correct. All regulations of the general immigration laws, including the one referring to contagious diseases, is equally applicable to all foreigners; and every child born to a foreigner is being considered a foreigner, when it enters the United States for the first time, in spite of the fact that his father in the interim has become a citizen of the United States.</p>
   <p>The actions of the immigration commissioner is therefore within the law, however cruel they may be at times.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0504.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But the law can be changed and ought to be changed. It can be changed without endangering our country with a mass immigration of sick people. The naturalization laws discriminate between children born in foreign countries, before their parents were naturalized, and those born in foreign countries, after the parents become citizens. All children born of American citizens, whether their parents are born here ot not-which are born in a foreign country, are American citizens just the same as if they were born here. Of course, this does not include such cases, where parents never have been in the United States. The same sick boy who is excluded today, because his father was not an American citizen at the time of the child's birth, would have been permitted to enter in spite of his sickness, if the father had been a citizen before the birth of the boy. All, who possess American citizenship, whether young or old, and in spite of any diseases they may have, must be granted the entry into the States. And if in such cases by observing certain preventive measures, the entry is permissable without endangering public health, then we can not understand, why entry is refused in the other cases. Certainly it does not happen very frequently that immigrants who have become naturalized, leave their sick children in the old country and send for them afterwards, that these newcomers would constitite a danger for this country. Besides, no steamship line accepts passengers, who are <pb facs="5418474_11_0505.jpg" n="5"/>afflicted with serious diseases.</p>
   <p>Under these circumstances there is no conclusive reason, to discriminate any longer between children or American citizen. If children, still under age, whose parents are living in the United States and are citizens thereof, come to remain here, should be recognized as American citizens, although they may not have been such by birth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
