<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-08-26">Aug. 26, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">German Parties Wrangling in America.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-08-26">Aug. 26, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN PARTIES WRANGLING IN AMERICA.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The battle of words between the different parties which recently raged in San Francisco, was, considered from a sober standpoint, absurd. The theme was purely a German and internal politically: here German Social Democrats, there National Socialists. Pamphlets were distributed, insults in point were handed out, all on account of the undoubtedly very serious question, in San Francisco, of who will save the German nation - whether the National Socialists or the Social Democrats?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0785.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The story begins with a lecture given by a certain Kurt Ludicke, who, according to the program spoke on "The German fight for Liberty in the Present Age - Marxism or Nationalism - Wall Street Dictatorship or People's Government?" What he said was the usual talk which at the present time is substituted hard work and actual deeds. Thereupon followed, of course, the answer of the opposition party, "the workers' educational society of San Francisco," and then the battle of words began.</p>
   <p>A glance over the contents of the pamphlets is sufficient to give us at once an idea about the purpose of this meeting. Mr. Ludicke expects of "every German" who has a spark of love left for his homeland and who possesses a sense of honor, that he will do his duty and attend this meeting. The "November crime," the "stab of a dagger from behind," and <pb facs="5418474_11_0786.jpg" n="3"/>other amusing descriptions were cited. And all this in San Francisco, in view of the great ocean, whose majesty apparently is unable to impress itself upon great spirits like Mr. Ludicke, or the members of the educational society, either.</p>
   <p>Now, it is possible that Mr. Ludicke will attempt, here in Chicago, to unchain a little civil war among those of German descent. But to prevent this, the question should be placed before us: Why do we concern ourselves about the party controversies in Germany? This question should be answered first by Mr. Ludicke, before he even attempts to lecture.</p>
   <p>The German element of Chicago takes a great interest in the old homeland and has often proved its warm and hearty sympathies for the country of <pb facs="5418474_11_0787.jpg" n="4"/>its fathers, and this is proved every day anew. But fo the political rivalry of parties we have here neither an ear nor the time. Here, it is nobody's "duty" to attend such meetings as Mr. Ludicke arranges. Our conception of duty leads decidedly in other directions, and in this direction lies our first duty to refuse individuals who are coming over to this country to spread discontent among German-Americans. Such refusals are necessary, because American soil is no place to carry on controversies, which are rooting 3,000 miles away from here. Such disputes not only injure the hospitality of our country, but also the spirit of Americanism. What would become of this country if it would permit itself to become a meeting place of all party disputes and political wranglings of the world? With regard <pb facs="5418474_11_0788.jpg" n="5"/>to this we had enough bad experiences of this kind during the war, and today, we are absolutely against any propaganda and any political baiting of any origin, whatsoever. Our supply of party politics is more than sufficiently covered with our own production, so that the Ludickes, wherever they may come from, can save their trouble and stay at home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
