<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-01">Nov. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Charles H. Wacker</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1229</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1229.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-01">Nov. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CHARLES H. WACKER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Charles H. Wacker died after a long illness at his country home in Lake Geneva. The deceased represented the ideal German-American. He was born in Chicago and, although proud of his home town and citizenship, he nevertheless, cherished his German ancestry. His sense of cohesion towards the source of his origin was deeply ingrained.</p>
   <p>Even as a young man this trend manifested itself, urging him to seek the homeland of his forebears. He studied in Stuttgart and Genf, broadening his knowledge by extensive travel. After acquiring a thorough, general and mercantile training he became affiliated with his father's malting establishment. Later he organized the brewery and malt house of Wacker and Birk. His co-citizens soon recognized his organizational ability and when Chicago planned to inaugurate a World's Fair, three decenniums ago, Charles Wacker was asked to be one of the directors.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1230.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whatever has been accomplished in a systematic building program of our city is due principally to Wacker's guiding spirit and Chicago may well be thankful for it.</p>
   <p>The World's Fair evoked the thought that a city facing a splendid future should not leave its development to mere chance. Not until 1909, however, was it possible to bring these ideals into concrete, tenable, practical form. At that time the Chicago Plan Commission was brought to life and Charles Wacker was nominated as its president. In this official capacity he was highly successful, resigning only several years ago [because of failing health. Translator]. Above all we are indebted to him for the present sense of order, system, and harmony which pervades our civic embellishments. The very nature of this gigantic problem precludes the possibility that one man may complete the enormous task. But to Wacker belongs the credit in having made us conscious of this aspect, in having aroused civic pride and in having paved the way for the eventual accomplishment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1231.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The most conspicuous and greatest work that materialized while he controlled the destiny of the Plan Commission, is exemplified by the encompassing changes of the old market district, the well-known and infamous South Water Street. It was converted into a double-decked street and a grateful, cognizant City Council named it Wacker Drive, in honor of its creator. Although Charles Wacker dedicated his labors and talents so unstintingly to his natal city, he never lost cohesion with the land of his progenitors.</p>
   <p>His extended journeys made him a cosmopolitan, yet he enjoyed himself most when among German compatriots. He shared their sense of sociability and even in dismal hours proved to be an honest friend. The German-Americans with their far-reaching, helpful activities during the World War, found a staunch supporter in Charles Wacker. Under his leadership festivals were arranged in the interests of various causes and even today Chicago's Germans become elated when they recall that period. Chicago mourns at the bier of this great man; in their bereavement the consoling thought arises: His work lives, he will not be forgotten.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
