<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-08-07">Aug. 7, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">In Self-Imposed Exile</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-08-07">Aug. 7, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">IN SELF-IMPOSED EXILE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opinion of the average American regarding immigration is that in almost every instance people come to this country because of the political and personal privileges it offers. And he cannot be shaken in his belief. Moreover, he is certain that the poor, tormented steerage passengers shed tears of joy at the first glimpse of the Statue of Liberty in the harbor of New York. This is, however, a great mistake. Those immigrants whose alleged preference for this country is the result of political and religious suppression constitute a mere minority. The majority come in quest of better opportunities for a livelihood.</p>
   <p>The intrinsic longing for the Land of Freedom is scarcely ever considered as the immediate cause of immigration. This interpretation of immigration <pb facs="5418474_11_0344.jpg" n="2"/>exists only in story books written by Yankees who thus reveal a colossal ignorance of the mental capacity of immigrants. Prior to the regulation of immigration by Congress, the economic situation of this country could be considered as a barometer of immigration, which increased and decreased according to the economic status of the nation. Statistics of recent years show that the number of those returning to their native land as the result of unfavorable economic conditions here is very large. In fact, some nations have more in-coming than out-going emigrants. And, it is quite easy to understand why, under the present circumstances, many immigrants prefer to return to their native hearth.</p>
   <p>But what about Americans who have chosen foreign lands as their permanent homes? The press is at present circulating a report according to which Anita Baldwin, a millionaire of California, has announced her intention to dispose of her property there and take up residence in Canada. When asked to explain this step, she said that her homeland <pb facs="5418474_11_0345.jpg" n="3"/>with its many different laws and high taxation has become burdensome to her.</p>
   <p>That a millionaire prefers to reside in another country does not usually constitute news, but the case of Anita Baldwin, however, proved sufficiently important to be given space in the press throughout the nation. This is not the first case of its type. According to statistics published several years ago, there are hundreds of thousands of Americans who prefer living in foreign lands. There are large American colonies, which do not consist only of students, in London, Berlin, Paris, and other European cities.</p>
   <p>What causes these men and women of wealth to prefer foreign countries to their own?.... Are all their cases similar to that of the California millionaire? As a matter of fact, the burden of taxation was only thrown out of balance during recent years. It is therefore obvious that <pb facs="5418474_11_0346.jpg" n="4"/>a similarity between these cases is out of the question.</p>
   <p>But how about Europe? Does not Europe insist upon collecting taxes? Indeed nobody is exempt there from taxation. What these people really wished to escape is the petty tyrannies of legislation. Prohibition is obviously considered one of these tyrannies. After all, alcoholic beverages are obtainable here despite Prohibition. But what arouses their resentment is the fact that one is considered a criminal in the eyes of the law when one indulges in a glass of wine or beer. Then there is the secrecy which has to be maintained in such transgressions.</p>
   <p>In sum, then, they are in revolt against the puritanical pattern so predominant at present in American life. These people wish to live their lives as they see fit, and object to restrictions on their personal liberty as long as they observe and respect the law. In Europe, they are <pb facs="5418474_11_0347.jpg" n="5"/>not subject to such restrictions. Spies and informers are a menace to them in their own country. They are constantly reminded of the puritan rule in public life.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, we must take cognizance of the heavy losses suffered by our country as a result of these self-imposed exiles. Although the material loss may not be of any great importance, the cultural loss is enormous. It would be well to remember that these Americans are men and women of bright intellect and independent judgment.</p>
   <p>However, they are performing a special service. They are determined to refuse both to yield to bureaucratic tyranny and to become slaves of public opinion. Nevertheless, it is rather regrettable, but at the same time understandable that in order to escape tyranny they have had to choose exile.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
