<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-09-26">Sept. 26, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Altgeld's Campaign Speech</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-09-26">Sept. 26, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">ALTGELD'S CAMPAIGN SPEECH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Democrats started their present election campaign last Saturday night, at the Auditorium with an impressive mass-meeting. Ex-Governor Altgeld was the chief speaker of the occasion. Altgeld's party-followers, however, are undecided, whether to thank the speaker for what he said, or to be angry with him. Following are some of his remarks and assertions: "The difference in general is to be found in the fact that the Republican party is dominated by corporations, monopolies, and corrupt men among their leaders, while just the opposite is true of the Democratic party. Two years ago this party started to go in a new direction. It abandoned all connections with corporations, monopolies, and corrupt influences. Although it may not be possible to drive out all grafters in such a short ime, yet they are powerless and have nothing to say in our council meetings. But, somebody will say, 'If we reject the Republican platform, the local Democratic party will win the election, and the local party is no better, than the Republicans, <pb facs="5418474_11_1619.jpg" n="2"/>and perhaps not even as good.' Let me reply in regard to this, that the Democratic Party has a number of candidates on their list, who are most honorable. On the other hand it is inevitable to find some political weaklings among 40 to 50 candidates.</p>
   <p>"I give you now the following good advice: If you find upon the Democratic election ticket one candidate, whom you conscientiously consider a grafter, then by all means, vote against this man. The Democratic party makes sincere efforts, to avoid all corruption and it will not feel obligated to you, if you support a grafter, even if he succeeded to get his name on the list. But before such drastic steps are taken, be absolutely certain, that he is really a creature that can be bribed."</p>
   <p>The words quoted, have caused considerable headaches, among the candidates of the local Democratic party. The gentlemen had definitely expected the indorsement of all the Democratic candidates by Altgeld, therefore, they were very much disappointed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1620.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The local Democrats are not particularly elated about Altgeld's speech in another respect, They had positively expected, that Altgeld would sharply reply to Governor Tanner's accusation in his Golconda speech, but instead of doing it, he reacted very mildly. Altgeld simply insinuated that grafters were responsible for the "Allen" and the "Gas Consolidation" bills, and that it has been in Tanner's power to prevent these abominable bills from becoming law, and that he defended and favored them publicly.</p>
   <p>The unfortunate silver question gave the speaker a welcome occasion to ride his hobby-horse. Altgeld blamed the Republican administration exclusively for the faults and defects, which the recent war exposed; but he asserted at the same time that his party was responsible for the quarrel with Spain, and therefore deserves the credit for the liberation of Cuba.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
