<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-03-15">March 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Louis Nettelhorst Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1753</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1753.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-03-15">March 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Louis Nettelhorst Dies.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the best known and most respected German citizens of Chicago, Louis Nettelhorst, died last evening - after only a two days sickness, at his home at 46 Wisconsin street. Whoever knew the deceased, and which German of Chicago did not - will receive the news of his demise, with great sorrow. - Because Louis Nettelhorst was one of those Giants, of indestructible strength, for whom, seemingly, there could be no physical suffering, and for that reason he did not pay any attention to the deadly malady, which got hold of him several weeks ago, and continued to attend to his professional business. Only Sunday did he consent, to have a physician called, but on Monday he went back to work as usual, but was compelled to go home during the day, - Dr.Matthai and Dr.Geiger, who were called, recognized at once, that he was suffering from a deathly kidney trouble, and in spite of all the assistance given, there was no help. Yesterday evening he lost consciousness, and three hours afterwards, he breathed his last, without being able to say farewell to his sorrowing family. Nettelhorst was striken with the Flu two years ago and could never overcome the effects of this malevolent sickness. Mr.Nettelhorst was born in Bremen, on February 4th, 1857. He received a good education, became a business man and emigrated to America in 1870. He was first engaged in the insurance business, entered the services of Eunnerich &amp; Co., and became 12 years later, a partner of the firm. Immediately after his arrival in <pb facs="5418474_11_1754.jpg" n="2"/>America, he devoted his time to trade unionism. He belonged to the Chicago Turn-gemeinde and was for 12 years its first speaker, he also was elected President of the Singing Society "Fidelia" in 1875. He also was a member of the "Germania Menschoir", the Freemason Lodge and later of the German Press-Club. Nine years ago, Nettelhorst was appointed a member of the School Board by Mayor Harrison. He belonged to this body, whose president he became, till his resignation las fall and his useful work in still in fresh memory. -</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
