<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-04-19">Apr. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Theodore C. Behrens to His Last Resting Place.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-04-19">Apr. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THEODORE C. BEHRENS TO HIS LAST RESTING PLACE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Rosehill cemetery the mortal remains of Theodore C. Behrens were buried yesterday. In the house of mourning, 2334 Farragut Avenue, an impressive funeral service was held. The United Men's Choir, the United Societies, also many lodges and clubs to which Mr. Behrens belonged, took part. Songs were rendered at the house and at the grave by the Chicago Liedertafel under the direction of Mr. Gerasch. The following selections were sung: Scottish Bard, Sweet and quiet is the slumber, and Peacefully rests the Heart. Pastor Rudolph John held a touching memorial sermon at the house. The ceremony at the grave was conducted by Sincerity Lodge, No. 982, (F. &amp; A. M.).</p>
   <p>Pallbearers were the following friends and co-workers in the directory of the Lincoln Trust &amp; Savings Bank; Judge George Kersten, Daniel Blau, F. O. Schmidt, Peter Reinberg, Dr. George W. Billig, William Michaels.</p>
   <p>Many beautiful wreaths filled the parlor in which the body lay in state. Places of honor were given to the large floral pieces of the United Singers, the United Men's Choir, the Northwest Singers Union, the Sincerity Free Masons Lodge, <pb facs="5418474_11_1433.jpg" n="2"/>the Korner Lodge of the Knights of Pythias, also the Belmont Council of the Royal League.</p>
   <p>Pastor John stressed in his sermon in the German language, that with Theodore Rehrens a man had passed, whom one could be proud to call a friend. Everybody who was privileged to shake his honest hands, had felt that he stood before a whole man.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
