<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-10">Sept. 10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Altgeld Movement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1767</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1767.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-10">Sept. 10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE ALTGELD MOVEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That colossal lethargy which manifests itself on both sides in this election campaign, does not in the least affect the Altgeld movement in Illinois, as far as the Germans are concerned, because their hearts are absorbed in the cause. Altgeld's tremendous capacity for work, his perseverance and extraordinary aptitude which he displays during the pre-election days, and proving himself to be a voluble defender of the poor and subjugated, one who swings the cudgel against monopolies, and our financial aristocracy, and who is always ready to protect the immigrant facing the native's hatred of foreign elements all that appeals to the German mind.</p>
   <p>More powerful and convincing even, is Altgeld's fight for the abolition of the Edward's statute, which he intends to replace with an entirely different "Compulsory School Attendance Law," something which creates no constraint for the German language, or to private, community and parochial schools, but protects the precious, indispensable German heritage from all attack.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1768.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From all parts of the state we receive the testimony which vouchsafes that conduct; it come from competent, respected Germans, and they are by no means partisan members of the Democratic party nor adherents of the old Lutheran church.</p>
   <p>Thus a highly esteemed German gentleman of Quincy informs us, that Altgeld's prospects in western Illinois are excellent and all the slander mongering in the newspapers, such as the Republican Quincy Whig and their ilk, are only beneficial, especially since the Illinois Staats Zeitung, the Germania of Quincy, etc., have so thoroughly refuted all charges.</p>
   <p>Another party reminds us that the much resorted to Republican excuse, referring to the Edwards law as a dead letter, is a cheap and tawdry lie, since many rural community schools are still suffering from the constant apprehension of new, atrocious interferences.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1769.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Similar news comes from all districts throughout the state.</p>
   <p>The German constituents, with infinitesimal exceptions, support Altgeld. Besides, the entire Democratic party backs him. The hopes, which the Republicans exprss with a certainanaive impertinence, that at least the Irish Democrats should do their share inpreventing the election of a "Dutch Governor," (verbatim) are not being realized. Even the Irish will as surely go to the polls for Altgeld, as they did two yeara ago, when the Irish disregarded the bait of the anti-Germans and brought in a spite-vote for Raab.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
