<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-07-16">July 16, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Nathan M. Plotke.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1584</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1584.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-07-16">July 16, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">NATHAN M. PLOTKE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5 - Mr. Plotke, the former German representative from the 21st ward, and one of the most popular German-Americans on the North Side, died yesterday at the age of 58 years.</p>
   <p>Among Chicago's best known and most successful German lawyers, Nathan M. Plotke has enjoyed high esteem. He served formerly as legislator, alderman and assistant attorney-general. He enjoyed especially the confidence of the German residents of the North Side, with whom he stood in close contact for business or political reasons. He practiced law in Chicago since the year 1871. Plotke was born in Germany in the year 1842, and immigrated to the United States at the age of 18 years. After his arrival he came directly to Chicago. For the future of this city, he entertained the greatest hopes. He was admitted to the bar in 1871, practicing law until his death.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1585.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not only as a lawyer did he enjoy an excellent reputation, but also in political circles. He was elected legislator, and served in this capacity, 1880-1881. He served as assistant state's attorney, 1885-1886, and as alderman of the 21st ward during the year 1896. Mr. Plotke was a member of the Chicago Turner District for more than 30 years. He was elected president of the North Chicago Sharp Shooters Society ten times in succession. He was past Grand Chancellor of the order of the Knights of Pythias, with which he had been associated for over 25 years. For a quarter of a century he was a member of the Chicago Free Masons, and he also was for a number of years a member of the Marquette, the Lakeside and many other clubs and societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
