<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-10-17">Oct. 17, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Lorenz Howored.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0936</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0936.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-10-17">Oct. 17, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">DR. LORENZ HOWORED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The famous Vienna surgeon Dr. Adolf Lorenz was cheered this morning at the operating room of the County hospital by more than 600 doctors and students after he made known in plain warm words his honest joy about the cordial reception which he had received there and a few introductory remarks about his new treatment method for hip dislocations in children. Dr. Lorenz then demonstrated his new method of treatment on some little patients and called forth the admiration of the audience who filled the amphitheater and every available space of the operation room. The news that he cures such cases without operation has spread from coast to coast and from almost every city he received petitions to undertake such cures. Too great is already the number of the little patients who were brought here for private treatment that the consented yesterday to another week's stay in Chicago before he leaves for San Francisco. Still he will have to give a number of the cases to local doctors who are now familiar with his treatments. Tomorrow, Saturday, he will give a lecture at the Wesley Hospital for young doctors of Northwestern University and on his way back from San Francisco he will pay a visit to his patients here as far as his time will permit.</p>
   <p>In honor of the famous specialist was arranged last night a banquet at the Athletic Club by the Chicago Orthopedic Association and the Chicago Surgical <pb facs="5418474_11_0937.jpg" n="2"/>Society. Dr. A. B. Hosmer gave a toast to "Our highly beloved guest" to whom the doctors of the old and new world are obliged to render thanks. Dr. William A. Evans in behalf of the Chicago Medical Society and Dr. M. L. Harris of the Illinois State Medical Society presented the celebrated guest with diplomas of honorary membership. Dr. Lorenz accepted all these tributes with the modesty of a really great man and spoke in fluent Engligh about his pleasing experiences in Chicago. He said that his stay at Chicago will always remain the finest remembrance of his life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
