<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-02-05">Feb. 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Mayor of Munich Thanks and Praises Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0799</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0799.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-02-05">Feb. 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">MAYOR OF MUNICH THANKS AND PRAISES CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Expressing his admiration for the industrial and commercial activity of Chicago, and his gratitude for the reception, accorded him by officials and private individuals, Mr. Karl Scharnagl, first mayor of the city of Munich, gave loud praise during a banquet arranged in his honor by representatives of the Fleischmann Company.</p>
   <p>Besides the many duties which his responsible position as first official of the Bavarian capital impose upon him, Mr. Scharnagl, attends also to his business as baker, and people who belong to that praiseworthy trade were in the majority among his mess mates yesterday evening. Besides him there were three other representatives from "Isarathen" present, namely: City Attorney Andreas Pfeifer, Treasurer Ferdinand Morath, and City Councilman Joseph Humer.</p>
   <p>As previously reported these gentlemen came to America in company with the mayor in order to negotiate a loan for the extension of the Munich Gas, Water, and Electric Works, to the amount of $8,700,000, a transaction which they claim could have been successfully negotiated in New York. Up to the <pb facs="5418474_11_0800.jpg" n="2"/>time of their departure tomorrow for Washington, where they intend paying their respects to President Coolidge, the party is staying at the Atlantic Hotel.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank Meyer, representative of the Fleischmann Company and former New York City Commissioner, and Mr. Max Strasser, president of the New York State Master Bakers' Association, are in a certain sense, the traveling marshals of the Munich delegation. It was Mr. Strasser who acted as toastmaster at yesterday's meeting in the Atlantic Hotel, after a large quantity of dumplings had been consumed, which no doubt awoke pleasant memories in the visitors and reminded them of their homes.</p>
   <p>Mayor Scharnagl pointed in his speech to the wonderful growth of Chicago, its enormous traffic, its importance as an inland harbor, and its commercial activity, all things which tend to secure for it the leading role in American economic life.</p>
   <p>"In such a city," he continued, "it is only natural that a European capital's representatives should desire to look around carefully and to inspect everything of interest. That such was made possible in spite of our short stay, <pb facs="5418474_11_0801.jpg" n="3"/>we thank Mayor Dever, the Chicago Consul General of Germany, Dr. Rudolf Steinbach, the Fleischmann Company, Mr. Frank Meyer, the Harris Trust and Savings Bank, local colleagues of the bakery trade, and other representatives of the city administration and private individuals.</p>
   <p>"We note with great pleasure and pride, how well the Germans in this country have succeeded, in spite of their love for and connection with their old home to secure for themselves in the economic and public life of America, honorable and respected positions.</p>
   <p>"Faithfulness to duty is the German's outstanding characteristic, and that he did not lose it, even away from the country of his birth, is best proven by the manner in which he does justice to the duties he is expected to fulfill as an American citizen."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
