<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-05-11">May 11, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">The Hatred of Foreigners.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0631</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0631.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-05-11">May 11, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">THE HATRED OF FOREIGNERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the Chicago Times were supposed to be considered the mouth piece of the new city council and that of the mayor, the aliens of Chicago could look forward to very comfortable times! The Times made an impertinent statement in its yesterday's issue according to which all the public grievances, unrest, and crime are attributed to aliens. Opposition to order, swindling the Government, bribing of officials, for all this the "strangers" are responsible. It could be acknowledged that the immigration was of great advantage to this country, but it would also be quite proper to ask the question whether this advantage is not outweighed by the debauchery, criminal inclinations and general demoralization which cines with immigration. It is about time to put a stop to such undesirable influences in that, the citizenship to immigrants should be limited and only, when such persons have lived long enough in this country to learn and understand the rights and duties of a citizen, is it time to grant him citizenship.</p>
   <p>Here we have the confession of the know-Nothing party and sentiment expressed by the Times. There is nothing new in this confession but to indulge in a <pb facs="5418474_11_0632.jpg" n="2"/>language as they did shows, that they had not the courage to do so in the past. It is different now of course for they figure that the influence of aliens in our city affairs became null for which the April 18th election is responsible. The Times formerly attacked only singularly and fought against any suspicion of snubbing foreign born citizens. Now its song has changed and is not in the least bashful to speak of the aliens as the cause of every thing undesirable and all the nuisance in public life.</p>
   <p>It would be very easy to name hundreds of native American vagabonds and thieves in order to establish, that the real source of public corruption is to be looked for among the pious and highly respectable native Americans. To convince them that roaring against immigration is really pure foolishness, would be wasting energy especially when it means the scoundrels of the Chicago Times.</p>
   <p>To engage in a dispute about such growling of the Times concerning aliens can not be thought of, but only to state facts. And the fact is that those Americans sharing with the Times the confused hatred of strangers, all without exception have voted for Thomas Hoyne and have done so in the hope that the <pb facs="5418474_11_0633.jpg" n="3"/>time has come when they will be able to trample upon the cursed aliens. It is possible that they will hide their claws under a velvety paw only until after the presidential election, but no longer.</p>
   <p>In the 101st year of the Republic's life, the wild hatred of aliens can go on.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
