<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-09-28">Sept. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Geographic Distribution of the German Born Rural Population.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-09-28">Sept. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE GEOGRAPHIC DISTRIBUTION OF THE GERMAN BORN RURAL POPULATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans form the largest foreign born constituent part of the rural population of our country. This is especially noticeable in the northeast section of the United States. Very large communities of Germans are being found in New York, Buffalo, Pittsburgh, Cincinnati, Chicago, St. Louis and Milwaukee. The largest district which contains a thickly settled German population is to be found in the eastern part of the state of Wisconsin; a state, in which, for half a century, the Germans according to their number, have been of great importance.</p>
   <p>The southern part of Minnesota, Iowa, and the eastern part of Nebraska show large sections of German rural populations. In every state of the union not less than a thousand Germans are among the rural population. The settlements in Texas and along the Pacific coast are very important. With the exception of Great Britain, the German immigration in many parts of the United States is just as old, as from other parts of Europe. Many parts of the United States showed at the time of the beginning an outspoken German character. The largest portion of the German immigration poured into this country around the latter half of the 19th century.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0417.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1854, 215,000 Germans landed in the United States. This was the height of a wave, which only in later years (1882) was surpassed, as the immigration from Germany reached a quarter of a million. Because the immigration on a large scale kept on going over half a century, Germanism in the United States is represented by a solid settled German population, in it being many, who spent practically their whole life here, and who have many American descendants.</p>
   <p>Because of these conditions it is not surprising that an important part of the German population is rural. It is however noteworthy, that the lack of foreign rural population in the south, bases itself upon the very old element of the rural population. The competition with negro labor kept foreign immigrants of all countries away, and prevented them from settling in the south.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
