<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-03-31">Mar. 31, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A Demonstration for Altgeld Voices of the Public Favor Harrison's Re-Election Women Voters Cannot Vote for Children's Playgrounds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1596</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1596.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-03-31">Mar. 31, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">A DEMONSTRATION FOR ALTGELD VOICES OF THE PUBLIC FAVOR HARRISON'S RE-ELECTION WOMEN VOTERS CANNOT VOTE FOR CHILDREN'S PLAYGROUNDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The followers of Altegeld, gave the Mayor's candidate a most enthusiastic welcome at the Auditorium, last night. The immense hall did not have a vacant place and beyond doubt, this assembly was one of the greatest election propoganda meetings of the present campaign. The Ex-Governor was greeted with jubilant acclaim, as he appeared on the stage, and his speech met with spontaneous approval. We submit an extract of his speech: "We notice here in Chicago, that all public utilities, with the exception of the water supply, are in the hands of private corporations, vertiable public leeches. It is about time, that these local monopolies be curtailed. We advocate no new methods. Our theory is based on Public Ownership. It is old and has been tried in actual practice; it bears the stamp of ultraconservatism. If the city controls the waterworks, why then should gas, telephone and electric power houses not be municipal property?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1597.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Street-Car Companies, became opulent under the 29 year franchise system; they garnered millions. In the year 1903 these franchises will expire, and it is but natural, that the street-car companies would like to have them renewed. During this interim however, the public applied circumspection and learned something. We do not want to steal or confiscate the property of the Transportation Companies; they have a full, legal right to demand proper considerations, but likewise, the sovereign people of Chicago, are justly entitled to make the same stipulations. The Street-Car companies will find it necessary, to ask for a continuance of their franchise privilege, and then, if the present movement is crowned with success, we will answer....before any negotations are considered, the fare must be reduced to four cents and this condition, as well as an option to acquire its properties at any time by the municipality will be the main clause, before any franchise extensions, will be entertained. Mayor Harrison how likes to brag, that we must be grateful to him especially, for the franchise victory. But all the citizens were behind him, and compelled him to act as he did.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1598.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I am a Democrat and do not lag in party faithfulness. We, who are assembled here this evening, represent the true democracy of Chicago. You can not find it at the City Hall."</p>
   <p>While the admirers of Mr. Altgeld filled the Auditorium last evening and gave the Ex-Governor such vociferous approval, another meeting was in progress at Haendel Hall, where the lamenting creditors of the defunct Globe Savings Bank congregated. They came in response to Mr. Frank E. Stone's invitation and accepted a resolution, in which the integrity of John P. Altgeld was questioned. In that document it is stated, that the Bank's bonded captial was only $200,000 and that Altgeld loaned $54,000 from that amount, i.e., $34,000 more, than is permitted legally. Later, to evade responsibility, he transferred his resources to personal friends, so that the receiver could not attack them. The assembly considered it as very regrettable, that the case is outlawed, and that Altgeld cannot be apprehended under the statutes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
