<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-22">February 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">City Mail</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0481</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0481.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-22">February 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CITY MAIL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is remarkable to note what sensible ideas our great City sometimes gets. Although Chicago and certain representatives of its English Press could be called the breeding place and protector of the worst nativism, from time to time the understanding comes through that without the foreigners, Chicago today would be nothing more than a modest provincial town, reaching the rank probably of Buffalo or Rock Island.</p>
   <p>In no way would it have become the second largest City in the United States. In the light of such a temporary understanding, which of course, may be caused by business considerations, the worst of our nativistic inciting papers are advocating a holiday in favor of those Chicago citizens who, during the past year, swore allegiance to the Stars and Stripes.</p>
   <p>Perhaps even the most arrogant Americans will be startled after looking at the statistics of the population of our City, and by hearing that the cradle of <pb facs="5418474_11_0482.jpg" n="2"/>approximately 800,000 Chicagoans stood on other than American soil. The census of 1910 proved that of a population of 2,185,283 souls, 1,693,918, that is over 75 5, must be counted as immigrants of the first and second generation. Our "natives" have therefore, every reason to remember with some respect the foreign element within our walls, and the proposed honor day could, at the same time, become an occasion to clarify the importance of the Germans in Chicago. The enormous total of 182,281 Germans residents who were born in the fatherland can hardly be passed up in silence. But if to this number are added 244,185 whose parents were both native Germans and 75,366 of whom either the father or the mother was an immigrant then the total of 501,832 is reached, which the official census reports as the population of"German Origin." The fact we could name still larger numbers. The census of 1910 showed 227,958 Austrians, 37,990 Hungarians and 7,192 Swiss of whom the larger part can be added to the German speaking population. Consequently the German element in Chicago can easily be estimated- at three-quarters of a million persons. Our nativism is turning somersaults. It cannot get away from the fact that America is tied by a thousand strings with foreign countries whose people settled here and helped develop the country. At the same moment when in Washington the often-tried attempt on <pb facs="5418474_11_0483.jpg" n="3"/>the life of immigration is repeated, the Federal Government sends a representative to Chicago at the honor-day of the newly nationalized citizens. Our nationalistic Press speaks smuggingly of those "lucky ones" who could put the citizen papers into their pockets during the last year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
