<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-20">Oct. 20, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Struggle for German Reconstruction</title><title level="a" type="sub">Brilliant Addresses by Dr. Loebe and Dr. Wirth before Enthusiastic Audience</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0820</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0820.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-20">Oct. 20, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE STRUGGLE FOR GERMAN RECONSTRUCTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Brilliant Addresses by Dr. Loebe and Dr. Wirth before Enthusiastic Audience</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"May your visit to this country be instrumental in bringing together the two great republics of Germany and America so that they will henceforth stand side by side and work together, as they did before the war, as defenders of the peace and the torchbearers of civilization." With these simple yet eloquent words, Mr. Frank Van de Westerlaken, president of the Germania Club, concluded his address with which he officially welcomed, on behalf of Chicago's Deutschtum, the German delegates to the Inter-parliamentary Conference, who are in the city on a visit. The occasion was a banquet held last night at the Germania Club.</p>
   <p>It was an evening which will undoubtedly linger a long time in the memories of all those present. The invitations were issued jointly by the Germania Club and the German Club, and about five hundred persons, among them the <pb facs="5418474_11_0821.jpg" n="2"/>most prominent German-Americans of the city, gladly accepted. What particularly distinguished this occasion from others of a similar nature was the spirited atmosphere which prevailed right from the start. The very prologue to the evening--the entrance of the German guests into the hall, which was festively decorated with American and German flags--was the signal for a demonstration that came from the heart and went to the heart. Like one man the festive company rose to its feet the moment the delegates of the German people made their appearance. Fritz Renk and his orchestra played "Deutschland, Deutschland ueber alles," which everybody joined in singing; and thus the keynote to the evening was sounded. Many more German songs were sung in unison by all those present at the banquet, and the guests were soon in the proper mood to listen to the numerous speakers of the evening.</p>
   <p>No better toastmaster for the occasion could have been found than Mr. Ernest Kruetgen. As one of the best known German-Americans of this city and as the former president of the Germania Club, he is highly <pb facs="5418474_11_0822.jpg" n="3"/>esteemed by his fellow citizens. To his right sat Herr Paul Loebe, president of the German Reichstag, and to his left, Dr. Karl Joseph Wirth, former chancellor of the Reich. At the long table of honor, which ran the entire width of the large hall, were seated Consul General Rudolph Steinbach, representative of the German Government, and Mrs. Steinbach; Theodore Brentano, the American envoy to Hungary, who is at present in America on a leave of absence; Frank Van de Westerlaken and A. F. W. Siebel, presidents of the Germania Club and the German Club respectively; and, interspersed among the German visitors, notable professional men and prominent businessmen of the city.</p>
   <p>To his greatest regret, United States Senator Charles S. Deneen, who gladly accepted the invitation sent to him, had to tender his excuses at the last minute; a bad cold, contracted a few days ago at the funeral of his friend, Senator Ralston of Indiana, kept him confined to his bed upon strict orders from his physician. Ex-Senator James Hamilton Lewis, absent from the city on urgent business, sent a letter in which he expressed his regrets at not being able to be present.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0823.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Miss Lora Bodenis, soprano, and a double quartet from the Vereinigte Maennerchoere provided a welcome variety to the program by their offerings. The series of speeches was opened by Mr. Kruetgen, who spoke approximately as follows: [Translator's note: It should be borne in mind that all of the addresses that follow are mere summaries, written by the Abendpost reporter in very bad German.]</p>
   <p>"Honorable guests, ladies and gentlemen! A relatively short time ago, we had the honor to welcome in this hall a great son of Germany, Dr. Hugo Eckener, who in a large German airship made the first flight across the Atlantic Ocean. We hope that this will not be the last trip of a Zeppelin over the sea.</p>
   <p>"This evening we have the honor to welcome to our midst the leaders of a new Germany, to whom have been entrusted the weal and woe of the German Reich--the land from which we have come, the land to which we cling with all the fibers of our heart. We have been loyal to the land of our fathers; <pb facs="5418474_11_0824.jpg" n="5"/>its struggle has also been our struggle. We have suffered with the German people; we have protested against the war; we have protested against the Schwarze Schmach (the Black Dishonor) [Translator's note: This expression was applied by Germans to the use of colored soldiers in the French occupation of the Rhineland.]; we have protested against the Frenchman's invasion of the Ruhr. We have sent our protests to Washington, to the President, to Congress. At all times the German-Americans were to be found on the side of the right.</p>
   <p>"Not until the German people were exhausted and disarmed did Frenchmen step upon German soil; they marched into the Ruhr to the beating of drums, the blare of trumpets, and the roll of heavy guns. That act was a breach of the peace and a violation of the treaty of Versailles.</p>
   <p>"Today we welcome men and women who are working for the reconstruction of Germany, and I believe I voice the sentiments of all German-Americans when I hail you [i. e., the visitors from Germany] with a hearty Gruess Gott!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0825.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We all hope that the mission which has brought you to these shores will be fulfilled, and that you will return with the conviction that here, on this side of the Atlantic, there are German hearts throbbing for Germany's freedom.</p>
   <p>"Not so long ago we celebrated German Day, and on that occasion thirty-five thousand fellow countrymen publicly pledged loyalty to all that is German Tonight we follow the call of German blood by welcoming the guests of honor from the old fatherland, and we pay homage to the great nation, to the nation of heroes, which for four and one-half years fought for home and liberty against a world of enemies; to a nation whose blood pulsates through our veins; to a nation whose culture has enriched all peoples with its abundant gifts.</p>
   <p>" 'Might is right' seems to be the guiding rule of the world today. Thus upon the German people were imposed the humiliation and the disgrace of the treaty of Versailles, the greatest crime of civilization. The guilt of the war! But truth is mighty and will prevail. The truth is also our problem, <pb facs="5418474_11_0826.jpg" n="7"/>and it is also our task to prepare a way for the truth, to the glory of our country, our German fatherland, and all the rest of the world. Our hearts belong to this great republic, but we also acknowledge our loyalty to Germany. He who offends the soul of the German people will meet with swift retribution at our hands."</p>
   <p>Then, with a few appropriate remarks, Mr. Kruetgen introduced Mr. Frank Van de Westerlaken, president of the Germania Club, who greeted the guests in the following words:</p>
   <p>"It is a signal honor for me to be able to greet you [ladies and] gentlemen--the representatives of the people of old Germania--in my capacity as president of the Germania Club.</p>
   <p>"Not often has it been our privilege to have such outstanding personalities as our guests. It may perhaps be unnecessary, ladies and gentlemen, to call your attention to the fact that never before has our Club had under its roof a former chancellor of the German Reich and a president of the German Reichstag.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0827.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"Perhaps never before have a people's representatives been confronted with a more difficult problem than that which Herr Loebe and his colleagues, whom we are greeting today, have had to contend with and will have to contend with. May their exertions and efforts be crowned with success, so that peace and economic prosperity will be secured for the German people and so that Germany will once more assume her place among the leading nations of the world.</p>
   <p>"A chancellor of the German Reich occupies the most responsible position that can be bestowed upon one person in any country. This heavy burden was shouldered and borne by today's guest of honor, Doctor Wirth, in the darkest hours of the old fatherland--the land in which the cradles of many of our members were rocked, the land from which most of those present on this occasion derive their descent.</p>
   <p>"More than six years have elapsed since the tempests of the horrible war have subsided--those tempests which have torn asunder the bonds of old <pb facs="5418474_11_0828.jpg" n="9"/>friendships, the bonds of friendship and of mutual respect that united our countries [Germany and America] from the very beginning. Considerable progress has been made since the war in effecting a rapprochement; a large part of the mutual distrust has been removed by means of the spoken and the written word, by intercourse and exchange of ideas.</p>
   <p>"May your visit to this country, my honored guests, be successful in achieving further gains in this direction, so that Germany and the United States of America will henceforth be able to act together, as they did before the war, as defenders of the peace and the torchbearers of civilization. With this thought in mind, ladies and gentlemen, I again bid you a hearty welcome."</p>
   <p>How Germany's future depends upon the youth of Germany and how, for that reason, Americans have done so much to help the poor, enslaved fatherland by sending charitable gifts, was described in moving phrases by Frau Christine Treusch, Reichstag member from Cologne. Among other things, she said (in approximately these words): <pb facs="5418474_11_0829.jpg" n="10"/>"This is the first time a woman member of the German Reichstag has been privileged to speak at an occasion of this kind. As a woman called upon to represent the German people, I gladly take this opportunity to thank you ladies and gentlemen, as well as all German-Americans, for all the good you have done in behalf of our suffering youth and our old people who are unable to work. May the good Lord bless you!</p>
   <p>"What is woman's duty in public life? Her duty is not to enter the lists against a man as his rival and enemy, but to work at his side, supplementing his efforts. Infinite good can be accomplished by a woman in the upbringing of youth and in preserving the national customs and traditions.</p>
   <p>"As most of you know, the sufferings and tribulations of the inhabitants [of Germany] were greatest in the Rhineland. We realize that we too must make sacrifices for the beloved fatherland, but we shall offer uncompromising resistance to injustice and highhanded acts, to unjustified sanctions and reprisals. Our hope lies in the coming generation; we trust <pb facs="5418474_11_0830.jpg" n="11"/>that it will again free the Rhineland, that it will again liberate Germany."</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Siebel spoke as follows: "Here where all of us speak German so beautifully, I am called upon, as president of the German Club, to make a speech. There are many good High Germans in this country, but there are also many Low Germans here, and so I would like to remind you of the Low German saying: 'Jungens un Dirns, holt fast!'" (Boys and girls, hold fast!)</p>
   <p>Continuing in English, the speaker said: "The German Club is proud of your noble work, and we hope that soon there will be lasting peace. We are awaiting the dawn of the day when all mankind will live together in one peaceful community of nations. We know that you will lead the good people of the old fatherland to the position they once occupied, yes, even to new heights. We ask that you take back with you our message: that we are convinced that the German people will soon again emerge as a great and mighty nation."</p>
   <p>Herr Loebe Speaks <pb facs="5418474_11_0831.jpg" n="12"/>"Ladies and gentlemen! When we accepted President Coolidge's invitation to meet with the representatives of forty nations, we knew that a special mission awaited the members of the German delegation: to clasp the hands of the German-Americans, who have contributed so much to the upbuilding of this great country. To them we bring greetings from the German Reichstag, from the German people. The German-Americans were the first to extend us a helping hand as we lay crushed and helpless. I shall leave it to the women members of the German parliament to discuss this topic in greater detail. It is our desire to awaken your confidence in the new Germany that has arisen after the collapse. Listen to us and judge for yourselves.</p>
   <p>"There was a time when aged Europe looked upon America as one looks upon a stripling, watching his sturdy and happy growth. Now Europe gazes upon a giant. We observed your proud city of Chicago as it wrested solid land from the lake and developed new residential areas for its population. In New York we saw the skyscrapers ascend ever higher into the clouds; we heard a Babel of tongues; and everywhere we observed new traffic roads under construction. Today, in the stockyards, we saw a mass production industry such <pb facs="5418474_11_0832.jpg" n="13"/>as one could scarcely imagine. But that is just one symbol of your magnificent achievements.</p>
   <p>"Up to 1914 both of us [Europe and America] made equally steady progress. Then came the great catastrophe, and Europe was hurled backward, whereas America's development continued. For example, agricultural production has declined fifty per cent in Europe since 1914, whereas it is continually increasing in this country. In 1914 the United States imported forty per cent of the world's silk production; in 1921, she imported ninety per cent. This is how we [Europe] have retrogressed; this is the way Europe looks today. If Europe wishes to remain in existence, she must travel a new road. This is also Germany's problem, if we are ever to attain prosperity again." [Translator's note: These puerile, incoherent, illogical sentences are faithful renditions of the sentences employed by the illiterate Abendpost reporter.]</p>
   <p>"We want to be frank with you. After the humiliations we endured as a result of the imposition of an impossible peace treaty--a peace treaty we were forced <pb facs="5418474_11_0833.jpg" n="14"/>to sign in 1918-19 because nothing else was possible: the whole world was arrayed against us, and Germany would have become the battlefield, the toll of war victims would have mounted to unheard-of proportions--after all our humiliations, we lay exhausted, but we did not despair. When France occupied the Ruhr we pounded our fist on the table, and for nine months we pursued a policy of passive resistance. The consequence was the ruination of German economic life, so that fifty per cent of our countrymen had to support the other fifty per cent. The Separatists continued to gain new ground; the danger became extremely acute that our country would be completely torn asunder; and misery became more widespread. It required much courage to tell our despairing people to be patient; that we could only make headway slowly, step by step; that we would have to bear the burdens the relentless peace had foisted upon us. One of those who found the courage to tell all this to the people was our chancellor, Dr. Joseph Wirth.</p>
   <p>"If today all European statesmen are breathing more freely, it is because a new epoch is in the offing. This is essentially the result of a policy <pb facs="5418474_11_0834.jpg" n="15"/>initiated by men who were often bitterly attacked on that account. It is a policy of reconciliation and recovery, but with new means. The pact of Locarno has once more made the Rhine a German river, and soon the Rhine-land will be rid of foreign peoples.</p>
   <p>"Here, in your presence, I should like to say a word in appreciation of Friedrich Ebert, the first President of the Reich, who rose from the humblest ranks of the people to the uppermost heights in his fatherland. He was always proud of his past. Among Americans, too, there are many who are proud of having reached the top from humble beginnings. He and Doctor Wirth initiated this policy [of reconciliation and recover]. In Germany everyone esteems this man highly; at his home I have encountered members of all political parties, and they all greatly respected him. Your Ambassador Houghton was a frequent guest at his home and esteemed him. I owe him this word of appreciation.</p>
   <p>"If the German people desire again to become free from without (nach aussen frei), <pb facs="5418474_11_0835.jpg" n="16"/>it must also be free from within (nach innen frei). There must no longer be a fixed hierarchy of classes in our country; the idea of the authoritarian state must be eradicated; and each and every German must realize that he too bears a portion of the responsibility for the strengthening and reconstruction of his homeland.</p>
   <p>"The German republic wants to link German Austria with the motherland. It is the duty of everyone to stick together with those who belong to us [i.e., those who are of our blood, who share our traditions]. We are happy to be with you, and we have listened with joy to the German folk songs. The new Germany greets you and bids you welcome, you who carry the star-spangled banner in one hand and the black-red-gold flag of the German republic in the other!" (Great applause.)</p>
   <p>It was quite natural that the address by Dr. K. Joseph Wirth, former chancellor of the Reich, should have been anticipated with great interest. The fact that he was at the helm of the German cabinet at a time which might well be regarded as especially critical turned the eyes of the world upon him, and it is only <pb facs="5418474_11_0836.jpg" n="17"/>natural that even today, when he is no longer directly active in public life, an expression of his opinion should not pass unnoticed. In the course of his address, Doctor Wirth said the following:</p>
   <p>"It is a great pleasure for me to speak to my German countrymen in America. Since earliest childhood it has been my most longing desire to know your country. Now my dream has come true, and I am grateful. Above all, let me stress the fact that with your contributions you have performed a deed of great political moment. The help extended by America has provided the foundation upon which Germany has been able to erect her new existence. With a despairing, hungry people in the heart of Europe it was not possible to achieve the real and lasting peace so longingly desired by everyone. My guiding principle has always been: I serve my people, and thereby I also serve all those imbued with humanitarian ideals.</p>
   <p>"It is not difficult to kindle a fire in the political life of a nation. But to keep the flames of contention from spreading and then to extinguish them is <pb facs="5418474_11_0837.jpg" n="18"/>the duty of the political leader. The evidence of our own eyes would be enough to bring home to us what communism has made out of Russia; the establishing of the German republic has been the salvation of Europe.</p>
   <p>"The present form of government has paved the way in Germany for mutual understanding. To criticize is not difficult, but to improve conditions is indeed difficult. We accepted the Dawes Plan because it was the sole basis upon which German reconstruction could be undertaken. The provisions of the Dawes Plan that are untenable will soon become manifest. Personally, I have the greatest confidence in Mr. Gilbert, the administrator of the reparation payments. What we need above all else is the confidence of the world. Then we shall rise by dint of our own strength. Even now there is only one course open to us--the way of work, the way of hard work."</p>
   <p>"We sincerely desire to co-operate in the effort for peace in a manner at once German and aboveboard. We are possessed of the will to mutual understanding. We too are in accord with the demand for security for all nations--security for France, our former enemy, but, above all, security and freedom for our <pb facs="5418474_11_0838.jpg" n="19"/>beloved German fatherland. Deutschland, Deutschland ueber alles!"</p>
   <p>Next followed a few brief speeches. Doctor Mittelmann spoke as follows: "We have received many lasting impressions in this country. We were especially impressed by the great interest manifested by German-Americans in the well-being of the land in which the remains of their parents are interred. The harsh ordeal visited upon our fatherland was unable to crush us. We are firmly convinced that our reconstruction will be successful. The symbol for the new and better future which you so ardently desire for your old homeland is embodied in the person of the President of the Reich, Field Marshal von Hindenburg. Once the imperial commander in chief of an army of ten million men,....he has now taken an oath to uphold the Weimar constitution.....</p>
   <p>"The heavy, intense darkness that enveloped Germany has given way; we see dawn upon the horizon, and if we remain united the dawn will merge into a beautiful, red morning sky--the beginning of a brilliant day of German greatness and liberty."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0839.jpg" n="20"/>
   <p>"....I have just returned from a workers' meeting, and as I was about to leave, several men came up to me and greeted me; they said they were neighboring countrymen of mine. They had left us in the course of the last few years because Germany could not give them work, could not even give them bread, and they did not want to live on the relief provided by the poor fatherland. They came to this country, to the New World. And when I asked them how they were getting along, they clenched their teeth and said, 'Gut!' Even the highly skilled workmen had to leave us, because we could not keep them. And now we must work hard so that our shattered fatherland may be restored to health.</p>
   <p>"We women in the Reichstag are making it our chief task to secure legislation for the rehabilitation of our men, so that they can again find work and so that Germany will be in a position to help herself. This can only be achieved by economic recovery, and for this we need peace and mutual understanding with all nations. We hope that they will help us achieve a real peace--not merely a <pb facs="5418474_11_0840.jpg" n="21"/>'paper' peace--so that we may again become a healthy and a strong nation."</p>
   <p>Then Frau Lang-Brumann spoke as follows: "Dear Brothers and Sisters! From Bavaria, from golden Munich, I bring you my people's greetings. Many of you know the city of Munich; anyone who has been there once always wants to come back again, and this is especially true today, when the city is well on its way to recovery. And if you really want to help, send a commission to one of our Munich artists to encourage him. We Bavarians are Germans, one and all! Once I was high up in the mountains. A storm was raging below, but soon the dark clouds receded, and it became clear again. And this, my dear friends, is just the situation in Germany today--the dark clouds are receding, slowly but surely."</p>
   <p>Dr. Meidinger delivered the concluding address: "As an Austrian from Czechoslovakia, I bring you greetings from ten million Germans living on foreign soil, from men and women torn from the fatherland and handed over to Poland, Czechoslovakia, Yugoslavia, and Rumania. But as long as we maintain our ties [with the fatherland], as long as we preserve our German culture and traditions, we shall remain united."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
