<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-11-27">November 27, 1876</date><title level="a">The 24Th Illinois Volunteer Regiment Held its Seventh Annual Reunion Last Saturday at the North Side Turnhall.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0184</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0184.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-11-27">November 27, 1876</date><title level="a">THE 24TH ILLINOIS VOLUNTEER REGIMENT HELD ITS SEVENTH ANNUAL REUNION LAST SATURDAY AT THE NORTH SIDE TURNHALL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. A. Georg, the President, introduced Mr. W. Vocke as the festival speaker, who said among other things: .....</p>
   <p>In the hour of enthusiasm, caused by the outbreak of the Civil War, originated our 24th Regiment of Illinois. Colonel Hecker, who, as even envy must concede him, always has been a brave soldier, resigned after three months as a volunteer under Sigel in St. Louis, and on the initiative of a few prominent Germans like Schneider, Butz, Hesing, Rapp and Brentano he came to Chicago to organize a regiment consisting exclusively of Germans. By the middle of June there were already eight completely equipped companies under arms. These later were joined by two other German companies, the Lincoln Rifle and the Union Cadet Company, which already had seen military service in Cairo.</p>
   <p>The regiment was then complete, and , after a short period in the instruction camp in Alton, it was sent to Missouri. In many hot encounters, in the largest <pb facs="5418474_11_0185.jpg" n="2"/>and bloodiest battles that were fought during our more than three years of service in the western war theatre, as well as in the outstanding campaigns, our regiment always took its honest share as the history of the Civil War and as the blood-soaked plains of Perryville, Stone River, Duck Gap, Chickamauga, Missionary Ridge, Buzzard Roost, Resacca, Kenesaw Mountain, etc. will indicate (and as those in our midst who still mourn a dear kinsman can fully attest.)</p>
   <p>And the few, who are still assembled here, have come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
