<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-07-08">July 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Germany and the German-Americans.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0876</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0876.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-07-08">July 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANY AND THE GERMAN-AMERICANS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the caption, Fie, Mr. von Jagow, the newspaper Herald published yesterday an editorial. This Anglo-American paper pays the German Secretary of State admiring praises, for his having expressed himself, face to face to Miss Jane Addams, that the United States were lawfully and morally fully justified, in supplying arms to Germany's allied enemies. The Fie, Mr. Jagow, is naturally meant ironically, and does not refer to Germany, but to German-Americans. "It is really depressing, opines the paper, in a witty ironical manner that such a prominent official, the undersecretary of the German foreign office, stand under such impressions. It is also surprising, that he is not sufficiently enterprising, to draw more correct information, from the different authoritative explanations, which are published from time to time on this side of the waters.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0877.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If Mr. von Jagow, had paid the necessary attention, to the treatment of the subject by experts on this side, he would have been convinced that the United States is treading on every divine and human right, by supplying the allies with arms and munition, through which act it becomes the murderer of innocent people. We, who intercede for prohibition of the arms export, and in the export of arms, perceive an outrage against higher human feelings, should simply consider ourselves destroyed, through the clumsy irony of our contemporary Anglo-American press. And we should be deeply ashamed, by the concluding words of that article, which says: "But Mr. von Jagow is only the German Secretary of State of the foreign office, and it cannot be expected of him, that he should show such interest in these questions, or come to such conclusions as our cis-Atlantic experts."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0878.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That Mr. von Jagow acknowledges the lawful right of our republic to the exportation of arms, proves, that Germany and its government, bows before the law, even if its tip is pointed against the German people. And this acknowledgment of the rights of neutral America, to support its enemies extensively, should teach the American people, to have more respect for the character of the Germans, whom they pictured - since the beginning of the war - as nothing else but a law breaking horde of savages.</p>
   <p>And we Americans of German descent, who at all times interceded for American ideals, even on the battle field, we American citizens of German descent want to appear before the world as living testimonial, that the purveyors of arms, and the British newspapers, printed on American soil do not represent the whole of the American people, and that the majority of this people, if it had to choose between cold right, and one originating from higher morals of warm human duty, would renounce the right, in <pb facs="5418474_11_0879.jpg" n="4"/>order to satisfy the moral and human duty. Just like in social life, many people within the border of the law, and their undeniable right, commit inhuman acts, for which no earthly judge can hold them responsible, but through its execution, in the sense of social morals, they are branded as criminals, the same way a nation might, within the border of undeniable right, act inhumanly, and thereby provoke the reproach of national immorality upon itself.</p>
   <p>And the American people acts, while taking advantage of a right, which of course assures a financial profit - for the moment. The moral loss will be of lasting effect, if we do not change our comprehension, about right and duty......To bring about this change, we Americans of German descent consider it our sacred task, unconcerned about what Mr. von Jagow, or the editorial of the Chicago Herald might say.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
