<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-31">Dec. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. K. Freitag of Elmhurst Passes Away</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, front view of Dr. K. Freitag]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-31">Dec. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">DR. K. FREITAG OF ELMHURST PASSES AWAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, front view of Dr. K. Freitag]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After a long and severe illness Mr. Karl Freitag, who was for many years the director of the advertising department of the firm, Dr. Peter Fahrney and Company, died yesterday morning in his home at 140 Prospect Street, Elmhurst.</p>
   <p>The body lies in Nielsen's Chapel, 3301 West Fullerton Avenue, Chicago, where the funeral will take place Wednesday at 1:30 P.M. The burial will take place in Friedhof Memorial Park.</p>
   <p>Mr. Freitag was a native of the Holstein country. He was born November 12, 1868, in Wesenberg, near Kiel. He attended the gymnasium at Ploen and, after graduation, went to the university at Kiel.</p>
   <p>Though his father was a major in the Prussian army, Mr. Freitag devoted himself <pb facs="5418474_11_1091.jpg" n="2"/>to the study of theology, and secured his doctor's degree in philosophy and theology.</p>
   <p>In 1899, when he was twenty-one years old, he came to Chicago. He soon became one of the youngest officiating ministers, at the newly founded congregation on Augusta near Robey Street.</p>
   <p>For ten years Mr. Freitag was active as minister, and was also owner and editor of the German paper in Michigan City. From October, 1919, until his death--almost a quarter of a century--he was in the employment of the wellknown patent medicine manufacturers, Dr. Peter Fahrney and Company. The position he last held was that of manager of the large advertising and publicity department.</p>
   <p>For twenty-three years the deceased was president of the Deutsche Neugeistige Gesellschaft (German New Spirit Society), which he founded, and he was president of the Verein Deutsche Presse (German Press Association) for twelve years. He also proposed the founding of the Damenzirkel (Ladies' Circle).</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He had a large number of personal friends, who always found a hearty welcome in his comfortable and hospitable home in Elmhurst.</p>
   <p>Besides his wife, Lotte, five children survive Mr. Freitag, the daughters Lydia Boe, Nelda Clough, and Siglinde Gunderson, and two sons, Emanuel and Armin Freitag.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
