<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-03-01">Mar. 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Gustave Berkes Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-03-01">Mar. 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">GUSTAVE BERKES DIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday morning merciful death released Gustave Berkes from his painful sufferings. His death leaves another vacancy in the ranks of the old guard of German-Americans and of the few remaining Turner pioneers.</p>
   <p>Deeply affected besides the members of his family, is the so-called "Round Table," which under the motto "Harmony" met for many years two or three times every week in Gills Tunnel Restaurant, and lately in the Atlantic Hotel. Gustave Berkes was one of the oldest members.</p>
   <p>Born 67 years ago in Oppenheim on the Rhine, the son of a confectioner, he learned the mercantile trade, which he later followed in Marburg on the Lahn. He came to America in 1883, was employed in a toy business for several years, and then became the manager of the North Side Turner Hall in 1885, a position which he filled until 1900, and then again from 1906 to 1914.</p>
   <p>As closely as the Chicago Turner Society is connected with the German element, so is the personality of Gustave Berkes connected with the North Side Turner Hall. Under his leadership, the well-known locality soon became a center of <pb facs="5418474_11_1279.jpg" n="2"/>all the cultural efforts of the German element. This position brought him into contact with thousands, and won him the friendship of many.</p>
   <p>Last year he contributed his share to the great success of the 75th anniversary of the Chicago Turner Society.</p>
   <p>It was his intention to make a trip to Germany this year to visit once more his old homeland and like ten thousand other Turners to participate in the German Turner festival in Cologne.</p>
   <p>His name will live for a long time in the history of the Chicago Turner Society, and of the Chicago Germans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
