<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-23">Sept. 23, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Where Was Germany?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1024</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1024.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-23">Sept. 23, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE WAS GERMANY?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is very humiliating to German-Americans that neither Kaiser Wilhelm nor Prince Bismarck considered it necessary to express his sympathy to this nation in connection with the tragedy which has befallen the United States in the death of President Garfield. At least condolences might have been sent to Mrs. Garfield. Americans, both those of English origin and more especially the German-speaking contingent, are fully justified in asking:</p>
   <p>"Could not Emperor Wilhelm or Chancellor Bismarck have shown the same courtesy as Queen Victoria and Gladstone, or President Grevy [France] and King Alfonso [Spain]? Why, under circumstances of this kind, did the German Reich relegate this matter to one of its inferior officials <pb facs="5418474_11_1025.jpg" n="2"/>(Busch), in view of the important part which Germans have played in shaping American culture both from the political and from the social angle?"</p>
   <p>We might condone the matter so far as Wilhelm was concerned (he has reached his eighty-fourth year), and on the day when Garfield died, the monarch's granddaughter was married to the great-grandson of the French wheelwright Bernadotte, and so the Kaiser's thoughts were probably centered on the strangeness of fate which united the old order with the new. (After all, the old man does not think much.) And so there was not enough gray matter left to consider the United States. But for Bismarck there is no excuse. He had time enough to comport himself like a gentleman, as Gladstone did and King Alfonso. However, Bismarck failed in this respect, and the incident was highly annoying to every citizen of the United States who was born in Germany. It proves that the German chancellor is disgruntled at the flight of his subjects who prefer to emigrate rather than to enjoy happiness under his rule, and this attitude of German citizens so affects <pb facs="5418474_11_1026.jpg" n="3"/>the man that he even disregards the common courtesies which are customary in matters appertaining to international relations. Busch--what is Busch to us? A sort of second-rate Bismarck! And that is the kind of person which the Reich's administration selected to express its regrets, whereas the Queen of England ordered mourning at her court.</p>
   <p>In Germany,where social indifferences predominate, or rather where the amenities of life and polite conduct are not emphasized, such matters may be considered trivial. But they are not. A little civility, a trace of courtesy, not only maintains but actually increases friendship among individuals as well as among nations. Not only are German-Americans an inseparable element of the United States; their sentiments are definitely American, and they consider themselves an integral part of the nation. And, therefore, this contingent considers it an insult and a disgrace that the land of their birth should act so abominably toward the land of their choice. The great misfortune which the United States has suffered <pb facs="5418474_11_1027.jpg" n="4"/>[Garfield's assassination] has brought expressions of profound regret from the Queen of England, Gladstone, President Grevy, the King of Spain, the Czar of Russia, the King of Italy, even the Sultan; but where was Germany? Where was old Wilhelm? Where was Bismarck? Ah--they had no time to act civilly; Busch had to attend to this detail.</p>
   <p>Well enough; the same courtesy and sympathy may be shown to Germany at some opportune time in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
