<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-27">Aug. 27, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">A Career Ended.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-27">Aug. 27, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">A CAREER ENDED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5.. The career of the excellent and widely known German physician, Dr. Ernst Schmidt was ended by death yesterday. As a physician he had brought relief to innumerable thousands. With Dr. Schmidt departed another of the prominent men who after the revolution of 1848 sought refuge in our land of the free. He was a genuine German of the old stock who worked unceasingly for the progress and the development of the Union.</p>
   <p>Dr. Schmidt was born March 2nd, 1829, at Ebern in Franconia. He was the son of Michael Schmidt, druggist and mayor of that city. There he attended the elementary school while also receiving private instruction. He later attended the Latin school in Bamberg.</p>
   <p>Still later he was sent for his further education to Neurenberg. He graduated from college at the age of 17 years and then entered the University of Wuerzburg to study medicine. Before long he took part in the Democratic activities of the students.</p>
   <p>After the uprising of Baden had subsided, young Schmidt, then a member of the National Executive Board for the revolutionary forces of Franconia, was <pb facs="5418474_11_1580.jpg" n="2"/>forced to flee. He left Germany at once and arrived in Zurich, Switzerland, without any money and without extra clothes. However, soon he resumed his studies, although hunger and cold were his steady companions, until past mid-winter.</p>
   <p>Then, an amnesty for minors proclaimed by King Max enabled him to return to his father's comfortable home. Although richer in experience, his attitude remained unchanged. The now quiet life of the universities seemed dull to young Schmidt. He became hypersensitive to the innocent jokes about his "foolish acts" and frequently challenged the offenders to a duel.</p>
   <p>After having received his M. D. degree he accepted the position of assistant to a medical officer of a certain district. Preferring teaching to the general practise of medicine, he became an unsalaried lecturer at the Wuerzburg University. He lectured to capacity classes, notwithstanding the fact that the medical faculty of the university included the names of famous men (Virchow, Markus, etc.). He became assistant to the celebrated Markus, on the staff of the famous City Hospital where he remained several years.</p>
   <p>But he was repeatedly reminded that his participation in the uprising was not forgotten. This intolerance prompted him to choose a free country for <pb facs="5418474_11_1581.jpg" n="3"/>his domicile and thus he came to America taking up residence in Chicago. Directly responsible for this step was the fact that the government of Bavaria declined to appoint him, the communist, as director of the newly erected National Hospital for mental diseases. This occurred in spite of the fact that Professor Markus had recommended him for the position.</p>
   <p>Dr. Schmidt came to Chicago in 1856 and began immediately to practise medicine. He became interested in the Abolition Movement. Much of his time he devoted to this cause, in spite of his rapidly growing practise. He was a brilliant public speaker, but because of a speech he delivered in tribute to John Brown, his popularity among the wealthy class of our citizens declined.</p>
   <p>This prompted him to accept an offer as lecturer at the medical college of St. Louis which was founded by a group of prominent German physicians of that city. At the out break of the Civil War Dr. Schmidt joined the 3rd regiment of the volunteers of Missouri. He was later appointed chief of the medical staff of that regiment. Col. Osterhaus urged the physician to take over the command of a batallion, but for this he did not feel qualified.</p>
   <p>He returned to Chicago where a hearty welcome was extended to him. Times <pb facs="5418474_11_1582.jpg" n="4"/>had changed, and the speech which caused his unpopularity was now considered a noble deed. Established once more in Chicago, he became a prominent figure in politics. He was elected coroner in 1864 but resigned soon, because he could not get reconciled to the existing conditions. He made a trip to Germany in 1866, accompanied by his wife and child. This was at the outbreak of the cholera epidemic in Germany.</p>
   <p>He promptly offered his services to help to combat that dreaded disease, when he himself was stricken. Upon his recovery the German government offered to reinstate him in the service of its universities with the promise to take into consideration the years spent in foreign lands.</p>
   <p>He would have accepted the flattering offer but for his wife who warned him saying: "With your blunt speech you would last here but a few months." Convinced that it was for the best, he returned to Chicago. He resumed his work, as well as his activities in politics.</p>
   <p>The Socialists nominated him candidate for mayor in 1879, Of the 50,000 votes, 12,000 were cast for him. He gave every possible assistance to the defense of the accused Haymarket Anarchists, and contributed much toward the support of their families.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1583.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Dr. Schmidt was chief physician of the staff of the Alexian Brothers and the Michael Reese hospitals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
