<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-10-25">Oct. 25, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">A Memorable Day.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D (Jewish)</item>
     <item>III B 2 (Jewish)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-10-25">Oct. 25, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">A MEMORABLE DAY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night's celebration, at the North Side Turner Hall was one of special interest to those members of the 82nd Illinois Infantry Regiment, Illinois National Guard, who fought in the Civil War. It was the 25th anniversary of the enrollment of this regiment into the United States Army. The hall was appropriately decorated with American flags, the eagle, and the flag of the 82nd regiment. The stage on which were placed numerous pictures of tents and cannon and arms, grouped in the well known military fashion, represented a battle scene behind the lines.</p>
   <p>Comrade Peter Adler was Master of Ceremonies. After Kretlow and his orchestra had played two pieces, A. C. Hesing upon the invitation of the committee stepped on the platform and announced that the speech, which was supposed to be delivered by Hempstead Washburne, would necessarily be omitted, as death had just taken his illustrious father, Elihu B. Washburne, and added that the deceased had shown himself by various acts throughout his life, as a warm friend of the German people. This friendship was also expressed in a special wish of Elihu Washburne, that his <pb facs="5418474_11_0171.jpg" n="2"/>funeral should be conducted by German people in the German manner, and to the strains of German music. Complying with this wish, a double quartette of the Orpheus and the Germania male choruses will participate in the funeral services. The Chicago Turner community will honor the deceased with a detachment of torch bearers in the funeral procession. A request was received from the family of Mr. Washburne, for a German guard of honor from the church to the depot. The family would be highly pleased if this guard could be composed of veterans only. Complying with this honorable request sixteen members of the 82nd and the 24th Veteran's Societies were chosen.</p>
   <p>Many prominent German and English speaking citizens have gathered for the program at Turner Hall. The thirty six surviving men of the 82nd Regiment, including a negro, who as the company's cook learned to speak German, took their stand in front of the stage where comrade Peter Adler introduced each one separately, each being loudly acclaimed by the audience. General Edward S. Salomon then gave the address, which was as follows: "It is a great joy to be here with you after an <pb facs="5418474_11_0172.jpg" n="3"/>absence of sixteen years, and to participate in the anniversary festivities, and to have the opportunity to speak of the glory of the 82nd Regiment, which was composed mostly of citizens from Chicago.</p>
   <p>It was October 23rd, 1862, when the 82nd Volunteer Infantry Regiment of Illinois was attached to the standing army of the United States. The organization of this Regiment encountered many difficulties, but with the liberal help of the German Americans of this city, the regiment with its 1,000 men was soon ready for battle. I consider it my privilege to mention those patriotic and self-sacrificing citizens, in behalf of our regiment, among them A. C. Hesing who deserves to be first mentioned. The excellent, Company B, known as the Hesing sharpshooters, had an equipment which was made possible only by the generous funds Mr. Hesing put at its disposal. Another noble patriot to be mentioned is Henry Greenebaum. He called a meeting of the Israelites and urged them, in an inspiring and patriotic speech, to recruit a company for our regiment. The result was astonishing and before the meeting came to a close, twenty three recruits had enlisted in Company E, and pledges for equipment to the extent of $11,000.00 had been made. Lorenz Brentano, <pb facs="5418474_11_0173.jpg" n="4"/>then publisher of the Illinois Staats Zeitung, assisted us greatly through the mighty influence of his paper."</p>
   <p>At the end of the address, Comrade Peter Adler fastened onto General Salomon's uniform a diamond set gold medal. The upper half bears a half moon, the sign of distinction of the 11th Army Corps, and the opposite side shows a star, the mark of distinction of the 20th Army Corps. The medal also bears the inscription: "To our commander, General Edward S. Salomon; a token of love and respect from the soldiers of the 82nd Illinois Infantry Regiment, whom he led with distinguished gallantry on the battlefields of the Union." The other lower side bears the names of the various battles in which the 82nd Regiment participated. The center of the star holds a wreath composed of diamonds. General Salomon expressed, then, his deep appreciation for the exquisite gift.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
