<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-30">Apr. 30, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">To the Rhine</title><title level="a" type="sub">Leopold Neumann's Travelling Group Ready to Start</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0793</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0793.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-30">Apr. 30, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE RHINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Leopold Neumann's Travelling Group Ready to Start</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Great enthusiasm prevails among the numerous members of the travelling group conducted personally by Leopold Neumann. On June 2 they will start their journey to the old homeland from the La Salle Street Station on the Nickel Plate Railroad.</p>
   <p>Prominent Germans of Chicago who have not set foot on their native soil for forty years, and German-Americans who have only heard their parents tell how beautiful it is in Germany, have signed up for the tour. German Austrians who would like to see the old Steffel [Translator's note: Dome of St. Stephen] and their beloved Vienna again; Germans from Burgenland and Hungary, all are eager for the journey, for the trip to Niagara Falls, for the Bremer Rathskeller [Translator's note: Famous beer hall in Bremen City Hall], for the Cologne dance festival, for Munich beer, for Duesseldorf, Stuttgart, Heidelberg.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0794.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many fine cabins are still available in the third class of the splendid steamship "Republic". The complete round trip from Chicago to Bremen with the side trip to Niagara Falls, amounts to only 249, including war tax, for a third-class fare.</p>
   <p>In the luxuriously equipped second class--there is no higher class--the entire trip from Chicago to Bremen and back amounts to only $383 and up, depending upon the location of the cabin. All applications for passports are filled out free of charge in Mr. Neumann's office. Noncitizen's will receive travelling papers from Washington enabling them to return to the United States without any difficulties. The comfort of the passenmers will be looked after in every possible way.</p>
   <p>In the old homeland the travellers will be given a reception, and on the excursion on the Rhine, which is open to all for a moderate extra charge, there will be music and song and full beakers of wine. Those who have not yet registered should do so immediately.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0795.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those who wish to bring over their relatives should get in touch with Mr. Neumann, since he visits many cities in Germany, Austria, Hungary, Jugoslavia, and Rumania, and comes into direct contact with prospective immigrants.</p>
   <p>The return voyage begins August 31, 1926, from Bremen.</p>
   <p>Office: Ashland Block, room 809, 155 North Clark Street. Telephone: Dearborn 9538. Open every day until 6 o'clock in the evening; Wednesday and Saturday until 8 P. M.; Sunday from 10 A. M. to 1 P. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
