<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-08">May 8, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Wolf in Sheep's Clothing</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0330</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0330.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-08">May 8, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">WOLF IN SHEEP'S CLOTHING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A subcommittee of the Legislature is now holding open hearings on a bill the purpose of which is the registration of all aliens in the State of Illinois. The bill also stipulates that no alien who refuses to become a citizen, or who fails to secure his citizenship papers within the prescribed time, shall have the opportunity to work except with the express permission of the authorities, or shall, under any circumstances, receive public relief.</p>
   <p>As justification for this scheme it is stated that there are over three and one-half million persons in the United States who have no right to be here. These people are to be compelled to show their colors. A person who wishes to live here, the advocates of the bill declare, should also be prepared to assume the responsibilities of a citizen. They have no intention whatever of putting any pressure on the aliens, they say; their <pb facs="5418474_11_0331.jpg" n="2"/>only interest is in winning aliens over to Americanism and in confronting them with their moral obligation.</p>
   <p>The proponents of this bill have set out on one of those tortuous paths which people like to travel when they have not sufficient confidence to put their cards upon the table. [Translator's note: The mixed metaphor occurs in the original.] They could not very well send all aliens back where they came from. That might injure Americans living abroad and, in the second place, would conflict with the American's traditional humanity. It is clear, however, that an alien who becomes a public burden, as the pretty phrase puts it, is subject to deportation. That these people have spent their money here for many years, and paid their taxes, and are today helping in many ways to support the native unemployed, no longer carries any weight. They have become a "burden" and some way must be found to relieve society of it.</p>
   <p>They do not wish to force every alien to become a citizen. Oh no, not <pb facs="5418474_11_0332.jpg" n="3"/>at all! The alien is simply presented with an alternative. He has the power to decide his own fate. He is not forced to do anything.</p>
   <p>It has been pointed out with pride that applications for naturalization papers have increased lately. It is brazenly claimed that this is due to the shadow which the bill is already casting before. In reality the applications were made at the time when the social legislation was proposed because there was the prospect that, by becoming a citizen, a person might share in the benefits of the old-age pension.</p>
   <p>It is quite clear that everything that has just been said here is well known to the originators of the bill. That must remain hidden, however, and so they have recourse to clever newspaper publicity.</p>
   <p>Representatives of radical organizations were naturally the first to attack the bill. This created the impression that it was chiefly these hard-boiled elements that were worried about the proposed legislation. According to this <pb facs="5418474_11_0333.jpg" n="4"/>way of looking at it, it would be a very good thing if the law were enacted. So much fear of the radicals has been whipped up that one can be rather clumsy in approaching the anxious citizens and can still count on success. "With this drink in him" [Editor's note: The quotation is from Goethe's Faust: "Mit diesem Trank im Leibe, Bald Helenen in jedem Weibe" (With this drink in your body, you'll soon see a Helen in every woman that you meet)] the good citizen sees everything as the originators of the bill wish him to see it.</p>
   <p>To say anything more against the bill would be a waste of ink. People think that the bill is directed against radicals, and they include in this category many whose only crime was that their homeland was too small, and that they came to America thinking that prospects were better here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
