<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-11-15">Nov. 15, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Jacob Pister Celebrates His 40th Year as Pastor of St. Paul's Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1181</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1181.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-11-15">Nov. 15, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">JACOB PISTER CELEBRATES HIS 40TH YEAR AS PASTOR OF ST. PAUL'S CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Pastor Jacob Pister of the Evangelical St. Paul's Church on Orchard St. and Kemper Place, celebrates his 40th year as pastor tomorrow.</p>
   <p>On this solemn occasion, assistant pastor Dr. Scherger, will hold a German and English service.</p>
   <p>Pastor Jacob Pister was ordained at the Philipuss Church in Cincinnati, Nov. 16 1890, by his father, the president of the Synod, Pastor Jacob Pister, Sr., Pastor Jacob Mueller of Philadelphia, and Pastor Jacob Meyer, who afterwards became the Swiss Consul.</p>
   <p>Later he served three congregations in Ohio. Among these was the largest German Congregation of the State, the St. Johannis Church of Columbus.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1182.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Finally in 1911, he was appointed as assistant-Pastor of the St. Paul's Church in Chicago, whose Pastor he became in January 1926.</p>
   <p>During the forty years of his activity as minister, Pastor Pister Christened about 4000 children. He married 4500 couples, 6000 children were confirmed and 4000 church members laid to their last rest. Under his leadership the membership of St. Paul's Church increased considerably in the last few years, because he succeeded to persuade 400-500 new immigrants to become members of the church.</p>
   <p>Pastor Pister received his theological education at the seminary of Elmhurst, near Chicago and at St. Louis Mo. His former teacher, Dr. Johannes Lueder, still lives in Elmhurst. He is the father of the Chicago Postmaster, Arthur Lueder.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
