<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-11-13">Nov. 13, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">Doctor Wagner, Chief Physician of the Twenty-Fourth Illinois Infantry Regiment, Resigns</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-11-13">Nov. 13, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">DOCTOR WAGNER, CHIEF PHYSICIAN OF THE TWENTY-FOURTH ILLINOIS INFANTRY REGIMENT, RESIGNS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Doctor Wagner, who has devoted his medical knowledge and skill to the cause of the Union without interruption since the outbreak of the war, has submitted his resignation, which has been reluctantly accepted after the competent military authorities had refused several times to accept it.</p>
   <p>As most of our readers know, Doctor Wagner was assigned to the old Hecker Regiment as soon as it was organized. He accompanied this contingent on all its hazardous marches, and was side by side with his "boys" in the thick of every battle. Of late, he served as physician to General Starkweather's Brigade.</p>
   <p>Few doctors in the United States Army are as zealously and conscientously <pb facs="5418474_11_0202.jpg" n="2"/>concerned about the health and happiness of their patients and prospective patients, as Doctor Wagner was. And few army physicians, are respected and loved by soldiers and officers as greatly as was Doctor Wagner. No one will blame him for resigning his military duties, since he has been absent from home for nearly three years, and during this time has served faithfully under great disadvantages and hardships. Moreover, the Starkweather Regiment has hardly as many men as a company generally consists of, and has two able doctors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
