<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-24">Mar. 24, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A Foolish Proposal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0433</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0433.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-24">Mar. 24, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A FOOLISH PROPOSAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting which was held in New York recently, the prominent inventor Hudson Maxim stated that the English Government contemplates settling a million Chinese coolies in Canada for the purpose of further developing that country. The question whether this information is based on a firm foundation or merely on a rumor may be left unanswered. Maxim even went so far, it is true, as to say that a contract had been entered into with the Chinese, and that in this contrast the Government promised them fifty cents a day and two suits of clothes every year. It is difficult to believe that the British Government would make such an agreement with the orientals. In the first place the Canadian Government would also have to be consulted and would no doubt have a principal part in any decision on the matter. And in the second place officials here and abroad could not be oblivious of the fact that any such measure <pb facs="5418474_11_0434.jpg" n="2"/>would immediately provoke a rebellion of the working classes.</p>
   <p>As is known, many coolies were brought from the Orient to France to take the places of workers who were called to service in the army or navy. But France was actuated by necessity. Certain kinds of work had to be done, and the men who were supposed to do it were needed at the front. It was a war measure, and the French will not delay a second in returning the "borrowed" coolies to China as soon as peace has been declared. But if England or Canada is thinking of importing great numbers of coolies at this time, when the conclusion of peace is close at hand, it must be the intention of those countries to keep the coolies permanently. It is not yet known whether or not England and Canada have such plans in the making, but the mere fact that the rumor is being circulated and believed permits the inference that the conditions existing in our neighbor to the north favor such an arrangement. There must be a scarcity of farm laborers and very likely the number of discharged soldiers and sailors will not be sufficient<pb facs="5418474_11_0435.jpg" n="3"/>to supply the need.</p>
   <p>This fact is interesting because in Canada as well as in America people have been discussing the advisability and feasibility of deporting those foreigners who have not yet sufficiently Americanized themselves. Of course, it is impossible to execute the mass deportations which are demanded again and again by nationalists. If all those who were born in Germany and other alien-enemy countries are deported, it will be necessary to send their children with them. But most of these were born in America or Canada, and are, therefore, American or Canadian citizens. Then the question arises: Can the Government at Washington deport American citizens, or can the Canadian Government deport British citizens? Or is it the intention of those who advocate deportation to act like barbarians, to separate children from their parents, and to send the latter out of the country, but to hold the former? It will not be easy to solve this problem.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0436.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And is it not foolish to deport useful workmen and farmers just because they were born in a country which we have defeated in war, and then to think of importing coolies from China to supply the demand for laborers? The offspring of hatred and ignorance are often very odd.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
