<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-12-09">Dec. 9, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[Germany and the Chicago Fire]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-12-09">Dec. 9, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[GERMANY AND THE CHICAGO FIRE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How deep an impression the catastrophe of the 8th and 9th of October has made on our brothers in Germany, one cannot only see from thousands of letters, but primarily from the rich results of the collections that are taking place in all parts of Germany. That these collections are particularly undertaken for their German brothers is natural and does not show in the least a lack of sympathy for the general misfortune.</p>
   <p>In all appeals for contributions for Chicago that we have seen, the enthusiastic siding of the Chicago Germans with Germany in its war with Spain is always pointed out, and each time it is emphasized that Chicago was the first city from where material help was sent by telegraph immediately after the French declaration of war. This is perhaps not literally correct, but, on July 19, Bismarck received a telegram authorizing him to draw $200 reward for the first soldier to conquer a French flag. (The sum was drawn very punctually - by return mail). As simple as this was from the American point of view, yet it made an extraordinarily favorable impression abroad. Over there one was not accustomed to see cash rewards going to "common soldiers," but only to higher officers, and perhaps saw in the telegram a demonstration which had in no way been intended. However this may be, this telegram, the whole merit of which consisted in coming in at the first moment (it was read before the regiments leaving Berlin) is now mentioned in practically every <pb facs="5418474_11_1041.jpg" n="2"/>every German newspaper; even Lorenz Brentano points to it in the Badische Landzeitung, though in connection with it the name of the paper that he formerly edited, seems to have slipped his memory.</p>
   <p>Anyway, the main thing is, that what the Chicago Germans last year did for the German cause, now is being repaid in the spirit of the warmest and most sincere sympathy, and that a consciousness of mutual trust and belonging together is generated, which up to now existed only on this and not on the other side of the ocean. As is only fitting, the new imperial city of Berlin has shown herself especially generous. This is due in part to the activity of the highly respected American Consul, Mr. Kreismann, who has especially directed the contributions to the German inhabitants of Chicago. As an old citizen of Chicago he was able to point out how much more difficult it would be for the small house-owners of the North Side to rebuild their old property than for the possessors of the twenty times as valuable plots in the business section of the city. Yesterday, Mr. Hesing received a $9,000 check on the house of Hardt and Co., to be turned over to the German Aid Society. For the sake of curiosity, Mr. Kreismann communicates to us an anonymous letter, full of misspellings, which was sent from Chicago to President of Police, Von Wurmb. It contains (aside from a flood of those obtuse and stupid insinuations in <pb facs="5418474_11_1042.jpg" n="3"/>which primarily such Germans please themselves who have never taken the trouble to learn to understand the American people and institutions) an invitation to Herr Von Wurmb to send over two or three German officials for the sake of an efficient distribution of the German gifts. What chaos must prevail in a skull in which such an idea could thrive!</p>
   <p>That in the first weeks after the fire, in spite of the best American talent for organization, errors have been committed, is understandable enough. That all such errors were immediately exposed to the public is an American habit to which one still has to become accustomed, over there. In consequence of this, distant observers easily, vastly over-estimate the extent of existing evils, or impute to the press of this country a malicious intent, that in truth does not exist. But those criticisms long since have had the desired effect, and though it is still highly desirable to send German gifts to the German Aid Committee, yet it must in truth be confessed and declared, that the Aid and Relief Society has long since freed itself from any suspicion of anti-German prejudice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
