<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-05-08">May 8, 1909</date><title level="a">Ambassador Bernsdorff in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0910</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0910.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-05-08">May 8, 1909</date><title level="a">AMBASSADOR BERNSDORFF IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Count Johann Heinrich von Bernsdorff, the German Ambassador in Washington, returned last night from a visit to Milwaukee, where he had been invited by the Milwaukee Business League, and honored by the German organizations in a two day festival. He took residence in Chicago at the Union League Club.</p>
   <p>Graf Bernsdorff was very enthusiastic about his reception at Milwaukee and he regretted to be unable to be the guest of the German organizations in Chicago, as it was impossible for him to stay another day, having important business at Washington tomorrow. Count Bernsdorff declared that the relations between Germany and the United States were of the very best nature and President Taft like President Roosevelt his predecessor, have furthered them to a great extent. This personal relations to President Taft were very good and his position at Washington very favorable. His aim is to get the closest relationship between the United States and Germany, and he is aware that the German government has its greatest support in the German organizations in this <pb facs="5418474_11_0911.jpg" n="2"/>country, and this is well known in Washington. For this purpose he has visited the districts containing a strong German element. The attention of the Ambassador was called to a cable just received from Berlin, and published yesterday by the AmericanPress, stating that the present tariff agreement between the U. S. A. and Germany was to be discontinued, and that the news created some anxiety in Germany, as it was expected that the new tariff would not be so advantageous to the German exporter. Count von Bernsdorff replied that it was to be expected that one day the agreement would end. It is too early to mention anything, yet, about the new agreement. It cannot be said yet if the new agreement will be so unfavorable to Germany as it is anticipated in some quarters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
