<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-26">September 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Autumn Campaign</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-26">September 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE AUTUMN CAMPAIGN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A movement for promoting Germanism has been established by the formation of the German-American Club of Chicago and Cook County. The object of the organization is a local political one, but non-partisan. The founders of the club have agreed to support the candidate of German or German-American descent for public offices. Charles W. Kellermann, election commissioner, has been chosen first chairman. Mr. Otto Doedurein will be the Secretary within a week, permanent offices will be taken in the loop, probably in the Bismark Hotel, which will be retained until after election in November. In the beginning, it was Only intended to promote the election of the former city treasurer, Mr. Sturkart, but it was later agreed to extend the support to all German-Americans. Every member of the club promised to do his utmost to bring the importance of the elections to the attention of the Germans in Chicago. Alderman John Richert, chairman of the Municipal Finance Committee, made a speech, as did Alderman Haderlein, Alderman Schaeffer of the 22nd Ward, and Alderman John H. Banler. They all promised to cooperate with the Germans. This organization will try to help the German-Americans in their rights and is not antagonistic to Americans and other nationalities. The next meeting of the organization will probably be held Monday evening at the Bismark Hotel. The last speech of former President Roosevelt created a great sensation. He has however received an enthusiastic <pb facs="5418474_11_0892.jpg" n="2"/>reception in Central Illinois. The progressives cannot deny. That the Republicans gain from day to day in the West, as do their friends in the East. The Republican chief quarters will be opened at the LaSalle Hotel next Tuesday on the fourth floor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
