<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1905-09-05">September 5th, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Consul Miller's Return. He Is Not Favorable to the German Government.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0926</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0926.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1905-09-05">September 5th, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Consul Miller's Return. He Is Not Favorable To The German Government.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>J. Martin Miller has been a war correspondent for some American magazines and has written some articles, which show his hate for Germany. Reports about the bombardment of Samoa by British and American warships, in which the German navy did not participate, were written by him, in which he accused Germany of all kinds of tricks.</p>
   <p>At the time of the Boxer revolution he abused the Fieldmarshal Count Con Waldersee, who as it is known, differed with the opinion of the American General Chaffee. He also wrote about a (presumable) interview with Admiral Dewey in which the latter-supposedly made some tactless statements about the German navy. Admiral Dewey denied these statements later. Notwithstanding this, Miller had been nominated as Consul in Aachen. This representative of a friendly nation was not favorable to Germany and a notice was sent to President Roosvelt, Miller has now returned to Chicago but denies, that he had come back on an official demand. The Consul <pb facs="5418474_11_0927.jpg" n="2"/>is also implicated in the action of the beautiful Mae Wood of Denver, Col. Miss Wood had a position in the Federal Capital and had some entanglement with Senator Platt of New York, so that the Senator, who married two years ago had to pay her $50,000 conpensation. Miss Wood bought another action in which she accused Consul Miller and the private secretary of Pres. Roosvelt, Loeb, for conspiracy to get rid of her in the interest of Platt. The place of this supposed crime should have been the Victoria Hotel in New York. Miller denies the accusation and represents the girl as crazy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
