<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-08-22">Aug. 22, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Peter Joseph Weber Died.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-08-22">Aug. 22, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">PETER JOSEPH WEBER DIED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Peter Joseph Weber, who died yesterday in his home of pneumonia, was one of the most prominent architects of the middle west, if not of the whole country. He was one of those men, who erected the large exhibition buildings of the Chicago World's Fair in 1893, later he erected in Chicago and in other cities a number of beautiful buildings.</p>
   <p>He was born in Cologne, Germany 59 years ago. He studied to be an architect. As a young man he immigrated to Argentina and it was there in Buenos Aires, that he earned his first spurs, for he designed the plans of most of the beautiful buildings of the whole city. Upon hearing the news, that Chicago would have a World's Fair he apprehended the fact that our city offered an excellent opportunity to practice his profession, and therefore removed the place of his activity to Chicago. He never had to regret this, because his work was crowned with success. The plans of a large number of exhibition buildings were designed by him. The recognition was not withheld. After the world's fair, he became associated with the well known architect Daniel H. Burnham, but not satisfied, he established his <pb facs="5418474_11_1397.jpg" n="2"/>own firm. Of the Chicago buildings which he designed, belong the Illinois Trust and Savings bank, the Mercantile and Fisher Buildings; also the buildings in Ravinia Park as well as the Public Library in Seattle, Washington.</p>
   <p>The now deceased participated in all German-American movements; especially in the in the German Old People's Home, to which he contributed large amounts. He was vice president of this home for a long time.</p>
   <p>He was a member of the American Institute of Architecture, the Illinois Society of Architecture and the Chicago Athletic Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
