<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-02-22">February 22, 1904</date><title level="a">Heinrich Merker Dead</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-02-22">February 22, 1904</date><title level="a">HEINRICH MERKER DEAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At his residence 1234 Wellington Street died this morning Mr. Heinrich Merker, a man who was widely acquainted and popular in German artistic and social circles as only few can be.</p>
   <p>Heinrich Merker, born in 1858, and son of well-to-do parents at Rothenburg on the Saale, received an excellent school education. After serving as a one-year volunteer at the guards-dragoon regiment in Berlin, he followed his love for the dramatic art, took a course at the Leipzig Stage School and became an actor. After playing for several years at different theatres in Austria and Hungary he came to America in 1884, and accepted an engagement with Isenstein and Collmer in Milwaukee. In the following year he moved to Chicago where Editor Witte in Ottawa engaged him as editor for the "Central Illinois Wochenblatt". Two years later he joined the staff of the Staats-Zeitung", with which concern he was connected for about twelve years. In 1898 he moved to Davenport with <pb facs="5418474_11_1537.jpg" n="2"/>the expectation that it would be possible for him to bring to the stage his composition of the "Blackhawk War". These hopes he could not realize. Merker returned to Chicago and became a member of the Staff of the "Abendpost".</p>
   <p>The deceased was a man of the most amiable and polite ways of conduct, and these forms corresponded with the honest, duty bound character of Merker.</p>
   <p>He leaves his wife, and three children at the age of six - eleven years. His body will be cremated, according to his own wishes, so that his family can bury his ashes in his beautiful homeland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
