<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-05-20">May 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Banquet Given by German University Students.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0763</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0763.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-05-20">May 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">BANQUET GIVEN BY GERMAN UNIVERSITY STUDENTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The assertion that some day Chicago would be chosen as a university city by German students would have been ridiculed several years ago. First of all, the distance from Germany is too great and secondly the expense of studying abroad is prohibitive to most German students.</p>
   <p>But meanwhile times have changed; the political situation and the relations between the countries make it desirable and possible for American students to go to Germany and vice versa, German students can come to America to study at American universities. It is significant that the number of German students studying at American universities is steadily increasing from year to year.</p>
   <p>Very few know that at the present time, a bout 35 German students are in Chicago, the majority of whom are studying at the University of Chicago. The so-called "Working Students in America" form a special group; they are working in American industrial plants for two years and then they return to Germany.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0764.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A group of other students is sent to America to study by the courtesy of the Rockefeller Foundation and the American German Student Exchange. Among the German students of Chicago there are also girl students. These students have now formed the "Group of German Students" of Chicago which will appear for the first time in public at a banquet at the Bismarck Hotel at which it is hoped to e stablish connections with those American circles and personalities that are interested in Germany. It is expected that the attendance of German-Americans will be very large.</p>
   <p>Among the speakers will be the German Consul-General, Dr. H. F. Simon, who has promised to come, and also the president of the German Club, Michael F. Girten. Professor Schutze of the German department at the University of Chicago and Professor G. B. Smith of the Divinity School of the University of Chicago, also will speak.</p>
   <p>Dr. Otto Brok, who came to America at the request of the Rockefeller Foundation, will speak in the name of the "Group of German Students in Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
