<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Record</title>,
<date when="1893-06-07">June 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Turners Are Angry. German Day at the Exposition Has Been Fixed for June 15.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0986</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0986.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Record</title>,
<date when="1893-06-07">June 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">TURNERS ARE ANGRY. GERMAN DAY AT THE EXPOSITION HAS BEEN FIXED FOR JUNE 15.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A hitch has occurred, however, which threatens to overturn the plans of Herr Wermuth and his friends, for the celebration of German Day, June 15, is the anniversary of the Emperor William's accession to the imperial throne of Germany. On that day will also be held the general elections for the return of members to the new reichstag.</p>
   <p>Those (Germans) who are citizens of the United States for the most part sympathize with the German parliamentarians who are fighting Emperor William's army bill, and they hope the new reichstag will refuse to adopt it, as did the parliament recently dissolved.</p>
   <p>It seems that the fact that the Germans of the World's Fair city will celebrate their national day on June 15, has been taken as an indication, in some quarters, that they indorse Emperor William's military policy and desire him to succeed at the elections. The turner societies of Chicago, which represent most of the brain and brawn of the race, most energetically disavow all sympathy with ideas of military aggrandizemend and they have emphatically refused to participate in the procession on German Day if it is understood that by <pb facs="5418474_11_0987.jpg" n="2"/>doing so they are but in the position of indorsing Emperor William and his plan of campaign.</p>
   <p>A leading member of the turner's society said last night: "Unless it is made clear that we are not to march on June 16, to glorify William, 20,000 turners will withdraw and hold a separate parade. Some prominent Germans living in America are sympathizers with the autocratic plans of the emperor, and they think to snatch an indorsement by getting us to celebrate his accession, and that, too, on the day of the general election. We detest militarism and monarchy, and we can't be used for any such purpose. The society in its convention at Joliet, decided to take no part unless given proper assurance that our participation will not be made use of in a political way. We believe that our German Day primarily is meant as an occasion when German-American should turn out and show their strength to the world. It is not meant to glorify kings nor emperors, and we intend it shall not be diverted to such uses if we can hinder it. Without the participation of the German masses the day cannot be made a success, and probably Herr Wermuth and his courtly advisers will come to see it. If they don't the celebration will become a favor."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
