<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-21">September 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Inciting a Breach of Neutrality</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0893</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0893.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-21">September 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">INCITING A BREACH OF NEUTRALITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>England has stated from the beginning that the violation of the neutrality of Belgium has caused the Great War of Europe, and that it was a case of honor for Albion to defend the violation of International treaties. Two members of the English Government the author Bernard Shaw and two members of Parliament Keir Hardie and Ramsay McDonald were of a different opinion, but the honor of Sir Edward Grey had been accepted. No proof was offered that Germany did break the treaty of the neutrality of Belguim. This particular agreement had been signed in London on November 15, 1831 by Prussia. The German empire was founded 40 years later and cannot be kept responsible for the obligations of Prussia signed 40 years previously. On the other hand Belgium had broken the neutrality agreement long before when she fortified her German frontier with French money and permitted French aviators to fly over her territory without protest, to throw bombs on German towns, before the war was declared. Italy had contracted a triple alliance with Germany to join her in case of war or in the least to maintain a benevolent neutrality. The honorable England, which stands and fights for the maintenance of treaties is trying with all kinds of promises to incite Italy to break her alliance with Germany and fight against her former ally. This is English morality in the light of truth. Furthermore England is trying her utmost to induce this country to give up her neutrality and involve her in the <pb facs="5418474_11_0894.jpg" n="2"/>European war. England is not satisfied in having mobilized troops in this country to fight against Germany and that she notwithstanding American neutrality procures horses, arms, ammunition, food etc. A local Anglo - American newspaper is violating the neutrality of this country in publishing an appeal to the American public by the London author Hall Caine, who writes: Is the neutrality of America justified? Is it possible, that in the terrible battle for justice, which has rocked the whole world to its foundation, a country of 90 million people in the States can remain neutral and look on, how all of Europe is destroying each other, their brothers blood relatives, people allied with them in intellectual ties, religious sympathies etc. Can they really maintain, that the bloody war is not their business, that they have nothing to do with the origin of the war? England also had nothing to do with it but still we were obliged to take part, duty bound by the articles of the moral code, which regulates the conditions between Nations and men.</p>
   <p>Such an article has been permitted to be published in this country by a foreigner while the President of the U. S. A. has refused to hear the petition of tens of thousands of good German-Americans, who stand for the maintenance of the peace of the Republic. The enemies of Germany are encouraged to do their duty work of inciting the break of neutrality over here, while the friends of the Republic, who have given their blood and labor for the good of the land are handicapped <pb facs="5418474_11_0895.jpg" n="3"/>everywhere. This is called in Washington, "Maintaining neutrality". Shell we Germans still keep a policy of reserve or is it time to show our teeth? If we wait much longer it will be too late. We shall nave no more teeth to show.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
