<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-10-07">Oct. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Germans Honor Carl Bunge, Musician and Man</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1157</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1157.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-10-07">Oct. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO GERMANS HONOR CARL BUNGE, MUSICIAN AND MAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>German circles of Chicago have fulfilled a duty toward a man who for almost forty years has played a leading role in the musical life of the city, especially in the musical life of the Germans of Chicago,--a man who by magnanimous self-sacrifice has created cultural values which will long outlast the short span of human life. To evaluate this man's artistic activity, it would be necessary to write the history of Chicago's musical life, beginning with the World's Fair of 1893. Today, at the threshold of old age, he can look back with satisfaction on his life's work, through which the glory of Chicago as a musical center has been extended far beyond the borders of the State of Illinois, and he has earned the honor of increasing the esteem with which Germans are regarded by the American nation.</p>
   <p>This man is Dr. Carl Bunge, the Nestor of Chicago's German musicians, who was simply and worthily honored yesterday afternoon on the occasion of his seventy-fifth birthday by a group of men prominent in public life who gathered <pb facs="5418474_11_1158.jpg" n="2"/>in the Bismarck Hotel. That Dr. Bunge's activity through many years of devoted service to the public is appreciated by the city was best proved by the presence of Mayor Anton J. Cermak, who appeared shortly after the opening of the celebration. A suggestion in the Abendpost resulted in the attendance of many prominent citizens of the German circles of Chicago, among whom were a number of Dr. Bunge's personal friends, including Dr. Otto L. Schmidt and Karl Eitel.</p>
   <p>Act of Unveiling</p>
   <p>In a short speech, Dr. Schmidt, acting as chairman of the celebration, pointed out its purpose, which was to afford to the grateful German citizens of Chicago an occasion to show their recognition of Dr. Bunge's services in promoting German music abroad and at home. Without keeping the guests waiting, Miss Kuebler proceeded to unveil the portrait of Dr. Bunge painted by the master hand of Professor J. Noerdlinger; it depicts the composer in his favorite pose as conductor.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1159.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After Mayor Cermak, greeted with hearty applause, had made his appearance, Ernest J. Kruetgen delivered an impressive speech in which he pointed out the influence of the German spirit in promoting idealism among the American people. In the hard, practical environment of this dollar-seeking country, said he, the German element has carried the thought of idealism to the masses. The activities and aspirations of Dr. Bunge himself have resulted in the founding of a number of musical and singing societies.</p>
   <p>The Life and Career of Dr. Bunge</p>
   <p>Carl Bunge was born October 4, 1856, at Luneburg, Hannover, Germany, and displayed at an early age a marked inclination and an uncommon talent for music. After he had received a thorough musical education in Hannover, his visits to Berlin and Hamburg gave a decisive turn to his career and attracted the attention of prominent musicians to his rare ability; his musical career was thus assured from the beginning. His good fortune remained steadfast as he <pb facs="5418474_11_1160.jpg" n="4"/>continued to practice his vocation. Dr. Bunge's performances on European concert stages caused a merited sensation in the musical world, and he had occasion to work with great artists such as Hans von Buelow, Rubinstein, Tschaikowski, Mahler, Sucher, and Weingartner. Engagements with the operatic orchestras of London, St. Petersburg, Berlin, Hannover, and Hamburg followed, and then, after thirteen years' activity in Hamburg, Dr. Bunge felt the desire to travel, and the World's Fair of 1893 attracted him to Chicago, [which he made his permanent place of residence].</p>
   <p>Mayor Cermak Speaks</p>
   <p>The Mayor tendered the congratulations of the citizens of Chicago to Dr. Bunge as a meritorious promoter of music and also seized the opportunity to thank the German element of Chicago's population for its support in the last election. The crusade which he is leading, said he, is not an easy one, and only his determination to pull Chicago out of its dilemma and put it on a sound financial basis makes him stick to his work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
