<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-03-12">March 12, 1896</date><title level="a">Concerning the School Administration the George Schneider School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-03-12">March 12, 1896</date><title level="a">Concerning the School Administration The George Schneider School</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was resolved to name the new school at the corner of Hoyne and Wellington Avenue after the well-known banker George Schneider.</p>
   <p>Mr. Schneider, born in Pirmasence in the Palatinate, Participated in the revolution in his homeland during the years 1848 and 1849, and came, after its suppression in France to the United States. After a short stop in St. Louis he settled down in Chicago and together with Robert Hoeffgen created a daily paper out of the weekly Illinois Staats-Zeitung. On the slavery question he occupied a firm attitude in favor of abolition, and played a prominent part in the foundation of the Republican Party. In the year 1861 he was nominated as Consul in Helsingfors by President Lincoln with whom he stood in personal contact. During his absence from Chicago he found it necessary to dissolve his connections with the StaatsZeitung on account of the sharp attacks this paper directed against Lincoln. In the year 1867 Mr. Schneider exchanged the field of activity as a journalist with the one of a financier. The National Bank of Illinois at whose head he stood for</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1681.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>decades as president, is one of the most important banking institutions of the country. Although Mr. Schneider has passed the seventy mark by three years already, he still takes an active interest in public affairs. As an active member of important Committees he performed valuable services on the directorate of the World's Fair Company for their magnificent undertakings. In order to strengthen the Chicago delegation to the National Convention of the party, the Republicans of the First Congressional District were permitted by the machine to vote for Mr. Schneider as a member of this group, but Mr. Schneider assures us that he will act at the Convention according to his own judgement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
