<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-17">Nov. 17, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Who Does Not Know Him? George K. Schmidt</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Picture of Mr. Schmidt Appears in Article]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1223</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1223.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-17">Nov. 17, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">WHO DOES NOT KNOW HIM? GEORGE K. SCHMIDT</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Picture of Mr. Schmidt Appears in Article]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>George K. Schmidt, member of the City Council, was born in Chicago in 1869. His father, Kasper George Schmidt, came to the United States in the year 1854, settling in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Schmidt was educated in the Chicago elementary schools, attended the German and English Academy in Milwaukee, and completed his studies at the Gymnasium in Worms, Germany.</p>
   <p>In the year 1897, Schmidt and his father, who was then vice-president of the Bank of Commerce, founded the Bank of K. G. <pb facs="5418474_11_1224.jpg" n="2"/>Schmidt and Son on Clybourn and North Avenue.</p>
   <p>After the death of his father, Schmidt continued the business, and in 1919 organized the Prudential State and Savings Bank on Halsted Street and North Avenue. He is the president of the firm. In the same year he was elected treasurer of the Wieland Ice Cream Company and also became a director of the Standard Trust and Savings Bank.</p>
   <p>Like his father, Schmidt interested himself in politics at an early age. From 1902 to 1906 he was alderman of the old 24th Ward, and from 1917 until 1923 he served as county commissioner, When Mayor Thompson was re-elected in 1927, he appointed Schmidt vice-president of local improvements, and when City Treasurer Fitzmorris left the office on October 1, Schmidt became his successor.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1225.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Schmidt married Miss Susanna Thome of Chicago in 1894. He is affiliated with many clubs and lodges, being a member of the Schwabenverein (Southern German Club), German American Citizens' Alliance, Song Club Harmony, and the Plattdeutsche Gilden (Pomeranian guild), and others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
