<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-11-27">Nov. 27, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">William Boeppler Celebrates 40th Anniversary as Conductor.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-11-27">Nov. 27, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">WILLIAM BOEPPLER CELEBRATES 40TH ANNIVERSARY AS CONDUCTOR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Singing Society, together with the Chicago Bach Chorus, the Bethany church choir and the Lake View Musical Society will celebrate the 40th anniversary of William Boeppler as choir master.</p>
   <p>Mr. Boeppler, well known personality in Chicago musical circles, especially among the Germans, and whose reputation reaches far beyond the boundaries of Chicago, celebrates this rare jubilee at the zenith of his activity.</p>
   <p>On this occasion we deem it proper to give a short biography of William Boeppler. He was born February 21, 1863. He studied theology, philosophy, history and languages at the Universities of Leipzig and Bonn and devoted all his leisure time to music.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1288.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>His teachers were men of reputation, like Gisbert Euzian of Kreuguach, Max Fiedler and Gustav Langer of Leipzig and Arnold Mendelssohn of Bonn.</p>
   <p>In 1887 he adopted music as his profession and that year conducted his first chorus, the Evangelical Church Choir of Crefeld. After further years of study, he emigrated to America in 1894 and settled in Milwaukee. There he founded the Milwaukee A Capella Choir, which under his leadership became one of the best choirs of the country. The following year he returned to Germany, but only to bring his wife, Ida Brueggeman of Wiesbaden, to America.</p>
   <p>After returning to Milwaukee, his sphere of activity widened. He became music critic of the Milwaukee Herald and later of the Germania. In 1899 he founded the well known Wisconsin Conservatory of Music, which later became one of the best musical institutes of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1289.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1904 he founded the Milwaukee Symphony Orchestra with which he performed numerous great concerts. Later this orchestra deprived of its leader, was dissolved when he moved to Chicago, where a greater field of activity was awaiting him.</p>
   <p>In Chicago he began his activity as conductor of the Germania Men's Chorus and of the Turner Men's Chorus, while continuing in the meantime his activities in Milwaukee, on Mondays and Tuesdays. In 1910 he organized the Chicago Suigverein the musical leadership of which he has held since that time. He also became chorus master of the First National Bank Chorus and of the Birchwood Ladies Chorus, which later became the Lake View Choir.</p>
   <p>In 1925 he also conducted the Chicago Bach Choral Society and the Bethany Church Choir.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1290.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Besides his activities in the different singing societies he was, in 1914-15, conductor of the North Side Turner Hall Concerts, and in the same year conducted the musical part of the 75th anniversary celebration of the Chicago Turner Society. He founded the Boeppler Symphony Orchestra, but had to relinguish it on account of ill health and over-work.</p>
   <p>In 1924 he conducted, during the North American singers festival, the great mixed chorus, at the Coliseum.</p>
   <p>During the following years, he performed with his choirs among others the following works of German masters: "St. Matthew's Passion" and other numerous cantatas by Bach; the "Missa Solemnis" and the Beethoven "9th Symphony;" the "Requiem" by Brahms, "The Creation" and "Four Sessans" by Haydn, "The Messiah," and "Samson" and "Judas Maccabeus" by Handel, Mendelsohn's "Elias," Schumann's "Mother Earth" and "On the Ocean," as well as numerous other.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1291.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Besides this, Mr. Boeppler has won a reputation as singing teacher and as teacher of piano and conducting.</p>
   <p>The Beethoven House of Bonn-on-the-Rhine appointed him as a member. He is the only American who has thus been honored.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
