<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-03-03">March 3, 1902</date><title level="a">Welcome Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0944</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0944.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-03-03">March 3, 1902</date><title level="a">Welcome Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With extraordinary satisfaction the Germans of Chicago bid welcome to Prince Henry, because his visit in the United States is a continuation of their own efforts to admit no ill-feeling between their motherland and the land of their choice. When the British incitements in this country started to produce an unexpected and inexplicable result and a large part of the English-American Press talked itself into a kind of war fury against Germany, the Germans of this city arranged a protest meeting that put an end to the alarm. They declared that there exists not the smallest reason for suspicion or for enmity from Germany, and that the attempts to stamp the entire American people as Anglo-Saxon or English, must be rejected firmly. Their protest found an echo over the entire nation and did not fail of its impression on the yellow press as well as the Federal Government. At least after this day another tone was evident.</p>
   <p>Since the German Emperor endeavored with great success to destroy the falsehood-webs of the British and to prove to the American people that Germany never has obstructed the way of the United States, and above all, never had any intention of snatching away the Philippine Islands or to found colonies <pb facs="5418474_11_0945.jpg" n="2"/>on American soil. In order to give them a positive proof of his friendly attitude, he ordered his only brother to pay a visit to the American people. The truly enthusiastic reception that was prepared everywhere to Prince Henry, shows without doubt that the Kaiser selected the right remedy, but he could hardly have reaped such a success if everything had not been prepared so excellently by the German-Americans. Therefore the Germans of Chicago, who started the ball rolling without immodesty can take credit for the warm demonstrations for Prince Henry and the country he represents as the crowning of their efforts.</p>
   <p>They salute the representative of the German Imperial House as a guest of the entire nation and as bearer of peace and friendship messages. First because they have become good and faithful citizens of the United States they rejoice that the connections are becoming closer between the land of their birth and their new homeland. Prince Henry is most heartily welcome to all of them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
