<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-10-01">Oct. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Peter Ellert Dead.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1392</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1392.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-10-01">Oct. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">PETER ELLERT DEAD.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The many friends and acquaintances of Mr. Peter Ellert, will learn with regret, that he died suddenly yesterday in his home, 1828 Barry Avenue. He went to the basement to get something, but did not come back and when they were looking for him, he was found dead, apparently the victim of heart disease. In August of this year, Peter Ellert celebrated in full rigor his seventieth birthday. He enjoyed the best of health, attended to his business Saturday as usual, and was in good spirits, even yesterday noon. A few hours later he was lying on his bier.</p>
   <p>Born in Flensburg, Ellert came to Chicago as a young man, and became a lawyer, enjoying a good name. In 1892 he was chosen for alderman. He attended faithfully to his official work and fully justified the confidence placed in him. After that he became secretary of the county council, in later years he acted as secretary of the Forest Preserve Administration. Lately he held the office of County Council's executive secretary. He was well posted in administration affairs of the county, and as such was often asked for advice.</p>
   <p>The deceased played in former years a prominent part among the Germans of the city. He was one of the oldest members of the Aurora Turnverein, and also belonged to <pb facs="5418474_11_1393.jpg" n="2"/>the Chicago Lincoln Club and the German Club. His wife and a daughter, Mrs. Anna Louise Stude in Milwaukee survive him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
