<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-07-31">July 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Albert W. Beilfuss Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-07-31">July 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ALBERT W. BEILFUSS DIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The representative of the 15th Ward in the city council died after a long illness, yesterday morning. Alderman W. Beilfuss, known as the father of playgrounds in Chicago, and councilman of the 15th Ward was the victim of heart disease, of which he suffered for several months. The deceased held this office since 1896, and was continuously re-elected by the citizens of his district. They knew and respected him for his reliability and for his honesty. He was a great lover of children, and in order to improve the health conditions of the little ones in a big city like Chicago he used all his influence, to erect playgrounds in different parts of the city, in which he succeeded in the main. He is, therefore, justly called the "father of playgrounds". Alderman Beilfuss was born in Prussia, and came to the United States with his parents in 1868, settling in Oswego, N. Y. He learned the printing trade, and moved to Chicago, in 1886, worked on the Freie Presse, later joining the printing business of Severinghaus, which was conducted under the firm name of Severinghaus and Beilfuss, he becoming its treasurer. He leaves, besides his wife, four daughters and a son. Among the Chicago Germans, the deceased was highly <pb facs="5418474_11_1459.jpg" n="2"/>respected for his conscientiousness and well known human traits, especially his love for children. The city council held a special meeting last Friday, to bring resolutions on the occasion of his death and to make for official participation at his funeral, which will take place Sunday afternoon. The directors of all playgrounds were requested to raise the flags to half mast, and to tell the children that the man who made it possible for them to breathe fresh air and to amuse themselves, has died.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
