<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-08-14">Aug. 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Distinguished Page in German-American History. General Niklas Hershheimer.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-08-14">Aug. 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A DISTINGUISHED PAGE IN GERMAN-AMERICAN HISTORY. GENERAL NIKLAS HERSHHEIMER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On August 17, 1927 it will be the 150th anniversary of the day, when one of the most prominent and famous figures of the American War of Independence had to pay with his life, because of his love for liberty and his loyalty to his fatherland.</p>
   <p>General Niklas Hershheimer, born of German parents, on Aug. 17, 1777, succumbed to wounds which he had received ten days before in the murderous battle of Oriskany, in which his troops were victorious. He died at his home in the Mohawk Valley in the state of New York. This battle is mentioned in American history as one of the deciding factors in the War of Independence; justly the contemporaries of Hershheimer valued his <pb facs="5418474_11_0128.jpg" n="2"/>courage and his capabilities by naming a city after him. A monument proclaims his fame, and yet, the public in general knows him only by the transformed name - Herkimer, and does not know his good German name - Hershheimer. This transformation, many German names have had to undergo in America....</p>
   <p>It was in the year 1776. The ringing of the Liberty bells, which were calling the country to war against English tyranny had echoed also in the peaceful valleys of the Hudson, the Mohawk and Schohaire, in the state of New York. There, - not far from today's city, Little Falls, at the junction of the Schoharie and the Mohawk, near Troy and the town of Herkimer - German immigrants, after many hardships, had found peace and permanent homes. War against the French and battles with the Indians kept the German colonists of the Mohawk Valley in practice.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0129.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore when the time arrived and Liberty bells called, the German immigrants on the Hudson, Schoharie and Mchawk, were not farmers any longer, whom the King of England could sacrifice. Now it was their turn to "check the King." Not as hired soldiers of a greedy monarch, but as free citizens fighting for home and independence, did they go into the war. The approach of the revolution had split the population of the state of New York into two factions. The large land owners and the merchants sided with England, while the young people, the small business men and the working classes desired freedom. In the Mohawk Valley the German farmers were also enthusiastic adherents of the revolution, while on the other hand, the old colonial aristocracy favored England.</p>
   <p>In Tyron County, which included the territories of the Mohawk Valley, the Republicans, mostly Germans, organized in 1775 a safety council to protect the country against the Indians.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0130.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This safety committee organized its fighting forces in four battalions which were commanded by four German Colonels. Niklas Hershheimer was in command of the first battalion, Jacob Klock of the second, Friedrich Fischer of the third and Hanjost Herchheimer of the fourth.</p>
   <p>In the Hershheimer battalion all the officers, with the exception of one lieutenant, were Germans. The president of the safety committee, Johannes Ball, was also a German. The Declaration of Independence found the Germans on the Mohawk River ready to fight, but almost two years passed before the war reached the valleys of the Mohawk and Schoharie. But when in June 1777, the English General Burgogne decided to advance from Canada along the Hudson River to New York, and Colonel St. Leger was sent with 750 soldiers and 1000 Indians into the Mohawk Valley, Hershheimer, who in the meantime had been appointed a general , issued a call to arms. All the men between the ages of 16 and 60 were recruited and assembled where now lies the city of Herkimer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
