<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-12">Aug. 12, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Emigration from Northern Germany During the Last Twenty Years</title><title level="a" type="sub">(For the Illinois Staats-Zeitung)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-12">Aug. 12, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">EMIGRATION FROM NORTHERN GERMANY DURING THE LAST TWENTY YEARS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(For the Illinois Staats-Zeitung)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In looking at the immigrants at Castle Garden one finds that it is still the "little fellow" as of yore, the laborer or the tradesman, who constitutes the vast majority, precisely as twenty years ago. But the journey formerly made by hundreds is now made by thousands. Have the conditions affecting these people changed so materially that they find it necessary to emigrate? To answer this question we must consider life--then and now.</p>
   <p>According to former laws a child born on a farm or in a city was legally restricted and considered a subject of the country or the city.</p>
   <p>If a person in later years wanted to obtain a job elsewhere, then a certificate had to be shown wherein was recorded the bearer's place of birth, <pb facs="5418474_11_0576.jpg" n="2"/>and a statement had to be obtained of the landowner or the mayor permitting the applicant to seek employment beyond the boundaries of his own community. No employment could be obtained without these documents because if the applicant became a pauper, or even if he became ill, the district in which the jobseeker was born had to take care of him. Even marriages could not be contracted unless the officials of the community consented because such an act might cause the impoverishment of the individual and thereby would cause a drain on the public treasury. If a young man had a job on a farm, then he tried to ingratiate himself with the proprietor so that he could advance and take the place of a [regular] laborer if one should die. The average salary was $15 to $24 a year and enabled him to buy a cow or a goat and one or two pigs, to which his employer gave his consent, of course. His bride earned less, but from her meager savings she managed to buy a bed and a few of the most essential household articles. So the marriage ceremony could be performed when the laborer had received [the proprietor's] permission. A few children were usually already present, since courtship lasted for many years, and <pb facs="5418474_11_0577.jpg" n="3"/>morality in the country districts was nothing to brag about; all that one could say was that betrothed [brides] remained faithful. The laborer had a good income, according to his own opinion. In the winter at threshing time he earned enough grain to supply bread throughout the year, and he raised enough potatoes to feed the family and fatten his pig. A few chickens produced enough eggs for his needs, and he also planted flax so that he had cloth for shirts and workclothes. Milk was supplied by his cow or his goat. His earnings, as far as money was concerned, were small; the average income was fifteen cents a day, but supplemented by the sale of hams, it was enough, and he saved a little, provided that there were no accidents, and that no sickness occurred. The poor were put into the poorhouse and worked there according to their ability. These paupers were families of which the provider had died and a few old persons who had no living relatives. Everybody abhorred the poorhouse, which usually had only two rooms, one for men and the other for women and children; the kitchen was shared by all, and consequently only two people, as a rule, lived at <pb facs="5418474_11_0578.jpg" n="4"/>the poorhouse, the most incompatible man and the most loathsome shrew. The laborer's widow married again if she was not too old, often [taking as husband] an exceedingly young farm worker, just to escape from the poorhouse; and lonesome old people lived with their children if they had any. The people were not accustomed to anything else. True, some families emigrated; but when glowing accounts of the new continent arrived, no one believed the stories because reports had been cunningly disseminated that the letters were only written to induce people to go to America so that they mignt be fleeced. Indeed, in one particular instance a lazy fellow came to America, and here he was more dissatisfied and more disinclined to work than he had been at home; so he wrote to his former boss for money to return, and the request was gladly granted. What the penitent sinner related upon his return was of such nature that no one for miles around thought about leaving. And such cases were numerous.</p>
   <p>Then came the year 1866. The soldiers from the country districts and <pb facs="5418474_11_0579.jpg" n="5"/>the small towns saw different environments, different people, and more liberal institutions, and they became familiar with a better mode of life. It made them think, and upon returning to the old localities, they found them too much restricted. The letters from the United States were now regarded differently; more understanding had come to the people, and many decided to emigrate. And the war of 1870 made the people still more receptive to the idea of freedom, since they perceived the less restricted conditions prevailing in France. The letters of emigrants who had left after the Austrian war [1866] generally contained good news, and so emigration reached unheard-of proportions.</p>
   <p>When the Gruenderjahre [boom years after the Franco-Prussian War] brought easy money and high profits, emigration diminished, but the crash followed, and with it a cessation of industrial activity.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, personal-property taxes were increased, and this particular brand of tax found especial disfavor among those who were not well to do, <pb facs="5418474_11_0580.jpg" n="6"/>since low salaries and rising living costs tended to make money scarce, and usually when cash was at a very low ebb, the tax collector came around to gather a small sum, a trifling amount in the latter's opinion, but really large as far as the little man was concerned. Besides, the average person had become accustomed to better living at the time of the war, and in the boom years thereafter, and in hard times which followed it was difficult to forget past prosperity and to become used to present restrictions. Although the administration passed new laws which eased the tension, dissatisfaction was not entirely eliminated because matters appertaining to liberty were generally held in abeyance. The new residential law which permitted a person to marry without obtaining consent if he had resided for two years in a community turned out to be a two-edged sword. The large landowners did not like to keep their laborers for two years so as to let them become residents. Instead, the landowner preferred to rent a place for them in some village or small town and to support them for two years [there] to get rid of them [for they would then be residents of the town]. As a result of this policy certain communities <pb facs="5418474_11_0581.jpg" n="7"/>were overcrowded with poor people, and consequently a high tax was levied to take care of them. All this promoted emigration.</p>
   <p>Besides, there were many successive crop failures, and farmers kept fewer laborers; but taxes did not decrease. They were even higher, for the works begun by the administration, such as churches and schools, in the boom years now arrived at completion. Whoever [now] owns land, from the smallest gardener who spades his plot of ground to the largest farmer, wants to sell. Regardless of the fact that the German prefers agricultural pursuits, and that prices are commensurate with actual values, offers to sell [now] exceed the demand. One need only look into the smallest country sheet or the largest city newspaper to verrify this assertion. And nearly all the people who wish to sell their land offer it with the intention of coming to America. Whoever has cash would rather let it remain in the bank, where no interest is obtained, than invest it. To this must be added the alarming conditions in Russia and their possible effect on Germany.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0582.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Although emigration apparently has subsided in Germany, in the fall and spring it will reach considerable proportions again. One must consider that according to German law the laborer can only quit his job in the spring or the fall. And then there is this year's crop failure in northern Germany to be reckoned with. Winter crops were practically destroyed by the severity and changeability of the weather, and summer crops, in many instances, failed to come up. Since March there have been continous drought and wind. Pastures are bare, and livestock must be fed on the clover intended for winter use. How herds will be depleted, how many heads of cattle must be sold in the fall in order to conserve feed for the remainder and keep them alive till next spring, can only be conjectured. And livestock is the main source of income for the farmers of northern Germany. No grain or dairy products to sell! Not only do the people in the eastern provinces complain, but even the cattle breeders in areas so highly cultivated as Mecklenburg, Holstein, and Pomerania. All the letters received from private sources in these districts express the same thought:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0583.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"Since March we have had no rain except that in July there was one shower which soaked the ground. How will it end?"</p>
   <p>Taxes, bills, and interest, however must be paid; these three things are oblivious to good or hard times. As a result of the succession of bad seasons the farmers now have little cash, and even people regarded as very wealthy have collapsed. It is not overpopulation which induces people to cross the sea but actual want. The wars of recent years made the people of northern Germany realize their situation, and necessity has showed them the way to make a better living; and while a German does not gladly leave his native land, actual want drives rich and poor alike to our shores.</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Elvers</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
