<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-30">September 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Is the German Outlawed in This Country?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0888</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0888.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-30">September 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IS THE GERMAN OUTLAWED IN THIS COUNTRY?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It appears as if the most Democratic Government of all countries has made it a principle to muzzle the German citizen of this country and force him to accept insults and humilations without protest. The slaves were permitted to trample down German and Austrian flags and the neutral Secretary of State, Bryan gave a willing ear to the lies told him. The Anglo-American newspapers are permitted to publish inflammatory articles by British authors as Sir A. Conan Doyle, Hall Caine, etc. A Belgium Delegation was permitted an interview with President Wilson to submit their lies of cruelties and atrocities to a neutral country. American diplomats were permitted openly to express their views and official buildings showed the British flags. Americans can sell all kind of war materials, ammunition, food, etc., to Germamys enemies. Our neutral administration does not object to this violation of neutrality. If a German however defends the violation of his right, he will be muzzled, as he is an enemy of America because he violates the neutrality. If the editor of this paper protests in the name of ten thousand petitioners, who wish to prevent the publication of the lies and libels, he gets no audience with President Wilson. Are we German citizens outlawed in this country? And shall we keep <pb facs="5418474_11_0889.jpg" n="2"/>quite after this treatment? Today's news from Washington states that President Wilson will censure Congressman Richardt Bartholdt because of his speech made in New York. Mr. Wilson forgets that Czarism has not yet been established in this country and that Congressmen are no schoolboys. The responsibility of a Congressman rests with his electors and not with school master Wilson. Mr. Richard Bartholdt made a speech in New York on German day, in which he dared, according to history, to prove that the Germans all times, especially in times of danger, have shown themselves friends of the Union, while England and France at different times have shown their hostile dispositions. His speech was as follows. "Did we forget that, during the Civil War, the Germans were our only friends, while Great Britain destroyed our commerce? Did not Bismark receive the American delegates, who had been refused admission in London and Paris with open arms and procured the money they needed? Did not Gladstone openly wish success to the confederates? Japan will demand her pound of flesh and perhaps Uncle Sam must give it to her. Perhaps, already she has been promised the superiority in the Pacific for the support she is giving to Great Britain. Who, I ask, if the hour of decision arrives, will be the natural ally of the United States.</p>
   <p>This question Wilson did not want to be asked, as he does not like to answer <pb facs="5418474_11_0890.jpg" n="3"/>it truthfully. For this reason the Congressman should be censured. Which country do we live in? Is everybody, who is not an enemy of Germany, outlawed? The patience of the good-humored German can also come to an end and we shall not keep quiet and be muzzled while official America preaches hate against Germans. As free citizens, we object to being "school mastered" and as Germans we protest against the violations of our sentiments even if they come from the Czar in the tail-coat.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
