<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-22">Sep. 22, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Republicans Interfere with the Naturalization Work of the Democrats.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 2 (Polish)</item>
     <item>I F 2 (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>I F 2 (German)</item>
     <item>I F 2 (Swedish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-22">Sep. 22, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE REPUBLICANS INTERFERE WITH THE NATURALIZATION WORK OF THE DEMOCRATS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The county judges held a conference yesterday in order to standardize the proceedings appertaining to naturalization. This became necessary as several judges, the younger ones in particular, relied upon their own interpretation of the law and their opinion was not always in conformity with the actual intent of the statutes.</p>
   <p>In many cases, people who intended to become citizens found their path blocked by uncalled for difficulties. The Republican campaign leaders have resorted to this method, since they note with terror that this is no opportune time to convert immigrants to Republicanism. The Germans who want to become citizens this year, are almost exclusively Altgeld and Cleveland partisans. The Poles, Irish, Bohemians, Italians,and Russians are at a loss to understand why they should become affiliated with a party which is dominated by the "Know-Nothing" element. This leaves only the Swedes for the Republicans and their vote will actually benefit Fifer, at least a majority can be relied upon to bolster their ranks. Small wonder then, that the Republicans already scent fraud everywhere, whenever naturalization comes to the fore and they vent their lofty moral <pb facs="5418474_11_0546.jpg" n="2"/>indignation and caterwaul for the state's attorney's help and intervention. The Democrats, however, will not regard these tricks with indifference and equanimity, nor will the immigrants remain apathetic to this contumely.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
