<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-08-01">Aug. 1, 1907</date>,
<title level="a">An Altered Sttuation. Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0917</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0917.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-08-01">Aug. 1, 1907</date>,
<title level="a">AN ALTERED STTUATION. Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Kaiser will be able to read with grim satisfaction the latest remarks of the Jungopress, about the late Morocco atrocity. The city Casablanca, was attacked by neighboring Kabyl tribesmen, opposed to the harbor and railroad construction, killing in the attack several Frenchmen. Hence France and England are in accord, that some action is imperative. But the London press, with ill concealed rage, concedes that the Morocco difficulty must first be solved in Berlin, before attending to it in Fez, and without the assent of Germany they cannot resort to severe measures there. Hence in the imperial government it is being urged to allow France and Spain, in the interest of order and civilization to garrison the country to stop the anarchy there. This sounds somewhat differently from the past, when the boastful threats, that Germany must be kept within bounds, if it should dare to want to alter the fate of Morocco agreed on by France and England. Then the German Empire, was only informed of the facts accomplished, as if it had only to submit silently, not having a voice in the decision of the great powers. Today it is admitted and, so to say, not even a hair on the head of the sultan of Morocco may be bent, without the sanction of Germany. Consequently the Conference of Algeciras was not a humbling of the Kaiser and the mentioned isolation of Germany has not in the least shaken his position of power. The polite requests <pb facs="5418474_11_0918.jpg" n="2"/>of the British, French will probably be more acceptable to the German diplomats, than the former threats. Germany has in Morocco only general trade interests, the protection of which France could positively insure by treaty. Otherwise it would not concern him, whether the evidently incompetent Sultan remains on his throne, not being able even to finish with the robber Raisuli, and who is even hated by the desert tribes. If France does not any more acknowledge British overlordship beyond her border, but also recognizes the joint determination of Europe, especially Germany, then no reason can be seen why there should not be a mutual understanding. The French government press repeatedly insinuated in the last few weeks, that it is possible to establish an understanding between France and Germany, if the latter would only give up its unfriendly politics in North Africa, and leave it to the French. If this (insinuation) is meant seriously, the German government should surely reflect, if its real good behaviour toward France is not worth more, then only an empty prestige. However it will not be satisfied with empty phrases. If France is ready to end its machinations against her and accept the peace of Frankfurt, without reservation, then Germany will be able to meet France. The latter should be the more ready for reconciliation with the conqueror of 1870-71 as its connections with Russia are seemingly critically weakened. The Russian government cannot stand France's censure of its reactionary policies and frequently shows its displeasure. At its court at present the party that favors <pb facs="5418474_11_0919.jpg" n="3"/>the severance from France and the rapprochement with Germany has the influence. Whether the Russian emperor under the influence of this party, will agree to the closer contact with Kaiser Wilhelm, whether this will have the result of changing Russian politics, can not yet be said, but that the continued unnatural friendship between Russia and France has cooled, there remains no doubt. Just for that Germany does not need to throw herself in the arms of Western Europe or be making admission without compensating returns.</p>
   <p>If the French in Morocco should be permitted, then they must show themselves appreciative, and not only with words, but by deeds. The time for ambiguity is past and the hope for the successful isolation of Germany has thoroughly failed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
