<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-02-19">Feb. 19, 1901</date><title level="a">The Changing Stream of Immigration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-02-19">Feb. 19, 1901</date><title level="a">THE CHANGING STREAM OF IMMIGRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the statistics of immigration for the year 1900 the fact is in evidence that the overwhelming majority of newcomers came from Italy and Eastern Europe. It demonstrates the movements of emigration from one part of Europe to another one. The increase of population in the United States which has reached such heights in one century, is to a great extent due to a ceaseless stream of immigration which poured into this country from the western, northern and central part of Europe. Just recently, the southern countries of Europe, as Italy and the Balkan states, as well as Russia, are beginning to take part in this movement toward the western continent.</p>
   <p>Although emigration from the different countries increases because of overpopulation, which intensified the struggle for existence, or because of political or religious pressure, nevertheless, it can be observed that a peculiar geographic change happened in regard to emigration tendencies. In the beginning of America's developments the nations of Western Europe sent their pioneers of culture to this newly discovered country. From Spain and Portugal came the founders of the Latin republics of Central and South America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0516.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From France came the first white settlers of lower Canada. From England, Scotland and partly from West and South Germany came the immigrants who settled in the colonial states of the East and South of North America. This took place during the 17th and 18th century, and during the first half of the 19th century large masses of people came from Ireland. When the Irish immigration diminished, German immigration set in, and from 1848 until the Civil War; and again reached a remarkable height from 1873 till 1889. It was a migration, as it were, of the Germanic nation, through which the United States received a certain nation element, whose influence over its economic and intellectual development cannot be sufficiently appraised.</p>
   <p>During the last decade of the past century the newcomers from Germany decreased considerably and amounted to 25% only of the previous decade. The reasons for these changes are to be found in the fact that Germany needed the available working men, and that economic conditions in the United States had become worse.</p>
   <p>Immigration from Scandinavian countries increased simultaneously with the German. It swelled from 1870 until 1890, and then diminished to one--half during the following decade.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0517.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On the other hand, few immigrants came from the South and East of Europe. in 1870 and during the following two decades. But since 1890 over one million more came from Italy, Balkan states, Poland, Russia, and Finland, then during the previous 400 years since the discovery of America. . .It appears as if the stream of immigrants is still swelling. Perhaps the political events in East Europe will cause a still greater increase of immigrants. Mass-immigrations from Finland is expected, and the number of those, desiring to emigrate from the Balkan states, is steadily increasing.</p>
   <p>During the years from 1870 until 1890 approximately 300,000 came to this country from Belgium, Netherland, Denmark, and Switzerland, but immigration diminished after 1890 from these countries.</p>
   <p>Of the 19,000,000 immigrants, who have come to this country since 1820, about 8,000,000 of them came from West Europe, about 7,000,000 from Central Europe, especially from Germany, 1,500,000 from North Europe and 2,500,000 from South and East Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0518.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As mentioned before, the stream of immigrants from South and East Europe are increasing continually, while it is diminishing from the other sections. It is a well-known fact that the steady increase from these sections is not altogether desirable for the United States and it appears that stricter immigration laws are necessary and inevitable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
