<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-16">Oct. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Huxmann, Senior, Fatally Injured in Automobile Accident Funeral of Noted Dentist to Take Place Wednesday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-16">Oct. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">DR. HUXMANN, SENIOR, FATALLY INJURED IN AUTOMOBILE ACCIDENT Funeral of Noted Dentist to Take Place Wednesday</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Regrets were expressed in many circles over the news of the sudden death of Dr. Fritz Huxmann, Sr. The 85-year old gentleman, quite well known in many circles, was the victim of a deplorable automobile accident. On crossing the viaduct not far from the Goethe monument, on Sheridan Road and Diversey Parkway, at about 1 P.M., he fell under the wheels of an automobile driven by Thomas Lantry, 4215 Sheridan Road, and was so gravely injured that death came as a relief, a few hours later, at the Columbus Memorial Hospital.</p>
   <p>The funeral rites will take place at 3 P.M. in Fred Westfall's Funeral Chapel, 3807 Lincoln Avenue. Burial will be at Graceland Cemetary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Fritz Huxmann was born in Virden, near Hannover, on March 10, 1848, and came to America in 1863, at the same time as his friend Henry von Oppen. Having finished his studies, for which he had received a good foundation on the other side, at a local high school and at Rush Medical College, he established himself as a dentist and became quickly known. For many years he conducted a dental school under the name of the German-American Dental College, 220 Wisconsin Street. In later years he retired conpletely from practice.</p>
   <p>With the passing of Dr. Huxman, Chicago lost a man who, at all times, took pride in admitting his German origin. Even though, as in late years, he no longer took the same active interest in German club life as he did forty years ago, he still took a vital interest in all German aspirations for decades. He used to be a member of the Germania Maennerchor, the Lake View Maennerchor (which has since then been abandoned),and of the Gesangs-verein Harmonie. He also tried his hand at writing and the readers of the <pb facs="5418474_11_1135.jpg" n="3"/>Abendpost had frequent occasion to acquaint themselves with his views on important questions of the day in "Eingesandtes" (letters to the editor). Until his death he was a man of rare agility and mental freshness.</p>
   <p>His life's companion for many years, Emma, preceded him in death already in 1924. Dr. Fritz Berthold Huxmann, Paul Julius, and Richard Huxmann are the three surviving sons who mourn at the bier of the departed one, together with the other members of the family and numerous friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
