<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-02-05">Feb. 5, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Charles W. Peters Dies of a Heart Attack</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-02-05">Feb. 5, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">CHARLES W. PETERS DIES OF A HEART ATTACK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The funeral services for the seventy-four year-old sheriff, Charles W. Peters, as yet, has not been arranged. In all probability interment will take place at Acacia Cemetery.</p>
   <p>Peters was troubled for some time with a stomach ailment. When he came home from his office yesterday, he informed his wife that he did not feel well and would lay down for a short rest. After one hour, Mrs. Peters called her husband, she found he was dead. A heart attack ended his active life. He first became a deputy sheriff in 1886, under Canute R. Madson. He applied for this position to lead a free life in the open air. In 1893 he was appointed first deputy sheriff by James Pease. In 1918 he was elected Sheriff on the Republican ticket. His opponent was at that time Mayor Anton J. Cermak. He held his position for four years. After that he became again a deputy sheriff under Sheriff John Traeger, he maintained this position under all succeeding sheriffs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1126.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last December he celebrated the 46th year of service in the Sheriff's Department. In 1909 Peters was elected president of the National Association of Sheriffs, and he was re-elected the following year. At the time of the Haymarket riot, he was first deputy sheriff, and directed the execution of the condemned. For a number of years Peters was a committee delegate from the 25th Ward. He belonged to the group of former United States Senator Charles S. Deneen.</p>
   <p>In Private Life</p>
   <p>The Devon Trust and Savings Bank was founded with his co-operation. Peters was a member of the executive committee when the bank was closed. Besides being a prominent member of the German Club of Chicago, he was active in Masonic circles.</p>
   <p>He is survived by his widow and two married daughters: Mrs. H. H. Wilcox of North Reading, Pa., and Mrs. J. D. Erickson of Glencoe.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1127.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1931, Mr. and Mrs. Peters celebrated their golden wedding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
