<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-12-20">December 20, 1897</date><title level="a">A Deplorable Decree</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-12-20">December 20, 1897</date><title level="a">A Deplorable Decree</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Federation of Labor, at its annual meeting in Nashville, accepted a resolution to request of Congress an acceptance of the Lodge Bill that is directed against immigration. The leaders who advised this step may soon find out that they have made a grave mistake. The American Labor movement will sink down to an egotistic, brutal and reckless battle for personal benefit, as long as the Unions stand for the point of view, that not the laboring class in general has to be elevated, but that only members of the American Federation of Labor must receive preference.</p>
   <p>After the American Unions have slammed the door in the face of all those weary and overburdened ones, who want to save themselves in the land of freedom, it is impossible for them to come forward as pioneers of sublime principles to improve the condition of entire humanity. On the contrary they have to admit that their sole ambition is to obtain for their members higher wages and better working conditions, than other laborers can find. Also this striving is fully qualified, in the same sense, as is the striving of each business man to obtain as great profits as possible. But with just as little right as when the merchant calls upon the world to honor his <pb facs="5418474_11_0533.jpg" n="2"/>passion for gain as a carrier of happiness to mankind, the Unions cannot appeal to public opinion while they only care for their members and intend to strive only for material advantages. In this, they put themselves on the same platform as the manufacturers who only demand "protection" for their own products, or with the agrarians who put down an appeal to the government to artificially raise the prices of wheat. But he who demands privileges for himself only, awakens the opposition of all those who must be neglected by individual favors.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding, it cannot be for the benefit of the trade unions to enact the "educational test". Those immigrants who cannot even read and write, do not figure in competition with the trained artisans, of whom the trade unions consist. The seeming exceptions to this rule are the coal miners, but it is plainly to be understood that contractors will draft, under no circumstanes, skilled labor for work that can be done by laborers of the lowest educational standard. Therefore the suspicion arises, that the leaders of the unions, who demanded the approval of the "educational test" not only excluded the ignorant immigrants, but would like to have prohibited the immigration entirely.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0534.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If the trade unions must be counted upon as a body that hates foreigners, they will lose a great number of their friends and their respectability will not increase.</p>
   <p>The resolution could have been frustrated if the German union men had brought in their full influence. But it is evident, that not only in this regard are the English-Irish influences authoritative - and this is absolutely for the harm of the labor movement. A little German idealism would certainly be to the benefit of the latter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
