<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-02-20">February 20, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">"He" and the Empire</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1012</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1012.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-02-20">February 20, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">"HE" AND THE EMPIRE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Is Bismarck right in his statement that the Reichstag understands only how to answer in the negative and to find fault with everything, but not to make it better? Perhaps. But did the Chancellor ever run the risk of an honest test? At the many changes which he undertook in the ministries, did the thought ever come to his mind, to select one of the party leaders from the Reichstag? Steeped in the traditions of the Old Prussian officialdom, he never wanted an honest parliamentarian government. He never could have endured the idea of having about him men who also have something to say. Reichstag and Landtag (State Diets) were always toys to him with which he enjoyed himself, according to his own whims and moods. The truth is, and he who reads Bismark's speech can note it between the lines, that the entire people's representation in the German Empire is a humbug and is only permitted to exist for the present because of the comtemptuous pity of the "mighty".</p>
   <p>He expressed with a Frankness worthy of acknowledgement how he would run things if necessary, without the Reichstag. If he cannot do anything with the Reichstag, he then turns to the diets of the different states with which he can talk easier, that is, which will obey orders more readily.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1013.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What shall become of the German Empire when it is so completely based upon two eyes ? Bismarck cannot live forever. His reign may survive the life of Emperor Wilhelm I, but who can continue the administration of the empire in the same way. as he? Where is the man, to whose whims and authoratative orders people and ruler alike would bow? It is the misfortune of the too - great men that they pay no attention to these questions. Cromwell and Napoleon have thereby become lonely pillars in the history of the world, - does not the danger exist that some day the same will be said of Bismarck? How long did Cromwell's power and greatness last in the care of his son, Richard? Of Bismarck, it is said, that he guides his son Herbert to become a Richard Cromwell!</p>
   <p>Whether Germany is able to form a vital constitutional state is a question that can neither be affirmed, nor answered in the negative because its present almighty ruler has never made a test. We will hope for it, but the proof can only be obtained after the almighty is gone. But as long as he has one breath left, "He" is the German Empire.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
