<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-08-11">Aug. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Carl Roessler.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-08-11">Aug. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CARL ROESSLER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The proprietor of the Hotel Atlantic, Carl Roessler, who, like his business partner Max Teich, is well known abroad and in America, as owners of the Hotel Atlantic, was born in Wurtlemberg, Germany in 1872.</p>
   <p>In 1886, at the age of 14, he was sent by his father to Innsbruck, Switzerland, to learn the hotel business. The future hotel owner had to go through quite a strenuous apprenticeship, because in those years, trade schools were unknown, and the young man had to start from the bottom to learn the business administration as well as the practical sides of the business. During this time he collected memories of prominent people, who were the guests of the Tyrolean Hof Hotel, about whom he could tell many amusing incidents, for instance, how he tried to learn out of a cook book, to mix a cocktail for old Mr. Gould.</p>
   <p>His years of apprenticeship brought him further around the world, to Cannes, France, London, Hull and Glasgow, because of the great importance of learning different languages, people and their habits. At the Hotel Bristol in Berlin he attained his first purpose, by becoming head waiter.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1237.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In 1894 Carl Roessler came to Chicago and assumed the management of the old Bismarck Hotel. At the beginning of the century, he and Max Teich took charge of the Hotel Atlantic, to which in 1917 the new 20 story annex was added. Besides the Hotel Atlantic, the two partners obtained five years ago the Hotel Kaskia of La Salle, and a year ago the Jefferson Hotel of St. Louis.</p>
   <p>Roessler belongs, of course, to numerous German-American Clubs and societies. The Hotel Atlantic is the well known resting and meeting place of many German-Americans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
