<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1864-04-30">Apr. 30, 1864</date>.
<title level="a">Officers of the Militia Meet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1864-04-30">Apr. 30, 1864</date>.
<title level="a">OFFICERS OF THE MILITIA MEET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, the officers of the militia met at the old Klinger Saloon on La Salle Street. The meeting was attended by Messrs. Peter Shimp, Pflaum, Nelson, Ries, Hausmann, and Lochbieler. In the absence of Colonel Knobelsdorff, Mr. Peter Shimp was elected chairman.</p>
   <p>It was decided to establish ten companies independent of all existing organizations, to permit each company to elect its own officers once it had reached full strength, and to elect staff officers in the manner followed by volunteer regiments. It was also voted to pay the recruiting expenses incurred by the officers appointed to do the necessary recruiting, and that each company be allowed three paid recruiting officers.</p>
   <p>It was further decided that the Committe shall be authorized to grant anybody permission to organize a company. [Translator's note: This Committee is not further identified.] Finally it was decided to publish the proceedings of this <pb facs="5418474_11_0200.jpg" n="2"/>meeting in the Telegraph and in the Illinois Staats-Zeitung.</p>
   <p>The following men offered to serve as recruiting officers: Company A, J. Hausmann; Company B, Captain Pflaum; Company C, Captain Albert; Company D, Captain Lochbieler; Company E, Captain Cronfloe; Company F, Lieutenant Ries; Company G Captain Westerberg; Company H, J. W. Doehler; Company J, Lieutenant Kafka; Company K, Captain Barcal.</p>
   <p>The meeting was then adjourned. Then Colonel Knobelsdorff appeared, protested against the procedure of the assembly, and attempted to hold another meeting. However, those present left without paying the least attention to him. [Translator's note: Colonel Knobelsdorff having been relieved of his command "for cause," he was persona non grata among the Germans of Chicago.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
