<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-06-04">June 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Death of Clara Rehtmeyer</title><title level="a" type="sub">President of Ladies Aid Society of German Old People's Home Dies Suddenly</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-06-04">June 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DEATH OF CLARA REHTMEYER</title><title level="a" type="sub">President of Ladies Aid Society of German Old People's Home Dies Suddenly</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many German-Americans living in Chicago and its vicinity will be deeply grieved to hear of the death of Mrs. Clara Rehtmeyer, president of the Ladies Aid of the German Old People's Home. Apparently in the best of health, Mrs. Rehtmeyer suffered a stroke at nine o'clock last night while in the midst of a cheerful conversation with members of her family. She succumbed before medical aid could be summoned.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Rehtmeyer was an outstanding example of a German-American woman. Although born in this country--in Milwaukee, Wisconsin--she was true to the German culture and traditions, and whenever German customs or the German language was at issue she was always willing to defend them. During the last ten years she had devoted nearly all of her energies to the maintenance of a German-American benevolent institution, the German Old People's Home.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1407.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>She was indefatigably active in its behalf, and no work was too difficult or too tedious for her when the welfare of the old people who spend their last days in the institution was in question. She was very conscientious in the performance of her duties; she was familiar with all details, and was the dominating factor in the administration of the affairs of the Home. Thus it will be no easy matter to fill the vacancy caused by her death.</p>
   <p>The deceased, who was the daughter of the prominert Haase family of Milwaukee, married Curt von Otterstadt and came with him to Chicago to establish a home. Later they moved to Portland, Oregon, where he assumed duties as manager of the Freie Presse (Free Press). After several years he died. Their marriage was blessed with a son, Curt Junior, who now mourns the death of his dearly beloved mother.</p>
   <p>Dependent upon her own resources, the young widow turned her attention to teaching, and passed an examination entitling her to instruct in high schools. She was assigned to teach at Lake View High School, where she taught the German Language for a number of years. Her excellent education and her <pb facs="5418474_11_1408.jpg" n="3"/>wide knowledge proved to be of great advantage to her, and her career as an instructor was very successful.</p>
   <p>In 1905 she resigned from her position to devote her time to marriage and domestic affairs. Her second husband was Hermann Rehtmeyer, a prominent businessman and a widower who had lost his wife a few years before. The newly married couple made their home at 5410 Lakewood Avenue.</p>
   <p>Like many other German-American women, Mrs. Rehtmeyer took great interest in the German Old People's Home, and the result was that she was elected vice-president. When the Home's able president, Mrs. Marie Kabell, died about ten years ago, Mrs. Rehtmeyer was chosen as her successor. And experience has proved that the choice was a wise one. Especially will the inmates of the Home mourn the loss of this true friend, who gave so generously of her time and money to make their sojourn in the institution comfortable and happy.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Rehtmeyer was also a member of the Columbia Ladies' Club, and served as secretary of that organization for several years.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1409.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Her son, husband, and eighty-two-year-old mother mourn her loss.</p>
   <p>The funeral service will be held Friday, at 11 A.M., in St. Paul's Evangelical Church, Orchard Street and Kemper Place. Afterwards the body will be taken to Milwaukee for interment.</p>
   <p>Louis Sal, chairman of the board of directors of the Home, has called a special meeting of that body. It will be held tomorrow, Thursday, at 3 P.M., at the Atlantic Hotel. Resolutions with reference to the death of Mrs. Rehtmeyer will be adopted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
