<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-04-07">April 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Immigration Decreases</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-04-07">April 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IMMIGRATION DECREASES</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the past year brought a larger number of immigrants than the previous one, it could be noticed, that the masses of arrivals this year show a decided decrease, compared with the number that came last year. The news of unsatisfactory conditions in business and industry, and the consequent decline of employment, has no doubt penetrated to the European countries, that have provided the largest contingent of immigrants. The unemployment, prevailing in almost every part of the country, reflects upon the the disinclination of Southern Europeans to immigrate and must be considered as the reason, that during the last weeks and months, more people have left the ports of the Eastern section, steerage and second class and larger numbers than in the previous year went back to Europe. Of those 152,969 steamer passengers who arrived in the United States, 3,384 were denied admission, twice as many as in the previous year.</p>
   <p>Daily can we learn of despotic acts and lack of consideration, with which the immigrants are treated especially by the New York inspection officials. In many cases young and strong laborers are rejected on the grounds, that at the place of their destination, they would not be able to find the expected <pb facs="5418474_11_0478.jpg" n="2"/>opportunity of employment, and therefore would become a burden to public charity. The tendency to curtail the immigration of the laboring class is much stronger under the democratic government, than ever before.</p>
   <p>But the immigration slackens by itself, so that efforts to stop it artificially, are not at all necessary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
