<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-09-29">Sept. 29, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Observations on the German Day Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-09-29">Sept. 29, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">OBSERVATIONS ON THE GERMAN DAY CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The bi-centennial celebration of the birth of Washington is rapidly drawing to a close. However, it was our observation that the public at large did not concern itself with this national celebration to the extent that the occasion warranted. Neither could it be expected that the citizens would become absorbed over a national hero in times of heavy economic stress. However, for Americans of German descent the celebration had a happy result because the name of Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben, the great patriot of German origin, was again impressively brought before the public.</p>
   <p>This was sufficiently demonstrated in General Parker's address, delivered at the German Day celebration, last Sunday. The General is <pb facs="5418474_11_0114.jpg" n="2"/>well informed about American wars, and it was indeed a pleasure to follow his speech and to draw one's own conclusions from his profound study of this subject. Thus his appreciation of Steuben's personality and great achievements is based on no mere incidental study, but results from a knowledge to be gained only by a student of history. Nevertheless, it is only on rare occasions that a member of the army gives a complete account of General Steuben's brilliant accomplishments and of his honorable participation in the War of Independence.</p>
   <p>General Parker's address was more than a masterpiece of accuracy; it was also a forceful piece of evidence that officers holding high positions in our army do not hesitate to acknowledge the part played by the Germans in the building of our country.</p>
   <p>However, it would not be altogether fair to disregard the faithful labors of the German press, which has been engaged for a period of years in paving the way for this better understanding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
