<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-05-11">May 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Flyers Will Be Guests of German-Americans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0741</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0741.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-05-11">May 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">FLYERS WILL BE GUESTS OF GERMAN-AMERICANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hearts of a city of millions welcome the brave conquerors of the Atlantic who today are in our midst as the guests of Chicago. If there were thousands to greet the flyers yesterday there will be tens of thousands today to acclaim them on their tour through the city, and at the stadium in Grant Park.</p>
   <p>Baron von Hunefeld, Captain Koehl and Major Fitzmaurice are at last guests of Chicago. It has required many efforts to bring the flyers to the city. Everybody wants to see them, the daring ocean flyers, every one would like to congratulate them, every one would like to shake their hands.</p>
   <p>Particularly happy is the German element over their visit; thousands upon thousands of German descent will offer their greetings to the flyers, when they lay a wreath at the foot of the Goethe monument. In the evening they will go to the Lincoln Turner Hall and the North Side Turner Hall.</p>
   <p>Shortly before 1 o'clock the flyers will ride to the South Shore Country Club, where a luncheon will be given in their honor by the Mayor of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0742.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After lunch a tour through the city is proposed which will take the flyers through the parks of the South and West sides to the Olson Rug Company, Diversey and Crawford Avenue. Here the flyers will dedicate the powerful beacon which is meant as a guide to aeroplanes. The light will receive the official name of "Bremenlight." The beacon which was furnished by Walter E. Olson, president of the firm, carries a searchlight of a million candle-power.</p>
   <p>The tour will be continued with a stop at the Goethe monument in Lincoln Park where a wreath will be laid. In the evening at 9 o'clock the flyers will go to the Lincoln Turner Hall. Here the chorus of the United Men's Chorus will greet them with the song "Harmony."</p>
   <p>Mr. C. F. Pegenan will receive and introduce them. All the events in the Lincoln Turner Hall, including the flyers' speeches, will be broadcast from Station W. I. B. O. on the Abendpost radio hour. The Turners will also be present at the reception. Leopold Saltiel, Adolph Gill and Bruno Knecht are members of the reception committee.</p>
   <p>In the North Side Turner Hall, where the Swabian Society, the Plattdeutsche Guilds, the German-American Citizens Union, the Mutual Friendly Society, the <pb facs="5418474_11_0743.jpg" n="3"/>War Veterans, and the United Austro-Hungarian societies will await the flyers. William Jauss, honorary president of the Swabian Society will give the speech of welcome and present the flyers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
