<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-03-04">March 4, 1902</date><title level="a">Germany's Messenger of Friendship</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0942</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0942.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-03-04">March 4, 1902</date><title level="a">GERMANY'S MESSENGER OF FRIENDSHIP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prince Henry of Prussia on his arrival yesterday evening was greeted by an enormous crowd and his reception by the people was very enthusiastic. As soon as the train stopped, Mayor Harrison, A. J. Eddy and Consul Dr. Wever with the City Council Committee, boarded the private car of the Prince, where Mr. Harrison, after an introduction by Ambassador von Holleben greeted the guest with the words: "I bid you Chicago's welcome!" "Thank you", answered the Prince, and then Alderman Mayor presented the greeting resolutions. The streets from the depot to the Auditorium Hotel were lined with thousands of people, 3000 members of German Clubs carrying torch lights and the parade was led by an honorary squadron of cavalry. Many music hands intoned, "Heil Dir im Sieger Kranz"...</p>
   <p>In an enthusiastic demonstration for the leader of the German nation the celebration found its zenith at the Armory of the first Regiment. Prince Henry himself after a short address invoked three cheers for his Imperial brother. Mr. Thies J. Lefens delivered an address in German with a poetic welcome address and several male and ladies' singing clubs sang German and <pb facs="5418474_11_0943.jpg" n="2"/>American songs. At the banquet at the Auditorium Hotel 160 guests were present. Mayor Harrison acted as Toastmaster. The Prince answered with a warm address in English. Later in the evening a grand festival ball was given at the Auditorium Hotel, the most elegant affair this city had ever seen. The Grand March, under the arrangement of Alderman Honore Palmer, was led by the Prince and Mrs. Carter Harrison.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
