<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-06-29">June 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Franz Ferdinand Assassinated</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0907</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0907.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-06-29">June 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FRANZ FERDINAND ASSASSINATED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Staggering news disturbed yesterday's Sunday peace. Franz Ferdinand, heir to the Austrian and Hungarian thrones has been assassinated in Serajevo, capital of Bosnia, in the public street. His wife the Duchess of Hohenberg died by his side. The murderer a young student and composer, is a citizen of Serbia and it is anticipated that the attack has a national character. The garrisons in Bosnia had been increased lately, to prevent Servian invasion as relations between Serbia and Austria-Hungary have been very strained. During the first Balkan war Austria mobilised against Servia and war was only avoided at the last minute. A few days ago only, Franz Ferdinand walked with his Imperial host of Germany in the magnificent rose garden of Konvpischt, where the triple Entente was again strengthened. The consequences of this assassination cannot be imagined. The ruler of the double monarchy is old and weak, and with his 85 years not fully capable to meet the situation. This assassinated heir, had shown himself as the right man for this difficult post, and the incident must be regarded as a hard knock to the Austro-Hungarian dynasty. The present heir, Karl Franz Joseph, has been of very little political influence, and very little can be said at this moment about his position in relation to Germany and its alliance. Great sympathy is felt with the old Emperor of Austria <pb facs="5418474_11_0908.jpg" n="2"/>who, even in his declining days, has not been spared by the terrible visitations of fate, the world mourns the death of Franz Ferdinand, but feels with the old Emperor, who with the crown on his head, has gone the way of all human suffering to the very end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
