<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-06-23">June 23, 1904</date><title level="a">Roaring Applause! Major General Osterhaus the Object of Great Honors. a Pride of the Germans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-06-23">June 23, 1904</date><title level="a">ROARING APPLAUSE! MAJOR GENERAL OSTERHAUS THE OBJECT OF GREAT HONORS. A PRIDE OF THE GERMANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Surrounded by the hurrahs of old comrades, by the rejoicing of hundreds of ladies and gentlemen, welcomed by blaring trumpets and praised by qualified speakers, by the comrades of the Civil War - so yesterday evening stood Major-General Peter Joseph Osterhaus at the flag-draped meeting hall of the old Tremont House. Snowy white are the hairs of his head and his whiskers, but keen-eyed, straight as a dart, a real military figure, a youthful old man of eighty-three years. General Osterhaus modestly accepted the homage paid to him not only by the American Institute of Germanics", the Military Order of Royal Legion and the Grand Army of the Republic, but also by the younger brothers-in-arms of German and American origin, the German-American and American citizen and the numerously represented fair sex.</p>
   <p>Reception in honor of the General Osterhaus. This announcement brought hundreds of both sexes in gala dress to the old Tremont House. They came with the bronze button of the Grand Army, with the commemorative medals of the 1870-1871 war, with bright orders and medals of warlike significance of other countries <pb facs="5418474_11_0143.jpg" n="2"/>and battles, to assemble in Booth Hall at the third floor of Tremont House in order to pass the old warrior and shake hands with the famous General......</p>
   <p>After the reception the assembly met at the large meeting hall. The chairman, Mr. Otto C. Schneider, President of the American Institute of Germanics , introduced, after a short welcome address, the speakers:</p>
   <p>First came President James of Northwestern University, who was followed by General Grant, the Commander-in-Chief of the Department of the Lakes, Harry Rubens, General Leake, Colonel Foster, Otto C. Butz, Adam Ortseifen and Wilhelm Vocke. The contents of all the short but substantially enthusiastic speeches dealt not only with honoring the merits of General Osterhaus and of our adopted fatherland in particular, but more with the honoring of the Germans in general.</p>
   <p>It is only regrettable, that certain elements could not hear how men like Generals Grant and Leake and Colonel Foster feel and think about the German element and its sacrifices of life and property for the preservation of the Union. As often as the name of the General Osterhaus was mentioned a storm of <pb facs="5418474_11_0144.jpg" n="3"/>jubilation burst forth, especially when General Leake related in a soldier-like way the war-like career of the guest of honor, who entered the war on the side of the North as Major of two companies of Missouri Militia, who fought in the East and South as Colonel, General and Major-General, and who received, as Commander of an Army Corps, the capitulations of the Rebel Generals, Lee and Smith. Jubilant exclamations of the assembly, the Reveille of the Grand Army of the Republic, the College yells of the students followed the words of the General and this tumult increased after the guest of honor himself, the war-hero and swordsman Osterhaus, expressed his thanks for the honors, and expressed admiration for the Americans' military courage and wished the everlasting sunshine of peace and welfare for their children and grandchildren. Modesty was the most prominent virtue of the old warrior. The tone of his voice was the only thing that reminded the audience of the years that rested upon his shoulders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
