<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-01-27">January 27, 1902</date><title level="a">Feels Himself a German Admiral Schley is Proud That German Blood Courses in His Veins.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0146</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0146.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1902-01-27">January 27, 1902</date><title level="a">Feels Himself a German Admiral Schley is Proud That German Blood Courses in His Veins.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans of Chicago have presented today their special respects to Admiral Schley at a reception in the Memorial Hall of the Library building. Mr. Wilhelm Vocke delivered the greeting address in the name of the German-Americans of Chicago, and Mr. Michaelis read the resolutions in honor of the guest.... With a grateful bow Admiral Schley accepted these resolutions, artistically executed on parchment and gave the following address:</p>
   <p>"My German friends! As you all may know, I also am a descendant of a German family that left the fatherland in 1769 to settle in America. They settled in the state of Maryland and named the county and the city founded by them, Frederick, after the great Prussian King. I am happy and proud that I am of German origin. Wherever the German turns his steps he always makes a good citizen.</p>
   <p>The United States owes to our great Germany a large part of its wonderful development and its amazing success. From my grandmother's side I come from a Huguenot family which, after suppression of the "Edict of Nantes", had to <pb facs="5418474_11_0147.jpg" n="2"/>flee from France and who found a safe home in Germany. So you see that my descendants on the father's side had found a protected sanctuary among the Germans.</p>
   <p>I feel sorry that the time does not permit me to make the personal acquaintance of a larger number of my German friends but my program of travel was made up before I came to Chicago. I owe you greater thanks than my tongue is able to express. This is one of the occasions by which the heart is so deeply moved that the tongue is not able to find the right words. Be convinced that this hour is not to be forgotten as long as I live."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
