<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-08-31">Aug. 31, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Consul Speaks to Architects from Germany.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-08-31">Aug. 31, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">CONSUL SPEAKS TO ARCHITECTS FROM GERMANY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The manifold impressions, which were gained yesterday by the 125 German architects and engineers on their numerous inspections, have not failed to awaken the admiration of the German guests. Tomorrow they will inspect the Stockyards, the Main Post Office, Edison Commonwealth Electric Company and the People's Gas Light and Coke Company.</p>
   <p>After a luncheon at the Bismarck Hotel three other groups will inspect the laboratory of the Building Safety Commission, the Municipal Pier, as well as the City Plans, according to which the beautiful lake front of Chicago will be built.</p>
   <p>Tonight a banquet will be given at the Bismarck Hotel to which also Mayor Thompson and other representatives of the city have been invited.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0752.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Consul Praises America.</p>
   <p>"America is the first country which has acknowledged the necessity of rebuilding its cities. It not only builds houses, it builds cities. Office and business sections are separated from factory sections, garden and representative sections become more and more pronounced. From this, Germany could and should learn. Germany of today needs,more than ever, city builders instead of architects."</p>
   <p>These striking words, spoken by the German Consul General of Chicago, Dr. Simon, at the Chinese dinner at the Realto Gardens yesterday, which the Celotex Company had arranged, were approved by all the German experts. Also the American architect, Irving K. Pond, was present.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0753.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He is known as an authority on German architecture. He was elected an honorary member of the German architects' union.</p>
   <p>He expressed his approval of German architecture and laid stress upon the fact that a foreign language is no barrier to the understanding of another nation because its spirit is revealed by its edifices.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
