<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-01-03">Jan. 3rd, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A. Klappenback Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-01-03">Jan. 3rd, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A. KLAPPENBACK DIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Again a man passed away, who was most prominent among his fellow citizens and whose name is closely interwoven in the history of the German-Americans of our city. He had been a good companion and a wonderful friend to man.</p>
   <p>Alexander Klappenbach died January 3rd, 1924, in his home at 2140 Fremont Street. Mr. Klappenbach reached the age of sixty four years, He was born in Texas, but as a boy, he came to Chicago and in his earliest youth developed a remarkable tendency towards German literature. In later years the wholesale distribution of German literature was the foundation of his wealth and public esteem. In 1885, after several years of employment in different book stores, he founded his own business under the name of Koelling, Klappenbach and Kenkal. Three years later the firm, besides the general tasks of a book store, specialized also in the importation and selling of German literature, developed into one of the biggest and most well known of its king in America.</p>
   <p>In 1894 a fire destroyed his business, but, Mr. Klappenbach started the reconstruction <pb facs="5418474_11_1402.jpg" n="2"/>of his new business, which was moved to 206 W. Randolph Street.</p>
   <p>About fifteen years ago Mr. Klappenbach retired. However, he preserved an active interest in art and literature and, especially, arranged for the sale of products of German-American authors, of whom many gave thanks to him in later years for their success.</p>
   <p>An almost complete collection of works, printed in the German language in this country, formed the particular pride of the deceased.</p>
   <p>Several German-American societies are obliged to him. He also was a member of several outstanding German-American societies.</p>
   <p>As a German-American book seller Mr. Klappenbach was a pioneer of German culture, and German art in the United States, as a person he was a man of magnificent characteristics and undefiled character. His death is indeed a great loss. Honor to his memory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
