<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1894-03-10">March 10, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Wetzoldt about the American School System</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0977</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0977.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1894-03-10">March 10, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSOR WETZOLDT ABOUT THE AMERICAN SCHOOL SYSTEM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Professor Wetzoldt from Berlin, as we remember, has been in America last year to study the American School system. He stayed also a few months in Chicago, to complete his studies.</p>
   <p>At present, Professor Wetzoldt is lecturing in Germany on our School system. We are publishing herewith some of this noted Professor's impressions about our country:</p>
   <p>Based on the individual freedom and liberal laws, the American people have a highly developed grade of self-consciousness, which is reflected in the mental attitude of teachers and pupils. The American child, going to school, is quickly advanced in character and knowledge. Subsequently, the school term, lasting eight years in primary schools, is often shortened to four years for some pupils.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, there are certain defective conditions, which darken considerably the picture of American schools. For instance, only 72 per cent of all children of school age are actually coming to school. The other 28% cannot be <pb facs="5418474_11_0978.jpg" n="2"/>traced by the law, as there is no official record of all persons in regards to their change of location or address. The pupils are going to school three to four months during the year. The number of school-days is actually only 134 (in Germany about 240 days). Home lessons are rare and not definite. There is a large number of Protestant and Catholic Church schools, which according to Professor Wetzoldt are inferior to the public schools as to teachers and curricula.</p>
   <p>Evidently, the woman in America is considered to be the bearer of cultural life, not only at home, but also in schools. Therefore most teachers are women. In the City of Chicago alone, there were 200 male teachers besides 3000 women teachers, who are admitted to the most responsible and highest positions. This is causing a steady decrease of male teachers, who gradually are falling off to look for more promising careers.</p>
   <p>The American School system is more or less under the influence of local politics, which are sometimes causes great inconvenience to the School Board and teachers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
