<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-02-07">Feb. 7, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Politics and Administratio</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bobby Burke's Lecture about Altgeld</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1604</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1604.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-02-07">Feb. 7, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS AND ADMINISTRATIO</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bobby Burke's Lecture About Altgeld</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We know that Altgeld often bragged in public that his influence resulted in elevating Harrison to the mayor's chair, two years ago. But now comes "Bobby" Burke, the experienced, undaunted scout of the City Hall politician, and explains that the Ex-Governor is merely telling lies when he makes such assertions. It happened last evening, at the Tremont House, during the founding of the "Carter H. Harrison League", that the little, corpulent oil inspector gave his party companions an "eye-full" behind the scenes and, he also divulged other reasons, why Altgeld appears today as an independent candidate. Among other items, Burke mentioned the following: "Two years ago, I was the Secretary of the Democratic County Central Committee. At that time I favored A. S. Trude as candidate for mayor, Harrison however, preferred John Barton Payne. As regards the latter, I know, that he never, never would be elected by a Democratic convention, because in 1896 he did not show sufficient interest in Bryan and Altgeld. I tried my utmost, to induce Trude to accept the <pb facs="5418474_11_1605.jpg" n="2"/>nomination, since I was sure of a Democratic victory, but all my efforts were useless.</p>
   <p>So I went to Harrison and asked him to appear as candidate. And he did, after Judge Payne, obligingly released him from his duties. Considering these truthfully presented facts, how can Altgeld show such temerity and declare, that Harrison is indebted to him because he is now the mayor of Chicago! There is more! Dr. Howard S. Taylor former chairman of the Populist City Committee, asked the Ex-Governor to support Harrison. Altgeld told him, briefly and bluntly, that he could not do it. Later, Altgeld tried to make us accept his personal friend, Judge Henry M. Shepard, as candidate for mayor. Furthermore, the Ex-Governor seems to take especial pleasure, in accusing the mayor, that he appointed "so many" gold Democrats. It is a fact, nevertheless, and everyone can readily convince himself, that of all the appointees which the present administration employs, there are only four gold-Democrats, which will suffice to prove, that Altgeld's assertions are exaggerations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1606.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Aside from this, the Ex-Governor is quite piqued, since we eliminated his control over the State Executives of the party. Now he would like to take vengeance, since where he cannot rule, he tries to destroy, that is why Altgeld labors to procure our defeat."</p>
   <p>Chairman Webb, Schoolboard members Thomas I. Gallagher, William L. Brennan and Thomas L. Courtney made similar anti-Altgeld speeches.</p>
   <p>The new "Carter H. Harrison League" obtained more than 500 Democrats, who joined immediately. They are to serve the mayor as a campaign committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
