<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-05-31">May 31, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Emil Hoechster</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-05-31">May 31, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">EMIL HOECHSTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Emil Hoechster, a widely known German citizen of Chicago, will celebrate the 75th anniversary of his birth tomorrow. The celebrant, whose keen intellect remained untouched by the passing of years, can still engage in a rather heated debate when occasion arises.</p>
   <p>Hoechster was born at Frankfort on the Main, June 1, 1836. Soon after his birth, his father's business connections necessitated a change of domicile, taking his family to Elberfeld. In 1849, his father accepted the position of an unsalaried lecturer at the University of Bern, Switzerland.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1478.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Young Emil was then sent to Berlin to continue his education. There, he attended the Joachimsthaler college, and thereafter, the University of Bonn, where he studied law. But in 1855 he decided upon a different career. Without consulting his parents, he joined a theatre company with which he came to New York. Dame Fortune was his companion, for the New York City Theatre Company engaged him to fill the vacancy of the "juvenile lover." It was there that he joined the organization of the United Turners of North America, whose distinguished member he remained to this day. The stage has held his interest until 1867, during the period of which he has given guest performances in all large cities throughout the land. He became a member of the Bernstein theatre company of St. Louis, Mo., in 1858, but terminated his connections with that company in 1861. He <pb facs="5418474_11_1479.jpg" n="3"/>entered the First Missouri Regiment of volunteers, at the outbreak of the Civil War as turner - soldier. At his first chance, he entered the service of company K of the famous 24th Illinois Regiment of volunteers in the rank of a lieutenant.</p>
   <p>Honorably discharged from the army after the conclusion of hostilities, Hoechster came to Chicago in 1865, where he married Miss Kaethchen Hand. The year following, he renounced the stage in order to accept the offer of the Staats - Zeitung to join its staff as city editor. However, he was no novice in that field any more, because while in St. Louis he was employed as journalist for the Westliche Post, and the Anzeiger Des Westens of that city. Later, he became intensely interested in the presidential <pb facs="5418474_11_1480.jpg" n="4"/>candidacy of General U. S. Grant, and devoted much of his time through 1868 in touring and delivering political speeches in Indiana, Ohio, and Illinois. In acknowledgement of his services, he was appointed Consul to Barmen, remaining there until 1875, when he returned to Chicago. Here he continued work in the field of politics. The Democrats indorsed him for Congress twice. In districts where Republican attitude predominated, he was beaten by small majority each time. He became assistant Sheriff in 1903, in which capacity he still functions.</p>
   <p>Hoechster was first speaker of the Chicago Turn Community for a number of years, and has become an indispensable personality of the "Chicagoana" <pb facs="5418474_11_1481.jpg" n="5"/>society. He is an active member of the German Press Association of Chicago, and also a member of various other societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
