<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-21">Jan. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Well-Deserved [Recognition]</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago Plan Commission Honors its President</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-21">Jan. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WELL-DESERVED [RECOGNITION]</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago Plan Commission Honors Its President</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In today's meeting of the Chicago Plan Commission, John G. Shedd, a member, proposed the following resolution, which was unanimously adopted:</p>
   <p>"Be it resolved that this Commission--and through it the citizens of the City of Chicago--sincerely thank Mr. Charles H. Wacker for his untiring, unselfish, and patriotic devotion to the general purpose of the Commission.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Wacker renders his services without receiving any compensation, and it is no trivial matter, indeed, to sacrifice one's commercial, financial, and personal interests to an ideal. And the ideals of the old Commercial Club, established by Daniel H. Burnham and his co-workers, and which became the common property of the City of Chicago through the community spirit of the Commercial Club, could never have been realized, had their attainment not been entrusted to a man whose personal ideals rendered him equal to the <pb facs="5418474_11_1417.jpg" n="2"/>great task. "The work which Mr. Wacker performed so diligently, carefully, and unselfishly, will benefit every Chicagoan, no matter where he lives or what his standing in the community is. These plans and ideas are on so grand a scale that they will touch every corner of Chicago, and thus they will contribute to the development of the entire city.</p>
   <p>"The Chicago Plan Commission is deeply indebted to Mr. Wacker for his services.</p>
   <p>"I move that this resolution be unanimously adopted and entered upon the record of this Commission."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
