<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-04-11">Apr. 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Germanistic Society Should Be Awakened to New Life Here</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-04-11">Apr. 11, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANISTIC SOCIETY SHOULD BE AWAKENED TO NEW LIFE HERE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a letter addressed to the editor of the Abendpost, Professor Erich von Schroetter, Dean of the German Department at Northwestern University, intercedes in favor of the revival of the Germanistic Society of Chicago, which ceased to exist during the War. It is to be hoped that the plan suggested by Professor von Schroetter will find favorable response among the Germans of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Professor von Schroetter writes as follows: "Should we have again a Germanistic society here in Chicago? We all know that the unfortunate war destroyed much that was beautiful in the German cultural life of America, and that the old meritorious Germanistic Society belongs also to the past. But must it remain like that all the time? Cannot the advantages of those times be restored again here in Chicago? That such a thing is possible, our neighbor city, Milwaukee, has proved to us. In this city the German poet Dr. Curt Baum <pb facs="5418474_11_1199.jpg" n="2"/>re-established the German Literary Society, which collapsed in 1920. It is a fact that under the able leadership of Dr. Curt Baum, this society has been elevated to its former standard in regard to the number of its members, the quality and quantity of its performances, and the excellent attendance to them.</p>
   <p>"Stimulated by many of the old settlers, as well as the newly immigrated German element of Chicago, I feel obliged to bring before the public the plan of restoring the Germanistic Society of Chicago.</p>
   <p>"Because I remember with pleasure the evenings spent at the Chicago Germanistic Society, and because of my activities in one of the academic institutions of <pb facs="5418474_11_1200.jpg" n="3"/>Milwaukee, where I had the opportunity to observe the immense development of the German Literary Society, I gladly accept this task. I know how strongly German spiritual life and German cultural achievements can produce an effect in this country; therefore, I believe I speak the opinion of many when I say, get to-gether, you Germans and you of German extraction of Chicago, if possible at the Bismarck or Atlantic Hotel, and express your opinion about this matter.</p>
   <p>"The result of the deliberation should be the re-establishment of the old Germanistic Society.</p>
   <p>"Conjointly with the Milwaukee Society, we then can invite to our meetings <pb facs="5418474_11_1201.jpg" n="4"/>German scholars, artists, authors, especially visiting professors and persons who are here for purposes of study, and thus be able to elevate and enjoy ourselves on German cultural achievements, as we did before the great catastrophe.</p>
   <p>"Because of the fact that we are not moved by political propaganda as concerns the European war, American party politics can be considered, excluding, of course, all narrow-minded, co-operative systems. As a consequence, there is no doubt that everyone will be able to devote himself enthusiastically to the cause.</p>
   <p>"Not German circles alone, but all who are anxious to help promote the immense cultural cohesion of the Western nations in general and who are appreciative of German spirituality in particular, should be just as willing to participate in <pb facs="5418474_11_1202.jpg" n="5"/>this work. Whether lectures should be held in German or English is a question, like many others, the decision of which rests with the committee to be appointed by the society.</p>
   <p>"Academic institutions of Greater Chicago that used to cultivate the German language and literature, as well as different societies with German cultural purposes, it is to be hoped will contribute their important advice also.</p>
   <p>"Few words are needed to prove the value of this cause. The Chicago German element, as well as other Chicago circles with a friendly attitude toward German cultural life, should have again a focal point where they may find their ideals realized. "It is to the interest of America to listen to important personalities of Germany, Austria, German Switzerland, and other <pb facs="5418474_11_1203.jpg" n="6"/>German-speaking sections of Europe. Whoever is a member of the German cultural circle, should have the wood (sic). He may have a home in Chicago, where he can work for the benefit of humanity. To create this home, this central point of German spiritual life, should be one of our aims.</p>
   <p>"Nobody should consider himself too important to co-operate, and nobody should consider himself as too small to be of furtherance of this cause. We write now, 1930, and the war ended 12 years ago! Spiritual life, knowledge, and Greater Germany's culture must find here an abode generally acknowledged. "To serve the cause, the signer is gladly willing to accept letters with announcements and propositions. Further details will be found in the Abendpost.</p>
   <p>"Dr. Erich von Schroetter, Department of German, Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
