<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title>,
<date when="1901-01-20">Jan. 20, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Fritz Frillmann Is Dead</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title>,
<date when="1901-01-20">Jan. 20, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">FRITZ FRILLMANN IS DEAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fritz Frillmann, one of Chicago's oldest German settlers, died on Friday morning at the age of seventy-five. Advanced age and an attack of pneumonia were the cause of his death. Through his demise, the city loses an outstanding man who played a leading role in its social and political affairs.</p>
   <p>Born in Hannover, Germany, on April 12, 1826, Frillmann attended school in the town of his birth, and on reaching his fifteenth year took a position as junior agriculturist in Loncading, on the Elbe. Later, possessed of an irrepressible yearning for the sea, he became a sailor, in which capacity he spent eleven years. In 1849, however, he decided to emigrate to the United States. He came to New York and, after staying there for a year, moved to Chicago, where he lived from 1850 until his death. Here he made at <pb facs="5418474_11_1563.jpg" n="2"/>first his living as a sailor and cruised on the Great Lakes for two years, visiting the port of Buffalo repeatedly. Back on terra firma, right on the corner of Wells and Division Streets he opened a combination grocery store, boarding-house, and tavern, and it was not long before he became a well-known, respected member of the community. He prospered, sold his business in 1869 and erected a building at 367 Division Street, where his former success was repeated. Two years previously he had become a manufacturer, building a large factory on Sixteenth Street, where he made special locks, for which he acquired a patent. Soon afterwards, in 1869, fire destroyed his plant completely, causing a loss of $20,000.</p>
   <p>The Chicago conflagration of 1871 burnt Frillmann's business establishment and seven of his residential buildings, yet his insurance policies paid him only $386,68. In spite of this, he started anew on Division Street, and his was the first new house in the district after the Fire. As a <pb facs="5418474_11_1564.jpg" n="3"/>member of the Aid Committee and Salvation Corps, which was organized after the Fire, his activity earned him the undying gratitude of his compatriots.</p>
   <p>In 1881 he retired from business in order to enjoy a well-earned rest during his declining years.</p>
   <p>The deceased became a member of the then newly founded Republican party, after having been affiliated with the Whigs, and was a staunch Republican to the end. From an historical standpoint, it may be of interest to know that the first Republican organizational meeting of Cook County was held at Frillmann's home on Wells and Division Streets. He refused to be a candidate for public office, even though the opportunity had been offered to him several times. However, he was associated with the Republican State and County Central Committee during several campaigns and became <pb facs="5418474_11_1565.jpg" n="4"/>an influential person in party politics.</p>
   <p>Frillmann had been affiliated with the Chicago Turngemeinde since this organization was founded. He was a man of powerful physique, abundant health, and was rated as the "strongest" man in the city, during his prime. He was also a member of the Senefelder Liederkranz (Song wreath Song Club).</p>
   <p>After passing the proverbial three score and ten, his wife Caroline, nee Seigele, preceded him to the Great Beyond. The marriage was an exceedingly happy one. His four daughters, Mrs. Caroline Fischer, Mrs. Emma Seibt, Mrs. Rosa Lang, Mrs. Ottilie Kleis, and two sons, Fred and George Frillmann, survive him.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1566.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The funeral arrangements have been made for today, the procession being scheduled for this afternoon at two o'clock, from 276 Fremont Street to Graceland Cemetery.</p>
   <p>Peace be with him!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
