<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-01-23">January 23, 1878</date><title level="a">How the Presbyterian Church Is Trying to Spread its Faith Among Germans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-01-23">January 23, 1878</date><title level="a">HOW THE PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH IS TRYING TO SPREAD ITS FAITH AMONG GERMANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For almost five years a small German Presbyterian congregation has been in existence, which apparently is facing a hard struggle at present, as the powerful Fourth Presbyterian Church, Superior and Rush Streets, is preparing to take the church building away from the said small German congregation.</p>
   <p>In order to understand the origin of this dispute, we have to go back to the year 1866, when students of the Presbyterian Seminary opened up a Sunday School on Orchard Street, which was visited mainly by children of the German residents in that neighborhood. The Sunday School flourished and finally received from Mr. Wesley Munger and his wife several lots with an adjoining building as a donation, with the written condition, that the said property should be used for the foundation of an independent German Presbyterian Church. This was accomplished under the guidance of the German pastor C. Wisner.</p>
   <p>In 1874, the Fourth Presbyterian Church started to force pastor, C. Wisner, to preach in English, which policy was refused repeatedly by the small German <pb facs="5418474_11_0054.jpg" n="2"/>congregation, Finally, pastor C. Wisner resigned, and the church service was led for almost two years by church elders and visiting preachers. In 1876 the Fourth Presbyterian Church installed A. Hager as pastor of the German Presbyterian Congregation and instructed him to preach in English. Again violent opposition on the part of the German Congregation set in. Angered by this attitude, the Fourth Presbyterian Church took the case to court and affected a decision, which gave the right to the Fourth Presbyterian Church to take over all property of the small German Congregation. The latter is fighting the decision through new court proceedings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
