<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-09-17">Sep. 17, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[A Naturalization Bill before the Congress]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0561</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0561.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-09-17">Sep. 17, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[A NATURALIZATION BILL BEFORE THE CONGRESS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Democratic Congressman Oates has recently handed down a bill in the house which demands in general the principles for rejection of naturalization of aliens. He states as reasons: Crimes, immorality, and unlawful immigration into the United States. Furthermore no alien shall be pronounced citizen by any court, either federal or state, who cannot speak the English language and cannot read the constitution in its original wording.</p>
   <p>Also excluded from acquiring citizenship are polygamists, anarchists, communists and socialists or members belonging to such societies. Besides, a person has to reside at least six years continously in the United States. The thing that interests us at present is whether this bill is an administration bill, as Cleveland says in his acceptance letter:</p>
   <p>"Before I take care of this part in the pending customs question I would like to voice my opinion in regards to a more direct and more effective protection of the interests of our working classes which although always carefully guarded at every change of our customs laws, will be improved by the prohibition or reduction of immigration.</p>
   <p>"The importation of workers from foreign countries in big swarms who have no <pb facs="5418474_11_0562.jpg" n="2"/>intention of becoming citizens or of taking any lasting interest in our affairs results in an overflow in all branches by people who work for wages that would not satisfy the American workers demand."</p>
   <p>Regarding the rush of this bill and other circumstances we suspect it to be another administration bill bringing our Grover's desires to the surface. An explanation of this question has become imperative before election, for the articles in the Oates bill do not only hurt the interests of the anarchists, communists and socialists and the polygamists, so tastefully combined with us, but concern the majority of the whole population of the United States whose mother language is not English.</p>
   <p>If all those should be excluded from citizenship who cannot speak the English language, then these papers could be refused to at least ninety per cent of all Germans, Bohemians, Poles, Frenchmen, Scandinavians, etc.</p>
   <p>We are, of course, for the idea and have voiced our opinion repeatedly, that every immigrant should get accustomed to local conditions as quickly as possible and adapt himself first of all to the English language, but for most of them this is not possible even in the course of a few years.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0563.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The immigrant worker is mostly employed in shops where his country men are working and if he should work with English speaking fellow workers all he possibly could learn would be confined to shopmatters or a few daily events.</p>
   <p>High words like those in the constitution will not be acquired this way. For a more extensive education, for a thorough study of the English language from books and papers, he lacks not only time but knowledge and money.</p>
   <p>Worse off even is the farmer who often has no chance for months to hear one English word. This present bill therefore is aimed against all non-English immigrants and the question as to whether it is an administration bill demands an answer urgently.</p>
   <p>We hope that the German Democrats who are immediately concerned by this bill, will not take too much time for the answer, otherwise we must accept silence as confirmation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
