<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-11-05">Nov. 5, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">Farewell, Turner Bernhard Vonerollen</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-11-05">Nov. 5, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">FAREWELL, TURNER BERNHARD VONEROLLEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our good friend and Turner, Georg Von Hollen, arrived here yesterday from Perryville where he braved the dangers of war to administer to the wants of those soldiers who were wounded in Kentucky battles. Mr. Von Hollen mourns the loss of his brother, Bernhard von Hollen. The latter, as everybody here knows, was severely wounded in the memorable battle of Perryville, at which time the upper part of both his arms were shattered. He died October 28, at the Perryville Hospital after having suffered intense pain which he bore in heroic patience. The loving care tendered by his brother Georg made his last days more endurable. However, Georg was not at Bernhard's bedside when the latter passed away; he had gone to Louisville, Kentucky to secure clothes for the men who were wounded and destitute of practically everything, food,medical supplies, medical attention, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0217.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Georg's plight is an example of the condition and fate of all soldiers who were seriously wounded at Perryville. No provisions were made for their needs, not even for their most urgent needs, and only the faithful ministration of their nurses makes their terrible lot somewhat more endurable. Dr. Wagner, the regimental physician spent a few minutes with each of them, having returned to them despite the fact that the regiment had advanced, and that his return could only be made in the face of great danger. However, duty called him back to the regiment after a very brief stay at the Hospital.</p>
   <p>The wounded at Perryville need help, immediate help, and as soon as the din of the political campaign has subsided, the local committee will take the steps necessary to alleviate the sufferings of these poor, unfortunate, and sadly neglected Union fighters.</p>
   <p>Bernard von Hollen attained an age of only twenty-four years. He was a <pb facs="5418474_11_0218.jpg" n="3"/>member of the Chicago Turngemeinde and joined the Turner Company when President Lincoln issued his first call to arms in April, 1861. Later this Company was assigned to the first Hecker Regiment. Bernhard had been in the service of his country continually since that time taking part in every battle of the strenuous campaign of Hecker's famous Regiment. As a reward for his military ability and his bravery, he was made an Orderly Sergeant, and after the battle of Perryville, in which he distinguished himself and was fatally wounded, he was advanced to the rank of Lieutenant. His fine character, intelligence, and honesty won him many friends. To them, but especially to his grieving mother, sisters, and brothers, we hereby express our sympathy.</p>
   <p>Georg von Hollen brought with him a piece of a Rebel bomb which he found on the Perryville battleground, and the missile is now on exhibition in the office of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
