<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-03-18">Mar. 18, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Fred Minuth Dies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_1204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-03-18">Mar. 18, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">FRED MINUTH DIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Grand Haven, Mich., where he had lived for a number of years, Fred Minuth died after a long illness. The Abendpost loses a valued editor of many years standing.</p>
   <p>Fred Minuth is well known to the readers of the Abendpost and Sonntagpost. For a number of years, he regularly wrote the "News from Michigan," in which he severely attacked prohibition, because this State was notorious in the excessive zeal with which it prosecuted violations of the prohibition law. For the Sonntagpost; Minuth furnished many articles which dealt with scientific questions.</p>
   <p>Minuth was a newspaper man for many years. He celebrated his 50 year jubilee as a journalist three years ago.</p>
   <p>He was born in Koenigsberg and his first article appeared in the Koenigsberger newspaper in April 1887. For ten years he participated in the literary movements of Germany.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_1205.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was also a co-founder of the still existing East Prussian Border News of Pillkallen. After a sojourn in Holland he came to America in 1888. As was the case for many others he had to be satisfied with any kind of work. He found work on a farm. But soon he was able to make connections and to enter the literary field once again. He wrote, mainly, for German newspapers, and tried to overcome the ignorance prevailing in Germany about American conditions.</p>
   <p>Homesickness induced him to return to Europe for a short stay.</p>
   <p>In March 1899 he again came to America. In 1908 he founded the newspaper Exchange of "North America," which, however, had a short life as he was unable to find understanding among German editors, for whom it was especially intended. Undaunted in 1912 he organized the monthly periodical The German Carrier of Culture which he hoped would find a market in Germany. The great war however, killed this enterprise.</p>
   <p>In 1916, Minuth joined the staff of Illinois Staats Zeitung to succeed the lately deceased Dr. Singer. Soon after this he moved to Grand Haven, where he became the correspondent of the Abendpost.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
