<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-11">June 11, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Evangelical Lutheran Synod of the District of Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_11_0035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_11_0035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-11">June 11, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">EVANGELICAL LUTHERAN SYNOD OF THE DISTRICT OF ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Evangelical Lutheran Synod of the District of Illinois adjourned yesterday evening. It had been in session at the Emanuel Church since last Wednesday.....</p>
   <p>The treasurer reported that about nineteen or twenty thousand dollars had been received. The report was accepted. The money will be given to the General Synod of the United States when that body meets in Columbus in July. The General Synod will apportion the money to various Evangelical Lutheran institutions.</p>
   <p>H. Bartling of Addison, Dupage County, was elected treasurer for next year, and B. Burfeind of Matteson, Cook County, was elected secretary.</p>
   <p>The following gentlemen were elected delegates to the Synodal conferences to be held in Columbus: Professor Walder, F. Lochner, and H. Grosse--clergymen; <pb facs="5418474_11_0036.jpg" n="2"/>Messrs. Heinz, Zuttermann, Frye and Lasen--laymen.</p>
   <p>Professor Craemer gave a memorial address yesterday at the Emanuel Church, in commemoration of Revereand F. Ruland....who died in a railroad accident. Professor Schieferdecker, of Madison County, gave the sermon.</p>
   <p>Messrs. A. Wagner, W. Bartling, and H. Zuttermann were elected to the committee on home missions.</p>
   <p>The delegates from out of town, about three hundred, adopted resolutions expressing thanks for the friendly reception and hospitality shown them.</p>
   <p>The next synod will meet on Thursday after Pentecost, in 1880, at Quincy, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
