<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-06-12">June 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Disgrace</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-06-12">June 12, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A DISGRACE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because of the immorality and detestable corruption of a few Greeks in our city, the reputation of the entire Greek community is threatened.</p>
   <p>There are a few hotels, owned and operated by Greeks, in which unspeakable orgies take place. Many decent Americans have protested against these breeding places of crime and corruption. Already the police have arrested many suspicious hotel owners who are now being questioned.</p>
   <p>In one hotel on Wentworth Avenue, thirteen couples registered as husband and wife in one evening--a Saturday night. It was evident that they were not married couples. After drinking heavily in the noisy and filthy atmosphere of a neighborhood saloon, they went directly to the hotel in the early hours of the morning.</p>
   <p>At another Greek hotel on Halsted Street, Florence Martin, a young girl, hardly <pb facs="5422062_4_0576.jpg" n="2"/>twenty years of age, was arrested by the police. At the station, she stated that some Greek by the name of Demos Baxas had hired her to sell her body for the sum of six dollars a week and forty per cent of the illegal and illicit profits. Thus, Florence was making between ten and twelve dollars daily, part of which Baxas wanted to get for his part in the filthy racket. Baxas, this infamous hotel operator, was promptly arrested and sentenced to a year in prison and fined five hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>These accusations and reports directed at the Greek hotel industry are so serious that we fear the American press and American public opinion will have to undertake a violent campaign of persecution against all the Greeks of Chicago, such as that which occurred in Kansas City, Missouri, In that city, the American press throughout the United States informed the public, a vicious and despicable syndicate operated by Greeks was engaged in white-slave traffic and exploitation.</p>
   <p>We are informed that there are many criminal and perverted characters among our <pb facs="5422062_4_0577.jpg" n="3"/>people in Chicago who are also engaged in this disgraceful business. For the purpose of avoiding a similar scandal and for the sake of the good name and reputation of our good and decent people, we advise all corrupt and filthy characters to mend their ways, to reform, and to close up their filthy places before the police catch up with them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
