<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1928-05-05">May 5, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Appeal.</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Reverential Clergy, Esteemed Ecclesiastical Guardians, and All the Blessed Christians of the Holy Episcopate of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0308</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0308.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-05-05">May 5, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">APPEAL.</title><title level="a" type="sub">TO THE REVERENTIAL CLERGY, ESTEEMED ECCLESIASTICAL GUARDIANS, AND ALL THE BLESSED CHRISTIANS OF THE HOLY EPISCOPATE OF CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Terrible misfortune befell our beloved Greece.</p>
   <p>All of you are informed that historic Corinth, the city beautiful, was entirely destroyed by earthquake, which left the city a pile of smoking debris.</p>
   <p>Similar fate met the suburbs of the city. Thousands upon thousands of citizens of the former prosperous country, panic stricken sped to safety, leaving behind their valuables to be buried by tumbling houses and buildings.</p>
   <p>The greatness of the catastrophe attracted the attention and sympathy of foreign people and nations. From everywhere,tents, provisions, medicines and other assistances arrived.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0309.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greek government at once erected shelters, dispatched provisions, doctors, nurses and every possible facility was placed at the disposal of the sufferers. Millions of drachmas were spent by the government.</p>
   <p>Of course the Greeks who live abroad did not remain inactive. From every part of the world, Greeks assisted.</p>
   <p>We want to believe that the Greeks of America, who in the past when Mother Greece rapped at their door for assistance, willingly and lovingly responded to her expectations, will not this time disappoint the sweet and tender hopes she entertains about them.</p>
   <p>Fortunately and properly the Greeks of America understood their duty and obligations and at once became active.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0310.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>With throbbing heart I observe that the Greek press in America, the Archdiocese, dioceses, communities, societies, organizations and everything that bears the Greek name, began to organize and marshall their forces to march to the assistance of our suffering brother Greeks.</p>
   <p>For this reason I fatherly appeal to the clergy of the Greek Orthodox churches in the periphery of the Chicago episcopate, that next Sunday, May 6th, they should deliver from the altar the appropriate invocations to the masses and request the guardians of the churches to pass around the collection plates. I also suggest to their respective church councils to form committees to visit all the Greek stores of the city for contributions.</p>
   <p>All collections and contributions arising from such activities should be sent to the diocese, which in turn will deliver to the Greek Consul-general who will wire it to Greece, and publish the names of the contributors. With prayers to our Savior.</p>
   <p>Bishop Philaretos</p>
   <p>Chicago Episcopate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
