<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-05-20">May 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Lottery Must Be Stopped</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0580</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0580.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-05-20">May 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">LOTTERY MUST BE STOPPED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 1.- Last Sunday the Chicago Record-Herald, an American newspaper, had an article dealing with the sale of lottery tickets by the Greek government to build a Navy. It is said that a man who has many dealings with the Greeks on Halsted street, asserted that over $200,000 has left the United States for Greece and her Navy. The Greek newspapers, it is said, come through the United States mail and are violating one of the most important rules of the Post-office.</p>
   <p>Every Greek must remember that although we are strangers in a strange land, we must abide by the rules and regulations which govern this country. We must always be truthful and honest, but we needn't go out of our way to do it, as Someone who reported that there was a "racket" among the Greeks on South Water Market and $200,000 in lottery tickets have left the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0581.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This Mr. Someone has been grossly misinformed. Where could these uneducated, ignorant, Greeks find $200,000 in their short time in this country? Miracles such as these cannot be performed every day.</p>
   <p>The reporters are very dumb because it can easily be seen that if we did have that much money, we would build schools and churches, not send it to the mother country which we left behind.</p>
   <p>Greeks are not interested in gambling of this sort. If this "racket" was as big as it is said to be, the police would have known about it and done something. It would not be necessary for a Mr. Someone to tell the government.</p>
   <p>We are aware that such lotteries are conducted in Athens and advertised in Greek newspapers, but that is as far as we go. It is an insult to the Greek nationality in Chicago to have such articles printed!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
