<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Program of the Ninth Annual Dance, Given by the St. Spyridon Educational Society, Chicago, Ill.</title>,
<date when="1936-10-28">Oct. 28, 1936</date>, pp. 17-19.
<title level="a">Article Translated by Peter N. Mantzoros, from the Greek Almanac of the Archdiocese issued in 1936, "A Summary of the History of the Greek Church of North and South America."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Program of the Ninth Annual Dance, Given by the St. Spyridon Educational Society, Chicago, Ill.</title>,
<date when="1936-10-28">Oct. 28, 1936</date>, pp. 17-19.
<title level="a">Article Translated by Peter N. Mantzoros, from the Greek Almanac of the Archdiocese issued in 1936, "A Summary of the History of the Greek Church of North and South America."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first Greek Orthodox Community in the United States was founded in 1867 in New Orleans, Louisiana. After the first Greek Orthodox Community was established others followed and all of their ecclesiastical activities were being directed through the Ecumenical Patriarchate in Constantinople.</p>
   <p>In 1908, the then Patriarch Ioakeim Ill, issued a "Patriarchal Volume" transferring his authority governing the church in America to the Holy Synod in Athens, Greece.</p>
   <p>For ten years the Greek Orthodox Church in North and South America was governed through the Holy Synod in Greece and in September of 1918 the Most Right Rev. Metropolitan of Athens, Meletios Metaxakis accompanied by the Right Rev. Bishop of Rodostolou Alexander, came to America to <pb facs="5422062_4_1925.jpg" n="2"/>study closer the needs of the Christians of our race residing here. Before returning to Athens he appointed Bishop Alexander to direct the activities of the Greek Orthodox Church of North and South America with headquarters in New York City.</p>
   <p>In 1922 the newly elected Patriarch of the Ecumenical Patriarchate in Constantinople, Meletios, took away the authority governing the Greek Orthodox Church in America from the Holy Synod of Greece and transferred it to Patriarchate in Constantinople, but he promoted Bishop Alexander to the office of Archbishop of North and South America and also created three new Bishops namely that of Chicago, San Francisco and Boston.</p>
   <p>During this period the Theological School of St. Athanasius was founded and a church publication was created, both under the supervision of the Archdiocese. These enterprises were short-lived, due to lack of funds for their upkeep. From 1922 until 1930 the Greek Orthodox Communities showed a remarkable progress, but unfortunately during the latter part of this period the political situation in Greece was shaken to such an <pb facs="5422062_4_1926.jpg" n="3"/>extent as to even find followers among our people in this country, with the result that many thousands of dollars were spent accomplishing very little.</p>
   <p>During the same period, while old country politics were being forced into the church, two large societies were founded and established in this country by Progressive Greek-American citizens, namely, the Order of Ahepa, meaning American Hellenic Educational Progressive Association, and the Order of Gapa, meaning Greek-American Progressive Association, who helped to some extent to divorce our church from the politics of the old country. These societies were also instrumental in helping to erect schools and churches where there were none and thus helped to keep our ever-growing population within the sphere of the church.</p>
   <p>The Archbishop with the three bishops, were working hard to educate our people and help them become better citizens, but the schism between our people on account of old country politics was still going on and so in 1929 when the new Patriarch, Photios II, took office in Constantinople, <pb facs="5422062_4_1927.jpg" n="4"/>he dispatched to this country his representative, the Most Right Rev. Metropolitan Damaskinos, with orders not only to take charge of the Greek Orthodox Church in America but also to try and reconcile the various factions. His mission was crowned with success after which, he left in 1931, leaving the authority of governing the church to the able leadership of Right Rev. Bishop Callistos, at the same time transferring the other two bishops and the Archbishop to Greece.</p>
   <p>In the latter part of 1931 a new Archbishop was elected in Constantinople who was designated Archbishop of North and South America and who arrived here in November of the same year and took up his duties with headquarters in New York City. Since his arrival many things have been accomplished and we hope he will continue this fine leadership.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
