<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-06-25">June 25, 1910</date><title level="a">Curious Things</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-06-25">June 25, 1910</date><title level="a">CURIOUS THINGS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Some very curious things happened last week and the principle character was none other than our Greek Consul in Chicago, Mr. N. Salopoulos, ally to the Atlantis in disrupting the peace of the Greek people here.</p>
   <p>The Atlantis writes that Mr. Salopoulos is the best Greek Consul America has ever had even though this man has tried his best to ruin Greek organizations and societies, causing trouble wherever he goes.</p>
   <p>This is a fact and all Greeks in America must open their eyes and acknowledge it. A Panhellenic Union we must have, else Hellenism in America will surely disappear.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1379.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Coming back to the subject in hand--all the Greeks in our community have been jolted by the actions of this "perfect" Consul, as the Atlantis states. We do not want to pour oil on an already raging fire, nor do we want to antagonize Atlantis, but we are greatly interested in the meetings at Hull House, where plans are under way to unite all Greek societies in Chicago. We do not intend to have these excellent plans ruined by the Atlantis and N. Salopoulos.</p>
   <p>The following is a brief summary of what has already been done.</p>
   <p>Minutes of the first meeting at Hull House on June 11.</p>
   <p>Today, June 11, Saturday, at 8 o'clock, Mr. A. Vlachos and the undersigned, invited the presidents of all Greek societies in our city to a Greek-American meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1380.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Raymond Duncan, a Philhellene, spoke to those present about ancient Greek politics, gymnastics, music, drama, etc. There were also several Greek and American orators. The organizer of this affair, Mr. Vlachos and the secretary, Mr. D. Eutaxias, invited all prominent Greeks to attend their second meeting which will be held soon. Mr. Duncan will again address the audience.</p>
   <p>Organizer</p>
   <p>A. Vlachos</p>
   <p>Pres. of the Pedalers Ass'n.</p>
   <p>Secretary</p>
   <p>D. Eutaxias</p>
   <p>Pres. of the Stereoladitans.</p>
   <p>Other Presidents</p>
   <p>J. Kokkalis, Restaurant Ass'n.; N. Athanasakos, "St. George"; Tanias; G. Evagelou, Tanias; N. Papantonopoulos, Trifyliakos and J. Boumbakis, Phoenix.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1381.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Minutes of the Second Meeting at Hull House on June 14.</p>
   <p>Today, June 14, all members of the Presidents' Organization, as well as other prominent men, gathered at Hull House and held a Greek-America meeting. This meeting accomplished the following:</p>
   <p>(1) Plans for a mass meeting were discussed by A. Vlachos and N. Salopoulos.</p>
   <p>(2) The mass meeting will take place at Orchestra Hall to accommodate all the Greeks in Chicago.</p>
   <p>(3) A committee consisting of K. Salopoulos, president, J. Zotalis, G. Evagelos, N. Athanasakis, B. Konstakis, J. Boumbikos, K. Matalas, and S. Kotakis will meet next Wednesday to discuss plans.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1382.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>(4) Raymond Duncan, Philhellene, spoke to the assembly. He was followed by two American and two Greek businessmen.</p>
   <p>(5) A collection was taken up and the money was handed to K. Konstantakis, treasurer. Donors were:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell/>
     <cell>(Clubs)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>N. Salopoulos</cell>
     <cell>$5.00</cell>
     <cell>(Greek Consul)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. Dimitrakopoulos</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
     <cell>(Young Men's Club)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. Boumbakis</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
     <cell>(Phoenix)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>B. Konstantakis</cell>
     <cell>5.00</cell>
     <cell>(Greek Res't Ass'n)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>J. Zotakis</cell>
     <cell>1.00</cell>
     <cell>(Pan Hellenic)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>N. Athanasakos</cell>
     <cell>3.00</cell>
     <cell>("St. George" Tanias)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>D. Eutaxias</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
     <cell>(Stereoladitan)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>A. Spiropoulos</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
     <cell>(Calapritans)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>P. Kolombakos</cell>
     <cell>5.00</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>N. Koutroulis</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1383.jpg" n="6"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>A. Ritsones</cell>
     <cell>$2.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>S. Kotakis</cell>
     <cell>1.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>G. Matalas</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>G. Giannois</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>K. Paleologos</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>K. Katsikeas</cell>
     <cell>1.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>A. Vlachos</cell>
     <cell>10.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>A. Galineas</cell>
     <cell>2.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$50.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Promoter</p>
   <p>A. Vlachos.</p>
   <p>Secretary</p>
   <p>D. Eutaxias.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1384.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>These minutes sound logical and above board. And we have no complaint to make in regard to them. But here is something we cannot understand. Mr. Athanasakos, one of our presidents, received the following letter from Mr. Salopoulos, the Greek Consul.</p>
   <p>Greek Consul of Greece</p>
   <p>Chicago, June 15, 1910</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Athanasakos:</p>
   <p>This afternoon I invited the president of the Young Men's Club to my office and instructed him to rent the Garrick Theater for Mr. Duncan's performance (Loxias Note:- $50 has been donated by the members for this purpose already.) Mr. Monstantakis is coming to my office at 4 o'clock tomorrow and I would like to have you come also, so we can go over the list of invitations together.</p>
   <p>Yours truly,</p>
   <p>N. Salopoulos.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1385.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>We contend that Mr. Salopoulos is a bystander not one of the organizers of this affair. To clarify our explanation, we quote from the Record-Herald of June 16--</p>
   <p>"Among those present were N. Salopoulos, Greek Consul in Chicago, and the presidents of fifteen Greek societies."</p>
   <p>Does this sound as if Mr. Salopoulos is promoting the affair? Hot to us. The Greek Consul may be the greatest man in the world, according to the Atlantis, but he had no right to send that letter, without the permission of the organization and without the secretary's knowledge. He had no right to take matters into his own hands and run them as he sees fit. The gentleman even appointed himself guest speaker of the evening, preparing a long speech for the occasion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1386.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>These are the curious things that have been going on this last week and nobody is to blame but Mr. Salopoulos. There is one thing this very important gentleman must learn and that is that the societies can take care of themselves. If they need the help of the Greek Consul, they will ask him. Otherwise, the Greek Consul must stay in his office and perform the duties his office demands of him. We hope he takes the hint we are giving.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
