<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-08-30">Aug. 30, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">[Eminent Attorney Advocates Co-Operation Among Greeks]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0908</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0908.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-08-30">Aug. 30, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">[EMINENT ATTORNEY ADVOCATES CO-OPERATION AMONG GREEKS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Having visited in his office at 105 W. Madison St. the eminent lawyer of our city, Mr. Diamantis Pan. Bouzanis, I was received with true Greek politeness, without added formalities of mixed barbarian origin.</p>
   <p>"The opinions of our countrymen expressed in your paper," he said, "give me great pleasure because of their stimulating and beneficial effect upon Greek-Americans. That is why I follow them, and I add the following as mine...academically....hoping that this work of the press will bear fruit in practice...</p>
   <p>"One of the many subjects that are handled properly is the question of cooperation. A wonderful idea, indeed, for the wonderful syllogisms of the ancient Greek philosophers, the thoughts of the present authors, Socialists, - the dreams of Bolsheviks and of all other mortals seeking salvation, are based on that! This word, - cooperation, -embraces a whole world of action and progress! It is enough to conduct one's self sincerely, with just scientific system and without partiality. There is a chance for all Greek Americans who, armed with cooperation, desire productive action. In alliance with this powerful sister of the God of profit Hermes, we Greek-Americans will be able to keep our position <pb facs="5422062_4_0909.jpg" n="2"/>in commerce and to improve it systematically. We will stand firmly....for our economic independence in the future. By this unconquered goddess we shall be able to erect perfect Greek-American temples in which the divine and eternal Greek literature will be taught not imperfectly but perfectly, so that through it the New World will be really illuminated, and we ourselves, the Greek-Americans. For the Greek-American the decade ahead of us is the battle of Waterloo; either he will leave traces worthy of his descent, or he will be utterly defeated as if he had never existed here.</p>
   <p>Although lack of space does not permit me to expand, I briefly exhort Greek heads of families in the name of Greek ideals, to avoid a disease of Pharaoh, to wit:</p>
   <p>Let them not allow their children to frequent European dances.</p>
   <p>The reason? Some other time I will deal with it in a lengthy article.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0910.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I urge them, however, to dance the unblemished Greek dance with decent songs and morals. So I am not to be considered insipid and to be punished by the Olympian gods."</p>
   <p>Mr. Bouzanis was born in Kosma of Kynouria, came here when very young, has studied law, having developed also his knowledge of the Greek language, for which he told us he is filled with adoration for its unparalleled beauty.</p>
   <p>D. J. Rigas</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
