<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-11-02">Nov. 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Education and Parents</title><title level="a" type="sub">by P. Pitha</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0873</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0873.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-11-02">Nov. 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATION AND PARENTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by P. Pitha</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wherever one goes it is always possible to hear a heated argument or discussion about the fate of the younger generations of Greeks in America. Generally, it is carried on by those who are conscious of the lack of Greek development in our boys and girls. They seem to become more and more Americanized every day, despite the efforts and desires of the older generation.</p>
   <p>Within the confines of their own homes the boys and girls strive to follow the Greek culture and customs. They speak the language of their fathers and act in accordance with their customs and ideals. All these things are rather burdensome to the young people; but respect and love for their parents, along with their inherent precepts, force them to try--and to try hard.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0874.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All of them would like to know the Greek language and to understand our beautiful literature and poetry; but--. When they reach a certain point in their development they see that nothing has been provided to help make this possible. Even children who have graduated from Greek schools do not have enough of their native background to enable them to retain their command of the Greek language. As a result, they weary of struggling alone, and find surcease from their effort by using the language native to them by birth--the English.</p>
   <p>Austere parents and all those of the older generation are horror stricken and filled with despair when they see large groups of their young people unable to utter a complete sentence in Greek. As a result of many such observations, the concensus of opinion is that the children of this younger generation will not retain a trace of their Greek heritage. Our people will survive in America only in certain strata. This will be the result of the labor of parents who are educated themselves, and not because of any churches or <pb facs="5422062_4_0875.jpg" n="3"/>schools our group may maintain.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that maternal influence plays a great part in the character development and the ability of the children in her care. Therefore, that mother who has a good education and a command of the Greek language which she uses in speaking to her children, cannot help but rear children who have strong predominant, Greek characteristics. They will speak her language with love and respect because they will always associate it with her kindness and love.</p>
   <p>A good example of this can be found in all the Greek mothers of enslaved territories, who gave their children a complete education despite the tyranny and repression of their oppressers.</p>
   <p>Women of good family and good upbringing do not allow their customs or <pb facs="5422062_4_0876.jpg" n="4"/>culture to die, no matter where they may be transplanted by destiny. The cultured mother or father can transfer to the children those ideals which kept the pure Greek alive during the period from 1453 to 1821. Then, the hope of liberty was the only incentive those parents had. And we shall be able to keep our language and culture alive in America for many generations. Our efforts will not be in vain; nor will they go unnoticed.</p>
   <p>It is noticeable that the children of well-educated Greeks are the only ones who speak the Greek language and understand and abide by the Greek customs and ideals. Their children are not ashamed of speaking a foreign language, because the culture of their parents seems to have made the use of it worth while; and they seek to imitate their example.</p>
   <p>It is unfortunate that we cannot rely to any extent upon the children of those parents who feel that bread is more important than leavening. They have not the proper educational stamina to "carry the ball" as is said in <pb facs="5422062_4_0877.jpg" n="5"/>football parlance. The ego of their kind is anemic, and will soon die. Let us hope that our strong players will become more numerous.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
