<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1916-02-16">Feb. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A Word for the Greeks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Chicago Daily News)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1916-02-16">Feb. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD FOR THE GREEKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Chicago Daily News)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1. -- I humbly beg to be allowed to inquire why Greeks are so very frequently accused and criticized in Chicago. For instance, some newspapers recently reported that a young woman had been kidnaped either by a Greek or by an Italian. This was a fabrication. When the Washington Park Bank was robbed, two Chicago papers stated that the chief bandit was a Greek. Again the statement was proved to be untrue. These are two of many instances in which the press has thrown blame on the Greeks. It is not fair.</p>
   <p>Some of our most learned and loyal American citizens today are Greeks. It has been my lot to come into contact with a great many people of this nationality, and I can truthfully say that one could not find more ambitious, industrious, and law-abiding citizens anywhere in the United States, and I am ready to back up my statement.</p>
   <p>There is no need for me to discourse on Greek history, since almost everyone <pb facs="5422062_4_0649.jpg" n="2"/>is familiar with it, but I cannot find anything in that history that should make Greeks the abused persons which they are in Chicago. Is it because the son of Hellas is a greenhorn as far as the English language is concerned that the American thinks himself superior? I think that the thousands of business enterprises built up by Greeks in Chicago prove whether their greenness is detrimental to them or not.</p>
   <p>I have heard a great many Greeks ask these same questions.</p>
   <p>Maisie Awnes.</p>
   <p>Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
