<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-05-12">May 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Seek Aid for Greek Sufferers in Asia Minor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-05-12">May 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SEEK AID FOR GREEK SUFFERERS IN ASIA MINOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thousands of our brothers are lacking the barest of essentials necessary for their existence. Thousands of women and children are expatriated and sent to the barren wastes of Asia Minor; victims of war and of mistreatment. There they die of exposure and starvation; while we are enjoying comfort, peace, and liberty.</p>
   <p>This is a great national danger, and if it is not remedied will result in a catastrophe or in the assimilation of our race.</p>
   <p>The Patriarchy is making strong pleas to the philanthropic instincts of the American people and the Greeks in America. It stated that the small sums contributed so far are not enough to staunch the huge wound caused by the barbaric war which is undermining the foundations of our race.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we should not be indifferent and wait for the Americans to show us <pb facs="5422062_4_0487.jpg" n="2"/>our duty. We must deprive ourselves of a few luxuries in order to show the Americans that we are interested in the fate of our fellow patriots, just as much as the Armenians and Syrians are. The Syrians have contributed a sum of over five hundred thousand dollars, and are soon going to contribute more, probably double that amount. The Syrians, although few in numbers, did so much while the Greeks have failed badly in their duty, despite the fact that in some instances the Greek refugees in Asia Minor are suffering far more than either the Syrians or the Armenians.</p>
   <p>In a conference between the Patriarch of Constantinople and the representatives of the Greek and American governments, a relief committee composed of Greeks and Americans was chosen. The Americans contributed $50,000 to be used for the relief of the Greek refugees. The Greeks on the committee obtained permission to open a drive for funds, appealing to the people that had felt the disaster less than the others.</p>
   <p>This drive in America is entirely a philanthropic one, and is in no way connected <pb facs="5422062_4_0488.jpg" n="3"/>with politics.</p>
   <p>We have hopes that this time the ties of brotherhood will be more strongly felt than before, and that this drive will bring rich harvests to aid the misery and privation suffered by innocent people in Europe.</p>
   <p>The president of the committee, Doctor Benton, writes the following to the Greeks of America: "I sincerely hope that the Greeks in America, who are living amidst peace and plenty, will not fail to hear the voice of their suffering brothers in Asia Minor. The purpose of this drive is more important than any other situation facing us right now. Our committee is willing to co-operate and aid you in this philanthropic work. It would be very sad if the Greeks of America were to refuse to aid these poor victims. The committee has centers all over the United States, and any of its members will be willing and eager to proffer any services possible."</p>
   <p>Since the severing of relations between America and Turkey, $150,000 have been sent by the American committee to Constantinople.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
