<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-05-07">May 7, 1930</date><title level="a">Hull House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0914</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0914.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-05-07">May 7, 1930</date><title level="a">HULL HOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5 There isn't a Greek in Chicago who does not know the philanthropic educational institution situated in the heart of the Greek district, Halsted Street, known as Hull House, whose manager and founder is our beloved Jane Addams.</p>
   <p>To the Americans, Hull House is a colorful story. To Jane Addams, Hull House is the embodiment of her life's dreams. To the foreigners, lonely, shunned, and despised, Hull House is a shelter, a welcome haven.</p>
   <p>It is hard to describe fully what that corner means to the Greeks of Chicago who have use the building for thousands of meetings, dinners and clubs. It has been the means of educating many Greek boys and men with the American ways of living. It housed soldiers of the Balkan War, soldiers who had fought under the leadership of J. Agriostathes.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0915.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The story of the Greeks of Chicago and their association with Hull House is a long and eventful one.</p>
   <p>In a three day celebration, Hull House is going to commemorate its 40th. anniversary. On Friday, Saturday and Sunday, May 9, 10, and 11, from two P. M. till evening, programs and exhibitions will take place in all departments of the institution. The planning of such a program has been rather a difficult task but we feel sure it will be a successful one.</p>
   <p>Among those present will be W. S. McKenze King, of Canada, and Prof. John Dewey. The climax of the celebration will be reached on Saturday evening at Bowen Hall when many notable speakers will be present who will laud Miss Addams as the "First Lady of the land" and who will acclaim her great achievements.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
