<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1923-10-13">Oct. 13, 1923</date><title level="a">Crime and the School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1923-10-13">Oct. 13, 1923</date><title level="a">CRIME AND THE SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the occasion of the Greco-Italian incident, due to the assassination of the Italian missionaries, and the degenerate tendencies observed in society after the last war, we are motivated to quote from a celebrated book on sociology--the chapter on "School and the Crime."</p>
   <p>"The basis upon which the molding and education of the Societies of all Nations took form was the School. The school, however, must have as its aids, the Family, the Church, and the State."</p>
   <p>By the cooperation of these branches of society comes about happiness and progress in the various societies, respectively. Indifference to one or more of these branches causes the failure and corruption of the society. Naturally, every evil is attributed to the lack of proper schools and to the poor tutorship of its functionaries.</p>
   <p>The author is trying to prove that on the basis of opinion and statistics, <pb facs="5422062_4_0749.jpg" n="2"/>that education works towards the diminishing of crime. Others explain crime and corruption on the basis of Darwinism, pointing out a class struggle. That, however, which ought to attract our attention is the investigation and definition of the evolution of the individual, who has become a criminal. Such a study is indispensable for it brings out the process of criminality in all its steps and phases. In this way causes contributing to its evolution will be recognized and methods of eliminating or preventing them from taking form will be worked out.</p>
   <p>School, the classic present day school, and education itself, do not prevent crime. The present day school is not a well of morality from which the student can draw his virtue and temperance. This is so, not because the letters and the School are not fit to educate the child morally, but because the conditions under which the school labors and letters are learned, may be parallel to those of the parable of the Husbandman in the New Testament. Those who earnestly watch evil and corruption grow and yet do nothing about it are right by the door of the school.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0750.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Church, the main social regulator, engaging itself in metaphysical and incomprehensible doctrines, does anything but educate mankind. What is, then, the remaining power? The agogi (training), we answer. That can be given in a greater degree by the parents. But when the cruel necessities of life keep the father absorbed in constant work to meet pressing economic needs and the mother to housework and other matters, the question arises: Is the rearing of children under such conditions destructive? Yes! Children, by instinctive persistence avoid the attention and supervision of the parents.</p>
   <p>Immunity is something that children believe in. All these tendencies and efforts quicken. When children should get acquainted with what is concealed, these tendencies create such a confusion on their minds that it is possible, from moment to moment, for thousands of bad tendencies to hatch. Subconciously, a physical predisposition for crime begins to make its appearance. Crime! Not only the crime that written laws condemn, but crime contrary to all natural, moral, and social laws.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0751.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>For the restriction of bad conduct and invigoration of children in moral education, a systematic social organization must prevail. When children get their rearing under supervision of the State, like the Spartans, so to speak, the morality will be considered an invincible religion, which no mysterious ignorance of the outer world, nor other sinister effort could effect a criminal manifestation. For this it is necessary that ability and virtue be recognized by all instructors.</p>
   <p>While the children of the poor nourish criminal instincts due to ignorance, the children of the rich are commiting crime due to listlessness.</p>
   <p>George Leledakis</p>
   <p>Professor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
