<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-17">July 17, 1929</date><title level="a">The Chicago Gapa Chapter Alexander Ypsilantis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-07-17">July 17, 1929</date><title level="a">THE CHICAGO GAPA CHAPTER ALEXANDER YPSILANTIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Gapa chapter Alexander Ypsilantis of Chicago, in order to fulfill the main purpose of its organization, that of preserving the Greek tongue in America, is making every sacrifice and considering every means realizing such an objective. So as not let too much time lapse with nothing to show for our efforts, we have hit on a clan which we think will be welcomed by everybody.</p>
   <p>We are inviting all the Greek people of Chicago and its environment to partake in a Greek language contest. With this invitation we hope to rouse the enthusiasm and zealousness of the Greek people for Greek art and letters. We are turning to the Greek woman for help because woman is the greatest strength of a nation. Women preserves or destroys ideals, religion, language, and customs. So it is on women we are going to depend to preserve our language for us because they are our greatest strength.</p>
   <p>We have decided to hold an annual Greek Language contest, among the Greek women in and around Chicago; the first event of which will take place in October, 1929, the place and day to be decided later.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1260.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Terms of the contest:</p>
   <p>To those wishing to participate: (1) They must be 18 years of age or more. (2) Born in America and never having been in Greece. (3) Born in Greece but having come to America younger than 5 years old and never having gone to Greece again. (4) Born in America and having visited Greece for less than a year.</p>
   <p>Directions for the contest:</p>
   <p>Those wishing to participate in the contest will come when the time, place and date are set, bringing with them nothing but a fountain-pen. The contest will be written. The contestants will be supplied with special test paper on which they will write their theme, which will be described more fully later. The names of the contestants will be sealed so the judges. will not know whose paper the are grading. The name of the winner will not be revealed until the prize is awarded at a ceremony in her honor.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1261.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Theme of the Contest:</p>
   <p>The committee has chosen for its first theme Ancient Greek mythology and a few popular songs. It would be wise for those wishing to take part in the contest to acquaint themselves with Greek mythology and the current Greek songs. The judges, who are chosen from the may teachers in Chicago, will ask for a certain phase of mythology and one song which the contestants will write from memory. The papers will be graded on the following: (1) Contents; (2) Spelling and Syntax.</p>
   <p>Note:- For brushing up on your Ancient Mythology, we recommend the history of Ancient Greece by A. Psillas. It is condensed into a few pages--.Contestants should study thoroughly up to page 55, the chapter titled, Sparta Return of the Herculeans. For further information see Dr. S. Loumos, 25 E. Washington Street, president of the Educational Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
