<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1920-04-17">Apr. 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Celebration of Greek Independence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1920-04-17">Apr. 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATION OF GREEK INDEPENDENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The celebration of Greek Independence Day was held on Easter Sunday, in the Louis XVI Room of the Sherman Hotel.</p>
   <p>The entire room had been trimmed with blue draperies and Greek and American flags.</p>
   <p>A large crowd began gathering at 8:00 P.M.; it marched to the inspiring strains of martial music, played by a Greek orchestra.</p>
   <p>At 8:30 P.M. the consul, Mr. Xanthopoulos; the president of the Celebration Committee, Mr. Paleologos; the orator of the evening, Mr. N. Salopoulos; also Reverend L. Pygeas, and Reverend D. Hatzidimitriou; the presidents of the Greek church boards of Chicago, and Mr. Kairofilas, took their places on the platform.</p>
   <p>The Greek and American national anthems were then played. A prayer by <pb facs="5422062_4_1645.jpg" n="2"/>Reverend D. Hatzidimitriou followed. Mr. C. Paleologos introduced the Greek Consul with these words:</p>
   <p>"The Board of Directors of the three Greek churches, heeding the voice of duty and patriotism, decided to plan a celebration for the Greek Independence Day. They received the co-operation of all the Greek clubs and societies in Chicago. They have chosen me as their spokesman, to ask you to assure the Greek government of the support of the Chicago Greeks. They want to pledge their support and aid to their fatherland. Tonight, when we review the history and problems of Greece, the need for our support will become evident.</p>
   <p>Then the Consul General spoke. He reviewed the past history of Greece, and compared the present and past problems of the government. He recommended unity of spirit and endeavor in order that the Chicago Greeks should be strong enough to aid the program.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1646.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. N. Salopoulos, the speaker of the day, was acclaimed by the assemblage, when he finished speaking.</p>
   <p>The orchestra played the "Poet and Peasant Overture" and then Mr. D. Emopoulos recited patriotic poems. The orchestra played a medley of songs and then Mr. G. Drosos, well-known teacher and progressive, was introduced. He presented two students dressed in the Greek national costume. Although they were short of stature the boys recited two patriotic poems in magnificent tones. They were heartily applauded by the audience. Mrs. K. Kotakis, a teacher from the Koraes School emphasized the necessity for spiritual freedom, and its need by the coming generation.</p>
   <p>Again the orchestra aroused the emotions with the spirited "Funiculi Funicula." Miss Pouli came next singing "My Distant Fatherland," with her lovely soprano voice.</p>
   <p>The consul general, then introduced Mr. Kairofilas, who praised the work of <pb facs="5422062_4_1647.jpg" n="4"/>Mr. Venizelos. The consul thanked the speakers and audience for their co-operation and loyalty to their fatherland.</p>
   <p>The enthusiastic and inspired audience left at 11:30 P.M. to the strains of "Solo Mio."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
