<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-08-11">Aug. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal Made by the Greek Red Cross Campaign Committee to the Chicago Greeks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-08-11">Aug. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL MADE BY THE GREEK RED CROSS CAMPAIGN COMMITTEE TO THE CHICAGO GREEKS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fellow citizens: Never before in the history of the world has such bloodshed, such suffering, such torture, occurred as now exists in the countries of Europe.</p>
   <p>Never before has humanity been subjected to such mental and physical anguish, to such destruction of its life and material wealth.</p>
   <p>Never before has the entire world organized to help some of its unfortunate inhabitants, regardless of race, color, or creed.</p>
   <p>Never before have the modern Greeks had the opportunity to show the rest of the world their humane and philanthropic feelings as they have now, by aiding <pb facs="5422062_4_0473.jpg" n="2"/>the efforts of the Greek Red Cross campaign committee.</p>
   <p>The Greeks in America, realizing the fact that America--the land of truth, justice, and democracy--defends our mother country, Greece; know that it is our duty to show some appreciation.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to show the world that the Greeks are good American citizens and are worthy of being called Americans.</p>
   <p>This is our only opportunity to repay the American Red Cross for the funds they collected for the refugees of Greece in 1881.</p>
   <p>Any worth-while effort we make will be remembered by the American people and will help us to establish ourselves more firmly in this, our adopted country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0474.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us raise more money than any other foreign group in America. We can if we try hard enough.</p>
   <p>Offerings to the American Red Cross are not only an obligation but actually a duty of the Greeks.</p>
   <p>The Greek Red Cross Campaign is guided by a central committee of eight well-known men, and by twenty regional committees of three. The Greek committee is not seeking small individual donations to the American Red Cross; it wants the sums which are given, to be credited to the Greek Fund.</p>
   <p>Show the American populace that the Greeks are an appreciative, humane race of people.</p>
   <p>(signed) Central Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
