<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-08-20">Aug. 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Panhellenic League Condemned by the Lyre of Regas Fereos</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-08-20">Aug. 20, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE PANHELLENIC LEAGUE CONDEMNED BY THE LYRE OF REGAS FEREOS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All those who are connected with the now famous, but rapidly disintegrating Panhellenic League, continue to believe that under the guise of patriotism they can exploit the Greeks of Chicago and those in other states indefinitely. But by reading the following report of our new and extensive nationalistic and patriotic society, The Lyre of Regas Fereos, the Greeks of Chicago, especially, will discover and see for themselves how corrupt and incapable the administrators and leaders of the Panhellenic League are. They will also approve of the campaign which The Greek Star and prominent Greeks have conducted against an organization which started on the wrong foot and whose record of activities showsthat not much was done to organize and benefit the Greek people. We intend to show our people that all Greeks will not tolerate the pseudopatriots <pb facs="5422062_4_1409.jpg" n="2"/>and exploiters of the sacred name of our country.</p>
   <p>There are still two Greek newspapers in Chicago which are defending the program and the past record of the League's leadership. They do this because they are profiting through the publication of the League's activities and by the squandering of funds. The people generally and former members of the League are now fully aware of the dubious and secret intrigues which have been going on in the executive council. That is the reason why the League and everything it really stands for have been discredited. The people have no more confidence in its leadership. Herewith, we are publishing a copy of a letter from The Lyre of Regas Fereos Society to The Atlantis, New York City Greek Daily, which was published in that newspaper on the eleventh instant. The Greeks of Chicago, many of whom had a hand in organizing the Panhellenic League and a great number of whom are members at the present time, will no doubt be interested in some new revelations. The letter follows:</p>
   <p>"To all Members of the Panhellenic League:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1410.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The members of The Lyre of Regas Fereos Society, a chapter of the nationwide Panhellenic League, received an official communication from the League asking for our Society's annual dues as well as for additional financial support. The members of our Society not only refused to send any money, but asked the executive council to condemn the policies and the practices of the League's administration. Seeing that the members had been thoroughly aroused the executive council proceeded to draw up the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>"1) The Lyre of Regas Fereos Society [Translator's note: Regas Fereos was the greatest Greek poet and champion of Greek freedom prior to the Greek War of Independence. He spread the gospel of Greece's desire for freedom not only among the enslaved Greeks, but also among the other subjugated peoples in the Balkans.] which was instrumental in organizing the League ceases to contribute any dues or fees and regrets to see that its expectations have come to nought. No doubt all those who saw how the financial and adminstrative affairs of the League were being handled were greatly disappointed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1411.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"2) The Society appeals to all the various Greek societies, clubs, and communities as well as to all the remaining members of the Panhellenic League and asks them to state whether or not the League deserves any more confidence. One can draw his own conclusions after seeing the many abuses and extravagances of the leaders. For example, the League secretary receives $100 per month, and other sums are wasted for stamps, announcements, and other unnecessary office expenses without gaining anything. With all these expenses the finances of the League are not improving; on the contrary, the treasury has been emptied. Perhaps the League was created in order to pay salaries to loafers and useless office holders. It is really a great shame to have a few clever racketeers plunder the pocketbooks of our poor and hardworking laborers who are members of the League. The money which the members pay is sacred because it comes from the sweat and hard-earned savings of the common laborer. The people's money should not be squandered and stolen by grafters and organization politicans.</p>
   <p>"Surely the $1,200 which is given the secretary and the thousands of dollars which are spent for useless correspondence and impressive pamphlets could be <pb facs="5422062_4_1412.jpg" n="5"/>sent to our homeland and used for the great needs of Greece. All of us know that we need a well-equipped and modernized army, a powerful fleet for the defense of Greece; the treasury of our National Greek Patriarchate is empty; therefore, the Patriarch is unable to defend and fight for the rights of the Christian Greeks who are being ruthlessly persecuted and butchered by the Turks. Finally, our families and homes in Greece need as much financial support as we can give because they live in a poor country which cannot feed its growing population properly.</p>
   <p>"We believe that under these circumstances there is no sane and patriotic Greek who sees any reason why we should tolerate dishonest and inefficient office-holders and defrauders. "Our executive committee publicizes these activities, not because it wishes to see the Panhellenic League dissolved, but because it wants to warn the various chapters and societies which are part of the League that great sums of money disappear or are spent foolishly while the League is making no headway. We think that it is our duty to protect the interests of the hardworking laborers who do not know what is going on in the inner councils of the League. It is only fair to ask that our money be spent for the urgent <pb facs="5422062_4_1413.jpg" n="6"/>defense and reorganization needs of our country.</p>
   <p>"If the leaders of the League are unable to work effectively for national and patriotic policies they should have sense enough to resign immediately.</p>
   <p>From the office of The Lyre of Regas Fereos</p>
   <p>Alexander Kaldelis James Vlettas</p>
   <p>Secretary President."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
