<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1928-03-31">March 31, 1928</date>, p. 3
<title level="a">The Celebration of Our National Holiday.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1592</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1592.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-03-31">March 31, 1928</date>, p. 3
<title level="a">THE CELEBRATION OF OUR NATIONAL HOLIDAY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 25th of March is the national holiday for Greeks the world over, as the 4th of July is the national holiday of our adopted country, and celebrated as such in every part of the globe where Americans live. Our new country became free and independent on the glorious 4th of July, so our Greece on March 25th gained her freedom and independence.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday the Greeks of Chicago and the suburbs celebrated their national holiday in the Ashland Auditorium with solemnity, elegance, and magnificence. Crowds thronged the place of celebration. Old and young, men and women, all came to partake in the national joy. The program of the day was very elaborate and rich, and its disposition was carried out with military precision. Dr. K. Theodorou acted as master of ceremonies.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1593.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The panegyric oration of the day was delivered by Right Rev. Philaretos, bishop of Chicago, who with characteristic eloquence brought out the gravity of the celebration. He was succeeded by Hon. G. Depastas, Chicago Consul-General of Greece, who kept the audience in awe-inspiring attitude with his profound patriotic utterances. His speech printed in full is on another page. But topping all as masterpieces of eloquence were the speeches of the two inspired orators, Andrew Vlachos and G. Kyriakopoulos, attorneys.</p>
   <p>All four speeches combined, made a bouquet of exceptional elegance, beauty and usefulness. The four orators enthused and electrified the crowds.</p>
   <p>Mr. D. Papageorge, with the choir of the church St. Basil, presented wonders upon wonders, he himself singing melodiously the "Gero Demo."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1594.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Miss Catherine Vainikou and Miss Emily Kretikos with musical talent played chosen selections appropriate for the celebration. The song of Democracy and the hymn of the "Nea Genea" were sung by the crowds preceded by the choir. Young girls altered in national costumes danced the Zaloggou dance.</p>
   <p>The American hymn was played at the opening of the ceremony and the Greek anthem at the end. Music, alluring music was supplied by N. Varzos' orchestra.</p>
   <p>The stars and stripes and Greek flags were displayed in every inch of the great Auditorium.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
