<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-20">Oct. 20, 1928</date><title level="a">Greek Aviators Seen Aid of Greeks America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-20">Oct. 20, 1928</date><title level="a">GREEK AVIATORS SEEN AID OF GREEKS AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Our fellow national, Mr. Louis Choromokos, who is very well known in our community, has received a letter from the aviator of the Greek army, Mr. Zacharias Sakellariou, in which the intention of the latter and also that of Mr. Alec Papatsoris is announced to the effect that they will undertake to fly from Greece to America.</p>
   <p>The Greek aviators convey to Mr. Choromokos an appeal, which we gladly publish, urging our countrymen to take it into consideration and provide the brave aviators with means to accomplish the aerial voyage that will contribute great honor to the Greeks of America.</p>
   <p>To The Greeks Of America.</p>
   <p>Many a time have our fellow nationals, in America, hastened to relieve our suffering country in every possible corner. Therefore, we know that they will not only give aid in this task of ours, but that they will hasten to contribute with great eagerness, proving themselves to be true sons of our glorious ancestors and our beloved country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0284.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not lacking in courage, self-sacrifice and ability, we are appealing to you after so many achievements by the Americans, Lindberg, and Chamberlain, the tour of the world by the Frenchmen, and other feats, to contribute cash for the purchase of an airplane, which we shall choose and in which we shall cross the distance from Athens to New York, via Africa, visiting all Greek communities.</p>
   <p>This aerial trip, the accomplishment of which would belong not to us, but to all the Greeks, will prove that we are true sons of our ancestors and of Daedalus and Icarus themselves.</p>
   <p>Please accept with enthusiasm and pride, this appeal of ours and hasten the collection of funds by intrusting a recognized society, or a committee, coming to an understanding with us on the project. We wish to prepare ourselves for the task by the first months of the coming year.</p>
   <p>Hoping that you will support us eagerly in this effort of ours, we, etc.</p>
   <p>Z. Sakellariou</p>
   <p>Adjutant of Aviation,</p>
   <p>A. Papatsoris</p>
   <p>Sub-Lieutenant of Aviation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
