<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-03-16">Mar. 16, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Sanctioned Murder</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0736</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0736.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-03-16">Mar. 16, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SANCTIONED MURDER</title><title level="a" type="sub">by G. Halepas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A small, ten-year-old girl died recently as a result of having been run over by an automobile. This tragic incident occurred before my eyes a few days ago.</p>
   <p>As always in such cases, a large number of curious onlookers gathered at the scene of the accident. One close by me turned and asked his neighbor what had happened. His reply was: "Nothing much. A little girl was just killed by that car." Soon the crowd dispersed, calmly and cheerfully--just as if a human life were the cheapest thing in the world.</p>
   <p>Of course, we all know that such things happen many times each day, and people are becoming accustomed to this type of murder. During the first month of 1933, over a hundred deaths resulted from auto accidents in Cook County. This is the price we pay for our mechanical progress.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0737.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"For what we gain in life, we have to pay the price," is well known to all of us. In the case of auto accidents, however, the price need not be so very high. If the Federal Government should take the preventive measures that are logical, humane, and timely, the lives of its citizens would not be in such peril. Laws could be made and enforced which would prevent certain people from driving cars. In other words, cars are not mules to be driven by anyone who wants to.</p>
   <p>Under existing conditions, how is it possible to avert tragedies?.....The solution consists in enacting laws forbidding a person to drive until he had passed a thorough examination. So many lives would not be sacrificed, and the price we pay for technical progress would not be so high. I do not mean that progress is to blame and that we should return to horse-and-buggy days.....But progress need not be so destructive of human life. The solution is simple: proper laws, and stringent medical examinations for would-be drivers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
