<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-12-06">Dec. 6, 1934</date><title level="a">Glory of Greek History Lives Again at Ball</title><title level="a" type="sub">Enormous Crowd Attends Colorful Affair in all Nations Series by Dempter Mac Murphy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-12-06">Dec. 6, 1934</date><title level="a">GLORY OF GREEK HISTORY LIVES AGAIN AT BALL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Enormous Crowd Attends Colorful Affair in all Nations Series By Dempter Mac Murphy</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greece, that cradle of civilization that wielded a greater influence over the course of history than any other nation, found all her glory and her greatness echoed last night at the Aragon Ballroom. There Chicago's Greek-Americans gathered for their charity in the Carnival of Nations. It was a ball to be remembered.</p>
   <p>Greeks were first to show the world what real civilization was and civilization in its most comprehensive meaning flowered at this festival.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0165.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Beautiful girls, beautiful music, beautiful entertainment, a beautiful setting--and with it, all the charm and grace and culture of a people who have understood all there was to understand about art and science and literature and politics for 3,000 years.</p>
   <p>More than 4,000 had arrived at midnight, and they were still coming. Everyone enjoyed the occasion, even Paul Demos, the chairman. The Greek and American National anthems introduced the entertainment program at 11 o'clock and Mr. Demos greeted the Greek committee's guests. Then Nickolas A. Christy took over the job of master of ceremonies, and while what he said was all Greek to everyone, it was an all-Greek audience who could understand it.</p>
   <p>Dance Team First Star Act</p>
   <p>The first stars introduced were Mario and Floria, the handsome young dance team from Chez Paree. Mario, an Athenian, was given reception, and he and his lovely partner responded with two enchanting and spectacular dances.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0166.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Bertha Floros then sang, winning a well-dressed ovation, and Elias Nickoletseas and Athena Boussios led a group in the Greek national dance. Young Mr. Nickoletseas, a cute little devil in his Greek constume has all the poise and assurance of seasoned professional.</p>
   <p>A high moment in the dances came with the dances of Miss Demetra Argyris and Miss Agle Argyris. Framed by a semi-circle of maidens in Greek costumes, the former interpreted "Anoixis" ("Spring") and the later "Theros"--which is summer.</p>
   <p>Mark Mamalakis led a Cretan dance of men and maids from Crete, and it was both amusing and delightful.</p>
   <p>Committee Sells Flowers</p>
   <p>Mr. Demos had scores of exquisite young women, worked hard for weeks, to put the Greek ball over in a big way, and they worked right up until the last patron entered the ballroom. You couldn't get by them without <pb facs="5422062_4_0167.jpg" n="4"/>buying a flower, and in this and other ways a large sum was made available for Greek charity. Each one of those girls deserves a column of credits; but they will get the credit that really counts and that is the credit that comes from the hearts of the unfortunates of their own nationality whom their efforts will aid through the winter.</p>
   <p>(Chicago Daily News)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
