<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1921-02-12">Feb. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Mission of the Liberal Political Leagues</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-02-12">Feb. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE MISSION OF THE LIBERAL POLITICAL LEAGUES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The enemies of democracy and political liberalism among the Greek people of America, particularly of Chicago, say that a pronounced and intensive activity in organizing and establishing the Liberal Greek political clubs or leagues is unnecessary and a lost and fruitless effort. They maintain that the re-establishment and restoration of monarchy and Royalist party control in Greece after the decisive elections of November 1, 1920 are a sufficient guarantee for a wise, efficient, and constructive administration of the affairs of the Greek government and people. Therefore, they contend that the opposition can be of little service to the national interests, especially in view of the fact that the Liberal party was discredited and renounced by the Greek people in the recent elections.</p>
   <p>All intelligent and sober-minded Greeks, who are not swayed by emotional appeals and sinister propaganda, who do not allow their passions and <pb facs="5422062_4_1335.jpg" n="2"/>political and partisan hatreds and jealousies to control their every thought and action, deeply regret the exploitation of the ignorance and passions of the masses of the Greek people. The Greek people were misled, misguided, cheated, and bullied by false promises, by empty and meaningless outbursts of emotional and political oratory. In this manner, the great accomplishments of the Liberal party from 1917 - 1920 were belittled, misinterpreted, and ridiculed by those same people whose policies and actions brought Greece to the brink of destruction and civil war. The royal house of Greece, the royalist parties and officials dared, and still dare, to scorn, abuse, and denounce Britain and France, the great powers of Europe. These powers created, protected, and supported Greece. Our independence, in large measure, is due to them; our political and economic power and organization are their contributions to a free, self-respecting, prosperous young Greek nation. Shall we be branded with the opprobrium of ingratitude? Shall we forget and forsake our benefactors? Are we in a position to invite the wrath and incur the hostility of the powerful peoples and governments who are masters of the destinies of the world? Can a small nation, such as ours, continue to exist and prosper without <pb facs="5422062_4_1336.jpg" n="3"/>the friendship, sympathy, protection, and support of the earth's great powers? We say that it cannot.</p>
   <p>Mr. Venizelos and his Liberal party have had, and continue to have, an historically tested and justified confidence in the support of the Allied powers. The Allies have never failed us, but they cannot tolerate a king and a party [King Constantine and the Royalist party] that supported the Central powers during the World War. The active support offered Germany and Bulgaria by the King's government, almost throughout the entire duration of the European war, has not been forgotten by England and France. Is there any wonder why these powers refuse to recognize the present king and government of Greece? Do we wonder why the promised loans are refused; why our foreign relations are pitifully unsuccessful; why our orders and credits for war materials are withheld? Retribution is coming fast for misleading the people, for failure to fulfill sacred promises, such as military demobilization, for ignoring and disregarding the all-important sympathetic attitude and assistance of England and France. Can the Greek people and army endure the strain and hardships or a continued war against <pb facs="5422062_4_1337.jpg" n="4"/>Turkey in Asia Minor without any friends, without material and financial resources? Was not the people promised that the war will be brought to an end by peaceful settlement? We now see the present government's bad faith, dishonor, stupidity, and cowardice; we are already witnessing the moral and political incompetence of a political gang leading the unsuspecting and trusting people to certain catastrophe, to national annihilation and destruction.</p>
   <p>Shall we, the Greek people of Chicago and America, remain indifferent and apathetic in the face of national destruction, defeat, and corruption? We are ready to defend and preserve the existence and greatness of our homeland. The Greek Liberal leagues have the patriotic duty and the historic mission to educate, enlighten, guide, and save the Greek people. The patriotism and loyalty of the Greeks of Chicago, and America in general, will not fail.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
