<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-11-24">Nov. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Cretan Brotherhood of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-11-24">Nov. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CRETAN BROTHERHOOD OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the fact that the Cretan Brotherhood is a comparatively new organization, its list of patriotic, philanthropic and national accomplishments is very long. This organization works silently--without the usual ballyhoo that, unfortunately, is characteristic of most Greek societies--and it lives up to its purposes and ambitions.</p>
   <p>There are Greek clubs all over America which are either national or local in their relationship to the homeland [Translator's note: meaning that either they are composed of any Greek who wishes to join--or are composed of Greeks, from a certain locality in Greece, as, in this case, the Cretans]; these groups are supported, not only by their respective members, but by all the Greeks in the community. These organizations are not only interested in their own members, but they are ever ready to support any movement that will help the Greeks, not only in America, but in Greece as well.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0058.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Cretan Brotherhood, in the face of terrific handicaps, due to the unsettled conditions of this country, has accomplished more than was thought possible. During the past year, it has paid for the hospitalization of two of its members, for many funerals of deceased members, and has contributed over eight hundred dollars for various philanthropic purposes. The Club subscribed three hundred dollars to the Liberty Loan drive, to which all the Greeks in America should subscribe, because by doing so they not only prove their patriotism and their support of their adopted land, but they also help their homeland.</p>
   <p>Twenty members of the Brotherhood are soldiers in the United States Army. They have sworn to uphold the American flag and they hope to bring honor to the Cretans and the mother country.</p>
   <p>During the general meeting the following men were elected to office: John Volikos, president; P. Kaloedas, vice-president; and.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0059.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Brotherhood and its new officers appeal to all the Greeks in America to join the Cretan Brotherhood of Chicago. It is their duty to do so, as the Greeks will benefit by a closer unity and a more brotherly feeling. It is a patriotic duty to the homeland, because the Cretans have formed centers at which meetings are held and discussions concerning the political situation in Greece are heard. Among the aims of the organization, is the liberation of Greece from her enemy, the Mussulman Turk.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
