<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-08-03">Aug. 3, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Must We Remain Greeks?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0963</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0963.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-08-03">Aug. 3, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">MUST WE REMAIN GREEKS?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our previous article we discussed the question of the adherence of Greeks to their mores, saying that it is not a question of pure sentimentalism but of pure interest, and from that viewpoint, we think, we must consider things in the present age and in this country especially in which we live.</p>
   <p>Perhaps such an investigation is something unusual and may be considered profane and offensive toward everything looked upon as sacred and holy to this day, inasmuch as it is known that "Of father and mother and all other ancestors, most honorable is one's country(native land) and most venerable and holy to gods and to men of judgment."</p>
   <p>But let the ultra-idealists and the Platonists allow us to say to them that the idealistic interpretation of things belongs to a past epoch, when humanity was yet in its adolescence, and the simplest ideas had to be interpreted symbolically to have their divine origin, and to be presented to men by revelation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0964.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>People of to-day, however, having reached manhood and having become too practical to limit themselves to philosophical utterances and symbolic presentations, want things to be simple and comprehensible, so that they shall know at least what are the advantages of each thing for which they undergo material losses, such as the question of nationalism and fatherland.</p>
   <p>Such an investigation is imposed upon newcomers from the fatherland, who, having settled far away from it, find themselves unfortunately in the midst of a foreign environment and have before them every day the problem of choosing between their native land and that in which they live.</p>
   <p>And so far as those who were born in Greece and have come to America in mature age are concerned, the question of adherence to the Greek mores is apparently solved in advance, for habits and customs, traditions and language are so firmly interwoven with our existence that even if we wanted to force ourselves to reject our Hellenism, it would be impossible. And even if one made a supreme effort to deny himself all contact and relationship with his Greek countrymen and really believed that he had <pb facs="5422062_4_0965.jpg" n="3"/>ceased to be a Greek, he would meet with the greatest disappointment of his life, for while he would believe that he was no longer a Greek, all Americans would know him as a Greek and would call him so.</p>
   <p>What does it profit him then to seek to change his nationality and his ego in defiance of every natural law?</p>
   <p>But even the Greek who because of his culture has had the opportunity to come into closer contact with the refined class of Americans will never succeed in concealing his Grecian descent because nobody can disguise himself. Why, even his own interest demands that he shall openly admit his Grecian nationality because the American people habitually appreciates everything Greek, and particularly at the present time every one ought to be proud of being a Greek.</p>
   <p>Here we desire to state that we must not confuse the question of American naturalization with the rejection of nationality, for naturalization means participation in the politics of the country, and it is important for every one who lives in a country and is taxed to take an interest in its <pb facs="5422062_4_0966.jpg" n="4"/>political life. Therefore it is the duty of all the Greeks of America, by acquiring the rights of American citizens, to demonstrate their active interest in the country in which they live.</p>
   <p>..... Naturalization is a matter of our own free will; nationality is a matter of birth and inheritance, of necessity, outside our own free will.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
