<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-01-01">Jan. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Philanthropy in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Few Illuminating comparisons between the Philanthropic interests of the Greeks and the other Foreign Groups of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-01-01">Jan. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">PHILANTHROPY IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Few Illuminating comparisons between the Philanthropic interests of the Greeks and the other Foreign Groups of Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large printing concern in Chicago has recently published a small volume in which are listed all the philanthropic causes contributed to in the last year. It gives details of who or what organization gave money, or performed deeds of kindness for the sick and poor of Chicago. It lists the actions of the various churches, creeds and nationalities, in relation to schools, hospitals, orphanages, homes for the aged, etc.</p>
   <p>We were ashamed to discover that there was not even one Greek person, club, or church listed in that book. We, at least, expected to see the name of one Greek Orthodox Church; or the name "Greek Womens Philanthropic Club," because the ladies are always proclaiming the philanthropic acts of their organization.</p>
   <p>However, the Greek ladies take the money supposed to be used for aiding the <pb facs="5422062_4_0499.jpg" n="2"/>needy, and put it in the bank to collect interest.....And let the poor starve!</p>
   <p>Have the ladies of Chicago or New York ever realized, that there are hundreds of Greeks in the city hospitals and institutions? Have they never considered how much they could ease the burden of these poor unfortunates by bringing them a few bright flowers or a box of candy? Which the ladies could easily get from a score of Greek merchants.</p>
   <p>We do not intend to preach or to moralize. Each individual has his own conscience, which should make him aware of his duty to his less fortunate fellow men.</p>
   <p>It is our duty, however, as editors of a newspaper, to bring certain facts to the attention of our priests, our church boards and the Greek men and women of Chicago, concerning the following colossal philanthropic achievements, of other nationalities:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0500.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During 1915, the Jews of Chicago, alone, contributed over one million, eight hundred thousand dollars to schools, orphans, asylums.</p>
   <p>And while all the religious groups, and all the national groups had made large contributions to worthy philanthropic causes; the Greek churches, and the Greek nationality made none whatever. We, the great philanthropists, gave nothing at all. Should we, or should we not, hide our heads in shame?</p>
   <p>It is not sufficient that we should be ashamed. It should be a severe object lesson to all of us. First of all, the priests and the church boards must make sincere efforts to reorganize the philanthropic organizations within the church; in order that they might become organizations whose actual purpose would be philanthropy. Now they are merely empty titles attached to clubs devoted to the social pleasures of their members.</p>
   <p>We realize that the Greeks of Chicago can never raise two million dollars, as did the Jews of Chicago; but we can, at least, do as much as the Danes <pb facs="5422062_4_0501.jpg" n="4"/>or Norwegians. "He who gives to the poor gives unto me."</p>
   <p>We have many needy Greek families in Chicago, and we are wondering, whether or not the Greek organizations are going to answer their appeal for help.</p>
   <p>What are the philanthropic tendencies of the Greeks of Chicago?</p>
   <p>We wait to see; do not disappoint us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
