<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-08-25">Aug. 25, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Ninth Annual Convention of Ahepa.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1820</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1820.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-08-25">Aug. 25, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE NINTH ANNUAL CONVENTION OF AHEPA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.. Yesterday the ninth annual convention of the Order of Ahepa held its opening session. This year the convention has met in the city of San Francisco. Regardless of the purpose of the organization (if it has a purpose) we should not forget that among the members of Ahepa are thousands who cherish a noble ambition to make their organization a source of great benefit to the Greeks in America.</p>
   <p>We have never criticized the worthy desires and ambitions of the members of the Order of Ahepa, but we have consistently expressed in these columns our well founded doubts to judge by the purpose for which the order was established that it can ever be beneficial to Hellenism of America or serve it in any way to realize the high ideals of some of its members.</p>
   <p>In order to be effective Ahepa must systematize its annual conventions so that they may produce beneficial results and be an asset to the organization and to its members. It is unfortunate, however, that to judge by the manner in which these conventions are conducted, they can prove of no value and cannot contribute to the improvement of the organization. The delegates to the <pb facs="5422062_4_1821.jpg" n="2"/>conventions do enjoy, however, the benefit of delightful entertainment and recreation.</p>
   <p>Almost the entire time of the conventions is spent in the formation of schemes and cliques for the election for the various officers of the Order and in campaigning to muster votes for candidates for the coveted supreme offices.</p>
   <p>In spite of all this, however, we cannot deny that the conventions reflect a vital Greek movement and reveal the strength of Hellenism in America, although this vitality is here manifested in the form of entertainment. From this point of view we wish to salute the ninth annual convention of the Order of Ahepa, and may it live to be a hundred!</p>
   <p>The Contradictor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
