<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Year Book of St. Constantine Church and Korais School</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 47.
<title level="a">Perpetuation of Our National Idealism</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0819</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0819.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Yearbook of St. Constantine Church and Korais School</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 47.
<title level="a">PERPETUATION OF OUR NATIONAL IDEALISM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Without the slightest doubt, either a layman or a clergyman can see with the naked eye the trend of the eradication of our national idealism. The power of religion first and the power of the Church second will serve as the only saviors of our nationalism.</p>
   <p>My assertion that these are the powers which will save us from extinction is not based upon illusions, hypothetical theories, and blind devotion to partisan advocacy, but it is based upon undisputable and demonstrated facts. Only the Church and the school can save us from the following conditions which would bring about the extinction of our Nationalism.</p>
   <p>The barring of immigration, mixed marriages, the lack of churches in small towns, the lack of adequate schools in big cities, the division of the Greeks here and in Greece into two fanatical political factions, the ever increasing complaints against the Church and the nation, the utter liberty extended to us in this country, the so-called cosmopolitans, the Students of the Bible, Communism, divorces, the inclination to slander and underestimate the administrators of the affairs of the church, and the power of environment <!-- 5422062_4_0818 omitted, duplicate of 5422062_4_0819 --></p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0820.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>are potent factors tending to bring about the destruction of our Nationalism. They are the ferocious enemies which tend little by little; to entirely annihilate every sign of Greek Nationalism.</p>
   <p>The power of religion and the power of our Orthodox Church, I reiterate, is the only hope we have of being saved from extinction. In order to verify my assertion, I will invoke historical data and verities of past and present history.</p>
   <p>During the subjugation of the Greeks in the duration of four centuries, by the barbaric hords of Mohamet, the power of our religion was the only factor that kept Greek Nationalism blooming. The Greek tongue was prohibited to be spoken and the Penalty for breaking the law of the Turks was to cut off the tongue of those who dared to disobey the barbaric law. The Greeks by necessity adopted the Turkish tongue as Mother tongue but they maintained secretly the services of the church even though the gospel was read in Turkish. The power of religion kept the Greeks from becoming Turks. Greek liberty and their language was lost, but the enslaved remained Greeks only and only by the power of the Church even though everyone suffered unbelievable tortures.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0821.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greek Turks of Crete, who lost their religion but maintained their tongue, on the contrary, became the ferocious persecutors of Christendom. The loss of their religion, made them rapacious beasts and they knew they were Greek decendants but they were nourished by the religion of Mohamet.</p>
   <p>What is that power now that makes the Students of the Bible and Franolevantines to hate and abhore anything Greek even though their mother language is Greek? It is the loss of the Orthodox religion. What is the power that keeps together the Jews the world over, as a race, the Jews who are persecuted and expelled everywhere? What is the power that keeps the Jews together even though they have lost their mother tongue, which is now only known by the Rabbis. It is the power of their religion; their devotion to their religious services which were and are rooted very deep in their heart and implanted there from generation to generation. The Jews the world over, I must say, are to be commended for perpetuating their race inspite of the extra-ordinary persecutions against them. The power of religion saved the Jews from extinction.</p>
   <p>What power made Spain, Mexico, France and Germany afraid to publicly proclaim their hostility against the Church openly? It was the fear of the Catholic Church, a powerful institution that works smoothly peacefully and harmoniously for the betterment of society.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0822.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>These are facts beyond any reasonable doubt, which ought to convince all those who for any reason are inimically inclined towards religion, that the power of religion is the only power to save and maintain Nationalism, language and the unity of the race.</p>
   <p>The Greek Church in America was established without a reigning head for some time, and without system. The Greek Church in America was organized in haste in order to serve the needs of the divided Greek population, nevertheless, it was the only power to bring back the waiting arms of religion those who for any cause became estranged or separated.</p>
   <p>The many Greek Societies, who for some time were separated kingdoms fighting one another for preponderance, today are united under one roof, the Church, although they maintain their individual entity.</p>
   <p>My dear children, in epitimizing, the only way to perpetuate our language and Greek Nationalism, is through the power of religion and our Church.</p>
   <p>Rev. Marcos E. Petrakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
