<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1931-10-30">Oct. 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks to Give First Carnival of Gala Series</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Robert Andrews</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1931-10-30">Oct. 30, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS TO GIVE FIRST CARNIVAL OF GALA SERIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">BY ROBERT ANDREWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 65,000 Greek-Americans in Chicago have taken first place among all the national groups co-operating in Chicago's greatest carnival of nations.</p>
   <p>Announcing not only a complete organization, but a complete program of many features, Paul Demos, representing Greek-Americans on the Civic Carnival Committee.,said, "We'll put on the biggest and best show you ever saw, and we promise something for everybody - thanks to the splendid co-operation we have received from all our people."</p>
   <p>This eager co-operation showed results in the action of Andrew Karzas, who came to Chicago from Greece twenty-five years ago and has built up his fortune as a citizen of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0199.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Karzas donated is huge Aragon Ballroom, at Broadway and Lawrence Avenue for the Greek-American carnival, and at the same time gave the services of two famous orchestras, those headed by Wayne King and Ted Weems.</p>
   <p>The Greek-American program will be given the night of Nov. 2, at the Aragon Ballroom, with Wayne King and Ted Weems orchestras, plus choruses of Greek dancers in traditional native costumes, many singers, many other special features, all on the same program - a program beginning at 8 P.M. and continuing until 12:30 A.M. There will be room for more than 5000 to see and take part in the carnival.</p>
   <p>Dancing to the two big orchestras merged as one, entertainment specialties, introducing the finest Greek-American artists in Chicago; a full four hour show "with something doing every minute" - these will be the contributions of Chicago's Greek-Americans to the great city-wide carnival.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0200.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Going even further in giving magnanimous support to the movement, Mr. Kargas agreed to print the tickets for the big carnival absolutely without expenses to the committee and to assume all other expenses incidental to producing the Greek-American show - so that every cent received for tickets will go direct to the Joint Emergency Relief Fund, for whose benefit the Daily News suggested the international carnival.</p>
   <p>"Tickets will sell for 75 cents, according to Mr. Demos,"and we guarantee more entertainment, more picturesque features, more color than you ever saw in any other show in Chicago," he said.</p>
   <p>Call Idea Splendid</p>
   <p>"Yours was a splendid idea, to create an opportunity for every one to assemble and assist in this great movement for relief," Mr. Karzas told the Daily News.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0201.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"I am truly grateful that I am able to contribute my share by presenting my ballroom and the music of my orchestras. I am confident that this entertainment, along with the other big programs you are arranging and the vast publicity and promotion behind it all, should attract a tremendous patronage and add greatly to the Joint Relief Fund."</p>
   <p>The committee includes; Mr. Demos, chairman; Mr. Karzas, and John Raklios, who said "Chicago has been kind to me. I welcome the opportunity to do what I can to repay some of the citizens who have helped me so much." C. N. Johnson, who said, "You can count on me and my organization for every assistance."</p>
   <p>(Chicago Daily News)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
