<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>American Hellenic World</title>,
<date when="1928-06">June, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Legion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The American Hellenic World</title>,
<date when="1928-06">June, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE LEGION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 9.- Hellenic Post, No. 343, of the American Legion has inaugurated still another movement, and hopes to establish one of the best women's auxiliaries in the country. So far the results, according to the Commander, Hercules Malapanes, and his able adjutant, D. Delevois, have been highly satisfactory. The idea of a women's auxiliary to the Post is not new, but it remained for the present administration to put it into effect, an initiative for which they should be congratulated. Perhaps very few of us can realize the importance of such a branch, and still fewer of us comprehend the whole significance of the Hellenic Post itself.</p>
   <p>Those who have lived in America long recall easily the love and the sympathy which surrounded the veterans of the Civil War when their lines were not so thinned. Today, of course, the few remaining are held in the highest esteem by the people of the United States and not without reason. Theirs is the privilege which no individual, however lofty his station in life, can acquire. The same thing is true, and will continue to be true, with the American Legion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0288.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Future generations will always pay their respects to the men and the women who offered their all on the altar of patriotism. This respect will be intensified and promoted by the united efforts of the veterans themselves. For the more they are united, the more they will benefit themselves and the country.</p>
   <p>To us the Greeks, the existence of the Hellenic Post, is therefore of the highest importance. In the future the American people will judge us to a degree by the strength of our veterans, that is by those who fought for this country, when she was in need. But the true meaning of our contribution will be lost unless the veterans are united. And the only way to be united is through the Hellenic Post of Chicago, which is one of the oldest posts in the country, and one with a very commendable record.</p>
   <p>The present administration is doing everything in its power to promote the interests of this Post, but in this it needs the cooperation of all the ex-service men who happen to reside within the confines of this city, and whose number, if we are not mistaken, mounts to thousands. For this <pb facs="5422062_4_0289.jpg" n="3"/>reason we will urge everybody who is an ex-service man to get immediately in touch with the proper authorities, that he may become a member of the Hellenic Post.</p>
   <p>An example of the service which this Post is rendering to the community is its activities around Memorial Day. Prior to May 30th, collections are in order throughout the United States on what are usually known as "poppy" days. This money is used for the benefit of the injured ex-service men, who are today in government hospitals in and around Chicago. Unfortunately, very few Greek public agencies, be they societies or communities, ever remember to visit these unfortunate men.</p>
   <p>The Hellenic Post, however, has always been on the job, more today than ever before. For this reason on "poppy" day the Post considered it advisable to appeal to the generosity of the people of Chicago along with the other Posts of the city, and with this in mind it appealed to the Greek ladies, especially the young ones, to help on the day of collection.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0290.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Unfortunately, very few of our representatives of the fair sex considered it within their dignity to carry a collection box around some busy corner on "poppy" day. The Chicago society girls who filled the loop to offer their services that day were no example for our proud and haughty beauties. We trust that in the future better counsel will prevail, and that the Greek mothers and fathers will encourage their daughters to serve more willingly on such occasions.</p>
   <p>Practically all the Greek restaurants in the loop, with the exception of two, allowed boxes of the Hellenic Post to be placed on their counters that day. And the sum that was taken in from all sources was considerable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
