<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1930-10-17">Oct. 17, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Would Give 10,000 Meais a Day to Jobless</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0246</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0246.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1930-10-17">Oct. 17, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">WOULD GIVE 10,000 MEAIS A DAY TO JOBLESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Restaurant men ask colleagues each to feed 10.</p>
   <p>Moved by the Daily Times story and pictures of unemployed sleeping on the lower level of Michigan Avenue, Dan Chirigos and his nephew Nick Markes, owners of the Sheridan restaurant, 3946 Sheridan Road, have a plan to relieve suffering this winter.</p>
   <p>"It's really Dan's idea,"said Markos. "It is this. If all successful restaurants in Chicago agreed to feed 10 worthy, homeless men a day, think of what good could be done. There are at least 1,000 successful restaurants in this city. Ten thousand meals would go a long way."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0247.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The problem would be to distinguish the worthy from the unworthy. That would be too much for the restaurant owners to check. They would need co-operation from some charity organization. The men could apply there for carfare and for tickets that would entitle them to, say 10 meals at a certain eating place. It would be up to the charity organization to choose deserving persons and reject those who would be bums under any circumstances.</p>
   <p>Have Special Hours</p>
   <p>"I don't know how other restauranteurs would feel about this, but I know that we are perfectly willing to go ahead, as soon as we are assured the co-operation of others. A definite time each day would have to be designated for those unfortunates, depending upon the convenience of the restaurant and its rush periods. Naturally it would not do to harm the regular trade. But, say, a time like 2 P. M. daily might be very satisfactory."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0248.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The charity organizations, I'm sure, would be glad to help. A restaurant that is well off can easily afford to do this. The loss would never be felt -the money involved might very well be eliminated from some other phase of the business."</p>
   <p>Can't Turn Them Down</p>
   <p>"I've been through some hardships myself - having served overseas in the army during the war - and I sympathize with hungry men. The poor fellows come in all the time, asking for food. I can't turn them down."</p>
   <p>"We never realized though, that so many men were homeless and hungry until we saw the pictures in the Daily Times, and read the story."</p>
   <p>Chirigos will suggest the plan at the next meeting of the American Restaurant Assn.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0249.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The building at 519 N. Union St., donated to the Salvation Army by Wrigley Jr., as a winter refuge for the homeless and jobless, has been opened.</p>
   <p>Soon Ready for 2,000</p>
   <p>"We are now taking care of 200 men," said Col. A. T. Brewstar of the Salyation Army, "and most of these men are aiding us in making the building ready for more. Within two weeks we expect to be able to house and feed about 2,000. Right now we are having plumbing installed and we are making arrangements for the necessary cots."</p>
   <p>(Chicago Daily Times, Oct. 14, 1930)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
