<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1929-02">February, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Ahepa as a National Organization of the Future</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1894</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1894.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1929-02">February, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE AHEPA AS A NATIONAL ORGANIZATION OF THE FUTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently the installation of the officers of eight chapters of Ahepa took place at the Trianon. No words can express or describe what a gala evening it was. Thousands attended.</p>
   <p>February 18th was the day on which the officers of the eight Chicago chapters of Ahepa were installed with great pomp and ceremony. The Trianon Ballroom owned by A. Karzas, B. Karzas and N. Nomikos was the scene of the great affair. At 8:30 exactly the ceremonies began. D. Alfange, Supreme President of the Order of Ahepa, was guest of honor.</p>
   <p>Chairman of the affair was D. Parry, lawyer, past-president of Chapter 46 and at present, president of the Falanthos society. As the Greek and American flags were brought in, the orchestra of the Varzos brothers played the Greek and American national anthem.</p>
   <p>A. Kollias was toastmaster of the evening and a very good one at that. P. Sikokis, Supreme Governor of the 8th District was the main speaker.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1895.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Supreme President D. Alfange depicted a brilliant future for Ahepa and described it as a future national organization.</p>
   <p>Other honored guests were A. Petrellin, George Peterson, Parascho Volo, D. E. Zaph, A. George N. Spannon, the Sons of Pericles and the presidents of twenty Ahepan chapters in Illinois, Wisconsin, Iowa, Minnesota, Indiana, Michigan, Missouri and Ohio.</p>
   <p>The eight Chicago chapters of Ahepa are:</p>
   <p>Chicago Chapter No. 46</p>
   <p>Woodlawn Chapter No. 93</p>
   <p>North Shore Chapter No. 94</p>
   <p>Oak Park Chapter No. 104</p>
   <p>Hellenic Center No. 202</p>
   <p>Garfield Chapter No. 203</p>
   <p>Evanston Chapter No. 204</p>
   <p>Pullman Chapter No. 205.</p>
   <p>Dancing followed the ceremonies and the great day came to an end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
