<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-02-19">Feb. 19, 1930</date><title level="a">My Inpressions of the North Side Dance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0260</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0260.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-02-19">Feb. 19, 1930</date><title level="a">MY INPRESSIONS OF THE NORTH SIDE DANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I attended a philanthropical dance last Friday given by the Liberal Arts club of Young Ladies to refill their treasury for the benefit of the poor. The Greek people of Chicago showed their appreciation of this action by attending. The crowds looked like a huge garden, the women representing beautiful flowers and the men dark leaves. The beautiful Medinah Athletic Club was a perfect setting for these gorgeous ladies. They were all magnificently dressed and groomed in the latest styles, and proved what we have asserted time and time again. As a race, there are no women nore beautiful than the Greeks. Not only that, they know the intricacies of the modern American dance well and have acquired a culture which leaves me speechless. The young ladies on the reception committee were wearing corsages of gardenias and graciously receiving their guests. They all had worked hard to make this evening a success and their efforts were rewarded. It would take columns to name all the people who attended, but a few can be mentioned.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0261.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the intermission we saw the Greek General Consul and Mrs. Depastas, Ass't Consul and Mrs. Tsopas, Rev. and Mrs. Marcus Petrakis, Rev. &amp; Mrs. Kesses, and Archrev. E. Tsourounakis.</p>
   <p>The dance ended at one o'clock. Everybody congratulated the young ladies for giving them a good time. As I was leaving, I was struck with the thought that we need have nothing to fear. We may expect much, and we shall receive much from the future Greek mothers of America.</p>
   <p>IFI TAKAGRA KOPADIS</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
