<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-12-21">Dec. 21, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Danger to Greek Confectioneries</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0740</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0740.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-12-21">Dec. 21, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANGER TO GREEK CONFECTIONERIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last week the Examiner directed a caustic attack against confectioneries conducted by foreigners as centers of corruption for girls of minor age.</p>
   <p>While it is true that it did not refer to Greek confectioneries, they are included among foreign-owned stores, and consequently the accusation that the confectioneries are centers of corruption is very harmful to the interests of Greek merchants.</p>
   <p>Greek confectioners, who are numbered by the thousands in Chicago, ought to maintain their dignity and not permit these accusations to go unchallenged, for the Examiner's way of presenting this matter is slander with intent to bring into disrepute thousands of Greek business establishments in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The denunciation of such an attack cannot be made single-handed and offhand.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0741.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The slander was directed against all foreign confectioneries and consequently against those owned by Greeks, and the denunciation of the attack ought to be made by the Greek confectioners combined....</p>
   <p>But how is it possible for them to defend their dignity when so large an industry remains unorganized?</p>
   <p>Once before, several years ago, we remember that similar accusations were printed against Greek confectioneries, and their owners organized and took up their defense against the slanderous accusations, but that association was kept up for a few years and then unfortunately, as is usually the case, was dissolved, and to-day it no longer exists.</p>
   <p>.....If the confectioners let their business go undefended now, who can guarantee that new accusations will not be brought against them tomorrow, so creating a prejudice against Greek enterprises which will greatly injure Greek interests in Chicago and all over the United States wherever Greek candy stores exist?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0742.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We consider it our duty to sound the alarm, and we urge the confectioners to organize as soon as possible, for only when they are organized can they defend their interests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
