<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1928-08">July - Aug., 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Order of Ahepa and the Detroit Convocation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1897</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1897.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1928-08">July - Aug., 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE ORDER OF AHEPA AND THE DETROIT CONVOCATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great national Order of Ahepa held its sixth convention in Detroit the latter part of August.</p>
   <p>The City of Detroit was decorated with the national colors of America and Greece and for a whole week the colors of Ahepa were hoisted on top of the Book-Cadillac Hotel, one of the finest hotels in America.</p>
   <p>Thousands of Ahepans and their friends visited the convention, spending an unusual holiday week. During the week's session, a great parade took place at Ypsilanti, Michigan. There over 3,000 people, from all parts of the country, paraded through the streets of Ypsilanti, going there to unveil a beautiful marble statue, made in Greece, honoring the General Demetrios Ypsilanti, brother of Prince Alexander Ypsilanti, who played an important part in the Greek Revolution for the independence of Greece from Turkey in 1823. The city was named at the suggestion of <pb facs="5422062_4_1898.jpg" n="2"/>the then Governor of the State of Michigan, Judge Woodward. The celebration was magnificent and unique. Never in the history of Ypsilanti, since the founding of the city, was such a parade held.</p>
   <p>Ahepa is growing steadily and strongly, having chapters in all but three states of the Union, with thousands of members. It will not be very long until the membership will grow such an extent as to be classes as one of the outstanding national orders of our country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
