<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Two and One-Half Cents</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">TWO AND ONE-HALF CENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All of you remember the promises given by the officials of the Greek-American Bank; the promises of their friends, of their investigating committees, and of the newspapers that so ardently defended the honor and integrity of those frauds. All these worthies swore that the bankers were the souls of honor, and that the depositors' money was safely invested, or loaned to trustworthy individuals who were paying interest on their loans.</p>
   <p>The newspapers proclaimed loudly that the depositors would receive every dollar that belonged to them. This was also the promise of the four bankers and their friends.</p>
   <p>The old proverb says: "The value of the wheat is discovered by the humble flour mill." Therefore, the value of the statements made by the four bankers will be "discovered" in the mill of justice. The first revelation indicating the validity of these promises has already been unearthed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0651.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We regret that we must inform the depositors of the following facts: The entire proceeds derived from the sale of the homes, property, automobiles, and furniture of the four bankers, plus the ninety-six dollars found in the bank, will only be enough to give two and one-half cents to each depositor for each dollar he had on deposit.</p>
   <p>According to the new type of arithmetic practiced by the honest bankers, anyone who had a dollar in the bank will be given two and one-half cents. We presume that they will use a hatchet to cut a penny in half. How unreasonable it would be for anyone to complain about this easy solution to a very unimportant problem!</p>
   <p>Anyone who had ten dollars in the bank, will receive the munificent sum of twenty-five cents, or, in other words, a quarter, or two dimes and a nickel. He may even get five nickels.</p>
   <p>Anyone who had a hundred dollars on deposit will be handed the bountiful <pb facs="5422062_4_0652.jpg" n="3"/>sum of two dollars and fifty cents--in any kind of change he desires.</p>
   <p>The happiest one will be he, who is weight d down with the twenty-five dollars that he will be given in exchange for his thousand dollar investment.</p>
   <p>Now--what are the hypocritical newspapers that denounced the Saloniki as being pessimistic and cynical, going to write in the face of such facts? The struggle has just begun!</p>
   <p>The four bankers are facing severe penalties, and are all under bond, until they are ordered to appear in the Criminal Court. It is there that the poor victims of these cheats and thieves must go, and tell of their suffering and sorrow. All the Greeks who know anything about the past conduct of these four men must testify against them.</p>
   <p>These four rascals, who have devoured the life-savings of hundreds of poor <pb facs="5422062_4_0653.jpg" n="4"/>ignorant people, are enemies of the entire community; because of their dishonesty, a blot has been put upon the Greek community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>As you all know, two of the bankers fled to Greece on the pretext that they were going to sell flour. However, a few days ago, George Douras returned to New York. When he learned of the seizure and arrest of his two partners, he hurriedly secreted himself aboard the Greek ship, "King Constantine". He now believes his whereabouts are unknown and his safety assured.</p>
   <p>What a surprise he will get when he is informed that the arm of the law is at the back of his neck, ready to jerk him back to America, so that he can answer a few questions!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
