<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1921-12-24">Dec. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Election of Officers of Liberal Society of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1320</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1320.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-12-24">Dec. 24, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTION OF OFFICERS OF LIBERAL SOCIETY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, December 18, the election of officers of the Liberal Society was held. It was carried out in a dignified, respectful, and brotherly manner.</p>
   <p>Voting began at 9:00 A.M. and ended at 9:00 P.M. Before a member was given a ballot, the committee in charge examined his record to see if he was still a member in good standing. The candidates for each office had their names printed on the ballot, and a check was to be placed at the side of the candidate's name. The names were.....</p>
   <p>Constantine Paleologos Mammonas was elected president; Dr. C. Theodore was elected vice-president; A. Tsikouris was elected second vice-president; Mr. G. Halepas was elected general secretary; John Raklios, treasurer; D. Dimitriades, corresponding secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1321.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The members of the council are: A. Karagiannis, K. Georgopulos, P. Petropoulos, Paul Demos, and A. Alexopoulos.</p>
   <p>The results of the elections were enthusiastically received by the people who had waited to get the news. After refreshments were served, the people began to call for a speech by the new president.</p>
   <p>Mr. Paleologos stepped forward and made the following speech:</p>
   <p>"My dear brothers:</p>
   <p>I receive your decision with so much emotion and gratitude that it is hard for me to find words with which to thank you."</p>
   <p>"Our organization has as its aim, the betterment of our homeland in the political and educational fields. As your president, it will be my sacred duty to help fulfill these hopes..... There are certain points that we must <pb facs="5422062_4_1322.jpg" n="3"/>strive for in our campaign; they are the following:</p>
   <p>"The education of all of our people in national and political matters.</p>
   <p>"The eradication in our fatherland of all destructive forces and policies.</p>
   <p>"The liberation of Greece from foreign domination.</p>
   <p>"The direction of all resources toward making and securing peace and security, by stabilizing the fatherland from within.</p>
   <p>"In order that these aims may be attained, much sacrifice, both personal and material, must be made. There can be no more sacred sacrifice than one made for the fatherland.</p>
   <p>"I am willing to make this sacrifice and I am sure I have the co-operation of all. I thank you."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
