<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-07-20">July 20, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">One of Our Countrymen Is the Victim of a Robbery.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0622</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0622.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-07-20">July 20, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OF OUR COUNTRYMEN IS THE VICTIM OF A ROBBERY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.3.--A few days ago we published something about the financial strength of our friend Mr. Bas. Karayannes. It appears that robbers took notice of this report and determined to get some of his money. According to his expression, "the thieves know where the money is."</p>
   <p>Mr. Karayannes sent his cashier, Miss Dorothy Constandellou, to make the bank-deposit as usual. While she was walking on the street she was attacked by a robber, who seized the bank-book with the money in it.</p>
   <p>Miss Constandellou screamed and pursued the robber, who ran to a parked automobile. She succeeded in grabbing his coat while he was climbing into the car; then somebody struck her and pushed her down upon the pavement as the car moved forward.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0623.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While the cashier lay screaming on the street, the car passed over her foot, but the little woman did not lose her presence of mind; she shouted, "Get the number! Get the number!" in spite of the pain caused by her fall and by the passage of the wheels over her foot.</p>
   <p>The result was that some persons got the number of the moving automobile, and certain suspects have been arrested, among them a man named Jim Bastou, who appears to be a Greek.</p>
   <p>Such are the unpleasant results of publicity of financial prosperity in certain cases; thieves make use of the information. We beg our friend Mr. Karayannes's pardon for this unpleasant experience and for the maltreatment of his cashier, who so bravely fought the robbers to save her employer's money.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
