<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-03-07">Mar. 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The New Generation Must Lead</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0846</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0846.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-03-07">Mar. 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW GENERATION MUST LEAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many often say in regard to our community and parish affairs that it is time for the older leaders to put the reins of leadership into the hands of the younger generation. Whenever, during a critical period, the situation became intolerable and destruction threatened a nation or a community, the people would turn against its leaders who had led them into such a situation. As a rule, these leaders were the pioneers of the community or nation who had tried to be of service--most of the time beyond their capability.</p>
   <p>There is no denial of the fact that sooner or later the young Greek-Americans will control the future of our communities and organizations. As time goes by and the old vanguard goes on into the night, the young ones will be forced to grasp the reins of leadership....It is, also, the duty of today's leaders to give way gradually to the younger people, so that when the time for their leadership comes they will be better qualified to undertake the entire responsibility alone.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0847.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, we do not believe that these young people should be given control long before they are prepared for the responsibility of it merely because we wish to evade our own duties by placing them on other shoulders.....The condition of our parishes and our community is the direct reaction to the type of leadership which has controlled them. The responsibility can be placed nowhere else. We have created the situation and it is up to us to get out of it. If we were so inefficient that we did not succeed in founding a parish, church, or school worthy of the name, it is not the fault of the younger generation. Therefore, we ask that from now on the younger people be given the chance to take part in our community affairs, so that they will understand the problems that will, in the future, present themselves. According to every social canon, older ones retire and make way for younger people--but not for inexperienced youths.</p>
   <p>So far, the Greek communities of America have youths and not men of the younger Greek generation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0848.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If we give ourselves into the hands of the inexperienced young, there is bound to be great regret.</p>
   <p>This can be avoided if there is a concerted effort to acquire the interest of our youth, and then to give it responsibility in graduated measures.....</p>
   <p>Most important of all, the Chicago Greek parishes should unite into one powerful, result-getting community so that our youth will have a worth-while inheritance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
