<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-11-23">Nov. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Sectionalism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1465</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1465.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-11-23">Nov. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">SECTIONALISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Negotiations are now in progress among the many Greek societies and associations in the Greek community of Chicago to bring these organizations together into one national alliance under one roof, with centralized activity. And from all indications, including the attitude of the various local authorities, unification is near at hand.</p>
   <p>Of course the Greeks of Chicago as chips of the old block, are not to blame for their tendency to regionalism. Their forefathers in ancient Greece shed plenty of blood because of their erroneous and destructive conception that a Sparton was something distinct from an Athenian. Ancient and glorious Greece was divided into many states, just as the Chicago Greek community is divided into various duchies, governed by their respective dukelings and local barons.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1466.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The ancient Greeks, in one way, were justified in their regionalism because every section of Greece was highly competent in state craft and in other things common to all Greeks. One section or state of Greece would not permit its neighboring state to dominate it because they were equals. Their development, mental and physical, was equal and similar. To let Sparta rule was absolutely unthinkable to Athenians, and vice versa.</p>
   <p>When Athens was threatened with invasion by the Persians, who came in great numbers to subdue and to punish that proud city, and the Athenian warriors were outnumbered ten to one by the Persians, the Athenians appealed to Sparta for assistance. Sparta replied, "I will come to help you win but I must command the armies."</p>
   <p>When Mother Greece asked her sons in Chicago to assist her with contributions for national defense, eash society in Greek Chicago, through its local leader or boss or what not, replied, "Yes, we will all assist Mother Greece, but our society must lead."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1467.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every organization wanted to be boss. It is absolutely unnecessary to divide the Greek community in Chicago among so many dynasties. The native of Megara, for instance, could function as such, and cooperate with his compatriots in sending money to his native town for a belfry,or a church,or a school and yet at the same time belong to one national Greek organization.</p>
   <p>Supporting so many societies not only tends to perpetuate sectionalism; it also tends to diminish our inherent love for Mother Greece and to render centralized activity impossible.</p>
   <p>The halls of the national organization could be utilized for meetings for the Arcadians, the Islanders, the Lacedaemonians, and others when local affairs were to be discussed. Tens of thousands of dollars could be saved in this way and used for the assistance of the mother country and for the improvement of our community. The $500 or more spent annually by each of thirty-seven Greek societies for stationery, banners, and other incidentals, amounting approximately to $20,000, would supply our colony with many useful things which it needs.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1468.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>All this has been taken into consideration by the heads of our thirty-seven Greek organizations and a serious movement is on foot to form a national fraternity with a coalition administration.</p>
   <p>That will be splendid, if and when it materializes. Let us hope that it will materialize.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
