<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-12-23">Dec. 23, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Christmas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1699</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1699.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-12-23">Dec. 23, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTMAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- It is nineteen hundred and thirty-two years since the birth of the founder of the Christian religion, and the anniversary of this joyful event is to be celebrated again by the Christian world.</p>
   <p>Our church proclaims in hymns of supreme beauty this great event, wherein Earth and Heaven bless the "advent in the name of God."</p>
   <p>As all religions do, Christianity has wrapped the birth of its founder in mysticism, for his supernatural conception by His ever-Virgin Mother is a mystery as well as his death and resurrection.</p>
   <p>But regardless of how much mystery envelops his birth and his death, his teaching was so simple and so convincing that it quickly conquered the hearts of his innumerable followers, for it appeals to the sentiments of human nature and aims at the relief and the consolation of the suffering and the afflicted.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1700.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Contrary to all other religions of fear and revenge, Christianity preaches love and forgiveness. It is, we may say, the religion par excellence of love and mercy. The sole commandent that it gives to its faithful adherents is, "Love one another." Upon this doctrine of loving one another Christ builds the whole structure of his teaching. And there is no doubt that the very moment this great commandment is applied, all problems that beset humanity will automatically be solved.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that among all religions now existing Christianity is the one of which the adherents are most advanced and best civilized, for the religion of Christ is the religion of civilization and progress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
