<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1913-12-27">Dec. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Lambros Koromilas</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-12-27">Dec. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">LAMBROS KOROMILAS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All the Greeks of Chicago were very happy to welcome to this great Greek center His Excellency, Mr. Lambros Koromilas, the Ambassador of Greece to the United States. Mr. Koromilas left his post in Washington, D. C. with the express purpose of visiting and inspecting more than seventy Greek communities and their institutions throughout the United States.</p>
   <p>From what His Excellency has thus far seen and heard, there seems to be an imperative need for planning, for organization, and for general improvement among all the Greek communities. He was especially impressed by the great activity and energy of our people in Chicago. We have been promised a lecture in the near future, at which time we will be given some practical suggestions in regard to the reorganization of our community forces.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1040.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Koromilas had a lengthy interview with our community leaders, and outlined the following program:</p>
   <p>All incompetent and unqualified consular officials in all the cities in the United States must be dismissed. The Ambassador has already relieved many consular representatives of their duties, including those in Butte, Nashville, and San Francisco;</p>
   <p>The entire community government must be organized on a new basis. Each member of all the communities in the United States will be asked to contribute one dollar monthly. The 400,000 Greeks in America would thus contribute $400,000 monthly. This sum would be sufficient to build and support our churches, schools, and charitable institutions;</p>
   <p>Other urgent needs include the establishment of an archdiocese and the appointment of a bishop to supervise the more than seventy churches throughout America. It has also been suggested that a consular office be established in every Greek community having a Greek church or a <pb facs="5422062_4_1041.jpg" n="3"/>population of one thousand or more Greeks.</p>
   <p>Many of these plans and projects of Mr. Koromilas' have been defeated in the past, but we hope that his visit and his advice will inspire all of us to do bigger and better things in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
