<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-05-03">May 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">We Shall Not Leave a Trace of Our Existence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_2023</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_2023.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-05-03">May 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WE SHALL NOT LEAVE A TRACE OF OUR EXISTENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When anyone outside of our city reads in the columns of the Greek Press about the activities of our Greek community, he receives the impression that as a group the Greek people of Chicago sail upon tranquil seas. We who live here and are aware of the real situation know that such is not the case.</p>
   <p>On the surface, all seems to be going along fine; but an examination of the financial condition of any one of our churches will reveal a deplorable situation. Neither the deliberate bankruptcies to evade the payment of second and third mortgages, nor the drastic wage and expenditure cuts seem to have lightened their financial distress. In the opinion of certain clerics and laymen, this indicates the beginning of the time of the survival of the fittest, according to the laws of evolution. Of course I do not refer to the basic, natural evolutionary laws; but to those employed in our ordinary <pb facs="5422062_4_2024.jpg" n="2"/>business methods, whereby we rid ourselves of competitors--imaginary or real.</p>
   <p>To prove this, we hereby aver that each one of the Chicago Greek churches is impatient for the moment to arrive when one of the others will be forced to close its doors. That will, of course, limit the competetion, and enable the remaining churches to get at more money. Many people seem to think that such tactics are fitting only for unscrupulous chain stores--but of course that only shows their lack of progressiveness.</p>
   <p>With such a formula and program we still have the boldness to demand that our children follow in our footsteps and continue to support our institutions. Of course, since they will be thinkers, and better educated than we, they will see through the sham and pretense of the heritage we shall leave them, and they will cast it aside forever. As a result, there will be no trace of our existence left in America as mute evidence of our courage, honesty, and <pb facs="5422062_4_2025.jpg" n="3"/>ability. If we wish our children to uphold their heritage, we must make it worth upholding. Then the picture will be entirely different.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
