<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1910-01-14">Jan. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Phoenix Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1394</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1394.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1910-01-14">Jan. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE PHOENIX SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those who would study the progress and the activities of our multifarious organizations will discover that not very much has been accomplished in the field of patriotic contributions during the last year. While it is true that many local organizations have done their utmost and have shown signs of progress, countless others have stopped doing anything whatever, others have retrogressed, and still others have disappeared altogether.</p>
   <p>Because it is physically impossible to mention separately the activities of all the organizations of Chicago, we confine ourselves to the discussion of the worked done by the Panhellenic League and the Phoenix Society which are not local in scope.</p>
   <p>Judging from its past record we notice that the Panhellenic League has been condemned to die, because there was no reason for its existence. To the Phoenix Society, however, we offer flowers for its patriotic services and excellent <pb facs="5422062_4_1395.jpg" n="2"/>charitable contributions during the past year. Glance at its annual financial report and you will notice that the Society has voted a handsome sum for the Ecumenical Patriarch, the earthquake victims of Elia, Greece, and Italy. It has spent $1,269.37 for the care and hospitalization of hundreds of its sick members. It has a cash reserve of $3,091.70 in its treasury and owns property and tangible assets valued at six hundred dollars. These facts prompt us to congratulate the officers and members of the Phoenix Society for their patriotism and charitable works.</p>
   <p>It is now obvious that, in contrast, the Panhellenic League has not measured up to the public's expectations; it is even doubtful if there are more than one hundred dollars in its treasury. It is now apparent how "ably" Mr. Bousoulas, the pompous and boastful president of the League, has guided the affairs of a once powerful organization. He does not seem to realize that the death of the League as a potent social and cultural force among the Greeks of America, is the responsibility of those who directed its destinies. Under such circumstances it is hard for the League to survive so Mr. Bousoulas should be relieved <pb facs="5422062_4_1396.jpg" n="3"/>of his "heavy"duties and the remains of the organization should be rescued by Phoenix which has the power and the prestige to become the greatest instrument in the hands of a united Greek people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
