<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1916-03-23">March 23, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Installation of Officers of the Pan-Hellenic Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1916-03-23">March 23, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">INSTALLATION OF OFFICERS OF THE PAN-HELLENIC SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2--Charm, beauty, and magnificience marked the ceremony of the installation of officers of the Pan-Hellenic Society last Sunday.</p>
   <p>The Corinthian Hall of the Masonic Temple and the halls adjoining were packed with members of the Society, and with friends and admirers of both sexes. The rooms were decorated with huge American and Greek banners and an abundance of flowers, presenting a spectacle of artistic beauty such as only the Greek imagination can produce.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Leontios Pegeas, archimandrite of the Greek Church, distinguished for his fine presence and his culture, officiated in the recitation of the liturgy and the ceremony of installation was conducted with great solemnity and decorum.</p>
   <p>The orchestra of the recently organized Homer Club played several delightful selections, after which the retiring president, Mr. E. Karavelis, took the floor and enumerated the accomplishments of the Pan-Hellenic Society, which is <pb facs="5422062_4_0063.jpg" n="2"/>the largest and strongest Greek organization in the United States.</p>
   <p>The musical society conducted by the Misses Poule and Palamare sang "The Vigil of Crete (Crete is Girded in Flame for Battle)".</p>
   <p>Thereafter the new president, Mr. D. Manousopoulos, mounted the platform and delivered a speech of fraternal and patriotic character. His speech is published in full on page four.</p>
   <p>Refreshments and a dance followed, lasting into the early hours of the morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
