<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-05-23">May 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">While Some One Gives His Life, What Are You Giving? Think a Minute--The Red Cross!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-05-23">May 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHILE SOME ONE GIVES HIS LIFE, WHAT ARE YOU GIVING? THINK A MINUTE--THE RED CROSS!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The wounded of the war, far away from the embrace of his loved ones, finds no other consolation than the Christian compression of the Red Cross. The Red Cross gives to the wounded man his medicine tenderly cares for his wound, embraces him as a mother, communicates with his relatives, and spreads healthful thoughts far and wide. The Red Cross is the bitter enemy of death, against which it wages relentless war. With care and pity it gathers the refugees and the orphans who have excaped the atrocities of Teuton, Turk or Bulgarian.</p>
   <p>In order that it may do its duty and successfully defeat Charon, we must supply and equip the Red Cross with its ammunition, that is, with medicine, provisions, and money. The noble work of the Red Cross cannot be overestimated. It is divine.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0448.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greeks of America have surpassed all other nationalities by these two distinguished achievements: that is, in proportion to the total Greek population of the United States more Greeks are in the Army and Navy than men of any other nationality, and more liberty bonds have been bought by Greeks, in proportion to their numbers, than by any other race.</p>
   <p>Now these patriotic American Greeks have the opportunity to attain another Great honor and for the third time to achieve destinction. Can we do it? Are we going to let some other group take away our laurels? Are we tired, old, and satiated with patriotism?</p>
   <p>Yes, we can do it as we have done it in the past and in the present, and we shall distinguish ourselves again.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0449.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>No, we are not going to let some other group wear the laurels; we are not accustomed to taking a back seat and applauding others, by our tradition we must be the heroes.</p>
   <p>No, we are not tired, old and satiated with patriotism. The Greek from the cradle to the grave retains his inherent patriotism. It is ever present and ever burning.</p>
   <p>America our country stands ready again to honor us and our Greek name when we achieve our third distinction. Never before have we failed, and we shall not fail now. This honor will be captured by the Greeks and by the Greeks alone.</p>
   <p>Chicago's Greek community is always taken as an example by fellow-Greeks of the land; let us begin to make our model worthwhile so that others will follow us. Chicago Greeks have been leaders, and they are leaders yet.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
