<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-05-31">May 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning the Celebration of the Birth of the Greek Republic.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1616</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1616.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-05-31">May 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING THE CELEBRATION OF THE BIRTH OF THE GREEK REPUBLIC.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1-The first Premier of the Greek Republic has thanked the Greek community of Chicago by telegram as follows:</p>
   <p>"Greek Community, Chicago, Illinois:</p>
   <p>"My sincere thanks to the patriotic Greek community of Chicago for its enthusiasm for democracy and also for its generous participation in the reorganization of our country. My sincere thanks and appreciation to the prominent Americans, Dean John H. Wigmore, Mr. James Hamilton Lewis, and Mr. Rufus Dawes for their splendid addresses on democracy."</p>
   <p>"Alexander Papanastasiou, Premier."</p>
   <p>The above telegram from the first Premier of the Grecian Republic was received in reply to the telegram below sent to him by the executive committee of the celebration for the restoration of the Greek Republic, which occurred last Sunday, May 25, at the Garrick Theater:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1617.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Alexander Papanastasiou, Premier of Greece, Athens, Greece:</p>
   <p>"The Greek community of Chicago has held a great Greek-American demonstration to celebrate the restoration of democracy in Greece. The Honorable John H. Wigmore, dean of the Law School of Northwestern University, presided, and addresses were made by James Hamilton Lewis, former United States senator, by Rufus Dawes, distinguished financier, and by several Greek speakers.</p>
   <p>"The community expresses its deep gratitude to its Grecian brethren, who by their vote in favor of the Republic have increased the prestige of the Greek race and have socially and commercially strengthened Hellenism abroad, especially that of the United States of America, which is devoted to democracy.</p>
   <p>"The community sends assurance of its satisfaction and confidence in the Government of Premier Papanastasiou for its generous and conciliatory internal policies and professes its admiration for those patriots of the Royalist Party who by their courage, loyalty, and sane regard for the peace and tranquility of our country have acknowledged and submitted to the will of the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1618.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"And the Greek community of Chicago hopes for the reorganization, progress, and prosperity of our glorious Greece, the mother of civilization."</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois, Sunday, May 25, 1924.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
