<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1934-10-07">Oct. 7, 1934</date><title level="a">Why Mr. Athenagoras Failed in His Mission. (From a series of articles about our church situation).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_2011</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_2011.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1934-10-07">Oct. 7, 1934</date><title level="a">Why Mr. Athenagoras Failed in His Mission. (From a series of articles about our church situation).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That Mr. Athenagoras has created a chaotic condition in our church affairs, and will continue to create new questions and make things worse, is proven beyond a doubt by his not calling, purposely, the conventions of the western territorial communities, while he did call the eastern ones and attended them personally, thus violating the rules and by laws of the church, which he applies as, and when, he pleases to make them serve his purpose.</p>
   <p>This omission becomes a real scandal, because Mr. Athenagoras deprives, by this procedure, a half of his flock of their opportunity to express an opinion in church and on communal matters, or else he may want to tell us that he does not need the western communities. In such a case, they ought to think about their own church administration.</p>
   <p>According to the by laws the Archdiocese is sub-divided into five communities and the different communities convene every year to discuss certain matters that the Arch diocese places before them.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_2012.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>By a resolution of the mixed council, the Archdiocese had to ask the opinion of the Local Conventions as to the creation of four or five assistant bishoprics and for other matters. Strange as it is, however, and obviously in violation of the by laws, Mr. Athenagoras failed to call the western communities because he, seemingly, believes, or suspects, that the western communities would not have been favorable towards him and the methods, by means of which he usually gets passed resolutions which he favors at the conventions........</p>
   <p>These are the reasons and the western communities have the right to look for a new Archbishop and place the matter before the supreme authority of the church, namely, the Ecumenical Patriarchate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
