<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Year Book of St. Constantine Church and Korais School</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 67.
<title level="a">Historical Pages of the Community of St. Constantine and St. Helen. 8th.- Administration, Presidents, Priests.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1959</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1959.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>YEAR BOOK OF ST. CONSTANTINE CHURCH AND KORAIS SCHOOL</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 67.
<title level="a">Historical Pages of the Community of St. Constantine and St. Helen. 8th.- Administration, Presidents, Priests.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thus, St. Constantine Church begins its regular career under the auspices of God, its defending patron Saint, and the devotion of its parishioners and others.</p>
   <p>The governing powers of the church are intrusted in the hands of chosen personalities as follows to wit: Mr. Dem. Stamos, president; Mr. G. Lempesis, vice president; Mr. John Drousias, treasurer; E. Kotsonis, secretary. Members of the council are, Mr. N. Nomicos, Dr. K. Theodorou, P. Rousopoulos, John Mpontsolas, P. Mpouzanis, G. Krokidas, P. Papaioanou, N. Karafotias, George Spyros and A. Agelopoulos. The presidency of Mr. Stamos was successful, and lasted until 1929, when Mr. D. Chrisos became president, with Mr. N. Kavouras as secretary. The presidency of Mr. Chrisos, as well as Mr. Lempesis', who succeeded him was peaceful and very successful.</p>
   <p>The cooperation of the council, the priest's, the prevalent spirit of progress, and the peaceful evolution of events, contributed to the welfare of the church. Thus, the needs and wants of the Christians were gratified with perfection and order.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1960.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is true, that the obligations of the church, the huge burdens of philanthropy, and the pressure brought about by debtors, forced the church to go through bankrupty proceedings, which took place at the end of Mr. Lempesis, presidency. As the iron comes out of the fire, our church came out of its difficulties stronger in finances. After the bankrupty of September, 1933, the presidency of the church was taken over by Mr. Rekas. The new president, Mr. S. Rekas, is well known for his devotion to the church, for his great activities in the Ahepa and other organizations, and for his executive ability in finances. His experience, knowledge, and his perpetual endeavors, (day and night) brought the finances of the church out of the red.</p>
   <p>The position of Cannonical Parish Priest for all periods was taken over by the headpriest, Rev. Mark E. Petrakis, whose efforts, activities, deeds and devotion, are the life and soul of the community. Father Petrakis took as assistant Rev. E. Tsourounakis, who is one of the most educated and clear-minded priests, that we have in Chicago. Rev. Tsourounakis took over the management of the school, until Rev. Constantine Glynos replaced him. Deacon Consto lynos is a modern graduate of the Theological Arcade of Halki. For the last two years His Deaconship vastly contributed to the magnificence and grandeur of the ecclesiastical rites which our community has witnessed with awe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
