<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-03-02">March 2, 1929</date><title level="a">The American Legion- Athens Post - Athens, Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-03-02">March 2, 1929</date><title level="a">THE AMERICAN LEGION- ATHENS POST - ATHENS, GREECE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 8.- The following is a letter of appreciation sent by the Athens Post of the American Legion, expression the gratitude of Greek veterans' families for the Xmas presents, which were bought with money sent by chapter No. 10. The letter is so important and very pathetic, that we have printed it in full.</p>
   <p>Edward Hines Chapter No. 10</p>
   <p>Disabled American Weternas,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Dear Comrades:</p>
   <p>On behalf of the officers and members of the Athens Post of the American Legion, I desire to express to the officers and members of your Chapter <pb facs="5422062_4_0278.jpg" n="2"/>our sincere thanks and deep appreciation for the courtesies extended to our Adjutant, at San Antonio, comrade Harry Maurikidis, by comrades Herman H. Weiner, James Bowers, Jr., Arthur Zohn, Carter Smith, Bill Bouliotis and Frank Slattery, all members of your chapter, during his visit to Chicago.</p>
   <p>I also wish to express the appreciation of this Post for the contribution of $50 for the benefit of destitute Greek veterans. In this connection I wish to state that after a discussion by the Executive Committee of the Post, it was decided to distribute this $50 in the most practical and useful manner. With the assistance of our comrades here fifty Xmas baskets were prepared which were delivered to fifty poor families whose names we obtain from the Greek Veterans Association and from the Greek Widows and Orphans of War Victims. The value contained in each basket, (actually a small burlap bag, as baskets were too expensive for that purpose) exceed that of $1.00 for each family. Those of our members who could supply at cost meat or foodstuff did so cheerfully.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0279.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Each bag contained 4 pounds of meat; Xmas bread; 21/2 pounds macaroni; 1 can of milk; 1/2 pound cheese and other little things. There was also enclosed a card reading as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Disabled American Veterans of the Edward Hines Chapter No. 10, of Chicago, wishes you a merry Xmas and a happy New Year, by the courteous action of the Greek ladies of Chicago--Athens Post of the American Legion."</p>
   <p>I accompanied comrade Calas of this Post on his charitable mission and I can assure you that this unexpected present was believed to be a Godsend and most of these people received it with tears in their eyes, blessing you for the deed.</p>
   <p>In this connection, my comrades, I venture to suggest that this noble action be repeated each year, if possible, and on a greater scale as <pb facs="5422062_4_0280.jpg" n="4"/>you cannot realize the misery and great suffering in which most of these families of Greek veterans live. Their scanty allotment by the Greek Government is not sufficient even for their daily bread. I believe this sort. of help, small as it is, reaches the depths of their hearts and creates a feeling of gratitude, especially when coming from such a distance and unexpected source.</p>
   <p>Will you kindly convey the thanks and appreciation of this Post to the Greek ladies of Chicago who were instrumental in this matter.</p>
   <p>With our good wishes for better health and greater happiness during the present year, I am, my dear comrades,</p>
   <p>Fraternally yours,</p>
   <p>Dr. Anthony Blase, Commander.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
