<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1922-12-09">Dec. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Hellenic Post, No. 343.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1314</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1314.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-12-09">Dec. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> HELLENIC POST, NO. 343.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Ill., Nov. 27, 1922</p>
   <p>Hon. Georges Clemenceau,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois,</p>
   <p>Honorable Sir:</p>
   <p>The members of the Hellenic Post, No. 343, of the American Legion, have requested me to extend to you a most cordial welcome. This post is made up of ex-service men of the World War, who have come from Greece and have made America their country. During the World War about eighty thousand men of Hellenic descent entered the military service of the United States to fight on the side of the Allies. Many of us saw active service in your native land and helped to Check the enemies of democracy. After the Armistice was signed, the entire world turned its attention to the negotiations at Versailles, and all were pleased that peace had finally been concluded. America was represented at the conference by its President, <pb facs="5422062_4_1315.jpg" n="2"/>Woodrow Wilsoen, who played a great part, along with your Honorable Self, in bringing about a settlement of the many difficult questions that came up.</p>
   <p>We, of Hellenic descent, were also interested in the treaty of Sevres and were highly gratified when that treaty provided that the Turk should be banished from Europe. Unfortunately, if reports are true, the present government of your country concluded a separate peace with Turkey, and, during the preliminary conference between the Turks and the Allies at Mudania, representatives of your country were responsible for the return of Turkey into Europe. Certainky such conduct on the part of civilized nations is not in keeping with the great principles for which we fought and for which many laid down their lives. It is pitiful to witness the slaughter of Christians by the Turks and the deportation of hundreds of thousands of children and women from their homes. And this is a direct result of the diplomacy of those responsible for governing your country, even though relations between Greece and France have always been friendly.</p>
   <p>All of these matters are matters of history, and it is needless to dwell <pb facs="5422062_4_1316.jpg" n="3"/>on them in a communication of this kind. I merely want to call your attention to the fact that thousands of millions of Americans and other civilized people throughout the world are disappointed in the diplomacy which has permitted the Turks to destroy Smyrna, to slaughter hundreds of thousands of Christians and to re-occupy Thrace.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that some of the wrongs already perpetrated may be rectified at Lausanne, and we exrnestly solicit your friendship for the cause of Freedom and Democracy as interpreted by you during your glorious regime as Fremier of France.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>James K. Nichols, Commander.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
