<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-02-22">Feb. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Unjust Criticism from the Bench</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0709</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0709.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-02-22">Feb. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">UNJUST CRITICISM FROM THE BENCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 5) With due devotion and obedience to the laws of this country and with extreme reverence and respect for our courts the Star, as champion and defender of Greeks and of the reputation of Greeks in America, takes issue with a judge's recent strictures on Greeks and begs to bring out the naked truth of an unpleasant episode.</p>
   <p>On account of one single culprit the Honorable Judge Frank Crowe last week let loose a vitriolic storm of animadversions against all Greeks engaged in the confectionery business. The Greek confectioners in Chicago, who number more than three thousand, were all included in the judge's tirade.</p>
   <p>The ire of the jurist was aroused when Theodore Economakes, a Greek, pleaded guilty to the charge of forcing his attentions upon a young woman, one of his employees, whom he embraced and kissed in the presence of other employees.</p>
   <p>If this Greek is guilty according to our established laws, let the ax of justice <pb facs="5422062_4_0710.jpg" n="2"/>fall upon him and upon him alone, and let him suffer the consequences of his crime, for we all approve of due punishment for violation of the laws, but to utter from the bench such strictures as "All you Greek confectioners lead our girls astray" is unjust, and the impartial administration of justice, in spite of all sincerity and honesty is bound to suffer when anger and other emotions becloud the fairness of jurists' minds.</p>
   <p>The stigma applied to so great a number of confectioners on account of one is not easily erased, but somehow Greeks are accustomed to bear, without whining, the burdens forced upon them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
