<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1931-11-03">Nov. 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks Score Triumph in First Carnival Event</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0191</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0191.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1931-11-03">Nov. 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS SCORE TRIUMPH IN FIRST CARNIVAL EVENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greek-Americans of Chicago, 165,000 strong, today set up a high mark for every other national group, large or small, to shoot at.</p>
   <p>Hosts to 6,000 cheering Chicagoans last night at the first spectacular show in Chicago's first carnival of nations, Greek-Americans tabulated returns today, reported success passed even their own expectations, and heard the cheers of leaders of every other national group in Chicago - applauding a triumph which stands as the key for the greatest international celebration the city has ever seen.</p>
   <p>Jamming the huge Aragon ballroom, crowding the dance floor until not another dancer could find room, thronging the mezzanines, standing packed together in the boxes overlooking the main floor, applauding again and again as Greek-Americans danced and played and sang, Chicagoans showed the sponsors of this first program that Chicago is proud of the citizens of foreign birth or extraction who have made the city great.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0192.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And today, when leaders of all other national groups gathered at the Daily News Building to set dates for their celebrations, they heard what Greek-Americans achieved last night - and pledged themselves to make every one of their programs equally successful.</p>
   <p>If anyone had wondered how Chicagoans in general would react to an actual carnival of nations, that doubt was set at rest by the ovation given Greek-American sponsors of the show last night at the Aragon. From the moment when, long before 8 P. M., the scheduled opening hour, crowds gathered outside the doors until after midnight, the orchestra played "Home Sweet Home", the program was vivid and varied and constantly entertaining - and the crowd grew and grew until Andrew Karzas, who donated the hall and two orchestras as his contribution to the Greek-American program, said he never had seen as great a crowd in the Aragon, which is famous for its crowds.</p>
   <p>"Miss Europe", Allki Diplarakou, danced gracefully, slowly, to Wayne King's Orchestra. Thousands stood silent, watching her, studying the slim, graceful girl in long Grecian robes who was chosen last year as "the most beautiful girl in all Europe". Then there was dancing, first to Wayne King's music, then to the music of Ted Weems' famous orchestra.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0193.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Then Greek girls from St. Constantine's School danced again with Miss Diplarakou. Then there were songs, musical trios, more dances and more solos, and the crowd kept growing. Greek-Americans in evening clothes, Greek-Americans who had come straight from work because they did not want to miss so fine a program; and people of every national background were there to see and hear and applaud.</p>
   <p>Not all of them knew that every cent they spent for tickets would go direct to emergency relief. Many came simply because they had been promised "the biggest show for $75". And nobody made speeches about charity; nobody said. "This is a benefit show, so you must enjoy it". Nobody needed to. It was so excellent a show, the evening was so crowded with events, that speeches would have been out of place. But today and tomorrow and all winter long, hundreds of needy Chicagoans will be fed and housed, because Chicago turned out for the Greek-American show last night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
