<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1927-11">Nov. 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Community of Chicago and its Story</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0950</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0950.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1927-11">Nov. 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK COMMUNITY OF CHICAGO AND ITS STORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- Our colleagues of the Herald and Examiner have devoted part of their columns to writing about various nationalities and various business interests in our city. Of course the Greek Community of Chicago had its turn to be publicized in the paper. For some time everyone has been wondering which Greek would be the lucky one to write the article about his fellow countrymen. Every one of the 50,000 Greeks of Chicago was sure he would be chosen for the honor.</p>
   <p>The person finally chosen was none other than our eminent friend and colleague, editor of the Greek Star, Peter S. Lambros, who always must show his ego.</p>
   <p>Many Greeks were opposed to this choice but they could do nothing about it. It is a shame that such a great mistake has been made by the Examiner.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0951.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Here are several phrases from the article in question:</p>
   <p>"Greeks were very prominent in fur trading in 1812."</p>
   <p>"Since the Chicago Fire in 1870, when Greek meets Greek they upen up a restaurant."</p>
   <p>Nothing was mentioned about professional men, Greek organizations or Greek politics. In other words his article was useless and did nothing for the 50,000 Greeks of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lambros may be able to edit a newspaper satisfactorily for his subscribers but we don't think he can write the story of our countrymen here. Hellenism has suffered enough from his "patriotic speeches." Someone should put a stop to it.</p>
   <p>George A. Kyriakopoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
