<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-03-30">Mar. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Women Organize Club to Aid Needy Expectant Mothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0119</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0119.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-03-30">Mar. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN ORGANIZE CLUB TO AID NEEDY EXPECTANT MOTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday afternoon, more than seventy Greek women met at the Chicago Maternity Center, 1336 Newberry Avenue, near the Holy Trinity Church.</p>
   <p>These ladies, representative of the finest type of Greek womanhood in Chicago, came from all sides of the city at the invitation of Dr. A. Martin [Marantes]. His purpose in calling them together was to discuss the possibility of the formation of a club that would aid needy Greek pregnant women. At present, such cases are being taken care of, free of charge, by the Center. Dr. Martin has been in charge of this department. His action, which is most worthy, is a step that has never before been taken by any Greek doctor--or for that matter, by any Greek.</p>
   <p>Various medical men gave speeches encouraging the ladies to do all they could for their needy and, often, desperate countrywomen. Mrs. Morris Fishbein, wife of the editor of the American Medical Journal, emphasized the direness <pb facs="5422062_4_0120.jpg" n="2"/>of the need of many destitute Greek women. She pointed out that it was the duty of the Greek people to help the Center, which had been created by Dr. DeLee to fill an enormous need. The Center is associated ith the Lying In Hospital.</p>
   <p>Mrs. A. Voulis was elected president of this newly organized club; Mrs. L. Yoha, vice-president; Mrs. G. Alex, secretary; Mrs. J. Askounis, treasurer. [Names of members of board of directors omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>The second meeting will take place next Friday, and it is hoped that many more women will attend and become members of this philanthropic society. The dues are one dollar a year. This money will be used for the mothers. The Club members will make layettes and help their less fortunate sisters in every way possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
