<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1919-02-08">Feb. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Greek-American Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-02-08">Feb. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK-AMERICAN ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have discussed many times the short existence of most of the Greek clubs. It is now the accepted fact that it is not the organizations' programs which are not good, but it is usually due to poor selection of officers. As a result, we see many successful and worth-while organizations disintegrate and fall into obscurity.</p>
   <p>The Greek-American Society, whose meetings we attended, seems to be a worth-while organization. A spirit of unity and fellowship pervaded the atmosphere of the meeting. The members had faith and trust in the president, and he respected the opinions of the members.....Each member must be a citizen in order to be able to cast a vote. The men who run for office must also be American citizens. The president, Mr. Paul Demos has done much to raise the organization to the level of the American clubs. The letters of Medill McCormick and other statesmen are evidence <pb facs="5422062_4_1355.jpg" n="2"/>of the effort made by Demos for our fatherland. Through the aid of Mr. McCormick, he was enabled to publish, in a leading Chicago magazine, a complete picture of the situation in unredeemed Greece, and the demands of free Greece. This article was a fine analytical work, and its meaning was perfectly clear.</p>
   <p>Mr. Demos, as the organizer of a patriotic organization, is to be praised. The only thing we feel necessary to advice him to do, is to proceed slowly. Anyone who organizes a club that is to have a national bearing must see that it lives up to its ideals and does not lose sight of its purpose.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
