<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-06-06">June 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Future of the Greeks in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0834</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0834.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-06-06">June 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE FUTURE OF THE GREEKS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I venture to state certain conclusions concerning the fate of the American Greeks. These conclusions are not in accordance with what I should like to see or with what I think ought to happen. They are based upon what has been happening time and time again for three centuries. Although they probably will not take my advice, I appeal to my people to do what common sense and hard facts of history plainly advise.</p>
   <p>Article after article is published in the Greek Press and in other Greek publications upon the questions: What will become of the younger generation? Will the Greeks survive as a group in America? Will their children preserve their ancestral traditions? Will the Greek language remain in use?.... Such discussions are often fraught with sentiment and wishful thinking. Moreover, they often speak of preserving the Greek spirit, but never say just what that is. I want to say most emphatically that there are plain <pb facs="5422062_4_0835.jpg" n="2"/>answers to these questions. It is not a matter of guesswork, of wishful thinking, or of sentiment.</p>
   <p>Here are the facts: Many other immigrant groups have maintained their group identity--but with modifications. Most of the Greeks have been here less than half a century. Some of the other national groups have been here five or six times as long, but they have survived with modifications.....</p>
   <p>The Dutch have ceased conducting church services in Dutch in order to hold the nea gennea [youth]. It has been the experience of immigrant groups in America that English must be used to hold the young people. Several years ago, the Russian church began having an English sermon as well as one in Russian. Some churches use the language of their national group in connection with English.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0836.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greeks might keep their liturgy in Greek and use English for the sermon.....the Greek churches in America will have to use more English or die. I should be sorry to walk into a Greek church and hear no Greek; but it is not a question of what one would like, or even what ought to be. It is a question of what has to be. The answer is plain--more English.</p>
   <p>The church of an immigrant group is its most effective rallying ground.</p>
   <p>If the history of other American immigrants has any lesson for the Greeks, it is this: that the surest way for them to survive as a group will be to support their church.</p>
   <p>One of the greatest weaknesses of the Greek Church is the lack of support it receives from the Greeks in America. I have not seen a single Greek <pb facs="5422062_4_0837.jpg" n="4"/>clergyman here who was born in America. The time is rapidly approaching when there must be an American-born clergy, if the church is to survive in America.</p>
   <p>It will not be found practicable to send students back to Greece for their theological education. The future of the American church is being injured every day because of the lack of a Greek Orthodox institution of higher learning where both future laymen and future members of the clergy may receive a good, general college education under the auspices of their own church. Co-education would also greatly help. Continued delay will be very costly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
