<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-05-05">May 5, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Program of the Third Convention of the Democratic Liberals of the United States and Canada</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1903</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1903.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-05-05">May 5, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROGRAM OF THE THIRD CONVENTION OF THE DEMOCRATIC LIBERALS OF THE UNITED STATES AND CANADA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 8- The Convention was in session for three days. The first day was May 12, 1923.</p>
   <p>The meeting came to order at 9:30 a. m. in the large club-room of the Democratic Liberals of Chicago. A president pro-tem was elected and the documents which certified the appointment of the delegates by their several clubs were submitted to him for examination and approval.</p>
   <p>About 1:30 p. m. permanent officers of the convention were elected and committees were appointed. After lunch the committees met separately and set to work on the special business for which they had been appointed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1904.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Second Day, May 13, 1923.</p>
   <p>At 9:30 a. m. the convention was called to order. The special committees reported the completion of their work. The president arranged the order for the day and the discussion lasted from 1:30 p.m. to 6:30 p. m. An intermission followed to 8:30 p. m. The session was then resumed and continued to 12 p.m.</p>
   <p>Third Day, May 14, 1923.</p>
   <p>The session opened at 8:30 a.m. and with an intermission of one hour for dinner, continued to 6 p.m. Various subjects were discussed and a resume was made of the conversations with propositions and conclusions. The minutes were read and accepted. The session closed about 6 p. m.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1905.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At 6:30 p. m. a dinner was served by the Democratic Liberals of Chicago in honor of the visiting delegates.</p>
   <p>At 9:30 p. m. the delegates conveyed in automobiles, attended the dance given at the Trianon, by the Young Women's Musical Association on behalf of the Greek Relief Committee for the benefit of our refugees from Asia Minor, as guests of the Chicago Democratic Liberal Association.</p>
   <p>The delegates at the expense of the Chicago Democratic Liberal Association, will travel in automobiles to visit places of interest in our city of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
