<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-11-17">Nov. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Need for a National Greek Club</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-11-17">Nov. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NEED FOR A NATIONAL GREEK CLUB</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the face of the disheartening failures of the past to form an organization for the purpose of furthering the progress of the Greeks in America, a great amount of courage is needed to suggest that another attempt be made. Nevertheless, it is an absolute necessity that we have some sort of national unity to fight for our interest, and to aid the church and school to keep the Greek language, religion and customs alive. This organization would make known our unity, and since "In unity there is strength", it would make us a group to be respected and considered.</p>
   <p>When the humble writer of these lines sees such an organization become a reality, he shall run with the same joy as did the messenger who announced the victory of the Battle of Marathon, and cry "Victory" and then die.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1358.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are many who raise dissenting voices; some say that the characteristics of our race would, in themselves, prevent such a move from being successful, others claim that if a general meeting finally were decided upon, all the empty "tin cans" [translator's note: Denekes--an insulting term applied to those who do nothing but talk--usually on subjects they have little knowledge of] would present themselves for membership. One "Deneke" will seek the presidency, when he is incapable of being a watchman. Another will want to be secretary and treasurer, despite the fact that he cannot even write his own name; and a third will seek to be a member of the council, when he probably should be in the hands of a keeper of an asylum. Along with the discouraged, the disagreers, and the advisers who say we should "stay on our eggs", [Translator's note: old Greek expression--meaning mind your own business, or stay where you belong] are those who try to influence us by their amusing use of proverbs and examples.</p>
   <p>One, who heard me talking before a group in a restaurant, said we were "looking for fleas in the hay". [Translator's note: This is similar to the <pb facs="5422062_4_1359.jpg" n="3"/>American Proverb only fleas is used in place of needle]. Another, smarter than the former, asked if we had seen the operetta "Sari" which concerns the fate of a village girl who went to Paris and was scorned and stared at by the Parisians. A third, who also had firm belief in the moving power of proverbs and axioms, remarked, "Well said, but I am afraid that a similar fate is awaiting your plans, as befell the people of Panarites parish, in Corinth. I am quite sure you have not heard about it. Listen and I will tell you:</p>
   <p>"In 1890 a plague struck the vineyards and destroyed most of the grapes. Those that were saved sold at a price of seven to eight hundred drachmas per thousand pounds. But the grapes raised in the parish of Panarites sold for one drachma per liter, because they were of such fine quality. Then the people of Panarites became rich from the sale of their grape crops, which were the best in all Greece. The Panarites became drunk with their newly-acquired riches, and tried to think what to do with their money, in order to properly impress the neighbors. They decided to build beautiful <pb facs="5422062_4_1360.jpg" n="4"/>houses with marble facades. When the houses were completed, the owners, who had previously lived in huts and hovels, prepared to move into their new homes. You can imagine what happened. In the parlor, with the marble fireplace they hung their baskets of cheeses, in order to prevent the rats from eating them. Try and picture the impression of a visitor to that home, which, incongruously, contained marbles and cheeses, odors and perfumes, pigs and peasants".</p>
   <p>"Now you demand that we form a club just because we have acquired a few dollars and changed from "Tsarouhia" [Translator's note: straw shoes worn by the peasants] to shoes--a club in which we will proceed to display to the world our egoism and quarrelsome natures. Go on your way, Christian, we are all right; and anyhow, who gives a dime for our race?"</p>
   <p>"Wait a minute," I answered; "for exactly that reason must we form this organization. We must make the world give ten-dollar bills and not dimes for <pb facs="5422062_4_1361.jpg" n="5"/>our race. In order to make them do this we must create something Greek which can be viewed with pride by us, and with admiration by other races. Now that we have a new consul general in Chicago, I hope this dream will become a reality. Let us form this club. What if we do fight and quarrel? Qarreling has its value, just as a storm has its awesome splendor. In this club we will hear and learn much; through it we will accomplish many fine deeds. All who agree are requested to send their names to Saloniki.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
