<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1927-05">May, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">George Gatsis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0768</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0768.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1927-05">May, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">GEORGE GATSIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- The Greeks of Chicago have been following the remarkable progress of a certain Arcadian gentleman residing in our city. He is George K. Gatsis, of the real estate business. George was born in Tegeas Strigos and came to America when eighteen years old. He succeeded in overcoming all the obstacles confronting a poor, ignorant immigrant and has now made an important name for himself.</p>
   <p>He was closely associated with the Britigan Realty Association for four years. Two years ago he opened new offices at the 139 North Clark Street Bldg., and still later he opened offices at 134 North La Salle Street under the name George K. Gatsis Realty Co. He moved from there to the South Side at 79th and Ashland and is now located at 1625 W. 79th Street.</p>
   <p>His latest investment was a subdivision which he bought jointly with other Arcadians. This subdivision cost $160,000 and is now the South-town <pb facs="5422062_4_0769.jpg" n="2"/>Subdivision which Mr. Gatsis bought previously with Harold J. Mc Elhinny, his partner at 110th and Western Ave.</p>
   <p>Mr. Gatsis is also in a syndicate which controls fifteen apartment buildings on Artesian between Western and Campbell Aves., worth $500,000.</p>
   <p>The new subdivision will increase in value because it is near 111th St. and the Rock Island Depot. Mr. Gatsis is in charge of all the above mentioned buildings, but this does not make him forget his duties to his native country. He recently donated $500 to the Arcadian organization.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago are proud of George Gatsis and wish him continued success in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
