<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Constant Theodore, <title level="a">"Business Aspects of the Next Ahepa Convention"</title> <title>Ahepa Herald</title>,
<date when="1935-06">June, 1935</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1790</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1790.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Constant Theodore, <title level="a">"Business Aspects of the Next Ahepa Convention"</title> <title>Ahepa Herald</title>,
<date when="1935-06">June, 1935</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Perhaps very few of our people realize the practical significance of the Twelfth National Convention of the Order of Ahepa to be held next August in Chicago.</p>
   <p>A convention that will draw to Chicago over fifty thousand people belonging to every walk of life and coming from all parts of the United States and who will spend over half a million dollars, is an affair that should serve to our people as food for thought with special reference to the many benefits which will result from the convention directly or indirectly to our business men.</p>
   <p>A convention of this type, although strictly an organization affair, is nevertheless an event that is national in scope, because incidentally it involves necessarily many racial, social, and business considerations.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1791.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The quality of persons being delegated to or visiting a convention of this type is of great practical importance. It is known from past experience that professional and business men comprise the greatest percentage of both delegates and visitors to the convention; and these are the persons who can afford to spend money and mix with other people, and who can consequently do advertising or promote and establish commercial contacts.</p>
   <p>In the City of Chicago there exist and thrive thousands of businesses of all kinds owned or directed by our people; Chicago is the metropolis of the Midwest and the cross-section of all transportation facilities of the country. This means that a few more thousand Greek businesses located in the surrounding Midwestern states may be added to those in Chicago which can in some way benefit by the convention. This is true especially with respect to the manufacture or sale of products consumed by the general or the Greek public all over the country. As regards business in Chicago, the benefits resulting from the convention will be more direct and more pronounced.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1792.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Ahepa Convention Committee has already secured the use of the Exhibit Hall in the Mezzanine Floor of the Hotel Sherman for the purpose of holding an exposition of Greek and other products during the convention. Space is being now sold to firms or persons interested in this exposition at very reasonable rates. An exposition of this kind is surely bound to have a highly salutary value from the commercial standpoint for all parties concerned.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, the duty of the brother Ahepans, as well as of all the Greek public to support the work of our organization being conducted by the Convention Committee with headquarters at the Sherman Hotel, and to advertise its practical importance and potential benefits to be derived by so many people directly or indirectly from holding a convention in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
