<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
   <date when="1929-09">Sept.  1929</date><title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
   <date when="1929-09">Sept. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> 1929</date><title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It seems that we are going to be cursed forever if we do not preserve our language--as if it is the fault of the language! Our mouths are always in action, we are either talking or chewing. Everyone knows what has been written about the refusal of the Ahepan organization to recognize the Greek language. Newspapers and individuals alike are up in arms against this revolutionary action of Ahepa. Imagine them spurning the mother of Plato, the heathens, the traitors, the foreign worshippers! ! ! !</p>
   <p>"My dear friend," a philosopher told me, "all this fuss shows how brainless, deaf, stubborn, and falsely sentimental we are."</p>
   <p>As a people, we have nothing to show of our own. We copy and imitate others. The Ku Klux Klan frightened us so much that we all became Americanized so that we would not be roasted. Armenians, who had no country, did not whimper in fear of such bugaboos, nor did they humiliate themselves by any undignified submissions. Immediately interpreters appeared ready to go to work organizing the boys.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1253.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Lacking purpose, plan or program of their own, they adopted the Masonic principles, not forgetting the fez, and held meetings and conventions, stripping the brothers of their dollars and filling them with hot air. The result: hollow hearts and purses. For five years and more they have been running around Europe and America preaching the Ahepan Bible. The 26,000 members have nothing to show but the fez, buttons, and trumpets. They vote thousands of dollars for this and that, something a clown could do as easily. Yet they are speedily becoming organized and I foresee a great future for them.</p>
   <p>Greek after Greek is becoming a member of this organization and the moment when they become organized and show signs of unison, the troublemakers wake up and see what they can do in the way of mischief.</p>
   <p>For once the Greeks have become organized and promise great things for the future, but they have to be interrupted by non-members who will tell them what to do. Why should the Ahepans speak the language of Hommer? They are not organized to speak Greek to one another. The deeds they intend to accomplish can be done by means of any language. It is much better to hold American meetings for the establishments of Greek schools <pb facs="5422062_4_1254.jpg" n="3"/>and churches, than to hold Greek meetings and accomplish nothing.</p>
   <p>The members, in their private businesses, speak American and keep their books in the American way. The priests of our churches are becoming more Americanised in their system of bookkeeping. This does not mean that they are to lose their nationality, ideals, and customs; they are merely substituting the American system of doing things, which is superior to to the Greek way. Ahepans are not committing a crime, they are improving a sluggish system. Let us not always try our best to retard any progressive movement on the part of our fellow-countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
