<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-01-15">Jan. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Justice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0661</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0661.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-01-15">Jan. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">JUSTICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two of the four officials of the Greek-American Bank of Chicago have been summoned to appear before the Grand Jury. These two gentlemen are A. Geokaris and George Stamatises.</p>
   <p>The other two men scented the danger and hurriedly left for Greece. This action will not obstruct the course of justice, because the Greek government has promised to turn them over to the United States authorities, so that they can explain the absence of the $138,000 belonging to some eight hundred Greek depositors.</p>
   <p>The four defendents, Mr. Geokaris, Mr. Stamatides, Mr. Douras, and Mr. Papakostas, were the representatives of the Greek steamship lines and commercial fleets. They paid large sums for their advertising space in the Greek and American newspapers. The Saloniki has never accepted <pb facs="5422062_4_0662.jpg" n="2"/>any of their advertisements, because we doubted the honesty and veracity of these men.</p>
   <p>We are happy to know that we did nothing to help or encourage the exploitation of the trusting, hard-working people who fell into the trap set by these defrauders.</p>
   <p>The other Greek papers of Chicago, which had been well paid by the bankers to keep silent, stood aside, and it was the Saloniki alone that dared to expose these frauds. Now that our prophecies have come true, we are content to stand aside and watch the storm break over their heads.</p>
   <p>One New York paper published a half-hearted criticism of these four frauds, but for some reason or other it stopped before it had hardly begun. The cowardice of the Greek papers is evident to all; so it is unnecessary for us to say anything more about it. The Saloniki has done its share in <pb facs="5422062_4_0663.jpg" n="3"/>bringing these men to justice; they are now in the hands of the eternally just American courts.</p>
   <p>We also wish to congratulate the well-known Greek lawyer, Mr. A. Pantelis, who has undertaken to fight this case. We advise all the depositors to attend the hearings and the trial, in order that they may have the satisfaction of seeing justice administered.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
