<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-08-04">Aug. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">We Must Remain Greeks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0959</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0959.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-08-04">Aug. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">WE MUST REMAIN GREEKS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- We wrote yesterday that it is only natural for those Greeks who came here in their maturity always to remain Greeks because their nationality is so indelibly impressed upon their individuality that even if they wished to renounce it, they could not do so. However, it is an entirely different matter for those who came here at a tender age or for those who were born here; the environment influences them strongly, and national ties are naturally less binding, which makes it easier for them to become Americanized.</p>
   <p>It was for them, for those people who came here at a tender age and for those who were born here, that we originally brought up this matter of nationality in a clear, logical way. We believe that they should always consider carefully to what extent it would be to their interest to remain Greeks, and to what extent they would be benefited by renouncing their nationality. Among them we count our youthful professional men, graduates of American colleges, who practice their professions among Greeks.</p>
   <p>Without wishing to imply that these professional men are not capable enough to exercise their vocations among other nationalities, we note that although <pb facs="5422062_4_0960.jpg" n="2"/>there is no absolute need for them to do so, they turn to the Greeks and seek to establish a clientele among them. This is very natural, for they already have Greek connections, and consequently they launch their careers among Greeks. It would not be so easy for them to enter other circles, for other nationalities have their own professional men. As for Americans, competition is so keen among them that even American professional men have found it necessary to abandon their professions and turn to other careers. Thus it often happens that a Greek doctor, lawyer, or dentist establishes a clientele sooner among Greeks than among his numerous American connections; in spite of the large American population he finds it no easy task to get clients.</p>
   <p>For these Greek professional men it is indispensable that they shall preserve their national integrity. They should try their best to understand that Hellenism must continue to exist if they are to have the opportunity of extending their practice, or even of continuing to practice. Thus professional men have more at stake than any other class, and they should realize that to them it is of the utmost importance that Greeks shall preserve their identity and cling to the race of their origin.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0961.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In like situation are Greek priests, teachers, and journalists; their interests are closely interwoven with the existence and the maintenance of Hellenism in America. There are also persons engaged in business for whom Greek circles constitute the chief market for their wares. We mean not merely those least in number, the importers of Greek products, but also the great multitude of merchants and representatives of American firms, - real estate agents, building contractors, the various small business men and enterprising persons who carry on their trades among Greeks; they have a ready clientele which they surely could never find among the immense American population. Their commercial success depends on their remaining Greek. Without their nationality they would never be able to carry on their business in this country.</p>
   <p>In all the higher professions and in business, careers are open to the younger generation. It is to their interest that Hellenism in America shall persist, for Hellenism offers to young men a chance to practice their professions profitably.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0962.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Let no one imagine that it is easy for a Greek to practice his profession among people of other nationalities. Those who boast that they have a clientele which is largely American lie in order to show that they have no need of Greeks; they are braggarts trying to demonstrate their capability. Even those Greeks whose business caters strictly to Americans, the proprietors of restaurants and of candy stores, have need of other Greeks because they employ them. It is not easy for them to get equal cooperation or equally prompt and loyal service from other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Greek circles are an invaluable field of business for those who know enough to benefit by them. Greeks are so closely bound together that if national ties began to relax, Greek business establishments in America would begin to disintegrate likewise. For this reason, as we said in the beginning, we must consider our own interests before we decide whether or not we shall remain Greeks; and our interests cry aloud to us that we must cleave to the race of our origin.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
