<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1930-05">May, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Poor Greek Orphans of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1930-05">May, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE POOR GREEK ORPHANS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- For ten years our community has heard about nothing but churches, priests, bishops, Venizelists and Royalists. In the coffee-houses, in the restaurants, on the streets, - These subjects are discussed everywhere.</p>
   <p>The one problem which should have more attention - that of Greek orphans and poor children - does not receive a single word, as if there were no orphans or poor children in our Greek community.</p>
   <p>Have our societies ever thought about the lives of these orphans? Have they thought about how they live, how they are dressed, how they sleep, how they get their education?</p>
   <p>No.!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0258.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The philanthropic and benevolent societies spend thousands for affairs where they can be seen and heard. How much do they spend for the needy orphans?</p>
   <p>There are plenty of Greeks in America. They should form a club for "Poor and Orphaned Greek Children." They should give them clothes, send them to camp where they can get fresh air and sunlight, instead of being locked up all day long.</p>
   <p>The Youth problem is our greatest problem, because it is the safeguard of future Hellenism in America. If we don't preserve the Greek language in our young people, what is the use of having ecclesiastical establishments? There won't be any future Greek people to go to them.</p>
   <p>We have the greatest opportunities in the world for helping orphans and every kindly deed we do for them will help solve the problem of future Hellenism in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
