<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-04-20">April 20, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Easter Services Draw Thousands of Greeks--Elaborate Ceremonies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1752</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1752.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-04-20">April 20, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">EASTER SERVICES DRAW THOUSANDS OF GREEKS--ELABORATE CEREMONIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.3-The supreme drama of all times, the Resurrection of our Savior from death, was celebrated this year by the Greek community of Chicago with elaborate ceremonies.</p>
   <p>Thousands of worshippers crowded the two Greek churches and filled the air with the greatest of triumphal cries: "Christos anesti (Christ is risen)!"</p>
   <p>Every face in the crowds within the churches and without shone with joy and reverence when the traditional lighting of the candles began. Every mouth of the thousands sang, "Christos anesti! I am the resurrection and the life!" And every heart, young and old, was filled with pure thoughts of goodness, kindness, and charity.</p>
   <p>Greek Orthodox Easter ceremonies are magnificent and awe-inspiring. On Easter Sunday the hearts of worshipers are lifted to their highest level, and the soul rejoices in sublime peace,tranquillity, and love.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1753.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The divine words of the Greek language uttered by the officiating priests and the hymns sung by the choirs are the forces which unite mind, body, and soul. Every Greek soul on Easter Sunday communes with the Savior. "Christos anesti" is not spoken by the mouth only; it is spoken by the full consciousness of the immortal soul, proclaiming to the world the great truth of the mystery.</p>
   <p>During the ceremony of the "Agapi," which enjoins the worshippers to love one another as they love themselves; friends and enemies, strangers and relatives, young and old kiss one another not with the mouth but with the purity and the nobility of the soul.</p>
   <p>Every Sunday the two Greek churches of the South Side are packed, and people are compelled to stand outside. Why this negligence in establishing the North Side church, which has been under consideration for a long time? It is advisable to increase the number of churches as the community increases.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1754.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no excuse for the delay. Worshippers are flocking to the churches, and the funds necessary to establish new churches could be raised in the twinkling of an eye. Why then inconvenience people by delaying to build new churches? The Greek community is scattered throughout the three sections of the city, North Side, South Side and West Side, and it is increasing rapidly.</p>
   <p>One or two more churches will not be sufficient to accommodate all the communicants.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that the newly-created council of the Greek community will take serious steps to remedy our lack of churches.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
