<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-02-08">Feb. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">An Answer to the Greek Medical Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-02-08">Feb. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">AN ANSWER TO THE GREEK MEDICAL ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was with great regret that we read the article by the Greek doctors regarding the program and affiliation of our club. We were greatly surprised, since the exact purpose of our club was fully explained to the doctors at one of the club's recent meetings. We feel that it is necessary to answer these gentlemen and enlighten them.</p>
   <p>The Greek auxiliary of the Chicago Maternity Center was formed to help needy Greek women who go to the Center. This Center was founded by the famous obstetrician, Dr. De Lee, and has been in existence for over forty years. During its existence hundreds of Greek women have received medical aid there during and after pregnancy. According to the usual practice at the Maternity Center the patients give birth at home and are attended by doctors and nurses from the clinic. Complicated or serious cases are sent to the Lying-In Hospital. However, as it was known that many Greek women do not <pb facs="5422062_4_0108.jpg" n="2"/>like to give birth at home, we arranged with Dr. De Lee that these cases should be received at the Lying-In Hospital. All the members of our club know of this arrangement and no one has the right to say otherwise.</p>
   <p>According to our arrangement with Dr. De Lee, as soon as the Club pays a certain amount to the clinic, patients who wish to do so will go to the Hospital. Unfortunately, up to the present our treasury fund has been very low, and we have been unable to pay any money to the clinic.</p>
   <p>During the last two months two needy Greek women came to us for aid. These women were unable to give birth at home so it was decided that they should enter the Chicago Hospital because its fees are so low. This decision was made because of the extraordinary circumstances and the illness of the women. It did not seem right to demand that the clinic pay for the care of these two patients in the Lying-In, since the Club has not as yet contributed <pb facs="5422062_4_0109.jpg" n="3"/>one penny for this purpose. In the future all the patients will be sent to the Lying-In Hospital and in no case to the Chicago Hospital.</p>
   <p>The Medical Association was fully informed of the facts in this case and there is no justification for the accusations made in that article.</p>
   <p>The Association also heard us say that our Club does not intend to confine its charitable deeds to pregnant cases alone. But the Association certainly cannot expect that our treasury will grow so rich overnight that we can immediately help all the Greek needy hospital cases. It would be wonderful if any organization could do this, but it is an impossibility.</p>
   <p>We shall work very hard to accomplish as much good as is humanly possible....But at present we are aiding those women whom we feel need aid more than the others--some who are awaiting the birth of a child do not have enough <pb facs="5422062_4_0110.jpg" n="4"/>nourishment to keep themselves alive. We know that the Greek women agree with us in our plans because they have hastened to join our ranks.</p>
   <p>The reason for our affiliation with the Chicago Maternity Center is because it is world famous and is considered the outstanding maternity clinic in America. It is also our duty to remain in such a relationship, because it was this Center which gave us the inspiration to form our Club, and also because it has helped Greek women of our community for many years.</p>
   <p>The doctors who give home care at birth are all specialists in obstetrics. Again we repeat, however, that our intention is that Greek women will be sent to the Lying-In Hospital.</p>
   <p>Let us cease being egoists and let us work harmoniously for the common good. This organization, although it may seem to be of service to a restricted</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
