<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-01-29">Jan. 29, 1910</date><title level="a">Many Traitors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1048</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1048.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-01-29">Jan. 29, 1910</date><title level="a">MANY TRAITORS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- We write in our columns that the Greeks in America are a bunch of "farmers." Many of them will object to being called this and they will become very angry. That will not bother us because we know we are telling the truth.</p>
   <p>For every 100 people in our community, we will find 20 honest, gracious, educated, logical, patriotic men who will admit that we tell the truth. The other 75 will get hot and bothered trying to deny the charge and acting just like "farmers" when they are doing this.</p>
   <p>We are contrasting the present generation in America with our forefathers of 1821. They were men to be proud of. Without education, without knowledge, without leaders, without money and without weapons, they succeeded <pb facs="5422062_4_1049.jpg" n="2"/>in regaining our lost country and built it up to what it is in the present day. They were not afraid of misery, starvation, hardships. We of today should be ashamed to mar the name of these true Greeks by being afraid to face the future in a strange land.</p>
   <p>We have many traitors among us, traitors to the glorious name our forefathers built for us. We have come to a strange land and, forgetting the spirit of our forefathers, have let ourselves be classed as low, ignorant, uneducated "farmers."</p>
   <p>We Greeks have nothing to show for the years we have been here. Our progress has been very slow. This is the beginning of a new year, 1910. Let us show our forefathers that what they did has not been done in vain. Let us show them that their noble and patriotic blood runs in our veins. Let us make them proud of us, wherever they may be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
