<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1922-11-16">Nov. 16, 1922</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook, P. 120, of Mr. P. S. Lambros, 130 N. Wells Street, Chicago, Illinois.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial of the Day. Americanization (Recast from the Greek Star)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0980</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0980.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1922-11-16">Nov. 16, 1922</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook, P. 120, of Mr. P. S. Lambros, 130 N. Wells Street, Chicago, Illinois.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL OF THE DAY. AMERICANIZATION (Recast from the Greek Star)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our love for Greece, the Mediterranean country where the warm sun first shone on us, is great indeed; still we can confidently say that nothing could be farther from the truth than to suppose that this justifiable sentiment of ours infringes on our loyalty to America, the country of our adoption. In our opinion that man is not to be feared who bears in his bosom an affection for two countries but rather he who does not love any country at all.</p>
   <p>We know only too well, and we have said it and written it many times, that it is the obligation of all Greeks to do whatever they possibly can to promote the welfare of the country which receives them so hospitably and treats them with a liberality unknown anywhere else.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0981.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They should qualify at the earliest possible moment to become citizens of this great Republic so that they may fully identify themselves with her. They should remember that no other country grants this right of citizenship to people of foreign birth. Thus in France and also in Germany and elsewhere citizenship is regarded as an inherited privilege. To become naturalized as a Frenchman is almost an impossibility.</p>
   <p>America has shown herself especially noble during the last few years in contrast to her associates in the war. She alone of all countries has disdained any thought of despoiling the conquered. Unlike the others, she fought for an ideal and contented herself with overthrowing the political system of her opponent, and she did not choose to cast him into economical or political bondage or to trespass on him geographically.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0982.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our hearts swell with pride in the Star Spangled Banner when we reflect on the fact that it belongs to a nation which waged a great war merely for the cause of liberty; a country which as a nation shows the same humanity that is characteristic of well-bred individuals and consists in being kind even to those who are weaker than we or are not our equals in fortune and in rank.</p>
   <p>To be or to become Americans--what a privilege!</p>
   <p>What a glory it is to belong to the foremost commonwealth of the world, foremost not only in power and resources but in all the acts of peace; to be able to say that we too may share in the pride of calling Washington, Lincoln, and Franklin our own!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
