<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-12-20">Dec. 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Why Our Dances Are a Failure</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1433</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1433.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-12-20">Dec. 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WHY OUR DANCES ARE A FAILURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Three great balls were given last week in this city by the local chapter of the Panhellenic Order, the Saint George Tanias Society, and the Phoenix Club. No one, of course, has any doubt about the good intentions of these organizations in giving these magnificent dances for the entertainment of our people. But upon considering the financial results of these affairs, we observe that the Greeks of Chicago spent the huge sum of $1,500 this year without receiving any real enjoyment or profit. On the contrary, the committees could not meet the expenses, which were far in excess of the receipts.</p>
   <p>In discussing these annual social affairs we notice that this year's ball given by the Panhellenic Order was a miserable failure compared with the <pb facs="5422062_4_1434.jpg" n="2"/>brilliant affairs given in other years. Even the dance of the Phoenix Club proved to be a failure from both the financial and the social standpoint. The only organization which succeeded in offering the Greeks of Chicago a real treat was the Saint George Tanias Society, which made a net profit of $350.</p>
   <p>In attempting to discover the reason for these failures of the Panhellenic and Phoenix societies, we find that in the case of the former methods of organization and the arrangements were so poor, and the committees appointed so inefficient and sluggish, that failure was inevitable. It seems that the Panhellenic Order has lost its vitality and force, although there is no reason to believe that it cannot regain its old glory and prestige. On the other hand, the Phoenix Club is to be blamed for having spoiled one of its best opportunities to make a favorable impression on those who are contemplating membership in a great nationalistic society. It was obvious that the dance committee overruled itself somewhat. This organization <pb facs="5422062_4_1435.jpg" n="3"/>has made the people tired of the many socials which have been given over a short period of time.</p>
   <p>The success of the Tanias affair was due to the fact that the people have not been called upon to contribute and support its socials more than once a year. Moreover, the board of the society has worked systematically and wholeheartedly in the sale of tickets,in the selection of a suitable and first-class hotel ballroom or hall, and in the proper reception and entertainment of friends and guests.</p>
   <p>It is very unfortunate that these balls, judged as a whole, should have failed, since their success would have directly benefited our Greek schools.There is no excuse whatever for the failure of these attempts to support our churches and our charitable and educational institutions. The financial and executive committees of any organization that expects to receive the <pb facs="5422062_4_1436.jpg" n="4"/>full and unreserved support of the Greek community must seek at the very outset the support of the press, the consulate, and the priests.</p>
   <p>No organization, regardless of its power or influence, should undertake to solicit funds for any community or national cause without asking the full co-operation of the other major organizations, the consulate, and our church authorities. Let us hope that no other society or club of any kind will attempt to act independently when an appeal is made for a cause that concerns the entire Greek community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>One can well imagine how much our nationalistic, our communal, and our patriotic interests can be harmed when we think and do things out of purely selfish motives.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
