<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-04-05">April 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Celebration of Anniversary of Independence and Declaration of Democracy in Greece.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-04-05">April 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK CELEBRATION OF ANNIVERSARY OF INDEPENDENCE AND DECLARATION OF DEMOCRACY IN GREECE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the auspices of the Liberal Democratic Club, the celebration of Greek Independence and the Greco-historical event of Declaration of Democracy in Greece, took place, with thousands of Chicago Greeks Jubilantly celebrating, at the Logan Square Auditorium.</p>
   <p>"Long Live Democracy," in big letters, was written above the entrance, and embellished with the emblems of the two countries.</p>
   <p>The spacious halls of the Club, bedecked with American and Greek flags, and crammed with people, reverberated with "Long Live America and Greece" when the anthems of the two countries were played by the orchestra.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1627.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Attorney Geo. Kyriakopoulos, president of the Club, in a brilliant speech outlined the history of the Club which was founded in Athens, the day after King Constantine returned to Greece, and which is the first founded Greek Democratic Club in the world.</p>
   <p>The panegyric was delivered by Mr. Halepas, secretary of the Club. Dr. K. Haloulus, who served in the Asia Minor expedition and as decorated for heroism, spoke of the event of the day, characterizing it as "the beginning of a new circle for Greece".</p>
   <p>Dr. N. Salopoulos, publisher of Saloniki, in his rich and fluent Greek, wreathed Democracy with encomiums, and eulogistically outlined the usefulness of the Club.</p>
   <p>All the orators were cheered and acclaimed, but Democracy was deified in frenzied applause by the multitude. The speeches of the respective orators are published on another page.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
