<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-05-22">May 22, 1926</date>, p. 8
<title level="a">Housing of the Greek Element of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-05-22">May 22, 1926</date>, p. 8
<title level="a">HOUSING OF THE GREEK ELEMENT OF CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Without hurting the pride of the Greeks of Chicago regarding our housing conditions, it is a necessary prerequisite to tackle the situation without color and brush. Let us proceed step by step in our analytical way on the subject of housing and immorality.</p>
   <p>Over-crowded homes, due to inadequate housing facilities, or for any other cause, breed immorality. Immorality and its twin sister criminality, easily flourish in dark, overcrowded rooms where there is no privacy, and where the demands of modesty cannot be met. Privacy is needful to the young in order to maintain modesty which in turn is a strong aid to clean, healthful thinking.</p>
   <p>The reason some of our young Greek-Americans have the proclivity to become criminals and immoral is mostly attributed to bad housing conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0744.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Indifference and neglect of the physical and mental needs of the child causes lowered resistance to disease, and lowered moral resistance. Some one said recently, that the city tough is not born, but is made by tenement houses, streets, and alleys.</p>
   <p>Let us not shrink from the truth, let us turn directly to the picture. Many of our homes are, or maybe, impressive outside and oppressive inside. For the sake of saving a few dollars we compel our families to live like sardines in a can. Let us curtail our expenditures in other things, and facilitate and ameliorate our housing conditions. Body and soul must be born and nourished in healthy surroundings, if we are going to have healthy citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
