<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1924-02-09">Feb. 9, 1924</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Resolution.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-02-09">Feb. 9, 1924</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">RESOLUTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has come to the attention of the American Association of the Greek Community of Chicago, that there is now pending in Congress, legislation which, if passed, will practically result in the exclusion of Greek immigrants to this country.</p>
   <p>And as we do not believe that Congress is fully informed as to the situation in America, with reference to its population of Greek-American citizens, and the class and character of immigration today from Greece to the United States.</p>
   <p>Therefore, be it resolved, that we unanimously pass the following resolution, and that a copy of same, together with a brief setting up the facts with reference to Greek immigration, be forwarded to the Hon. Henry R. Rathbone, Congress-man-at-large from Illinois, requesting that he present the same to the proper committees in Congress.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1109.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And be it further resolved, that copies of said brief and resolution be also forwarded to all Illinois Congressmen and to both Senators from this state.</p>
   <p>The American Association of the Greek Community of Chicago in meeting assembled unanimously resolve.</p>
   <p>We do not believe in an open door immigration policy. We are firmly against it and we sincerely believe that the immigration laws should be enforced more rigidly and that there should be a stop to hundreds of aliens who come in monthly through other channels than those prescribed by the Immigration Department. We believe that those people who come in as stowaways and as"human smugglers" are not the kind of people that we want in this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1110.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Immigrants who have been expelled from their native countries are undesirable and they enter the United States to spread their propaganda.</p>
   <p>We believe, however, in reuniting families, and that American citizens should be able to bring over to this country their wives, children and parents, their sisters, if single or widows, their fiances, and their brothers if they are less than twenty-one years of age.</p>
   <p>We further believe that those aliens who have come into this country in good faith, and have declared their intention to become American citizens, should be allowed to bring over to this country their wives and children. We also believe that the law which was passed in September, 1922, allowing an American woman to retain her citizenship after she married an alien and denying citizenship to an alien woman who married an American should be repealed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1111.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The idea that families need not have common nationality is against the laws of nature and against the laws of civilization. It is preposterous to think that an American citizen who has married an English woman should go to the British government and ask protection for his wife.</p>
   <p>We believe in the restriction of immigration but earnestly insist that the provisions in the New Immigration Bill providing for admission on a basis of two per cent of the foreign citizens of each county here in 1890 is discriminating against the Greeks, because in 1890, there were very few Greeks in this country. The Greeks began coming to this country after 1890 and in the short time they have been here have made wonderful progress as patriotic American citizens, and have shown that they are an asset to our American citizenship.</p>
   <p>Paul Demos, President</p>
   <p>Geo. W. Prassas, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
