<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1919-07-05">July 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Fourth of July Should Also Be a Greek Holiday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-07-05">July 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOURTH OF JULY SHOULD ALSO BE A GREEK HOLIDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States has just celebrated the one hundred and forty-third anniversary of its independence. One hundred and forty-three years ago, this country threw off the British yoke. Since the time of the Achaean unified government, the next country to realize the strength of unity was America, which was followed by the French fifteen years later. It is a fact that the Americans were the first to realize the necessity for representative government. The states increased until we now have forty-eight. In the future all the Western Hemisphere will be under one form of government, as predicted by the Monroe Doctrine [sic].</p>
   <p>Liberty is the greatest gift of humanity--a gift from Greece. Ancient Greece fought for the freedom of the people and her fight is now being carried on by America.</p>
   <p>Had America not entered the war, the small countries of Europe would have lost their freedom, since the four great powers--England, France, Russia and Italy-- <pb facs="5422062_4_1649.jpg" n="2"/>are still under the old despotic rule.</p>
   <p>We are all familiar with peace treaties....and had America not been represented at the Peace Conference, Greece would have never realized her hope of reclaiming her lost lands.</p>
   <p>We as Greeks must give credit for our motherland's benefits to the American standards of freedom and democracy.</p>
   <p>Since America helped our national ambitions to materialize, what can we as Greeks do to repay this kindness?</p>
   <p>We should be good Americans, and follow the example of the 65,000 Greeks who joined the United States Army. We must be proud that we are Americans, and must take part in all American activities. We must celebrate this Fourth of July in Greece as a national holiday.</p>
   <p>Forward, then, Hellenes! Celebrate with the other followers of the Stars and <pb facs="5422062_4_1650.jpg" n="3"/>Stripes. Recite poems, give parades, and send telegrams to President Wilson.</p>
   <p>Remember that because of America's influence in the Peace Treaty, Greece holds a higher place--both here and in Europe--than the Turks, Bulgarians, and Rumanians.</p>
   <p>Hurrah for America!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
