<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-10-02">Oct. 2, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Wanted: a Candidate</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1051</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1051.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-10-02">Oct. 2, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">WANTED: A CANDIDATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not known, as yet, whether Mr. Argyros, the president of the church board of directors of the Greek community of Chicago, will be satisfied with the announcement that a second candidate has appeared or may appear for election to the office which Mr. Argyros has been occupying up to now as an "able administrator", according to the opinion of his partisan friends. There is no doubt whatever that the new candidate is awaited as a new Messiah, a savior, during election time, for, if we follow the elections of the Greek Community of Chicago, we shall see that Mr. Argyros has had no opponent in any of the recent elections. The present president has had to solve many problems. Because of many serious errors and harmful policies, however, he is very eager to let someone else assume the office of president. In some instances he will be very glad to see some one else at the helm who will have the courage to <pb facs="5422062_4_1052.jpg" n="2"/>untangle the mess which has been created in our community affairs. When such a candidate appears, he, like Archimedes, will exclaim, "Eureka, eureka". [Translator's note: "I have found (it), I have found (it)".] Nevertheless, he is still interested in the office.</p>
   <p>In reality the office of the president of the board of directors does not demand as much work as that which must be done by the executive and finance committee of the board of directors. In most cases, this committee is composed of members who are capable of doing only one thing, and that is, taking the collection basket around on Sundays and holidays. Our church executives bear high-sounding titles, but let not the people be deceived. We have such a mania for offices and titles without thinking of the responsibilities which must accompany them.</p>
   <p>We have written before about the proper leadership and organization of the Greek settlements and communities in America. It may be said that in the real sense <pb facs="5422062_4_1053.jpg" n="3"/>of the word, as yet, there is no well-organized Greek community in America. In most cases the present directing church committees do not represent the wishes and sentiments of the members of the communities. In spite of this, men like Mr. Argyros who occupy some office, think that these community organizations are in a position to control all the affairs of the Greeks of America. These people must be reminded that there are many other means by which the problems of the Greek immigrant can be solved successfully.</p>
   <p>The very fact that there are hardly any Greeks who are willing to become candidates for community or church offices is proof of the lack of faith our people have in the leadership of our institutions. This means that we have communities in name only; in reality they are inactive bodies that have no power to render real and constructive services.</p>
   <p>The need for new men, then, who will revitalize and reorganize our social, economic, and church forces, is imperative.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1054.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Inefficient and incapable church officers have done irreparable damage to our community. We wonder whether Mr. Argyros knows that only two years ago, inefficient administrators forced the church to spend five thousand dollars for court and attorneys' fees in trials involving church officers. Similar confusion and muddling have been noticed in the Greek community of New York City which was split into two enemy camps and two church communities. The Greek communities of Lynn and Lowell, Massachusetts, and that of San Francisco have also been involved in court actions because of administrative abuses and community election frauds.</p>
   <p>So, we must admit that as a whole and as individual communities we have not tried to select the best qualified men for public office. As yet we are not mature enough, politically, to stop this mockery during our annual elections. Is there an election without candidates? If we do not like a candidate, instead of trying to present a better one, we abstain from the election altogether and have nothing to do with the community and the institutions which it supports.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1055.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In several cases, as we mentioned before, some communities are split and form separate and independent communities.</p>
   <p>Mr. Argyros and the present administration of the church community need not worry too much about the coming elections. The Greeks of Chicago are determined to clean house this time by removing the incompetents and by electing a church executive and finance committee worthy of its mission.</p>
   <p>We have got to understand that the activities of our community must not be restricted to committee and officers' elections. There is so much work to be done in other fields of activity.</p>
   <p>Let us try to discover what the church administrations in recent years have done regarding sorely needed charitable and educational institutions. The Argyros administration too has done very, very little to support and encourage such institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1056.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Where is there in Chicago a Greek hospital? Or isn't this a great and indispensable community institution which should become the permanent possession of the Greek people of Chicago by finding suitable organizers, by planning and working systematically without having to depend upon the inefficiency of the executive committee of our present church community? Where is our gymnasium? Haven't the various and numerous athletic exhibitions and games among our youth proved that we have excellent athletes who need all the facilities to train and exercise their bodies? Again, shall we wait for the church committee to take action? I'm afraid that it will be a long wait.</p>
   <p>Or do we have any intellectual gatherings when there are so many hundreds of educated men and widely-known professional people among us? Our community is badly in need of an educational center to create a spirit of good will and conceive and discuss new ideas for our general improvement and welfare. Does anyone think that Mr. Argyros and his church committee can accomplish this? Many Americans have been following our progress; some have seen that we lack all <pb facs="5422062_4_1057.jpg" n="7"/>these social necessities. Among other things, we have been told that we should have evening schools and recreation centers for both adults and children. Reading rooms and small libraries are also sadly needed. Of course, we, the Greeks of Chicago, as well as all other foreign-born immigrants and minority races are very fortunate that such a great social center as Hull House on the West Side affords so many opportunities for education, recreation, and public amusement to non-Americans.</p>
   <p>All the activities and institutions which we should have demand capable and energetic men, who, if sought out and asked, will no doubt be generous enough to offer their services and skills for the common good. We should not rely upon the irregularly and hurriedly elected church officials and the cliques which support them to accomplish what we have been discussing.</p>
   <p>If we really want a new Greek community pulsating with life and activity, let us concentrate on and work for the realization of such social and educational <pb facs="5422062_4_1058.jpg" n="8"/>centers as we have outlined above and let the church work in its own sphere. The church leaders should not be led to believe that they can also be leaders outside the church, in social and educational matters.</p>
   <p>Let us bear constantly in mind that political cliques, partisan preferences, and noisy elections arrest the progress of society, especially that of our own fluid organizations. With concord and co-operation we will be assured of success and progress.</p>
   <p>So, let us remind Mr. A. Argyros that the election of a new president of the church board of directors is really unimportant and inconsequential. If he desires a new president he can insert a notice in the want ad section of the newspapers saying: "Wanted: A Candidate." Mere elections lead us nowhere. What we need is a realignment of all our community forces.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
