<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-04-24">Apr. 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Quarter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1019</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1019.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-04-24">Apr. 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK QUARTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the small church of Holy Trinity was bought twenty years ago, many Greek coffeehouses, grocery stores, and saloons on Halsted, Polk, and Blue Island Streets transformed this section of the city into a Little Greece. This is where one could come from his home town in Greece and feel that he is still in the market place of his village or town, among the teaming activity of a genuinely Greek environment.</p>
   <p>Twenty years ago, it would have been quite easy for the first Greek immigrants of Chicago to buy property in the neighborhood of the present Greek quarter for a very low price. Especially the first arrivals should have purchased important buildings as well as small homes for a very reasonable price. Today, however, because of increased demand, property values and rents have soared to great heights. As a natural consequence, no one will even think of making any purchases at this time.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1020.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many thousands of large Greek families have been confined to a filthy, diseased, and stuffy section of the city with narrow, dirty streets and a most repulsive atmosphere. If you will ask the doctors, you will find that the rarest and most curious maladies are playing havoc with the Greek people, and especially with the small children, among whom the mortality is terrific because of the lack of fresh air.</p>
   <p>Hundreds of Greek families have clustered around the Greek school on the West Side. The prospective occupants of every home which has been for rent in this section have largely been Greeks, because of the desire of the parents to live as near the Greek school as possible, so that the children will not have to travel far from home in order to learn the Greek as well as the English language.</p>
   <p>But, above all, our children need fresh air and a wholesome environment, these two indispensable prerequisites of a healthy and pleasant community are not found at Halsted Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1021.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Naturally, the Greek community in Chicago, like our towns and cities in Greece, will be formed around our churches, our schools, and our business establishments--hotels, restaurants, grocery stores, and amusement centers. These are the essential points which we shall discuss today.</p>
   <p>About three thousand Greeks in Chicago operate their own businesses within the narrow confines and congested business centers of the city proper. Only a few Greeks are financially independent to the extent that they can have their homes at some distance from the noise, confusion, and unhealthy atmosphere of the central part of the city. They establish their residences in many instances in the outskirts of the city, in order to enjoy and breathe the fresh air. How fortunate are those well-to-do Greek families that can live just within Chicago's city limits or in the clean and healthy suburbs, where their childrens' health and normal development are assured!</p>
   <p>Up to now, very few families have been able to live in their own homes. They should be informed, however, that merely with the rent that they are now paying, <pb facs="5422062_4_1022.jpg" n="4"/>they can afford eventually to buy a home of their own.</p>
   <p>There are quite a number of Greek families that are scattered among other foreign or exclusive neighborhoods. Such families, unfortunately, face the unhappy prospect of losing contact with one another. This is partly overcome by the tendency of wealthy Greek families to move closer to the heart of the city when fall comes. Also, many of the families scattered about in the city are forced to move to some even more densely populated section or neighborhood where social contacts with other Greeks are more frequent. Thus, for many Greek families the first of May is moving day.</p>
   <p>If only one tenth of the total number of these fairly well-to-do Greek families would agree to occupy a definite, suitable section of the city by purchasing a large number of buildings and homes there, the problem of establishing a beautiful and attractive Greek center and residential district would be solved. This can be accomplished also if one hundred Greek businessmen took the initiative in buying entire blocks of lots on which large buildings and numerous homes <pb facs="5422062_4_1023.jpg" n="5"/>could be profitably built. This is where the Greek community would be established; this is where our beautiful church would be erected; this is where our great modern schools would be constructed, which would house all the young Greek students and thus take them away from the polluted and diseased atmosphere, from the smoke-filled and drab manufacturing district to a clean, healthful, and pleasant atmosphere. All these suggestions will seem novel and amusing to those who know little or nothing about real estate.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, may we suggest that anyone having one hundred dollars and paying twenty dollars monthly for rent can, within five years, become the owner of a beautiful one-family bungalow home within the city limits of Chicago and in a wonderful location? At the end of this period you will own a home worth three thousand dollars. In contrast, the average Greek family today pays from fifteen to twenty or twenty-five dollars monthly for rent and lives in filthy homes and a depressing atmosphere in the condemned neighborhoods of Halsted Street or Grand Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1024.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The united Greek community of Chicago could enlighten and assist the thousands of Greek families in securing their future and their happiness by building or buying a new home. The organized Greek community will teach the poorer families how to protect the health of their children.</p>
   <p>Now how can we establish a purely Greek quarter which shall be the accumulated property--representing a value of millions of dollars--of our Greek people? Surely, only when our community forces are united, when we pool the intellectual resources of all the good Greeks for the benefit of all our fellow countrymen, when we build the foundations of a new church and a new school at a suitable location which guarantees health, and when one hundred Greek businessmen form a corporation that will negotiate the purchase of thousands of lots for the establishment of a new Greek quarter.</p>
   <p>Only then will the Greek people of Chicago become truly strong, only then will they properly organize and prosper, only then will they live in comfort and be considered the best, the most progressive, and the most remarkable Greek community in the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1025.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>If two or three "phony" and swindling Greek bankers can succeed in collecting three hundred thousand dollars in deposits from the Greek people of Chicago for the [ostensible] purpose of buying real estate for these depositors, but in reality to rob them, cannot one hundred businessmen collect an equal amount of money to build a new Greek settlement? For three hundred thousand dollars one can buy three thousand lots within Chicago's city limits and an equal number of homes can be built on them.</p>
   <p>We realize that these are bold thoughts, and that our discussion of our plans for the future bears the mark of our customary optimism. If our thoughts and plans materialize, however, it will be because we have faith in our ability and because we are determined to work, think, and act together for the attainment of common objectives. Our very first and most urgent objective is to lay the foundation for a new Greek community. To do this, we must first of all unite. All other considerations are really secondary.</p>
   <p>In suggesting the many methods by which we can improve ourselves, Saloniki desires <pb facs="5422062_4_1026.jpg" n="8"/>to remind its many friends and all those who espouse the cause of a united and consolidated community to extend their efforts further by appealing to the boards and leaders of our three churches. They are the ones who must initiate and give impetus to the unification movement. When this is accomplished, we will then consider everything else that we require.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
