<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-09-18">Sept. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Kaffenia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-09-18">Sept. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE KAFFENIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first signs of autumn are the cause of great joy to the individuals who own Kaffenia (cafes). When it is cold outside, all the laborers, all the men who have a few hours off in the afternoon, will hasten to wedge themselves into a cafe. I say "wedge themselves" because it is practically impossible to even find standing room in these establishments on cold days.</p>
   <p>The atmosphere is thick with the smoke of the pipes, cigarettes and cigars of the customers. Through these clouds of smoke the dim figures of would-be orators can be seen, and their stentorian voices can be heard discoursing on practically any subject under the sun. No subject is feared by them. European and foreign problems are solved very easily, but they all reach their forte when Greek politics is the subject.</p>
   <p>Strange pictures appear upon the marble-topped tables; divisions of the Near East are drawn, military strategies, and imaginary Russian retreats are also <pb facs="5422062_4_0755.jpg" n="2"/>to be found. Here, also, is a plan for the bombing of the Dardanelles, and next to it a sketch of Venizelos.</p>
   <p>At these same tables, the hard-earned dollars of honest workers are lost in card games to not so honest professional cardsharps.</p>
   <p>In the Kaffenia of America, one can see practically every type of individual that the wave of immigration has brought to these shores. Many of these individuals were ruined because of their lack of success in the competitive business world. Mental and physical wrecks are present in large numbers, a nice collection of diseases is always represented.</p>
   <p>Therefore, not only is the moral welfare of the individual in danger, but his physical power is threatened also. Many well-meaning young men or simple laborers become wrecked mentally; and usually they acquire some deadly sickness or disease from the impure air in these cafes. And the poolrooms are no better!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0756.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Sensible young men should spend their spare time attending night school in order to improve themselves physically and mentally, and should not patronize these places that can only bring about their downfall.</p>
   <p>We do not intend to condemn the Greek cafes in their entirety, as many of them are clean and well ventilated; nevertheless, great care should be taken by the cafe patrons. If any one believes otherwise, he would probably change his mind if he studied the police records, and if he saw the large number of Greek gamblers and owners of cafes who have been brought before the courts on all kinds of charges</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
