<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1927-03-05">March 5, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">National Egotism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0954</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0954.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1927-03-05">March 5, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">National Egotism.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reader of history will notice that besides the many national characteristics, the ancient Greek, was imbued with a marked National Egotism. Strong evidence of this is the ancient Greek saying, "He who is not a Greek is a Barbarian." Later, the Romans using the Greek axiom as a basis , paraphrased that to, "When you are in Rome, do as the Romans do," which is practically adopted now by all the people of the different nationalities. For example, the British people think, that no one else is comparable to them, that London is the Metropolis of all the Nations. The American people believe that they are a hundred years ahead of all other peoples, in progress. The Germans, that they hold the scepter of culture and chemistry; the French, that they are the University of Science, Politeness, and Liberty; the Austrians, that they are the Pantheon of Aristocracy; and the Italians, that they are the heirs of the Fine Arts. Therefore the above mentioned Nations and others, adhering to National Egotism developed respectively <pb facs="5422062_4_0955.jpg" n="2"/>the dogmatism, that the gains, prosperity, and everything that is good belongs. if not exclusively, always preferable, to the natives born of that country, respectively.</p>
   <p>Exception to the above general rule, of National dogma, is only the United States of America. The American people believe in Equality and Justice; they live and let live. Such humanitarian, just, and uplifting methods of the American people were the causes which induced initially, practically every immigrant to become an American citizen, sooner or later, and eventually the causes which brought about the assimilation of the former immigrant as an integral part of this great country. Even the Greek, who until yesterday, attempted to remain tenaciously a Greek, believing that it would be impossible for him to become anything else, lost his National Egotism, and became an American.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
