<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1918-05-18">May 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Red Cross</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-05-18">May 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE RED CROSS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Red Cross is a symbol of victory as well as of the welfare of all peoples. It is the only consolation for the sick; it is the symbol of the martyrdom of our Lord Jesus Christ for the salvation of mankind.</p>
   <p>Finally, the Red Cross is an agency of mercy and kindness offering life-saving succor to the wounded and to our brothers who are fighting for faith and country.</p>
   <p>Hasten to support a great institution which is functioning in the name of the cross! Help increase its material resources! Remember what the Master said: "....And while in hunger ye fed me, while thirsty ye gave me to drink, while in sickness ye attended me."</p>
   <p>That is what our brothers will say to all those who make their offering for the relief and healing of the wounds of our countrymen, shedding their blood on the battlefield in order to protect us.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0451.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If they were willing to leave behind their loved ones, their goods, to go to war to fight for our common country, in which are our possessions and interests, endangering their very lives, then those of us who remain at home and enjoy all these goods must offer our material support to the common struggle, on the happy outcome of which our destiny also depends.</p>
   <p>If we disregard these our sacred duties, and if we do not obediently heed the parental admonition of our great country, which, through our adored leader [Translator's note: Mr. Venizelos] and its government, advises and urges us by frantic appeals to make every possible sacrifice, then humiliating and disastrous defeat is our only alternative. Then, how can the Red Cross or any other agency heal the wounds inflicted by a fierce enemy?</p>
   <p>This is a question which everyone should ask himself.</p>
   <p>Daily we read of the wounds that the enemy is inflicting upon us. Continually, we hear of the development of new instruments of revenge, destruction, and <pb facs="5422062_4_0452.jpg" n="3"/>fanaticism on the part of our enemy. From every quarter we hear about the atrocities and cannibalistic barbarisms perpetrated by the savage Hun. Children are massacred; women dishonored and butchered; men killed and disembowled like cattle; while the tongues of our captured brave men are cut off, and their eyes put out. Innumerable acts of savagery, and atrocities are committed against us.</p>
   <p>while all this is taking place and while the enemy is becoming more ferocious and more dangerous, who will not strive to offer the greatest possible assistance for our own safety?</p>
   <p>Let us rush to support the Red Cross willingly that our wounded brothers may recover and defeat the enemy and, thus, safeguard our lives.</p>
   <p>If we pay insurance premiums to protect our relatives after we die, is it not more reasonable to pay a premium to insure and prolong our life? This is another benefit afforded by the Red Cross, and again it proves that it is the <pb facs="5422062_4_0453.jpg" n="4"/>best insurance company for our life and safety.</p>
   <p>Let us all, then, stop before the Red Cross box and contribute generously whatever we can afford both for the aid of our fighting brothers and for our own safety.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
