<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-01-20">Jan. 20, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">New Year's at the Chicago Greek Consulate</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1629</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1629.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-01-20">Jan. 20, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">NEW YEAR'S AT THE CHICAGO GREEK CONSULATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the afternoon of New Years Day, after the holiday religious ceremonies, the Chicago Greek consulate opened its doors for the first time in the new year to welcome the families of the Greek colony and to wish them a Happy New Year.</p>
   <p>The sincere invitation extended by the new and progressive consul general, Mr. Vasilios Mammonas, was warmly received by the Greeks of our colony, and they hastened to exchange holiday greetings with the consul and to show their respect and their appreciation.</p>
   <p>The Greek consulate, redecorated and refurnished, had been transformed into a first-class Consular office. Pastries, cigars, and cigarettes had been placed upon tables at the disposal of visitors. Many bouquets of flowers had been sent to the consul general by his friends and admirers, and the four rooms of the consulate were transformed into a beautiful flower-garden.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1630.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From 2:30 P.M. the colony, which consists of people of various walks of life, paid its respects to the consul general, feeling a thrill of national pride as they entered the consulate.</p>
   <p>The new consul general, Mr. Vasilios Mammonas, the vice-consul, Mr. Trinketa, and the secretary, Mr. Tsiope, received the visitors. The receiving hours appointed were from half past two to five in the afternoon, but because of the great crowd which continued to arrive special permission was obtained of the office of the building to prolong the reception to seven o'clock.</p>
   <p>The beginning of a new consular regime in Chicago, offering its services not from 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. but from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., with many other changes, has brought hearty congratulations from our colony to the consul general and to the Greek Government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
