<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-06-01">June 1, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Three Thousand Greek Boys in Slavery--An Organized Syndicate--Greek Church Behind the Slavery Movement--Fantastic Stories of the Daily News.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-06-01">June 1, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THREE THOUSAND GREEK BOYS IN SLAVERY--AN ORGANIZED SYNDICATE--GREEK CHURCH BEHIND THE SLAVERY MOVEMENT--FANTASTIC STORIES OF THE DAILY NEWS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1--At whatever cost and by whatever means Greeks and the reputation of Greeks must be abused in order to make news. The Chicago Daily News recently published an article blackening the Greek name so much that not only did Greeks resent it, but many prominent Americans also thought that these fantastic stories were pure vagaries, emanating from the news-hungry mind of a reporter. Greeks make good news-items; hence the fantastic story.</p>
   <p>"It has been discovered that a well-organized body of Greeks exists in Chicago of which the object is to exploit Greek boys. Three thousand Greek boys in the city of Chicago are kept as slaves, working for the bosses of the syndicate for only their food and their clothing.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0598.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Prominent members of the Greek community are the heads of the syndicate, and colossal sums of money are spent for the upkeep and the functioning of the slavery syndicate.</p>
   <p>"The Greek churches in America tacitly encourage the movement for pecuniary profit; when more boys come to America, the Greek communities are increased, and the Church's income is increased in consequence."</p>
   <p>All the Greek clubs in Chicago, all the societies, and the Greek Business Men's Association recently held a meeting attended by representatives of the Church and resolved to petition the United States Government to use its iron hand to uncover the alleged syndicate of exploitation and if it exists to prosecute those who are guilty in the federal courts. They further resolved to request the Daily News, for the good of all concerned, to make public all the facts concerning the so-called organized body of exploitation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0599.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A reply to these charges was prepared by K. N. Karalopoulos and sent to the Daily News for publication. This reply the paper has published in full.</p>
   <p>Mr. Karalopoulos emphatically denied the existence of such an organized syndicate slavery, and pointed out that not only will Greeks appreciate the exposure of the syndicate, but the United States Government will also be assisted by them to the utmost in uncovering this unlawful organization. The Government is more interested than anybody else for the simple reason that if the syndicate really exists, the Government should and will get after it, unearth it, and put an end to it.</p>
   <p>As for the participation of prominent Greeks in the alleged syndicate, this is absurd because no prominent Greeks the world over ever stoop so low; it is not in their blood. History tells us that prominent Greeks in order to become and remain prominent have refrained from all practices which would impair their prominence.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0600.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Bloodsucking is not in the Greek's nature. He may, as a human being, have certain weaknesses, but he never permits himself to fall so low as that.</p>
   <p>As for the statement that the Greek Orthodox Church, that pillar of granite in Christendom which for centuries has stood out as the symbol of true Christianity, has tacitly encouraged the exploitation of Greek boys in order that the Church may profit financially, it is no less than blasphemy against that holy institution of Christ. Those who know the Greek Church and its rulers will substantiate the statement that it is the holiest institution of Christ on earth. Kings, emperors, czars, and sultans have failed in their endeavors to turn the Greek Church from its right and just course. Bribery and pressure have been used to compel the Greek Church, that pure and true mother of Christianity, to be subservient to the wishes of the various civil rulers in whose territory she has wrought, but her immortal clergy have preferred death to submission to the unchristian designs of tyrants.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0601.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>No earthly power, no earthly gain, and no earthly inducement will ever be able to thwart the Greek Church's divine mission. It is really unmanly to attack the Greek Church with accusations so fantastic.</p>
   <p>It is an indisputable fact, as official records show, that the Greek Church for ethnological reasons, is not in favor of Greek emigration. But if her communicants wish to go to the four corners of the earth, she, the Church, must go with her subjects to imbue religious, racial, and educational principles in them that this immortal race may survive through the ups and downs of life among this world's varied civilizations.</p>
   <p>The allegation that three thousand boys are acting as slaves here in Chicago for the bosses of the syndicate is also silly and incredible. Why, the whole community comprises only eight thousand Greeks, and there are no more than one hundred or one hundred and fifty boys.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0602.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It is true that Greek boys as well as adults are working hard and working through long hours, but work and progress is their middle name. Every month these boys, true to their religious and racial traditions, send home to their parents a certain portion of their earnings. Every Greek boy who comes to America is under the immediate supervision of a parent, a relative, or a friend of the boy's family. We have no stray youngsters to be picked up and lured into a syndicate of any kind. If the alleged organized body of exploitation really exists, then a parent, a brother, a relative, or a friend of every boy in it is connected with the syndicate to bleed the youngsters. But where do the great sums of money sent to Greece every month come from if the boys were kept in slavery and receive only food and clothing? Absurd, illogical, and pure fabrication!</p>
   <p>The only truth which this fantastic story contains is the fact that Greeks, old and young, work hard for many hours each day in order to accomplish their object. That is in accordance with divine law; nothing worth while can be accomplished without a struggle. And the Greek immigrant, who as a rule lacks experience in any trade and does not speak the language of the land and yet is determined to become somebody <pb facs="5422062_4_0603.jpg" n="7"/>in this, his new country, of necessity must work to compete with others who have the advantage of him. Work, hard work, and plenty of it to achieve his object is what every boy is taught before he leaves his home for America.</p>
   <p>The writer of the exploitation story might have avoided much exasperation, misunderstanding, mud-slinging, and abuse if he had honestly investigated the facts concerning the so-called syndicate of exploitation, which is a myth.</p>
   <p>We request the Daily News and the law enforcing agencies of this country to delve into these allegations and to bring out the truth. And after so doing they should then render justice to the accused Greeks and to the Greek name; and the blasphemous charges uttered against the Greek Orthodox Church should be withdrawn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
