<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-08-28">Aug. 28, 1929</date><title level="a">The Reception of the Ahepan Representatives</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-08-28">Aug. 28, 1929</date><title level="a">THE RECEPTION OF THE AHEPAN REPRESENTATIVES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A body of Ahepan representatives for the Kansas City Convention, from the Eastern cities, were given a reception in Chicago, Saturday, by the various chapters.</p>
   <p>At 10 o'clock in the morning, the representatives were met at the Union station by a committee. Many other members were there to welcome them. Everyone piled into cars and drove down Michigan Blvd. to Grant Park where the Ahepans placed a wreath on Lincoln's monument and were photographed.</p>
   <p>From there they went north through Lincoln Park till they came to Solon school of St. James Church, where the visitors expressed amazement at the building and congratulated the Greeks of Chicago for having such a wonderful school.</p>
   <p>A sumptuous banquet was awaiting them at the Oak Park Arms Hotel, prearranged by George Kokkinos, Chairman of the Reception Committee. A very delightful program followed the banquet. Some of the participants were: Themis Georgiou, Andrew Vlahos, Spiros Bekatoros, and P. Vournas.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1891.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our Supreme Governor of the 8th District, P. G. Sikokis welcomed the visitors and was followed by A. Katsonis who spoke on behalf of the visiting representatives.</p>
   <p>Among those representing the Eastern cities were: Former president Mr. Tsimpides; treasurer, Mr. Gobatos; Governors Bournas, Beras, and Tzanetis and a member of the Supreme Consul, Mr. Tsakadas. The Eastern and Chicago representatives all left on the 7 o'clock train for Kansas City.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
