<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Red Cross</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE RED CROSS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Certain individuals of our Greek community in Chicago, feeling the need for an expression of gratitude toward this our adopted country--a country which welcomed all of us with open arms when we were lonely immigrants--decided to form a committee to organize a Greek Campaign for the Red Cross. The members of the committee are: Andrew Vlachos, chairman; John Alex, secretary; Geo. P. Chiagouris, treasurer; Peter Tzoumis, Demo. Papatony, Constantine Johnson, and Thomas Valos.</p>
   <p>Now that America and the Allies are in trouble in their fight for justice and liberty, it is the duty of the Greeks to show their willingness to do all in their power to help them. The Red Cross received their offer of help gladly, and officially recognized the Greek campaign.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This committee, made up of prominent men in the Greek community, sent out seven hundred letters to our most active citizens asking their co-operation in this campaign. The Masonic Temple was chosen as the headquarters for the campaign, and a meeting was called for last Sunday evening at seven o'clock.</p>
   <p>On the appointed day the committee was in its place, and ready to welcome the patriotic and philanthropic members of the Greek community who had responded to the earnest call of their country.</p>
   <p>But the overflowing house they expected to see did not materialize. Instead of thousands of interested people responding to this holy cause, they saw a sea of empty chairs; only occasionally did they see a human being as their unbelieving eyes swept over the house. The whole number present, including the committee, amounted to twenty-five people. The hour had passed and the faces of everyone reflected their feelings of despair and disillusionment.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0477.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Then a voice from above seemed to say, "Take courage, my children; do not fear. You hold in your hands the deadliest of weapons, the Cross, on which are the words 'By this shall we conquer'. And you shall conquer! Forward to your duty, and the Cross shall emblazon you with the glory you deserve, to the sadness of those who did not respond to the call of the Cross."....</p>
   <p>With unfaltering steps Mr. A. Vlachos, approached the speaker's dais; and explained the purposes and intentions of the committee of which he is president. He emphasized the necessity for doing our share despite the terribly apparent indifference of most of our Greek community. Upon conclusion of his inspired speech the small audience applauded vigorously.</p>
   <p>The Reverend C. Hadzidimitriou was the second speaker, and he discussed the matter from a religious standpoint.....Then Mr. C. Paleologos discussed the Red Cross, saying that it is to our advantage to show our interest in <pb facs="5422062_4_0478.jpg" n="4"/>anything that benefits America.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was the well-known Mr. D. Eftaxias, who showed his usual deep interest in patriotic undertakings.</p>
   <p>Mr. Chiagouris characterized the purpose as a lofty one, and insisted that the community again be approached and made to realize its duty; whereupon it would rally to the support of the Committee.</p>
   <p>It was decided that the present committee should remain in command of the campaign. At this point we wish to acknowledge the co-operation of the Greek concern, Peppas and Alex, and Mr. J. Alex, partner of the concern.</p>
   <p>The central committee then appointed sub-committees for the various districts as determined by the American Red Cross.</p>
   <p>A suggestion was made that before the community was approached for donations, <pb facs="5422062_4_0479.jpg" n="5"/>the immediate group should start the ball rolling. The first man to respond was the successful merchant Mr. C. Johnson who gave $100. The same amount was given by Mr. Chiagouris, Mr. Alex, and Mr. Christ Zoes. Other amounts were given by....In all $723.00 was collected.</p>
   <p>Everyone is duty bound to be present at the next meeting which will be held in the Masonic Temple next Monday at 7 P. M.</p>
   <p>The Greek Community of Chicago must attend this meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
