<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-01-22">Jan. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Beginning of the End</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0658</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0658.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-01-22">Jan. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE BEGINNING OF THE END</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are honored by having the privilege of printing the pictures of Mr. A. Pantelis and Mr. Resa in this issue of the Saloniki. They are the two Chicago lawyers who succeeded in gathering the evidence against those four Chicago bankers who are by now notorious for fraudulent practices.</p>
   <p>They gathered enough conclusive proof to convince the district attorney of the guilt of these men. At last the eight hundred depositors will have a chance to fight for their life-long savings, which they were unfortunate enough to trust to a pack of wolves.</p>
   <p>The two lawyers have worked for a long time in an effort to collect evidence against these men. They had help from no one, except the staff of <pb facs="5422062_4_0659.jpg" n="2"/>the Saloniki, and three or four of the depositors. The other 795 depositors were of little or no help because some of them were employed by the railroads and were far from Chicago, and others were misled by the promises of reimbursement made to them by the bankers.</p>
   <p>At the last moment it looked as if the bankers were to be declared innocent because the victims were not represented by a good lawyer, and were ignorant of what course to follow.</p>
   <p>The timely entrance of Mr. Pantelis changed the situation of the depositors. The fraudulent activities of the four bankers were exposed, and they could not escape their fate, when the jury heard the truth.</p>
   <p>Now the four gentlemen anxiously await the verdict. At any moment they expect to feel the heavy hand of the law upon their shoulders--a hand weighted with exactly $138,000 worth of guilt.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0660.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Even the best and most accomplished crooks make some mistake, or overlook something of value when they are plying their trade. Our friends are no exception. It has been found that there was ninety-six dollars in the bank which they forgot to take. Better luck next time! When Mr. Pantelis was asked to give his opinion of the case, he said that he had only done his duty as a Greek; and that he could not stand idle and see his fellow countrymen cheated out of their hard-earned savings without making a sincere effort to prevent it. He also thanked the Saloniki for keeping the issue before the public, and for giving him so much support.</p>
   <p>Neither of the lawyers expressed any hope of having the money returned to the investors by the bankers of their own free will.</p>
   <p>Both insist that even if the money is never returned to the owners, at least the fraudulent bankers will be punished for their crime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
