<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-05-02">May 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Second Generation Actually Can Maintain its National Background</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-05-02">May 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND GENERATION ACTUALLY CAN MAINTAIN ITS NATIONAL BACKGROUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every time we concern ourselves with our community and our community life an effort is made to evade those issues which are debatable and intangible....</p>
   <p>Our contentions are summarized in this fashion: Since the Hellenism of America is distant in tens of years and in social consciousness from Greece, it is the duty of the older and the newer generation, in combined effort, to create ideal Greek communities. These groups should be organized and conducted in such a manner that every Greek will be able to find therein an ideal setup for the maintenance and usage of his national background.....</p>
   <p>We were not carried along by our patriotic feelings when formulating this belief. It is because we question the fact that our people can ever be <pb facs="5422062_4_0844.jpg" n="2"/>completely obliterated and assimilated into the diverse but unified population of America, even if we set aside all of our national customs, beliefs, and practices. This contention has recently been strengthened by our observance of the church attendance during Holy Week and...the not-so-recently developed but continuous tremendous support of Greek affairs and lodges.</p>
   <p>That which, perhaps, impressed us most was the large percentage of young people at the church services partaking in the ceremonies with undisguised zeal and fervor. Reference is not being made to the very young children who, perforce, must obey the will of their parents, but rather to the young men and women who go where and when they choose. These young people have finally begun to comprehend the great part they are to play in our Greek community life. Social contacts will naturally develop as an outgrowth of that participation; and since the social life of an individual molds many of his concepts, customs, and habits, it is not unreasonable to suppose that these young people will grow in the Greek environment into true Greek individuals.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0845.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Of course, this statement will be doubted and questioned by many of our readers. One from St. Louis says he is certain that obliteration will come about in time because the members of the younger generation speak English even in the church; which proves, he contends, that they do not understand and are not even interested in the sermon and the liturgy. We cannot answer his contention in this article because it would entail consideration of other related matters. As, for instance: Does the liturgy have to be in Greek in the future?....</p>
   <p>These things are of secondary nature in our estimation. The pertinent and primary problem is the keeping of the younger generation within our national atmosphere. These young people can be kept within our social structure if we make it a flexible one. There is no reason, for example, why our affairs cannot be conducted in the English language, which is more comprehensible to them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
