<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1936-06-25">June 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1929</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1929.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1936-06-25">June 25, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not one or two, but myriads are the reasons for the unification of the Chicago Greek Churches. Since this city is the headquarters for the Bishop, and most of the Greek people are aware of the immediate need for action to prevent the loss of more community property--two churches are already in the hands of receivers--and public opinion is strongly in favor of unity, it puzzles us to know what factors are preventing this unification from taking place. The advantages to be enjoyed from a central governing body are obvious to anyone who has the slightest understanding of organization efficiency.</p>
   <p>A unified community will have the necessary strength to impose certain obligations upon indifferent factors of the community and influence them to take an active, beneficial part in the church program. A unified, directoral <pb facs="5422062_4_1930.jpg" n="2"/>body will bring a system--and results--analogous to the Catholic Church. We are constantly admiring their accomplishments but never imitate their methods to an extent that would enable us--like them--to send the majority of our Greek-American children to our own private schools.</p>
   <p>Following their example, we too could have large community centers and all types of social services available to our people. As a result of this amalgamation, expenses would naturally be lowered while profits would be increased. The benefits for the average church-goer would also be plentiful. Many unnecessary fees could be eliminated if the Bishop's offices and the central Orthodox Church offices of Chicago were in the same place. For the first time, the services in all the Greek churches would be uniform in text, order, and time.....</p>
   <p>We could have a capable superintendent for our Hellenic schools and an extra <pb facs="5422062_4_1931.jpg" n="3"/>priest to officiate at emergency periods.</p>
   <p>Now, we do without the benefit of these aids, as if we still lived in the blackness and ignorance of the Dark Ages.</p>
   <p>All these things can be ours if certain individuals will realize that there is no other way to save our institutions. They must not allow their own selfishness to destroy them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
