<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-07-12">July 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Path of Duty Is Ahead of Us</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_2018</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_2018.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-07-12">July 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE PATH OF DUTY IS AHEAD OF US</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As much as we desire to laud the condition of our social institutions, it is impossible to say a word of praise about our greatest and most important institutions--our churches and parishes. It is very true that the mine Greek Orthodox churches in the city of Chicago have succeeded in staying open, but this, in itself, should not be considered an accomplishment. They are all just one jump ahead of their creditors and always in danger of fereclosure. We cannot discuss such a thing as a church treasury, because all of them are empty.....and burdened with large debts.</p>
   <p>The worst part of it all is that as time passes, instead of decreasing, the debts continually increase--despite the fact that no increase of activity and no sign of progress is evident as justification for the evergrowing debt. In fact, our parish activities continually decrease.....The only things we are not deprived of are the Sunday and holiday and saint day observances. We are of the opinion that the <pb facs="5422062_4_2019.jpg" n="2"/>destined purpose of our churches is not merely to hold weekly church services. No one disagrees with this contention except those few who are natural opposi-tionists, and who never agree with the rest of the people...</p>
   <p>The matter speaks for itself. If preventative and curative measures are not taken soon, the damage will be beyond repair. There will be nothing left for anyone to salvage. Not, of course, an immediate disappearance of our churches and parishes, but a steady decline in influence, power, and prestige will take place until they shall have become hollow shells that soon will crumble away into nothingness.....</p>
   <p>The only salvation our tattering churches can find will be in the unselfish, un-egotistical co-operation between the leaders of the Greek Community, and also in the logical unification of our parishes into one undivided body, centrally governed.....The present individualistic attitude can lead to nothing less than chaos. Past experience should have taught us the truth of that. No one contradicts the fact that the fifty thousand Greeks in Chicago have left nothing and have planned nothing to leave for the future; which speaks very highly of them. Under a centralized system, our chances for noteworthy achievements would be more than <pb facs="5422062_4_2020.jpg" n="3"/>multiplied. The duty before us is as plain as a well-marked highway. It is to our benefit, and it is also our duty to follow it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
