<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-04-10">Apr. 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Blessing of God and Country</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1027</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1027.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-04-10">Apr. 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE BLESSING OF GOD AND COUNTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>United we stand; divided we fall. Our national ideology demands that our national forces become united. Every Greek of Chicago must do his utmost to bring about this union. The noble and patriotic example of the priests and doctors of Chicago must be emulated by all. Our enthusiasm for celebrating the national Greek holiday together must take on a practical character.</p>
   <p>The priests of our three Greek churches of Chicago are living examples of the great apostles of a united Greek nation, and as true Greek priests they have proclaimed through the columns of Saloniki to the Greeks of America that the entire community of America, and Chicago especially, must unite. The reverend fathers have worked and are still working hard to unite our community and religious forces by preaching from the pulpit and thus drawing the people's attention to the blessings that will come to us.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1028.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We also have the twenty-four professional men within our Greek community who are united under the same banner, and who are doing all in their power to support our priesthood and the press in making a success out of the idea of a united Greek community of Chicago. It is fitting that they should band together on the occasion of the anniversary of our National Independence Day.</p>
   <p>Our priests' idea of a united community has been accepted by those good Christians among us, who attend Mass on Sundays and who fill our churches to listen to the divine services and the soul-stirring sermons. These are the ones that are contributing their money for the upkeep and progress of the work of the churches.</p>
   <p>In the name of faith and country, the boards of directors of our three separate and independent churches must abide by the wishes of the members and bring about the union that all of us are demanding. But even the public opinion of the twenty-five thousand Greeks of Chicago, regardless of whether most of us attend church regularly or not, is for this union. This is corroborated by the judgment which was expressed by our professional men whose names we have featured <pb facs="5422062_4_1029.jpg" n="3"/>prominently in our previous issue.</p>
   <p>Every professional man is a true representative of the attitude and wishes of the people of the particular province of Greece from which he comes. Without exception, we say that in the persons of our twenty-four professional men, all the small provinces and districts of both liberated and unredeemed Greece are ably represented. Because the banner of our union is as significant to us as our national flag, our leaders invite all Greeks in common and brotherly loyalty to celebrate the anniversary of our national independence.</p>
   <p>"United we stand; divided we fall." This is the motto of Saloniki, the newspaper that was born out of the soul of the people of Chicago. Saloniki does not ask for recognition or selfish praise. It merely asks for the good in the name of the spirit of our Orthodox faith and our country. For the sake of these two causes, our ancestors and conquerors of the Turks fought and died. For faith and country, for these two united and inseparable ideas, our forefathers and many of us who are still living fought and vanquished the enemy. Since these two <pb facs="5422062_4_1030.jpg" n="4"/>sacred ideals are united in our hearts, how can they be divided into three parts in this, the greatest Greek settlement in America? No, we should not tolerate this state of affairs any longer. After our priests and doctors, there remain the people, who must demand the speedy union of our community. But before this takes place, the boards of the three independent churches must do their duty. In this way the celebration of our national holiday will be complete and will be blessed by God and country.</p>
   <p>The great ideal of every Greek is to see the union of all Greek lands and all Greek institutions and interests under one sovereign, under one government. The great ideal of the Greek nation is to unite all Greeks everywhere under the White and Blue [the Greek flag].</p>
   <p>But how can we become united when we, and especially we who are in foreign lands, are divided into separate, mutually remote organizations, into separate churches, into separate councils, without any justifiable reason and simply because of ridiculous and childish misunderstandings?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1031.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Our fatherland wants us all united and let us be assured that the blessings of God will be with us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
