<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-04-24">April 24, 1926</date><title level="a">Grand Charity Ball for the Benefit of the Near East Refugees under the Auspices of the Ahepa in Cooperation with the Near East Relief Committee.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-04-24">April 24, 1926</date><title level="a">Grand Charity Ball for the Benefit of the Near East Refugees Under the Auspices of the Ahepa in Cooperation with the Near East Relief Committee.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 9. Proclamation.</p>
   <p>Whereas, Greece, the mother of Civilization, was deprived of her freedom with the fall of Constantinople on May the 29th, 1453, and suffered under the domination of the Turk through the Dark Ages for almost four centuries, and on March 25th, 1821 declared her independence from the Turkish yoke, and--</p>
   <p>Whereas, this experience has made Greece akin with the United States of America, March 25th, being to Greece and to those of Hellenic extraction, what July the 4th is to the American citizens of all nationalities, and--</p>
   <p>Whereas, it is altogether fitting and proper that the sons and daughters of Hellenic origin, observe this day in some fitting way, and---</p>
   <p>Whereas, there is a national organization in the United States, chapters <pb facs="5422062_4_1608.jpg" n="2"/>of which have been organized and long existed as a powerful factor in our Community, known as the Ahepa, which is chiefly composed of Americans of Hellenic origin, designed to inculcate and foster American ideals, principles and institutions and loyal support to the United States Constitution, and--</p>
   <p>Whereas, this organization desires to observe this day, March 25th, on which Greece's independence was declared, in a manner that will bring the promise of joy and gladness, not only to themselves, but also to the thousands upon thousands of refugees and orphan children now within the borders of Greece, and---</p>
   <p>Whereas, the Ahepa of Chicago, has to that end, assumed the leadership, in cooperation with the Near East Relief, for a Charity Ball to be held at the Trianon Grand Ball Room on Monday evening, May the 10th, and---</p>
   <p>Whereas, this good news is to be heralded abroad on this day, March 25th, the day of Greece's declaration of independence.</p>
   <p>Now therefore, I, William E. Dever, Mayor of the City of Chicago, in pursuance <pb facs="5422062_4_1609.jpg" n="3"/>of the request of the American citizens, of Hellenic origin and of other co-operating American citizens have pleasure in appointing the following Citizens' Committee to sponsor this notable event.</p>
   <p>William E. Dever.</p>
   <p>(Full)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
