<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1913-10-05">Oct. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">An American Appraisal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-10-05">Oct. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">AN AMERICAN APPRAISAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune, which calls itself the world's greatest newspaper, published an article on the Greeks of Chicago last Sunday. The author wrote an excellent report on the life and activities of our people in Chicago. It is true that he did not give a proper account of the progress of our people in the commercial, professional, and real-estate field; nevertheless, in many instances he was too well informed. For example, he mentions that the value of real estate owned by Greeks amounts to $500,000, whereas the truth is that it is worth $10,000,000. He writes that the Greek quarters are on Halsted Street, and on Wentworth and Grand Avenues, whereas most of the corner locations in the city and some of the best stores belong to Greek businessmen.</p>
   <p>We are sorry that our good friend, The Tribune reporter, does not know that three fourths of the restaurant, the confectionery, the florist, and the fruit and vegetable business of Chicago, and the entire shoe shine business, <pb facs="5422062_4_1043.jpg" n="2"/>are in the hands of Greeks.</p>
   <p>We are happy to note that the two main subjects of his article dealt with the fundamental prerequisites of any society.</p>
   <p>The writer makes prominent mention of our one Greek-American banking institution and our Greek press. It is to our honor, he says, that we maintain the only Greek-American Bank in Chicago and a fine Greek newspaper.</p>
   <p>You will notice that The Tribune writer placed so much emphasis on these two institutions that he forgot about the thousands of Greek restaurants and confectionery stores. It seems that the man was not sufficiently enlightened and informed about our affairs. The banking institution, according to him, is the measure of our economic strength, while the Greek press is the measure <pb facs="5422062_4_1044.jpg" n="3"/>of our intellectual strength.</p>
   <p>Whether the remarks of The Tribune are true or not is something which every Greek in Chicago is intelligent enough to know. What we want to emphasize here, however, is that our reputation as able businessmen depends to a very great extent on our great banks and exceptional news organs.</p>
   <p>Just as our ancient Greek colonizers always sought a plentiful source of water in order to build a village or settlement from which they could irrigate their fields and provide water for the beasts of burden, so must we immigrants, if we are to boast that we have established ourselves and have prospered, organize our institutions on a permanent basis--not only our banks, but also our churches, our schools, and our business houses.</p>
   <p>We are indeed happy to see that the Chicago Tribune has made a flattering <pb facs="5422062_4_1045.jpg" n="4"/>though incomplete reference to our commercial, financial, and press institutions. We are sorry that lack of space makes it impossible for us to print the Tribune article in Saloniki.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
