<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1934-09-08">Sept. 8, 1934</date><title level="a">Our Church Situation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_2014</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_2014.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1934-09-08">Sept. 8, 1934</date><title level="a">Our Church Situation.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We were hardly through urging the encomium of the new Bishop, when the Bishop-making machinery presented us with a new Reverend.</p>
   <p>The official announcement tells us that on the date of the 18th, of the year of our Lord, 1934, and with the day break of a Saturday, the Archimandrite Mr. Arsenios Saltas was ordained Bishop of the Most Holy Bishopric of Brooklyn and New Jersey.</p>
   <p>We confess that we were dumbfounded with the news, because A. Saltas has been one of our best clergymen in America, having served Hellenism in Minneapolis, as well as other communities, for years, and had enjoyed the esteem of the parishioners, and he was, in addition, one of the three choices for the Bishopric of Chicago. We never expected that he would accept under such terms.</p>
   <p>We have no doubt that one astonishment for such Bishop-makings is shared with the whole of Hellenism in America, and we let fly the question: How far can this hatching of Bishops go, and what are the most important steps taken in Greece and in the Patriarchates for this particular situation?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_2015.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For, if those in the Patriarchates fancy that with exhortations and aphorisms they can heal the new sore with the advice of Mr. Athenagoras, they are miserably mistaken and the results of their deceit will be repaid, unfortunately, by the Greeks of America and not by the Patriarchates, especially those who have proved to be incapable of governing the churches in America.</p>
   <p>They ought to have known a long time ago that Mr. Athenagoras has failed in his mission, or rather ought to know, that they were making a big mistake in sending Mr. Athenagoras to America.</p>
   <p>We certainly would not become a supporter and follower of such revolutionary movements, but we would become their most ardent supporter if we were to keep silent, instead of hastening to enlighten the Patriarchates as to the real causes of the illegitimately created situation today.</p>
   <p>We thunderously voice, with all our power, the facts that this situation has been created by Mr. Athenagoras, and his stay in America any longer will be the cause of greater misfortune.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
