<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1934-10-21">Oct. 21, 1934</date><title level="a">The United Community.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_2009</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_2009.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1934-10-21">Oct. 21, 1934</date><title level="a">The United Community.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Most Rev. Archimandrite, Mr. Daniel Golemis, in an article of his published in the Greek Press of October 11th, emphasizes the need of establishing a United Community in Chicago, to which all fellow nationals in Chicago should be compelled to belong.</p>
   <p>Without the least objection to Father Golemis' suggestion, for it would be a vain labor, inasmuch as he is not presenting us with a plan, he simply limits himself to expressing a wish for a unification of all parishes into one Community. We would ask him to please elucidate his plan and tell us how applicable it would be. We are much afraid that it is a Utopian question and nothing more.</p>
   <p>It is usual for those who are not acquainted with the affairs of our communities to discuss Utopias, but not for Father Golemis, who knows things, and still talks about matters that obviously are dreams and impractical aspirations. Being unwilling to investigate the question of establishing a United Community and how beneficial or harmful such would be, we accept the suggestion and say to Father Golemis, "Show us the way?"</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_2010.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To facilitate Father Golemis in his laying down of the plan, we ask: Which is the power that will compell the parishes to unite? Is it the Archdiocese perhaps? But, that has tried and failed, miserable, because the communities did not pay to it any attention whatever. Undoubtedly, the Archdiocese could ex-ercise its moral influence if it had such, but unfortunately, it has lost it and, consequently, we can expect nothing further from that quarter.</p>
   <p>What is left is for the communities to do, to unite of their own free will. But does Father Golemis see anywhere in the Communal horizon such thoughts and intentions?</p>
   <p>There are thoughts beautiful, magnificent plans, dreams and fancies, but there is unfortunately, the experience of reality. But how will the plan be realized? And how will the communities be compelled or be convinced to unite in one community? And how will the execution of the plan commence?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
