<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-08-29">August 29, 1931</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Ahepa's Ninth Convention in San Francisco, Cal.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1817</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1817.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-08-29">August 29, 1931</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">AHEPA'S NINTH CONVENTION IN SAN FRANCISCO, CAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Monday, the Ninth Congress of Ahepa opened its sessions at 10 A. M. in San Francisco. The Chicago delegation was in San Francisco three days ahead of scheduled time.</p>
   <p>At the opening session of the Convention, the Most Rev. Athenagoras, Archbishop of North and South America, began the rituals of a doxology assisted by all the clergy of the churches and amidst a crowd of distinguished Americans, who came there to honor the Convention with their presence, and also to attend the doxology officiated by the Greek Hierarch.</p>
   <p>Theodore Andronikos, President of the central organizing Committee of the Congress, addressed the Convention in a very eulogistic speech and then introduced the Supreme Commander of the Order, Geo. Philes, who spoke on the beneficial work of the organization. Archbishop Athenagoras was continually interrupted by the cheering crowd. The American notables were awed by the eloquence and stately impressiveness of the Greek prelate.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1818.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among the prominent Americans who spoke at the Convention, the Hon. Angelo Rossi, Mayor of San Francisco and His Excellency, James Ralph, Governor of California, were the only ones who spoke very extensively, extolling the work of Ahepa and the eulogizing Greek traditions.</p>
   <p>The city of San Francisco presented a Hellenic aspect. In the principal centers, the Greek flag was flying at the side of the Stars and Stripes. The Greek populace of San Francisco put on its toga of celebration and gave vital support to the visiting Greeks. The American press front-paged comments on the work and purpose of Ahepa with warm sentiments for the Ahepa Congress and Greeks in general.</p>
   <p>In the gigantic hall of the Civic Auditorium 10,000 people received and honored notables of the American Army and Navy and delegates to the Convention. This reception was sponsored by the chapters "Golden Gate" and "Pacific."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1819.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Jim Londos, wrestling champion, for the first time in his life acted as referee in a wrestling exhibition given by the champions from Idaho and Oklahoma for the entertainment of the Ahepans.</p>
   <p>Demetrios Veras of Scranton, Pa. was elected Grand President, and Demetrios Parry, attorney, from Chicago was elected Secretary of the Order.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
