<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek News</title>,
<date when="1935-11-02">Nov. 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Proper Method of Appointing Bishops</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1961</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1961.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek News</title>,
<date when="1935-11-02">Nov. 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROPER METHOD OF APPOINTING BISHOPS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Politics has made us forget our local problems, especially the church question, which the last lay-clerical congress brought up by its resolution in favor of creating new bishoprics by the appointment of assistant bishops.</p>
   <p>On this most important question, the Greek News will submit to the Patriarchates an exhaustive document which is published in another column of this paper. In this memorandum, we call the attention of the Patriarchates to the ways of forming bishoprics; for the method which Mr. Athenagoras pursues will again create an independent church in America, and so we shall gradually cast off the ties that bind us with the mother church.</p>
   <p>The creation of additional bishoprics in America is imperative; but it is also imperative, however, that these bishops shall be responsible directly to the Patriarchates and not be governed by assistant bishops, as Mr. Athenagoras desires.</p>
   <p>It is necessary, in other words, that this immense archbishopric of North and South America be divided into three or four archbishoprics independent of one another and depending directly on the Patriarchates.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1962.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Only such a division into archbishoprics will facilitate the church government of our communities in America and will serve the interests of the church, and our national interests generally.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
