<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-02-13">Feb. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Community of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-02-13">Feb. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK COMMUNITY OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent articles which have appeared in Saloniki concerning the closing of Greek cafes, and the insults heaped upon the Greek name and reputation, have made every Greek in Chicago aware of certain trends. They have become aware of certain wary--but nonetheless real--tactics of persecution practiced by the American public.</p>
   <p>The American people are not to blame if they have a rather low opinion of the Greek race. We alone are to blame if the impression we have created has been unfavorable. We appeal to Chicago Greeks for their co-operation in order that their social status may be improved. Let us unite and march toward a new goal--a goal of progress and co-operation, of unity and fellowship. Only in this way can we acquire the respect of our fellow citizens.</p>
   <p>If the Greeks of Chicago are to be honored and respected as a group and as <pb facs="5422062_4_1036.jpg" n="2"/>individuals, they must forget their differences and unite. This unity must be complete; basic differences must be eradicated!</p>
   <p>We must cease this sectional enmity that keeps us divided. It should make no difference whether we are from Sparta, Tripoli, or Macedonia; we are all Greeks. Every Greek should be faithful to a sacred idealism which is of greater value than his own selfish interests.</p>
   <p>This sacred idealism is the ego of the Greek ideology--the ego of the Greek family. The ego of the Greek respect and the honor of the Greek name must be put above all else. As a group we must imbue our fellow Americans with respect.</p>
   <p>In order that we may achieve this goal our fundamental institutions must be unified. Therefore, we must give our immediate attention to the Greek Orthodox churches and parishes.</p>
   <p>Why are we classified as Greeks of the West, North, or South Sides? Is it because we have three priests? If this were the reason, then we would be <pb facs="5422062_4_1037.jpg" n="3"/>committing a sacrilege, for the priests are instructed to preach harmony and brotherly love. Then what does cause this division? The churches? Again we would be going counter to the purpose of the Church, for the Church is the magnet that held our nation together for five hundred years. Why are our churches enemies? The Greek Orthodox Church of the Holy Trinity, the Greek Orthodox Church of Saint Constantine, and the Evangelismos Greek Orthodox Church,--are they not one and only one Church?</p>
   <p>Still, who is at fault? We shall not seek to identify the individuals who keep the fires of hatred alive. Instead we shall devote our attention to the solution of the problem. Our priests and church councillors must unite and begin a program of co-operation and accomplishment! They must become one strong and undivided power, whose command will be heard and obeyed by every Greek in Chicago.....Just as the priests of enslaved Greece kept the Greek language, religion, and patriotism alive despite the fear of torture and slavery, so must the priests of today become the bulwark of Greeks in America.</p>
   <p>If this is to be accomplished we must first conquer our appalling egoism, and <pb facs="5422062_4_1038.jpg" n="4"/>our individualism. Our pride and dignity should make it impossible for us to stoop to petty actions which only serve to keep us divided. We will have to stop saying, "Look who I am," and, "Who do you think you are?" It is imperative that we adjust ourselves to the idea of a mutual ideology worthy of the Greek name we claim, and of the Holy Baptism of our church.</p>
   <p>We will become soldiers of a national idea--the same ideology that our forefathers strove to keep alive. Thus, we will be in a position to defend our honor, and fight for the rights of our people in this foreign land.</p>
   <p>Otherwise, the position of the Greeks of America will be a very insecure one. Their activities will be curtailed, and they will find themselves an ostracized group. Let us not forget that we are all Greeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
