<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-06-09">June 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Stop Our Endless Political Talk</title><title level="a" type="sub">(By Aristotle Damianos)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-06-09">June 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LET US STOP OUR ENDLESS POLITICAL TALK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(By Aristotle Damianos)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The coffee shops reverberate to the loud excited voices discussing politics from morning until night. The walls of the restaurants bear mute witness to the innumerable clashes, debates, and sometimes even pitched battles, about the political situation. On the street, in automobiles, and at private affairs, the subject of politics is predominant. We are all patriots, conservatives, sympathizers, or liberals; but only by virtue of our endless speeches. We suffer for our fatherland so long as there is no danger of our actually having to do so. In every state of the Union we have organized drives "to aid the refugees and the victims of Bulgarian tyranny" for the sake of our fatherland, and our suffering brothers. From all sections funds flow steadily from the pockets of the poor workingmen of America to aid the Greek refugees.</p>
   <p>But, in Chicago, Greeks burn with a flaming ardor at the tables of the Kaffenion (cafe); but this ardor evaporates rapidly when requests are made that <pb facs="5422062_4_0481.jpg" n="2"/>they show their patriotism by their contributions.</p>
   <p>It took a man called Nick Lambropoulos to set a real example for the thousands of Chicago Greeks to follow. Mr. Lambropoulos is entirely worthy of receiving the congratulations of everyone, because, by a contribution of two dollars he practices the teachings of Christ that a true Christian should divide and share his possessions with his less fortunate brothers.</p>
   <p>It is not the size of the donation made by Mr. Lambropoulos, but the sentiment with which it was given, that makes it hard for me to find words strong enough to express my admiration for his action. Imitating his good example, I wish to add twenty-five dollars to the amount sent by Nick; and I appeal to the truly patriotic Greeks of Chicago to contribute their share toward this fund which shall help staunch our country's wounds. Philanthropy has no social standing nor does it belong in any caste system. We are all brothers and we must work together to accomplish some good for our refugee brothers and our fatherland.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0482.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Saloniki will gladly aid in the collection of money for this drive started by the National Herald of New York.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
