<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-06-27">June 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Surface Calm Belies Internal Strife</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0832</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0832.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-06-27">June 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">SURFACE CALM BELIES INTERNAL STRIFE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that the graduation exercises of our Hellenic schools are over and we have been thrilled because a few of our young generation have managed to learn a few fundamentals of the Greek language, we enter upon the period of community inactivity. The multitudinous picnics are the only breaks in our social lull. Lacking a centrally organized community, which is imperative to a successful and fruitful social program, we allow matters to develop in a direction which holds no good for our future existence. Thousands of problems beset us--problems that belong to each one of us; yet there is no joint action being taken by the community to solve them.</p>
   <p>The surface seems to be calm, but this is not at all indicative of the condition of affairs beneath the surface; this is known by the priests and the boards of directors of our various churches.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0833.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many dollars are taken in, but they are lost in the chaos of expenses, which are far higher than is necessary. In another column there is printed a facsimile of the check written by the community of St. Basil as first payment on its debt.</p>
   <p>We who follow parish activities know and appreciate the labor, zeal, and interest which made the raising of that amount possible.....</p>
   <p>It should be possible, however, to amass such a comparatively small sum without so much sacrifice; and the committee should not have to cultivate the spirit of co-operation in the breasts of the parishioners....As matters stand now, we are proceeding without a compass and minus a goal or purpose. We merely solve our small daily problems. The large ones are put aside for tomorrow.</p>
   <p>The problem of a central united community, organized somewhat on the plan of the government of the United States, is becoming increasingly important.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
