<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-05-31">May 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Demonstration to Celebrate the Formation of the Greek Republic</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-05-31">May 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">DEMONSTRATION TO CELEBRATE THE FORMATION OF THE GREEK REPUBLIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 8 - On the afternoon of last Sunday, May 25, the great demonstration to celebrate the reestablishment of democracy in Greece was held with magnificent solemnity in the Garrick Theater.</p>
   <p>The theater was packed with people eager to listen to the speakers. The presence of James Hamilton Lewis, former United States senator, John Wigmore, dean of the Law School of Northwestern University, and of the prominent Chicago financier, Rufus Dawes, added distinction and significance to the affair. After the national hymns of America and of Greece had been sung, the chairman of the assembly, Dean John H. Wigmore, opened the meeting and read congratulatory telegrams from many prominent Americans at Washington, D. C., and elsewhere in the United States.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wigmore in a brilliant speech praised the people of Greece because they have once more established democracy, and he reminded his audience of the sympathy <pb facs="5422062_4_1613.jpg" n="2"/>expressed for Greece in her struggle for liberty about a hundred years ago in the speeches of Daniel Webster, the celebrated senator from Massachusetts, who in addressing the Senate of the United States prayed for the freedom of that race fighting to throw off its yoke and extended to it the best wishes of this Nation for its eventual success in its struggle.</p>
   <p>The chairman then presented Mr. Spiros Kotakis, the eloquent editor of Kathemerene, who expressed the sentiments of the crowd and their joy for the return of democracy in Greece and pointed out that now is the time for action and not for trite speeches.</p>
   <p>After Mr. Kotakis the chairman introduced Mr. Nik. Salopoulos, the editor of Saloniki, who for the last six years has fought for the return of democracy in the mother-country. Mr. Salopoulos's speech was a paean proclaiming Greece's glorious past and the blessings which it will derive from democracy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wigmore then called on the celebrated financier of our city, Mr. Rufus Dawes, who in a serious speech full of wonderful ideas compared the different systems of democracy in ancient Greece with the present democracy of the United States, <pb facs="5422062_4_1614.jpg" n="3"/>where the system of checks and balances exists, by which the good judgment of the best men is brought to bear on the Government for its protection as well as the enthusiasm of the demagogue.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dawes was followed by Mr. James Hamilton Lewis, whom the chairman introduced as "the great orator, a type produced by the Grecian development of civilization under Pericles."</p>
   <p>The eloquent orator in a short and forceful speech was able to cover many fields of the glorious history of Greece, to compare the times of Pericles with the present, to explain the conceptions of democracy cherished by the republican Democrat Thomas Jefferson and by the democratic Republican Abraham Lincoln, and to salute Greece as the mother of democracy, the pillar that led by day, the flame that guided by night.</p>
   <p>Despair, he said, was never the inheritance of the Greek; ignoble surrender was never his crime. By the long life-struggles and the heroic deaths of Greeks Greece has taught the oppressed world how to hope and has showed persecuted mankind how to fight.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1615.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>From rise to fall and from fall to rise, through generations of suffering and betrayal, Greece has taught patience to the disappointed devotees of freedom and has given courage to the despairing children of light. The orator ended his speech with thanks to God that by His will the Greeks have become Americans.</p>
   <p>After Mr. Lewis the chairman called on Mr. Andreas Vlachos, who also extolled the blessings of democracy and advised the Greeks to have faith in it and to become democratic at heart.</p>
   <p>Finally Mr. Paul Tzavaras, the secretary of the committee, spoke and read a resolution in Greek and in English which was unanimously adopted.</p>
   <p>The enthusiasm of the audience during this demonstration was great, and all the speakers were wildly applauded.</p>
   <p>The speeches and the telegrams are published on the front page of Saloniki (from which the extracts above are cited).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
