<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-07-19">July 19, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Our Present Status</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Establishment of a Patriotic Organization Composed of All Greeks in the United States (Editorial by Soterios J. Georgiadis)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-07-19">July 19, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PRESENT STATUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Establishment of a Patriotic Organization Composed of All Greeks in the United States (Editorial by Soterios J. Georgiadis)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One can find abundant evidence of the material and commercial progress and prosperity of the Greeks in the United States. We in Chicago, however, can see no evidence that we have succeeded in making similar progress socially or even as a loyal national Greek group. The Greek people have not shown enough loyalty and patriotism to our fatherland either individually or collectively.</p>
   <p>It seems that when we left our fatherland, the idealism, the native culture, and the education which were given us in our homes and schools were forgotten. Only one thought occupies the mind of the educated, the farmer, and the <pb facs="5422062_4_1458.jpg" n="2"/>laborer alike; only one mission is to be fulfilled--to make money, no matter how or for what purpose.</p>
   <p>Most of us have plunged into work without trying to live a wholesome, normal, and happy life. And while many have been favored by circumstance and luck and have thus become financially independent, we seldom think of changing our habits and improving ourselves intellectually and socially. It is a pity that we have forsaken our first loyalty and abandoned our ideals and patriotic devotion to such an extent that we have heard many say that money is their country. Little do they care for the rest of the world!</p>
   <p>Is this perhaps due to the materialistic environment of the New World, or must we attribute it to a wrong conception of the purpose and proper use of material success? Though it is not in the nature of our people to forget our debts and obligations to Greece, it seems that quite often <pb facs="5422062_4_1459.jpg" n="3"/>here in America, we refuse to work and contribute to a cause which is of national importance. We were indeed shocked to hear a young educated Greek say that there is no adequate reason why we here in America should help or care for Greece. He betrayed and forsook his country because he was dismissed as an employee of the Greek government.</p>
   <p>Such degeneracy and indifference could be easily checked if some means could be devised which would educate and guide us in the right direction. No Greek immigrant would refuse to join an organization which is governed by our best and most patriotic men. Who would not be proud to do his part in working together for the success and welfare of a national organization, instead of letting our sentiments and fondest dreams fade and die?</p>
   <p>We must admit that in difficult times our people have on many occasions rallied to express their deep concern for the fate of Greece. They have responded with willingness and generosity to urgent appeals for financial <pb facs="5422062_4_1460.jpg" n="4"/>help. It seems that we have the material and the men with which to forge a powerful machine. As in everything, a plan and an efficient system are the best means to spread the idea of a great organization and thus insure the progress of our people.</p>
   <p>We now ask: Are we in a position to establish such a great organization, which will become a permanent Greek institution? Our people are scattered throughout the length and breadth of the land, and because of the nature of their work they are forced to live for the most part in the great metropolitan and industrial centers. Therefore, if patriotic centers and organizations are formed in large cities where our people may come together and contribute to the common interest, the Greeks of America could do great things, especially in regard to mutual aid.</p>
   <p>Because the members of such organizations, unlike the members of mutual aid societies, would be united by no material bonds, but, more properly, by a <pb facs="5422062_4_1461.jpg" n="5"/>moral and spiritual force, it will be necessary, in order to keep all the members together, to appoint traveling agents from within the organization for the purpose of stimulating the interest of the Greek people everywhere. These agents must see to it that the purposes of the organization are explained and supported; they must also strive to get new members.</p>
   <p>For a more efficient operation of this system of organization a common treasury must be established and a national convention must be called once a year to formulate new policies. In this way, the entire national organization will be closely integrated through the work and common purposes of the individual local chapters, which must be established in every large town or city where a goodly number of Greeks are concentrated. The headquarters of such an organization should be either in Chicago or New York, with their large Greek communities.</p>
   <p>If we ever accomplish this great task, we shall win greater respect, and <pb facs="5422062_4_1462.jpg" n="6"/>we shall be strengthened by the increased favor of the American people. Our status in America would then be similar to that of the Greeks of Egypt.</p>
   <p>The great Greek community of Chicago can take the initiative in promoting and putting into practice the idea of a national Greek patriotic organization. Let us work together and see whether we are strong enough to do it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
