<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-08-08">Aug. 8, 1931</date><title level="a">The Sixth Congress of Gapa Greek-American Progressive Association at Montreal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-08-08">Aug. 8, 1931</date><title level="a">THE SIXTH CONGRESS OF GAPA GREEK-AMERICAN PROGRESSIVE ASSOCIATION AT MONTREAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- The sixth annual convention of Gapa, a national Greek Order, whose aim is to promote Americanization among the Greeks of America, took place this year at Montreal, Canada. The five day convention, comprised of delegates from all chapters of Gapa, transformed the old city of Montreal into a Greek community. The Greek visitors, true to tradition, did not refrain from paying due respect to Bacchus, and to prove their devotion to him did not refrain (inspite of the prohibition law) from bringing some gifts to their friends on their return trip. Well all in all, it was a Greek affair (to bring gifts) and indeed it was with the patron god's permission.</p>
   <p>The city was bedecked with flags and the colorful standards of the Greek Order was displayed everywhere, and everybody enthusiastically welcomed the visiting Greeks, whose faces were beaming with joy. The Mayor, with other dignitaries, cordially received the Most Rev. Athenagoras, Archbishop of North and South America, and the Hon. Simopoulos, Greek Ambassador <pb facs="5422062_4_1843.jpg" n="2"/>to the United States. The presence of these two distinguished Greeks, played a major part in the brilliant success of the convention. The sessions of Gapa's Congress were dignified, in spite of the convivial attitude of the crowds, by the stately presence of the above mentioned two Greek leaders.</p>
   <p>The Congress of the Gapa telegraphed greetings to His Holiness Photios, Ecumenical Patriarch; to Alexander Zaimis, President of the Greek Nation; to His Excellency, the President of the United States, and to the Governor of the Dominion of Canada.</p>
   <p>The Congress held all its sessions and ceremonies at the Windsor Hotel. The program of the sessions was as follows:</p>
   <p>Monday, July 27th--Opening of the session with consecration by the officiating Archbishop Athenagoras. Present at the consecration were the Greek Ambassador, the Consul Generals of Greece in Canada and the United States, the Mayor, Congressmen of the Dominion and many other dignitaries.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1844.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Tuesday, P.M.- Tea party in honor of the Greek women delegates, sponsored by Artemis, Delphic chapter of Gapa.</p>
   <p>Wednesday night- Official Symposium, distinguished for pomp, magnificence and conviviality, in which many notables of Canada participated. The Mayor in the name of the City of Montreal extended greetings to notables and delegates of the Order, eulogized the ever progressive spirit of the Greek race, and wished the Order success in its endeavors. He introduced Dr. Mavrokordatos as Master of Ceremonies. Among the many distinguished speakers, who honored the symposium with their presence, were Canadian Congressmen and other intellectual Greeks of the United States and Canada.</p>
   <p>But the most conspicuous personage among this selected assembly was the Greek Archbishop, Athenagoras, who very eloquently brought out the devotion of the Greeks to their adopted countries and their inherent faith in their religion.</p>
   <p>Thursday- Excursion on the St. Lawrence river, and the holding of a brief session in the private hall of the boat.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1845.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Friday - Automobile expedition, free of charge with free beer and refreshments to all wearing the Gapa insignia.</p>
   <p>Saturday - Dance - "Believe it or not, those bloody blooming Greeks know how to attract attention," was the comment of Canadians.</p>
   <p>In spite of the great hospitality extended to the visiting Greeks and the free affairs, the Greeks being Greeks in manner and thought, and being in Business themselves, did not forget to put the almighty American eagle in circulation to the delight of Montreal business houses. The city was flooded with American currency. The bloody-blooming Greeks know how to spend money, and make a showing.</p>
   <p>The Greek Order, Gapa, ended its convention and departing delegates, due to certain immunity or privilege, took quite a quantity of Canadian three star gifts with them for fellow Greeks in the States.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly the City of Montreal wishes for another Greek convention.</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
