<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-01-17">Jan. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Women's Club Gives a Ball</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-01-17">Jan. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK WOMEN'S CLUB GIVES A BALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual ball given by the Greek Women's Club of Chicago in the magnificent ballroom of the Sherman Hotel was crowned with complete success. Many hundreds of our best Greek families and a large number of prominent American guests were present. Those who were fortunate enough to attend this gala affair were greatly pleased and entertained. Receipts from the bar and the sale of refreshments amounted to one thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Thus, the humanitarian and progressive Greek women of Chicago accomplished the dual purpose for which this magnificent festival was given. On the one hand, everyone had a fine time, and on the other hand, the Greek Women's Club made enough money to continue its admirable task of giving relief and support to many sick and poor families. The charitable activities of the Club are well known to all of us.</p>
   <p>This is the way true, worthy, and progressive organizations should function.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0510.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>May the Greek Women's Club serve as an example for emulation and imitation to all the Greek women throughout America and to all other organizations!</p>
   <p>The officers and members of the club deserve the highest praise for their idealism and the efficient way in which they are helping humanity and relieving suffering and poverty. Some of the most active officers are: Mrs. John Refakis, chairman; Mrs. A. Giokaris, vice-president; Mrs. William Inglezom, treasurer; Mrs. John Kapantais, secretary; Mrs. Andrew Vlachos, Mrs. Constantine Salopoulos, Mrs. Andrew Diamesis, and Mrs. Katherine Bardaloukas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
