<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-06-10">June 10, 1929</date><title level="a">Daily Items</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Speech of the High Commander of Gapa</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-06-10">June 10, 1929</date><title level="a">DAILY ITEMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">THE SPEECH OF THE HIGH COMMANDER OF GAPA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- We are gladly publishing a part of the fully patriotic speech of the High Commander of G.A.P.A. which he delivered on his arrival in Chicago last week. It outlines the purpose of the G.A.P.A.</p>
   <p>Partial prosperity and commercial evolution become the cause of unpleasant consequences if moral and material progress do not keep pace with each other. To this point I call your attention unprepared at the last moment.</p>
   <p>We have been parted from our country and beloved families and while here we cannot escape the laws of social process. For this reason the preservation of our descendants is our principal anxiety.</p>
   <p>"Let us leave it to our children. Some say they will be Americanized."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1267.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But is it possible for an olive tree transplanted in America to change into an apple tree? The voice of history will deliver us and others from imminent destruction. Let this voice of history be heard from the mouth of each one of us in time of danger and let us alter evil with logic. The solution of our problem is organization. Here is the accomplishment of the GAPA. To possess and also to communicate to the coming generation our culture, our language, our religion, and to see that all the Greeks in America are fraternally united, to live, to act, and to achieve great things.</p>
   <p>To organize is the command of our country and the ardent wish of our adopted country. Let us be organized as humans and bring into being again the civilization that Greece was at one time proud of; let us again bring into being the Greek intellect to life.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1268.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As an organization the Gapa is our new social religion to which everyone of us is indebted, never to forget that it is our shield of orthodoxy. Organization means endeavoring to forward the supreme themes of our language; the language which will keep our new generation flourishing in our traditions. It is an organization which will keep and allow the Greek schools in America to communicate the torch of our paternal traditions to our delicate youth.</p>
   <p>The Greek school has as its duty, to proceed with its advice uniting the link of our generation with the future one; the link which will bind every delicate Greek heart of America with our forefathers. Thus the new generations on receiving this achievement will raise it to where our forefathers had it before.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
