<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1924-10-18">Oct. 18, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Greeks in America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-10-18">Oct. 18, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE GREEKS IN AMERICA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3..</p>
   <p>Dear Friends:</p>
   <p>The winter is approaching, and the terrible upheavals in the Near East are still in progress. Two hundred thousand new refugees are now on their way to Mother Greece from Asia Minor. Thousands of little Greek children are in the refugee settlements at Salonika and elsewhere in Greece.</p>
   <p>Homeless, ragged, hungry, and thirsty, they live in an environment full of filth and infections. The number of deaths every day is terrific, and if we do not take immediate measures to alleviate this condition, it will grow worse, and all those who escape death will become sickly and undernourished and a dangerous burden to the population in the future.</p>
   <p>The American relief committee, the Near East Relief, desires to do everything possible to save these innocent and unfortunate children. It is already doing philanthropic work among thirty or forty thousand orphans in its orphanages, and it asks special assistance for these small victims.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0361.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We appeal once more to the Greeks in America as friends and co-workers to save these Greeks, the victims of the war. With $15 the committee can disinfect, clothe, and support for three months one child in the refugee settlement. It will then place the child in a good-hearted and philanthropic Greek family.</p>
   <p>May we not have your immediate and generous help to save ten thousand children in a short time? We hope so. Please help immediately. The need is urgent. Delay may be disastrous. How many children will each one of you save? You may send your contributions to the Near East Relief, 151 Fifth Avenue, New York City, with the notation: "For the Greek children in camps."</p>
   <p>For the Near East Relief:</p>
   <p>John H. Finley, vice-chairman,</p>
   <p>Henry Morgenthau, member of the</p>
   <p>executive committee,</p>
   <p>Charles V. Vickrey, general secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
