<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-09-05">Sept. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Women's Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0505</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0505.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-09-05">Sept. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK WOMEN'S CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The charitable acts and the kindness of the Greek Women's Club of Chicago are well known to all of us. These women are all willing and eager to devote their time and energy to any worthy cause.</p>
   <p>The Club is composed of the finest Greek women of Chicago, and it has done much to alleviate the suffering of unfortunate Greek families. However, its activities are curtailed for the present because of an unfortunate occurrence.</p>
   <p>This philanthropic organization worked very hard to amass a sum of money with which to help poor families during the winter, but they made the mistake of putting the money in the Greek-American Bank for safekeeping. As a result, six hundred dollars which could have been used to help some needy families is in the clutches of the four thieves who directed the so-called bank.</p>
   <p>Because this bank has closed, additional families will be in need of financial assistance during the coming winter months. It is a pity that their last hope <pb facs="5422062_4_0506.jpg" n="2"/>of assistance should be taken from them.</p>
   <p>The kind ladies must not lose courage because of their loss. They, as an organization, can fight for the return of the money which the bankers pocketed. At the same time they can appeal to the Greek community to help create another fund to alleviate suffering. We are sure that the Greek businessmen will be generous with their money and will help the benevolent ladies.</p>
   <p>Now more than ever before it is the duty of the Greek clubs to help the poor Greek families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
