<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-07-14">July 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Mysterious Necklace and the Greek Who Found It</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-07-14">July 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE MYSTERIOUS NECKLACE AND THE GREEK WHO FOUND IT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- Great excitement has been aroused in this American city over the finding of a necklace by a Greek named Kiriakos, whom a Court recently ordered held in police custody until the owner of the necklace was located.</p>
   <p>This mysterious pearl necklace was found on the street about a year ago by Kiriakos. Unable to tell how much it was worth, he took it to several jewelers for appraisal. Eventually he went to one of the largest downtown jewelry stores. The jeweler there discovered that the necklace was worth $20,000. He immediately notified the police and turned over to them the ornament and its possessor, strongly suspecting that the necklace had been stolen.</p>
   <p>Kiriakos was held by the police for three days. He succeeded, however, in persuading them that he had found the necklace on the street, and asked the Court to return the valuable ornament to him. But the judge, Mr. Fetzer, before whom the case had been brought, ordered yesterday that <pb facs="5422062_4_0633.jpg" n="2"/>the necklace should remain in the hands of the police for six months, after which, if the owner failed to claim it, it should be disposed of according to the law of Illinois by being deposited in the city treasury.</p>
   <p>And thus Kiriakos, the finder of the precious ornament, has lost it, and he, like others, may well cry, "Treasure is so much dirt."</p>
   <p>All in all, both the losing and the finding of this valuable necklace remain a mystery, and especially mysterious is the silence of the owner; for though news of the discovery was published everywhere, the owner has failed to make his appearance to claim it, and it seems likely that he never will do so. And as long as the rightful owner cannot be located, it will be impossible to substantiate Kiriakos' declaration that he found the necklace on the street, although there is every indication that he is telling the truth.</p>
   <p>The Contradictor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
