<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-07-20">July 20, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Club of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-07-20">July 20, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK CLUB OF CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.. The former center of the Greek Liberals, known as the Liberal Club, has been acquired by Mr. Demetrios Economides, a well known citizen of our colony. Under its new management it is named the Greek Club and has been remodeled to accommodate the needs of its patrons. The intention is to make the Club the most pleasant place of meeting for Greeks and their friends.</p>
   <p>Already the Greek societies have begun to use the Club's spacious hall for their meetings and the new management intends to charge only a nominal fee for the hall in order to attract and satisfy customers.</p>
   <p>It is the desire of the new management to make this Club a real Greek center by giving the best possible service to the various societies and to provide all the conveniences which it can afford. Already a radio has been installed so that patrons can enjoy music at all times and especially the Greek Hour every Sunday from 6 to 7 p. m.</p>
   <p>At the Greek Club Greek businessmen will find quiet and a place to rest and forget their troubles for a few hours. There are also games of backgammon <pb facs="5422062_4_1171.jpg" n="2"/>and chess in which real Homeric battles are fought by the players. With this program of social service the new Greek Club will doubtless become a real Greek center and will give the opportunity to its new owner, Mr. Economides, to serve his friends and to earn a profit at the same time.</p>
   <p>This reorganization of the Club was necessary in order to obliterate memories of past political battles between Royalists and Venizelists.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
