<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-03-22">March 22, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">An Announcement by the Greek Parishes of Chicago-Holy Trinity Annunciation of the Virgin Mary, St. George, and Assumption of the Blessed Virgin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1605</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1605.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-03-22">March 22, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">AN ANNOUNCEMENT BY THE GREEK PARISHES OF CHICAGO-HOLY TRINITY ANNUNCIATION OF THE VIRGIN MARY, ST. GEORGE, AND ASSUMPTION OF THE BLESSED VIRGIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- The persons who have signed this announcement below, presidents of the Greek parishes in Chicago - Holy Trinity, annunciation of the Virgin Mary, St. George, and Assumption of the Blessed Virgin - churches and parishes which are well known to the Greeks of Chicago, notify the Greek people that the programs being circulated bearing the signatures of the West Side, North Side, and South Side parishes do not come from those parishes at all and consequently are intended to deceive the people and to get them to attend a private anonymous church on the Day of the Annunciation, a church known to be on the West Side.</p>
   <p>We should like to bring to the attention of the Greeks of Chicago the results of the meeting which took place in the Greek consulate and was presided over by the consul general, Mr. George Depasta, for what occurred <pb facs="5422062_4_1606.jpg" n="2"/>in this meeting certainly refutes the statement on the programs. First, it was decided to do away with scattered panegyrics on our Independence Day, March 25. Instead of each church's having its own celebration on that day, all the parishes were to unite in giving a ball, the proceeds of which would go to the Greek community schools in Chicago. Then occurred that which discredits the statement on the programs. Mr. Depasta, in the presence of all the presidents of paishes, announced that on Independence Day he was scheduled to take part in the doxology at the new Masonic Temple church. Consequently, the statement on the programs which are being circulated is untrue, and the programs bear the signatures of the parishes only to deceive the people.</p>
   <p>Nick Kokkinis, president of Holy Trinity Parish</p>
   <p>Geo. Karabelas, president of Annunciation Parish</p>
   <p>A. Flambouras, president of Saint George Parish</p>
   <p>John Koliopoulos, president of Assumption of the</p>
   <p>Blessed Virgin Parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
