<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-04-09">April 9, 1930</date><title level="a">Coffee Houses</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0922</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0922.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-04-09">April 9, 1930</date><title level="a">COFFEE HOUSES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- A stranger, recently passing through our city, was dumbfounded at the number of coffee houses and customers we have. He went away astonished still not understanding why those employed as well as the unemployed go there. He couldn't understand that it is in the Greek blood. A Greek comes from another city and his first question is, "At what coffee house are you frequently found?" If you say you don't frequent any, he is dumbfounded.</p>
   <p>The life story of almost every Greek becomes known in these coffee houses. They discuss politics; they form associations; they discuss business problems; they argue; they quarrel and make up.</p>
   <p>I once had business with an import executive, but could never find him at his office. At a tip from the policeman on the corner, I went to a neighborhood coffee-house and his only answer was, "I sign all important papers here."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0923.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every Greek has the word "coffee-house" at his tongue's tip. I'll see you at the coffee house; I went by the coffee house; I heard at the coffee house; I'll talk it over with you at the coffee house; I'll telegraph from the coffee house, etc. These are familiar phrases.</p>
   <p>Men sit and talk for hours on thousands of important and of trivial things. They are men of all classes, ages, and differences, yet all go to their respective coffee houses as regularly as they go home to sleep at night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
