<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek News</title>,
<date when="1935-08-24">Aug. 24, 1935</date><title level="a">Editorial - the Work of Ahepa's Convention.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1772</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1772.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>GREEK NEWS</title>,
<date when="1935-08-24">Aug. 24, 1935</date><title level="a">Editorial - The Work of Ahepa's Convention.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is not the first time that we have dealt with the work of Ahepa; commenting now favorably, now unfavorably, and attacking it, particularly when it had as its purpose the program, "One hundred per cent Americanism". Ever since its ranks have been filled with pure patriots and its national course became indisputable, our attacks against it have lessened, and our criticism and comments, in regards to it, are directed towards strengthening Ahepa.</p>
   <p>It has been, often, argued in print and persistently discussed that Ahepa has no purpose in view and consequently no reason to exist. But those who argue so, forget that in many things we would vainly look for purposes and goals, nevertheless things are there, because some need keeps them there, or possibly they have acquired an accelaration which, is not so easy to check.</p>
   <p>In so far as purposes and programs are concerned isn't it customary that we, as men, think that we pursue some purpose, while in reality, we act to no purpose, and sometimes accomplish very little? And so, the Ahepa in the beginning <pb facs="5422062_4_1773.jpg" n="2"/>had some purpose in view--to protect the Greeks from the attacks of the K.K.K., but such a danger does not exist today and the organization of the Ahepans has expanded in such a manner that it is not easy to disband it, just because the purpose for which it was founded is not there any longer.</p>
   <p>That is why we have said above that we should leave on the side the purposes and consider the needs, and there is no doubt whatever, that if Ahepa continues to exist--even without a purpose in view--, it will fulfill some need of its members, and we can also say, of the Hellenism of America.</p>
   <p>Nor can anyone dispute that Hellenism in America needs a strong organization, expanding from the Atlantic to the Pacific and from the North to the South of the United States, to be used as a Herald and an Advertizer of Hellenism among Americans. And such organization must use American ways and means to advertise Hellenism and gain the sympathies and interest of Americans for the Greeks and Greece in general. Nor can anyone dispute that Ahepa, through its conventions and its activities fulfills the need, and renders valuable services.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, must not get anxious because we believe that Ahepa has no <pb facs="5422062_4_1774.jpg" n="3"/>purpose and to want by all means to create for her programs and purposes.</p>
   <p>The best thing to do is to let her alone and to lead the way marked by her conventions, picnics, demonstrations, and chapters, and let us be sure that, although apparently Ahepa may have no purpose, it, nevertheless, performs a great purpose and fulfills a great need of Hellenism in America, that is, it serves as a good connecting medium between Hellenism and Americanism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
