<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1920-04-24">Apr. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Heartfelt Complaint</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1641</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1641.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1920-04-24">Apr. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A HEARTFELT COMPLAINT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"It is quite a few years since I have had the privilege of being present at an Athenian celebration of our Independence Day.</p>
   <p>"In general, the entire audience was standing.</p>
   <p>"All around were soldiers--handsome officers in dress parade uniforms, men of importance bedecked with diplomatic ribbons and medals, who, added gaiety and brilliance to the scene.</p>
   <p>"None of this had ever touched me as deeply, nor made me realize the sanctity and graveness of the day, as much as the sight of a group of students that were approaching.</p>
   <p>"In their midst was borne a white haired old man--the only living reminder of 1821.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1642.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"At that moment, I wished I were that old man, who was carried so reverently. The thought came to me that I and others like me could someday have the same honor as this man. If we could fight for freedom and our country, perhaps we could be held up as examples of patriotism and bravery to the next generation.</p>
   <p>"The opportunity sought did not take long in coming; and we were called to our country's defense in 1912. We went keeping in mind our heroic forefathers, and I am glad to say we did them justice.</p>
   <p>"But there seems to be a change in attitude. At the Chicago celebration of our Independence very little, if any, attention was given to those who had served their country. I saw many veterans scattered in the hall, who were neglected and forgotten.</p>
   <p>"The heroes of Bizani and Kilkis sat with hurt expressions on their faces.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1643.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There was reflected the bitterness of being forgotten. They--who should have been held up as living examples of patriotism, they--who sacrificed their lives in order to give us a chance to have a day of freedom, they--who should have been honored, were forgotten.</p>
   <p>"Who, perchance, is to blame for this oversight? No one individual certainly, it is the fault of each and everyone who calls himself a patriot. This was my complaint and I feel that it is a justifiable one."</p>
   <p>Signed,</p>
   <p>One Who Fought.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
