<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1919-10-11">Oct. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Why the World Suffers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by C. Salopoulos)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0752</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0752.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-10-11">Oct. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE WORLD SUFFERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by C. Salopoulos)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The wrong-doers unite and give mutual aid among themselves in order to accomplish more wrongs, while the good influences stand aside uninterested, and make no effort to protect the right and fight the wrong. By this I mean that in the majority of cases evil-doers use the uneducated, the dumb, and the childish to further their plans; while on the side of the right are the intelligent, the educated, the alert, and the social-minded. Despite this, the right never seems to be able to overcome the wrong. Perhaps it is because the educated group is indifferent to social conditions that do not have an immediate visible effect on them. Of course there are exceptions. We see many good individuals striving to fight this gigantic group, but sad to say, they accomplish nothing. This is due to their lack of numbers, not to their lack of interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0753.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is interesting to note the zeal with which the undesirable group defends the unjust and the wrong-doers, while quite the opposite is true of the good group. Justice is supported indifferently and spasmodically. If justice were supported as ardently as wrong-doing, then there would be no wrong-doing. Man, as a rule,has leanings towards doing bad things. It is only a fear of legal punishment that keeps most people from straying.</p>
   <p>It is necessary that society create harsh and severe penalties to be inflicted upon law-breakers; and then to stigmatize and ignore them. The laws must be just but severe, because lenient laws are conducive to boldness on the part of the law-breakers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
