<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of Panionian Society to Greeks of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF PANIONIAN SOCIETY TO GREEKS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear fellow countrymen:</p>
   <p>"We appeal to you, as brother to brother, and as Greek to Greek, to solicit your material support for the benefit of the Asia Minor refugees in Greece.</p>
   <p>"The cry of pain that comes from the soul of the martyred refugees of Asia Minor has moved us deeply, as it must have moved you. This spiritual appeal of the people of Asia Minor for the immediate and prompt treatment of their ills, has found a response in every Greek soul, and, especially, in ours.</p>
   <p>"Our organization represents the determination of American Greeks to give speedy aid to the miserable victims of the Asia Minor tragedy, who are homeless, ill-clad, and ruined financially. Their only hope <pb facs="5422062_4_0408.jpg" n="2"/>for salvation is from the generous, sympathetic, patriotic, and unified sentiment of all Greeks, everywhere.</p>
   <p>"Brothers, our obligations toward our refugees are many and great. We should fulfill them immediately. One of our greatest and most fundamental obligations is to contribute whatever we can to meet the needs of the refugees. Let us contribute, because we have the opportunity to show that we recognize our obligation toward the refugee family of today, to the generation of tomorrow from whom Greece expects much. Let us not wait until the last moment. It is our duty to keep the pangs of hunger and the bleakness of winter away from the refugee. Our surviving refugees must be encouraged, they must live. At this very moment, their life depends on the charity and philanthropy of every Greek, of every Christian. It depends on us.</p>
   <p>"Brothers, although no ties bind the American people with the victims of the tragedy in Asia Minor, they respond by performing their duty <pb facs="5422062_4_0409.jpg" n="3"/>as Christians and humanitarians. They are gathering money and clothing for the victims. If an American man or woman contributes one dollar for the refugees, we, as Greeks, should contribute even more by making sacrifices. We should prove ourselves capable of assistance on this occasion. Let us prove ourselves worthy of the expectations of the refugee. By contributing, we will prove that the refugee can count on us.</p>
   <p>"Our society was established in order to assist the American Greek in the performance of a most sacred duty--the rehabilitation of half a million of our suffering brothers. As a purely national, philanthropic society, which is interested in the fate of our refugees, subservient to the influence of no political or partisan group, we appeal to all Greeks in America.</p>
   <p>"We expect all, irrespective of business or social status, to support our drive to collect funds for the refugees. All of us should contribute. All of us, with no exception.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0410.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Send your contributions to our offices. Appoint local committees. Contact us, if you desire any information. Work systematically among yourselves and among your American friends. The refugees are suffering. It is our duty to relieve them."</p>
   <p>"The Panionian Society for the Relief of Greek Refugees,</p>
   <p>N. Antoniades, President."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
