<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-04-27">Apr. 27, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Disillusion of a Newly-Arrived Greek - America Is Not What it Is Supposed to Be - Appeals to His Consul.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0712</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0712.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-04-27">Apr. 27, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">DISILLUSION OF A NEWLY-ARRIVED GREEK - AMERICA IS NOT WHAT IT IS SUPPOSED TO BE - APPEALS TO HIS CONSUL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3 - America has lost its good name in the eyes of George Drossos, who has been here only twenty days. The newly-arrived young Greek was held up by two men at the point of a gun and robbed of his watch and chain and $1.75 in money, all that he had.</p>
   <p>With his dreams of America the great thus dissipated, totally disappointed in the country of freedom and of justice, his face wearing an expression of disenchantment, he went to the Greek consul in Chicago and as a citizen of Greece demanded justice against those two barbarous Americans, who differed very little from cut-throat Bulgarian brigands.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0713.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He further told the Greek consul, as if the Greek diplomat did not know it, that foreigners in Greece are respected and esteemed by the populace, while here in America they are robbed.</p>
   <p>The disappointed and inexperienced immigrant Greek left the consulate in a pleasant mood after the consul had convinced him that real Americans are not robbers, and that the two so-called barbarous Americans who had taken his money and watch and chain were not Americans of the older stock with which the Greek had been enchanted but were Americans in the making. These explanations pleased the young immigrant, and he thanked the Greek diplomat for his elucidation, resumed his proud Greek composure and walked out of the consulate wearing an expression of victory on his unshaven but otherwise clean face.</p>
   <p>Editor's note: What the Greek consul failed to convey to the victim of this heinous crime is that the robbers may have been foreigners of the type that never will become Americans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
