<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-05-31">May 31, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Victims of Graft and Exploitation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0699</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0699.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-05-31">May 31, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">VICTIMS OF GRAFT AND EXPLOITATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten fellow Greeks, Mr. J. Tsatsares, Mr. Basil Bazeras, Mr. John Kolovos, Mr. George Kolovos, Mr. S. Batargas, Mr. John Kamaras, Mr. Andrew Gregoriou, Mr. Andrew Bekas, Mr. George Gravaretes, and Mr. Pan. Papagonis, were the the victims the other day of a dishonest act perpetrated by fellow Greeks established in Chicago and doing business under the name of Karavelis and Bousoulas, located at 327 South Halsted St.</p>
   <p>The victims, being railroad workers, applied for work at the offices of Karavelis and Bousoulas, who are labor agents for various railroad companies. Mr. Bousoulas promised them jobs at Ogden, Utah, and requested a fee of $25 for each man, $10 down and $15 on the first pay day.</p>
   <p>Each of the ten paid the $10 down payment and prepared for shipment. The next day Mr. Bousoulas informed the ten victims that he could not send them o Ogden, Utah, but he could ship them to Wyoming to another job.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0700.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>
   </p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0701.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Bousoulas and inform him of the consequences if the money was not refunded. Mr. Bousoulas was just as nice to Mr. Kominakis as he was to the ten victims.</p>
   <p>A short time later Officers Herby and Birmingham, from Maxwell Street Station, visited Mr. Bousoulas' office, with orders from the captain, "either the money must be paid in full or Mr. Bousoulas is kindly requested to accompany the two officers, on a visit to the captain." Not only was the money paid in full, but good Havana cigars were thrown in for good measurement by the so-called big-shot, Mr. Bousoulas.</p>
   <p>From all indications it appears that the reputation of the house of Karavelis and Bousoulas, as they call their railroad labor agency, is going to the rocks. Legitimate labor agencies would not do that kind of business, and honest and conscientious fellow-Greeks would not stoop so low as to attempt <pb facs="5422062_4_0702.jpg" n="4"/>to rob and swindle our fellow-Greeks, who happen to be in need of a job.</p>
   <p>First of all the fee of $25 is absolutely too much and the refusal to refund the money, when the fault lies with the agent is also against the law. But the house of Karavelis and Bousoulas, judging from this incident, and maybe from other unknown incidents, has swerved from its right road and recognizes neither decency nor law, nor the racial spirit. This is the death blow to such a practice. The death of the house of Karavelis and Bousoulas is imminent, and the pall of a similar fate will cover other business men who are in the same category as Karavelis and Bousoulas.</p>
   <p>With sadness we publish this incident, but The Star, as a guardian of the Greeks in America, can not overlook the dishonest action of these fellow-Greeks who fall upon the ignorant worker like a raven falls upon the carrion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0703.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It is also very sad to say that The Star would consider it a favor, if the advertisement of Karavelis and Bousoulas is withdrawn from publication.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
