<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-05-19">May 19, 1928</date>, p. 6
<title level="a">The Greeks of America. How They Established Themselves. Their National and Economic Sense. the Role of Ahepa. by Mr. Alfange, Supreme President of "Ahepa"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-05-19">May 19, 1928</date>, p. 6
<title level="a">THE GREEKS OF AMERICA. HOW THEY ESTABLISHED THEMSELVES. THEIR NATIONAL AND ECONOMIC SENSE. THE ROLE OF AHEPA. BY MR. ALFANGE, SUPREME PRESIDENT OF "AHEPA"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek, rightly and justly, is called the "migratory bird." In ancient times he always traveled to foreign lands where he created the famous Grecian colonies, transplanting there the scintillating light of Greek civilization. Those colonies perpetually maintained an ever-lasting love and devotion to Mother Greece and, with her, they fought the battles of enlightenment and civilization.</p>
   <p>The modern Greek, as real descendant of his progenitor, inheriting all their virtues and short-comings, could not do otherwise than inherit the peculiarity of their "wanderlust." Intrepid by nature, his ever-working mind always seeks the far-away and unknown, at which he dashes with untold courage,without being affected by distances,hardships, vicissitudes and ignorance of the language.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1277.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today one with certainty could say, that there is no spot on earth where a Greek merchant, industrialist,laborer, technician or sea-navigator could not be found.</p>
   <p>Thirty or more years ago, when the current of immigration was hastening to the land Columbus discovered, the Greek, although he woke up rather late, dashed to the new land of plenty equipped, as usual, with courage, industry, persistence and progress of his tradition. Reaching America, notwithstanding the fact that he knew nothing of the habits and customs of the country and not speaking the language, he immediately set his powers in motion. His original decision was to acquire a few thousand dollars and return to his native land and to his beloved family.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1278.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He never thought to colonize this expansive land. In coming here he had made up his mind to quickly return to his own land with the sum of money that he was after. Taking up any occupation that came his way and with devotion, patience and persistence, he worked for the acquisition of that money.</p>
   <p>After hard fought battles and endeavors, the Greek immigrant began to jump from success to success. Thus, the street peddler became a business man, the waiter, a restaurant keeper, the railroad and building laborer a contractor, the clerk, a proprietor, and, in general, the Greek immigrant began to steadily set his foot firmly on the first step of the American commercial ladder. But the Greek is still here. His success and his love for this country compelled him to temporarily postpone his going back to Greece. The various postponements have created greater success and interests for the Greek and at last, the environment brought about a change in him.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1279.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Greek altered his original decision. Instead of going back, he brought his family here and permanently established himself in his adopted country.</p>
   <p>The permanent establishment of hundreds of thousands of Greeks in America is a matter of fact now.</p>
   <p>In the past the Greek immigrant, always thinking of returning to his beloved Greece, refrained from buying real estate and especially refrained from taking active part in the political and social life of America. This aloofness created a certain misunderstanding of the Greek. He was thought by many as not belonging to the class of very desirable citizens; also he was judged as the type of immigrant who comes here to grab money and take it out of the country without having offered lofty services to the nation as a lawful inhabitant of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1280.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>On account of these beliefs, prejudice arose against the Greek element of the country and on top of that, the political and social frictions among the Greeks, themselves, began to picture them in the eyes of Americans as a people with diputes, and divisions. Everywhere in the country the division of the Greeks was noticeable. Despite prospering here he has acted as an individual, ignoring nationalistic tendencies.</p>
   <p>All of us observed the racial disintegration and all of us spoke of the necessary measures to thwart it, but, none took the initiative to stem it and lead the national movement.</p>
   <p>Under such unpleasant circumstances, a few Greek immigrants in Atlanta, Ga. deeply feeling the impending danger of national disintegration, held a meeting in the school of their community in July, 1922, and after long discussions, and deliberations, they resolved that in order to disabuse the mind of the many who were biased against the Greek element and, in order to restore unity, peace and brotherly love among the Greeks of America, an organization must be formed along the lines of the American brotherhoods, with principles and a program that would reverse the aforesaid conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1281.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Without delay the needed organization was founded and the name Ahepa was given it.</p>
   <p>The word Ahepa is made of the initial letters of the words American Hellenic Educational Progressive Association. The fundamental principle of Ahepa is to spiritually unite the Greeks of America into a federal system of mutual guarantee.</p>
   <p>For the organization to succeed, it was absolutely necessary not to clothe it with a purely Greek toga but a Greek-American emblem; therefore, the language of the land was adopted as the official language of the Association. Ahepa consequently was officially recognized by the authorities of the country as a first-class organization, and won the esteem and sympathy of the American people. Other advantages and interests, arising from the use of the English tongue, are from the crowded enlisting in Ahepa of Greek Youths who were born in this country and cannot speak Greek.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1282.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>This enlistment of youth in the ranks of Ahepa is a great national service, because through Ahepa they come into closer contact with other Greeks,learning the Greek language, and are imbued with the Greek conciousness, thus entering into an environment of Greek-American character, which would have been impossible if Ahepa had been clothed with a purely Greek garment. Other nationalities, through such organization, have succeeded for many generations in maintaining the national consciousness and prestige of their origin. To be a true American is a great honor and pride and to be a true American of Greek origin is a double honor and pride.</p>
   <p>Today, after six years of systematic work, Ahepa has 170 chapters all over the United States, and little over 20,000 members. Every Ahepan is a loyal soldier in the organization and a devoted worshiper of its principles and idealism. The spirit of brotherhood is so great that often fanatical enemies of yesterday are mutual friends today, through the ties of Ahepa.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1283.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>These 170 chapters ever so often, organize official symposiums, dances, enlightening lectures and other gatherings to which notable Americans are invited. At such affairs Ahepa presents the best of Greek traditions,renders the opportunity to Americans to become familiar with the habits, customs and virtues of the old and new generation of Greeks and due to its propaganda, a friendly sentiment is created among Americans towards Greeks in America and towards Greece.</p>
   <p>Ahepa with pride declares that it created an overwhelmingly Philhellenic sentiment all over the country. Ahepa further declares that it succeeded in uniting the divided Greeks into one united national front to defend the prestige and interests of the race. Undoubtedly the Greek Government is aware of the Ahepa's activities regarding the Greek loan, and Ahepa's systematic efforts with the United States against the ratification of the Treaty of Lozaine.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1284.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>At Ahepa's suggestion, the Greeks in America have entered the political, social and commercial life of the country, proudly displaying their racial origin, their wonderful virtues and the progressiveness of their race. Today, Ahepa is the largest Greek organization in the world, with gigantic influence and power.</p>
   <p>A prospective member must be Christian must be just and high-minded, believe in the ideals of Greece, obey and abide by the laws of the country he inhabits and be ready to offer services and sacrifices to Greece and his fellowmen. Ahepa's cardinal principle, as already stated,is to Americanize its members and sympathizers, but the meaning of Americanization is not similar to "Bulgarization" or"Turkization."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1285.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Americanization is a great privilege and a great honor. It is the best "ization" in the world. It grants freedom in religious beliefs, freedom to love your mother country, freedom to function according to your habit and custom, to use your language, to maintain your church, protected by the laws of the land; freedom to celebrate your racial and religious holidays, but, on the other hand, in wearing the honored toga of Americanization, one must be a loyal and true citizen of this greatest Republic. Being a loyal and true citizen, it unfolds before you untold possibilities and potentialities and it urges you to reach, (if you are qualified), the highest offices in the country, without racial or religious discrimination or bias being used against you.</p>
   <p>There are, today, many foreign-born personages who, after naturalization, became holders of high offices and some of them became members of the cabinet, without ceasing to be concerned for the country of their birth.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1286.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>The American people disdain those who ignore and forget their mother-country, their language and members of their race. It is said and certainly it is a logical inference, that one not loving his mother land would not love his adopted country. People of this type are barred from the ranks of Ahepa. Ahepa, today, is the personification of the noblest Greek ideals and systematically works to spread and uplift the lofty and immortal Greek idealism.</p>
   <p>Ahepa affectionately took care of the new Greek generation in America by founding the chapter, Sons of Pericles, for Greek boys and the chapter, Daughters of Athens, for Grecians girls, both being under the immediate protection and auspices of Ahepa. These two chapters are a colossal national asset to Hellenism, because through them and by them our race and idealism in America will be perpetuated.</p>
   <p>When our organization began to realize the achievements of its step-by-step unfolding program, the idea of excursions to Greece became ripe.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1287.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Such excursions will render our connection with mother Greece mutually beneficial and will strengthen our ties with the mother of all civilized nations.</p>
   <p>Not only Greek of the old and new stock will participate in these excursions, but many Americans will take the opportunity to visit Greece and become acquainted with that glorious country.</p>
   <p>The executive council of the Order resolved to have the first excursion of Ahepa to Greece at once. The reason for this haste of the resolution was to take mother-Greece by surprise, fathom the ground and lay down possibilities for future excursions to occur annually.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
