<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-09-25">Sept. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Panhellenic League</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-09-25">Sept. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE PANHELLENIC LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About the middle of next month, the Panhellenic League of America will call a conference in Chicago for the purpose of forming a great Greek organization of the multitude of various small, independent Greek nationalistic, patriotic, and benevolent organizations.</p>
   <p>At first this project seemed like an excellent idea and a most desirable undertaking. Nearly every Greek most enthusiastically approved the idea when it was first proposed by a group of progressive Greeks in New York City. A local committee was appointed which undertook to send letters and notices to all the Greeks in the United States through their nationalistic organizations, church communities, and consulates. The objectives and purposes of the proposed Panhellenic League became known very quickly to the scattered and poorly organized Greek communities throughout the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1428.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In part, the noble objectives of the newly born organization were recognized, for its ideas and the plan of the League satisfied one of the most urgent needs of the Greek people of America.</p>
   <p>Last year a conference of all the small, independent Greek organizations was called in New York City, during which quite a few of the most important societies and nationalistic clubs were well represented and in which a great number of prominent Greek church, community, business and professional leaders participated. Thus, the nucleus, so to speak, of the organization was formed. It was this small body of men that formulated the original policies of the Panhellenic League. At that time it decided to hold the conference of 1908 in Chicago, which is an important center of Greek immigrants, second only to that of New York.</p>
   <p>However, since its last meeting, the League has not made any noteworthy progress. So, now, while it is contemplating a meeting in Chicago as a conference of representatives from all the communities in America, it has no concrete proof <pb facs="5422062_4_1429.jpg" n="3"/>of its practicability and effectiveness as an organization which purports to benefit all Greeks regardless of class or occupation.</p>
   <p>There may be a few excuses for not having accomplished much, but as a whole the officers of the League have not contributed anything toward the unification and organization of the loosely knit and disunited Greek organizations and communities in America.</p>
   <p>Naturally, the arrival of his Excellency the Greek Ambassador to the United States, Mr. Lambros Koromilas, halted the progress of the League activities. As soon as he set foot on American soil, this shrewd and intelligent man observed the conditions under which the Greeks live and work in America. He could not fail to notice the disunity, bad government, hate, suspicion, ignorance, and incompetence which prevailed among the majority of the people of our communities. He was especially affected by the inefficiency and incompetence of our community leaders.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1430.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Koromilas visited Chicago only a few months ago and told us of his plan to reorganize all the public, church, and civic affairs of the Greek communities throughout America. He has been making a personal inspection of the communities in other settlements so that he may present a program for a united Greek organization which will be nationalistic in scope and which would be composed of all the Greek-American communities.</p>
   <p>We would advise the conferees of the Panhellenic League not to act until the Greek people get a chance to hear what Mr. Koromilas has to offer us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
