<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-02-01">Feb. 1, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Medical Association of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-02-01">Feb. 1, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK MEDICAL ASSOCIATION OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members of the Greek Medical Association of Chicago discussed the program of the newly organized Greek auxiliary of the Chicago Maternity Center. This women's club was formed for the express purpose of giving financial aid and home care to needy Greek expectant mothers. The membership of the Medical Association was puzzled by the following omissions in the program of the new organization:</p>
   <p>They are unable to understand why this philanthropic club has limited itself to aiding only pregnant women; for it might just as easily have been organized as a Greek charitable club to provide assistance for all needy Greeks in hospitals or those trying to obtain medical care.</p>
   <p>They also ask why this woman's club will work with and recognize only one hospital in Chicago. If they expand their program a woman patient will be <pb facs="5422062_4_0112.jpg" n="2"/>free to select the hospital most convenient to her. They question the fact that only one doctor was chosen to give medical care, thus preventing women from feeling free to have their own regular physicians.</p>
   <p>Why has the Chicago Hospital been chosen by this auxiliary when our Medical Association and the American Medical Association does not recognize it? The members of this philanthropic club are mistaken when they say their clients will go to the Lying-In Hospital. Only complicated and dangerous births will be assigned there; all the other cases will be sent to the Chicago Hospital, and, in the majority of cases the deliveries will be made under the care of students.</p>
   <p>This selection of only one hospital and one doctor will be a tremendous handicap to the rest of the Greek doctors in Chicago. Greek doctors have repeatedly entered charity patients in most of the Chicago hospitals and have <pb facs="5422062_4_0113.jpg" n="3"/>given their services free. When it becomes known that the Greek community of Chicago is raising money to pay for its charity cases in only one hospital, the other hospitals will no longer allow the Greek doctors to enter Greek charity patients, as heretofore.</p>
   <p>The Greek Medical Association acknowledges the good intentions and the charitable hearts of the Greek women, but it feels that they are ignorant of the facts pertaining to the organization of such a club. As it is out-lined now the Greek Auxiliary of the Maternity Center will only cause trouble and instigate scandal, and those who give money to it will be helping that to happen [sic].</p>
   <p>The Greek doctors in Chicago have never ceased giving free services and care to needy people, and shall continue to do this in the future--despite the fact that none of them are very secure financially. The various relief and <pb facs="5422062_4_0114.jpg" n="4"/>charity stations are accustomed to assigning Greek patients to Greek doctors. We feel sorry to see that Greek money is being amassed to pay someone who has always been paid for his services when there are Greek doctors who have often worked without pay.</p>
   <p>The Greek doctors are willing and able to co-operate with any club or group for any philanthropic purpose, but it cannot recommend this newly organized women's club.</p>
   <p>(Signed) The Members:</p>
   <p>K. Theodore, S. Loumos, Nittis, P.</p>
   <p>Pitsios, N. Nicholson, S. Zaph, S.</p>
   <p>Soter, G. Anagnos, E. Touloupan, E.</p>
   <p>Pernokis, G. Choulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
