<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-06-06">June 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Again the Community Problem</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1968</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1968.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-06-06">June 6, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AGAIN THE COMMUNITY PROBLEM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is recalled that more than five years ago the debts of our various churches amounted to more than four hundred thousand dollars according to the findings of the Bishop's office. At that time an effort was made to reduce this sum, and by various legal procedures this was accomplished, leaving a remaining indebtedness of three hundred thousand dollars. This reduction was supposed to have saved the churches for the time being. Nevertheless the economic instability was not remedied; on the contrary, it seems continually to have been getting worse.</p>
   <p>Even the most hard-pressed small businessman does not suffer from the economic strain more than our church parishes. We sympathize with the people who are in charge of our community affairs, and we praise them for managing to keep their heads above water. We do express our dismay and perplexity as to why they insist upon following such destructive policies.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1969.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>....Is it possible that reasoning people hope to build a heavy structure upon so weak a foundation? It is impossible! It is hard to believe our community suffers from mental as well as economic instability. The only logical solution is to re-open the discussion about a united Greek community in Chicago. This should be done by our Hierarchy and be discussed with our parish directors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
