<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-14">Sept. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Day at Fair Well Attended</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-14">Sept. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK DAY AT FAIR WELL ATTENDED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, September 10, was Greek Day at the Chicago World's Fair. It was attended by more than ten thousand Greeks--nearly the largest number of Greeks ever to come together....</p>
   <p>The program opened at three o'clock in the afternoon. The platform was occupied by such notables as Rufus Dawes, Bishop Callistos, and H. Simopoulos. The entire Greek clergy of Chicago was there; as was, also, the choir, composed of young men and women. The singing of the Greek and American national anthems opened the day's program. Then Mr. Paul Demos greeted the assemblage in behalf of the organizers and performers, and outlined the program. Following Mr. Demos' speech, Bishop Callistos and the Reverend Tsourounakis chanted a prayer and asked God for a blessing. Then the Byzantine Choir chanted special, ancient, Byzantine Church hymns.</p>
   <p>Mr. Simopoulos then spoke in Greek, and then in English for the benefit of the <pb facs="5422062_4_1497.jpg" n="2"/>many American people present. He was heartily applauded. The choir sang two Greek popular songs, the well-loved "Gero Demos" and "Sti Leventia Sas". Mr. Rufus Dawes, president of the Exposition, gave a short speech in which he expressed very high appreciation of both the ancient and modern Hellenes. Again the choir thrilled the entire audience, this time with a "Hymn To Apollo" and an ode written by Pindar [ancient Greek lyric poet].</p>
   <p>Then to the rhythmic singing of the choir, various dancing groups, wearing their local native costumes, thrilled the audience with their various types of Greek dances. The Cretan group won special acclaim because of the intricacy of their dance steps and the quaintness of their costumes. In fact, part of the charm of the day was due to the fact that all the performers were garbed in Greek costumes. Of course, members of the Byzantine Choir, as one would expect from its name, wore ancient Greek draperies banded in blue and silver ribbons. The choir, and the performers who were dressed in bright, varicolored peasant costumes made a lovely spectacle.</p>
   <p>The best numbers on the artistic program were presented by Miss Bertha Floros <pb facs="5422062_4_1498.jpg" n="3"/>and the two Argiris sisters. Miss Floros, who possesses a beautiful soprano voice, sang two poignant Greek songs which for an instant transported the entire audience back to its beloved Greece. She deserved the tremendous applause the audience gave her. Her voice was fine and her poise superb.....</p>
   <p>A few more numbers followed, and then the promoter of this Greek Day, Mr. Demos, thanked all who, by their presence, had honored the performers and organizers of the affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
