<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-12-18">Dec. 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">What an American Thinks of the Greeks</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. M. Rife Vi. Ex Ekion Ta Beli (From Their Picture, Beauty)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-12-18">Dec. 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT AN AMERICAN THINKS OF THE GREEKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. M. Rife VI. Ex Ekion Ta Beli (From Their Picture, Beauty)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In this, the last article of the series, it is a temptation to include all the stray remarks I had intended to make, but forgot in previous numbers. However, I shall attempt to confine myself to the title indicated above.</p>
   <p>Was there ever a race to which those four words could be more often applied than to the Greek? To the American it seems not. The more he becomes acquainted with Hellenism the more clearly he sees this trait as a continuous feature of its entire history. In our American school textbooks we read how Greece was divided into small, mutually inaccessible districts by the mountainous nature of the Greek mainland and by the more or less isolated communities of the archipelago; thus it was unable, in classical times, to <pb facs="5422062_4_0925.jpg" n="2"/>attain any stable political unity.</p>
   <p>Today the American is amazed at the large number of mutually hostile political parties which figure in Greek elections. Factionalism, and bitter disagreement seem to be chronic. Without it Greeks would not be Greeks. Perhaps it is an element of strength, though it is usually regarded as an element of weakness.</p>
   <p>The Greek is his own best critic. Every individual Greek seems to delight in picking all the flaws he can in every other Greek. The first thing any Greek said to me about this series of articles was that he hoped I would be unsparing in my faultfinding. I fear I am not sufficiently Hellenized to satisfy him. I like to see the good as well as the bad. In fact, I prefer to be "to their faults a little blind."</p>
   <p>Sometimes I think it is just plain jealousy which makes them hypercritical. I certainly deplore the factionalism in the Greek church. What place do <pb facs="5422062_4_0926.jpg" n="3"/>Greek politics have in American church life? None that I can see, unless Greeks just must have something to quarrel about. Can it be that this self-criticism is one of the features which has preserved the existence of this remarkable people through three millenniums? Or have they merely survived in spite of it?</p>
   <p>On the other hand it must be noted that there is a certain decided clannishness among Greeks. Time and again I have received the cold shoulder when approaching Greeks as an American whereupon two or three words of Greek have proved an open-sesame. The same man changes in an instant from a surly suspicious ignoramus to the most gracious and hospitable scholar and gentleman, becoming a bosom friend for life simply because I spoke a sentence or two of Greek. I can use English, or any other language he knows from then on, but the magic key must be applied first. Why is this? I do not like it. He has changed completely, but I have not changed. I was just as friendly and well disposed toward him before I spoke the Greek as afterward. Why should the American <pb facs="5422062_4_0927.jpg" n="4"/>be rebuffed and the stranger who knows a couple of words of Greek be received with open arms? The Greeks quarrel bitterly among themselves, but they are clannish just the same. I like the Greek immigrants, and personally, shall be sorry when they become Americanized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
