<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-02-14">Feb. 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Benefit Dance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0157</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0157.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-02-14">Feb. 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">BENEFIT DANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Tripolitan Society, "Kolokotronis," which is soon going to give its annual benefit dance in behalf of the Evangelismos Hospital of Tripoli, has just received a letter from the head of that Hospital. Since it is of great interest to all Greek people, we print the most important parts of it.</p>
   <p>"As for the effort to enlarge the usefulness and, in general, improve the Hospital, we are sorry to say that the funds (or perhaps the zeal to supply them) have not been sufficient to give greater help than before to the needy sick. During 1934, 230 destitute patients received 5,500 days of hospitalization. These figures indicate the immense need of greater facilities and more space for the needy. The paying patients received but 3,200 days of hospitalization. Therefore, the hospital spent 300,000 drachmas ($3,900) for the 5,500 days of care for nonpaying patients. Such a large sum has never before been set aside for the care of needy sick from all sections of Arcadia. The doctors and nurses in the hospital have pledged themselves to do everything within their power to further relieve the <pb facs="5422062_4_0158.jpg" n="2"/>plight of the destitute people who appeal to them for medical care. They cannot perform miracles, however. So please urge your members to make additional efforts to help us perform our work unhampered by lack of materials or funds.</p>
   <p>"The Tripolitan Society has been very generous in the past, but we hope that this year all the Arcadians will contribute to this fund; for we do not serve the Tripolitan sick alone, but all of the Arcadians.</p>
   <p>"Enclosed are pictures of the building and the staff members. Again we desire to thank the Greeks of Chicago for their understanding and philanthropy."</p>
   <p>(signed)</p>
   <p>"....."</p>
   <p>(Note to Greek Press (sic):</p>
   <p>Every Tripolitan and, in general, all the arcadians owe much to this philanthropic <pb facs="5422062_4_0159.jpg" n="3"/>organization which yearly sends benefit funds for the assistance of the friends and relatives of its members who are still in Greece. Therefore attend the dance to be given, as a matter of duty, if not of pleasure.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
