<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-10-15">Oct. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Panhellenic League's Farewell Ball</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-10-15">Oct. 15, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE PANHELLENIC LEAGUE'S FAREWELL BALL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The long-heralded farewell ball of the expiring Panhellenic League took place last Saturday at the Association Auditorium. This affair was given wide publicity throughout the state of Illinois and in Chicago through the semi-official journalistic organs of the Panhellenic League and by special invitations sent to all the influential Greek leaders in Chicago. The leaders of the League left no stone unturned to offer a successful and brilliant social affair in order that the Greeks of Chicago would be favorably disposed toward this organization:</p>
   <p>When the big event came off, forty invited guests and twenty others who went to the now famous "ball" out of curiosity made up the "great crowd" that "swarmed" into the auditorium to fill the fifteen hundred available seats. By the way, the event had been publicized as one of the greatest <pb facs="5422062_4_1402.jpg" n="2"/>of our community's social gatherings.</p>
   <p>Because of the small attendance, the celebration began at 9:30 P. M. and came to an end at 11:30 P. M. with no dancing, no instrumental music; so, the League lost an excellent opportunity to show its skill in the waltz as well as its astounding progress to our people.</p>
   <p>Because of this miserable failure, expressions of complete disappointment and disillusionment were quite manifest in the faces of the leaders. They were thus convinced that the Greek people of Chicago have no intention whatever of becoming a bridge over which any unpatriotic organization can cross. Nor will they allow any incompetent and selfish pseudo-patriot to play and promote themselves at their [the people's] expense.</p>
   <p>That the so-called "ball" failed miserably is proven by the statement of Mr. Lekatsas, the celebrated Greek actor, who expressed his sincere sorrow for having been invited by the League to address a few remarks to such a <pb facs="5422062_4_1403.jpg" n="3"/>small audience. In great anger even Mr. Argyros declared, while staring at the 1,440 unoccupied seats of the hall, that the Greek Community of Chicago was most conspicuous by its absence.</p>
   <p>Upon the success of this social affair depended the reputation and the regard which the Greeks would hold for the League. In the minds of the Greeks the League is a condemned organization with no good reason for continued existence. Nearly all the Greeks of this great Greek Community, except sixty unknowing guests, have refrained from encouraging an anti-Greek organization. One may justify the small attendance at this social by saying that the people are so busy that they cannot go to every social affair even though it be an important one. To these alibis, however, we produce evidence to the contrary. It is a well-known fact that the Greek Young Men's [Christian] Association brought more than fifteen hundred fellow countrymen of ours together at their annual dance. It would interest our people to know that a net profit of more than a thousand dollars was realized <pb facs="5422062_4_1404.jpg" n="4"/>by our young Greek men. The entire sum was sent to the Greek Orthodox Patriarch at Constantinople in order to strengthen the much needed material resources of the Holy Patriarch.</p>
   <p>In contrast, the supposedly extensive and powerful League could realize no appreciable profits with an attendance of barely sixty people during its social affair. So, that high-sounding organization is in no position to extend any important financial or even moral support to our nation's institutions.</p>
   <p>Compare this year's soiree with that of last year and you will see that the League, which was instituted a year ago under so auspicious circumstances and which was enthusiastically hailed by the people, is now a discredited and rapidly disintegrating organization. It is passing from Chicago's scene without even a last adieu. It has proved to be unworthy of the aspirations and high purposes of the Greek people not only of Chicago <pb facs="5422062_4_1405.jpg" n="5"/>but of all America.</p>
   <p>The only saving gesture that can be made on the part of its leadership and delegates to the forthcoming national convention at Boston is to ask our ardent patriot and highly esteemed propogandist of Greece's sacred cause in America, Mr. Spiro Matsoukas, to take over the League's half-depleted treasury before it is completely emptied by preying loafers and pseudo-patriots.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
