<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-09-27">Sept. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Panhellenic Order</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-09-27">Sept. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE PANHELLENIC ORDER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the occasion of the invitation of the organizers of the national convention of the Panhellenic Order at New York to participate in its deliberations, the Greek Community of Chicago has been considering whether it would benefit by sending a number of representatives to New York. As yet we are unable to make any definite announcement as to whether the Greeks of Chicago will be represented at the convention in view of the fact that the matter is being discussed and debated; nevertheless, we undertake to express our own opinion in regard to the intentions and plans of our friends in New York.</p>
   <p>The purposes of the Panhellenic Order are sacred and noble. Every Greek in America would like to see a national Greek organization flourish and prosper. We are all for the idea, but we must bear in mind that such a <pb facs="5422062_4_1448.jpg" n="2"/>tremendous undertaking carries a great responsibility with it. That is why we think that this proposal should have been analyzed, discussed, and examined from every angle. But, unfortunately, as is the case with us Greeks in most instances, the leaders of the Panhellenic Order have failed to organize and build the organization on a sound basis. First, they have written and appealed to the presidents of the communities and various societies and clubs, but they have neglected to write to the consular officials, to our clergymen, and to the newspapers for advice and support.</p>
   <p>We also notice that our leaders here in Chicago are inviting the consul, the priests, the presidents of the community other minor organizations, and the professional men, but fail to invite our businessmen.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to accuse the inspired administrators of the Panhellenic Order with incompetence and lack of energy. We are merely pointing out that their method of organization must be greatly improved if they wish <pb facs="5422062_4_1449.jpg" n="3"/>to see the order grow and win supporters in every state of the Union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
