<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-06-20">June 20, 1931</date><title level="a">Installation of Officers of Appolon Chapter of Gapa</title><title level="a" type="sub">Greek-American Progressive Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1188</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1188.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-06-20">June 20, 1931</date><title level="a">INSTALLATION OF OFFICERS OF APPOLON CHAPTER OF GAPA</title><title level="a" type="sub">Greek-American Progressive Association</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- Under the organized efforts and auspices of Navarinon, a chapter of the organization Gapa, the newly created chapter of youths,held a meeting last Wednesday and installed their officers. This newly formed chapter is composed of forty Greek youths, the majority of them being chartered as members of the Greek Olympic Athletic Club.</p>
   <p>The installation, in which all the chapters of Gapa participated, took place at German Hall. Constantine Soteracopoulos, Grand Commander of Gapa, presided at the ceremony. The newly organized chapter was named Apollon.</p>
   <p>The enthroned officers are as follows: Evangelos Pavlatos, Pres.; Basil Metropoulos, Vice-Pres.; N. Laskaris, Sec.; P. Haritopoulos, Treas. Members of the Board of Directors are: G. Andrianopoulos, Leo S. Kountzos, Dionysos Pavlatos, H. Marcopoulos, and M. Apostolatos.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1189.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the installation the Grand Commander, in conjunction with the Presidents of all the chapters, congratulated the youths, amidst thundering cheers from the crowd, which had thronged there to admire the new generation of Greek-Americans.</p>
   <p>In the name of the youths, Master Evangelos Pavlatos spoke as follows:</p>
   <p>"Brother Grand Commander and brother Gapans, it is true that we haven't seen our Greece, the land from which you and our progenitors came, but that which we did not acquire in vision, was acquired through teaching and it remains deeply engraved in our minds and hearts. Our Greek schools in Chicago have enlightened our minds on the glory of Greece, and taught us to be proud for being sons of Greeks, and Greek-American sons of immortal and glorious Greece. We stand proudly before you, our elders, and ask that you and every Greek in Chicago assist us in every possible way, to make the Greece of America just as glorious and great as the Greece of the past.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1190.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Due to the fact that we are young and inexperienced in molding the future Greece of America, we, as sons of Greeks, proudly ask your cooperation and vigilant observation in achieving our goal.</p>
   <p>The composure, the poise, and fiery oratory of the Greek-American youth, astounded the crowd which stood breathless lest they miss a word from the speech of the blossoming orator. The hall thundered with cheers.</p>
   <p>It requires a Greek poet to be able to put into words the passionate sentiment and emotion of the cheering Greeks.</p>
   <p>After quiet was restored, the Greek anthem was sung by Miss Maria Shiountri and the meeting was terminated with congratulations to Navarinon chapter for the excellent and thrilling meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
