<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-04-10">Apr. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">[The Future of Greeks in America]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0919</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0919.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-04-10">Apr. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">[THE FUTURE OF GREEKS IN AMERICA]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I have visited the prominent physician and surgeon of our city, Mr. Stam. Demosthenes Zapheriades, known as Dr. Zaph. With his simple and kind manner, as becomes a Greek, he welcomed me, the worthy minister of the divine art of Hippocrates.</p>
   <p>.....Although he rightly guessed the purpose of my visit, he asked me,and I told him that it was concerning his opinion in regard to the future progress of the Greeks in America.</p>
   <p>"Certainly," he answered, "I will give you briefly a few ideas, which, please, present clearly and analytically, for their purpose is most beneficial and delightful.</p>
   <p>"I have read in the Chicago Greek Daily the opinions of our fellow-countrymen, which are brilliant and more or less progressive. But the question is: how will they become beneficial and practical? However, from the strenuous work of the Greek press and other factors working in different ways toward the Greek-American future, some good will result, but it requires the efforts of the many and the few. By all means, let the Greek population of North America know that they ought to be steadfast, <pb facs="5422062_4_0920.jpg" n="2"/>with self-sacrifice, to our mores, considering them the most valuable and inestimable paternal heritage! That will bring about a brilliant name and future happiness to them. And this can be accomplished through the perfect functioning of the Greek institutions of learning. Tell them, besides, not to be worshipers of strength, showing thus a bad example to their children, depreciating themselves. For hearing us depreciate our race, our children engrave on their tender brain cells this thought, and it remains there, to our own detriment, ineffaceable.</p>
   <p>"In addition, talk Greek at home. Let us teach our children that the Greek race does not lag behind other races, that it stands in the first rank and in many respects is superior to them!</p>
   <p>"Tell the Greek people that we ought to be united in relations of sincerity and love and not to treat one another with carelessness and falseness. To wit: let us not,when we enjoy health and happiness, embrace strangers, and then in suffering run to our own people. Yes, let us learn that nobody will love us and support us more than our own race! This is what I have to say," said Dr. Zaph.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0921.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Zaphiriades was born in Promyrio of Pelio in Thessaly (Promyrio is so named for the landing of Xenophon with his ten thousand Greeks), and having come to America as a lad, he studied medicine, having, by diligence and labor, raised himself to eminence in the intricate and life-saving art of surgery. Mr. Zaph is an excellent family man and a prominent scientist, but, he is also "a Greek and a man" in the real meaning of these words.</p>
   <p>D. J. Rigas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
