<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-09-13">Sept. 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Panhellenic League</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-09-13">Sept. 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE PANHELLENIC LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many attempts have been made by several professional men and active members of our Chicago community to associate ourselves with the splendid Panhellenic League of New York.</p>
   <p>The noble and patriotic sentiments and the repeated appeals of the united and consolidated Greek clubs and organizations of New York City are well known to all the Greeks of Chicago. Our brothers and beloved countrymen in New York City have been attempting to influence Greek organizations of all kinds for several years in the hope that the latter will form one, great Greek organization which will be national in scope, and extensive in its influence over the political economic, social, religious, and educational lives of the Greek immigrants of America.</p>
   <p>Naturally, it would be reasonable to accept the leadership of the most <pb facs="5422062_4_1451.jpg" n="2"/>influential and most powerful Greek organization in America, the Panhellenic League of New York City, and use it as the strong nucleus of such a national organization.</p>
   <p>Though the idea has been gaining ground and winning thousands of supporters, no serious attempts have been made to implement the organization and its activities or to propose any definite and concrete course of action. As yet no qualified Greek leader or official has come forth with a workable and practical plan.</p>
   <p>Though the developments are hazy because of selfish considerations, subtlety, and idle talk about the matter, we find that under the present circumstances many other obstacles must be overcome. Nevertheless, there is every indication that we can accomplish much in our drive toward our ultimate goal.</p>
   <p>At the present moment, it is more likely that our efforts will fail. However, the hopes and aspirations of our patriotic brothers in New York are sufficient <pb facs="5422062_4_1452.jpg" n="3"/>to stimulate and encourage us here in Chicago to accept and appreciate their most cherished hopes. In this way and in due time the question of a general unification of our numerous organizations will be widely and thoroughly discussed. As a result, ways and means for the fulfillment of our desires may be found.</p>
   <p>But, even if the final objectives are not realized, because of the difficulties which we have mentioned, we hope that the appeals and efforts of the Greeks of New York will be the beginning of a closer and more intimate unification of the prosperous New York community. Our brothers in New York hold high hopes for their future and for their fatherland.</p>
   <p>So, whatever the outcome of their untiring struggle to spread their splendid cause, we hope and believe that they have made a fine start; and the day is coming when we will see their work crowned with success while our beloved fatherland will shower its blessings on its scattered children in the New World.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1453.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>To receive this joyful news--the proposal for the unification and incorporation of the Greek clubs and organizations throughout the United States by all means, we must be prepared. We, here in Chicago, are expected to take the initiative; it is up to us to respond promptly and perform our imposed duty.</p>
   <p>It is clearly our duty to rid ourselves of enmity, strife, insults, jealousy and hatred. Let us cleanse our minds of every evil and sinister thought. Let us forget the sad past and put in order the affairs of our own house--the community--in which we live and work. Let us all strive toward a brighter future.</p>
   <p>With such ideas on the important question of the projected Panhellenic League, we deem it our duty to examine the affairs of our own community to see if we are worthy of, receiving the biblical groom of the parable.</p>
   <p>Hastily inspecting the condition of our Chicago community, we note with sorrow <pb facs="5422062_4_1454.jpg" n="5"/>that the eyes of all are centered on local pride, self-contentment, and self-satisfaction by individuals and groups. It is precisely because of these factional forces that the power and vitality of the community have been weakened and sapped. As far as the fulfillment of the patriotic obligations on the part of the members is concerned, the community has been slowly deteriorating. Because of this too the gangrene of local pride and complacency within our local provincial clubs and societies, is eating at our vitals by undermining our loyalty and devotion to everything that is Greek.</p>
   <p>As if all these were not sufficient, we have to account for our community backwardness because of which--though a year since the community elections--nothing important has been accomplished from the nationalistic and patriotic standpoint.</p>
   <p>As those who today govern the affairs of our church remember we had all agreed and decided to rehabilitate our community and proceed to organize a real, large nationalistic order. Since then, two years have gone idly by without having done anything of a lasting nature. What does all this mean?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1455.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It means that the Greek Community of Chicago, in spite of the remarkable progress of our people as individuals, is always prone to retrogress and be torn asunder by the ignorance and stubborness of a few blockheads who are relying on their perverted minds--caring little about the common good.</p>
   <p>This regrettable situation notwithstanding, we think that because of a few individuals progress can by no means be stopped. We must realize that they are making us lose valuable time by delaying the organization of Chicago chapters of the nationwide Panhellenic order.</p>
   <p>We must awaken from our stupor and get rid of the petty arguments and hateful personal animosities which are ravaging our communal life. We must all strive to organize the Panhellenic League, whose main purpose it is to serve and promote our national interests in the United States of America as well as in our fatherland.</p>
   <p>For the attainment and realization of this ideal we must all stop our silly <pb facs="5422062_4_1456.jpg" n="7"/>arguments, petty grievances, and personal antagonisms. There is no reason or excuse for them.</p>
   <p>As we said before, we are all of one opinion; we seek only one purpose. Forward! Let us all put our shoulder to the wheel and help organize the Panhellenic League and we are assured of the blessing of God and the benediction of our fatherland, who will provide us with a compass to guide and support us in this short life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
