<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1924-05-17">May 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Greek-American Meeting to Celebrate the Declaration of the Greek Republic</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1619</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1619.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-05-17">May 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK-AMERICAN MEETING TO CELEBRATE THE DECLARATION OF THE GREEK REPUBLIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- To the Greek people of Chicago and suburbs:</p>
   <p>A splendid and blessed event took place today in the country where we first saw the light of the sun, in our beloved and beautiful Greece.</p>
   <p>Today the resurrection of the Hellenic democracy from the grave of the past is there an accomplished fact. Today the complete political liberty of the Greek citizen was there declared.</p>
   <p>Today the independent thought of the Greek people there triumphed, and the power of the Greek will was asserted.</p>
   <p>The champions of the liberty of the Greek people demolished the political structure of a dynasty which now belongs to the history of the past. The building of a new Parthenon for a new Grecian life was there begun when on the 25th day of last March the cornerstone of the Greek Republic was laid by the vote of the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1620.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greek nation has continually fought for the ideals of Greek civilization and for the liberty and honor of that glorious country which has contributed so much to human enlightenment. Greece waged almost incessant war and made incalculable sacrifices from the glorious and successful year of 1912, when the army of King Constantine victoriously swept the plains of Thrace, Epirus, and Macedonia, to the terrible and disastrous defeat in Asia Minor in 1922.</p>
   <p>The people by a great majority have decided to abolish the royal dynasty and have declared their preference for the republican form of government as the best type to insure the cooperation of hostile factions. And thus Greece by a fine gesture has become a republic like the other nations of the world which lead in human progress.</p>
   <p>The news of the declaration of the Greek Republic filled with joy the hearts of Greeks everywhere, and the nations of the world gazed with admiration at the land of Pericles.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1621.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But most jubilant of all is the Hellenism of America, which lives, works, and prospers in this great liberal Republic of the United States. We are confident that the Greeks of Chicago, who have never ceased to take an active interest in the progress and happiness of Greece and have endorsed the movement to establish democracy there, rejoice to hear the great news.</p>
   <p>Therefore, in order to express this joy of the Greeks in America for the establishment of the Greek Republic and to give encouragement to the founders and builders of this new Government there, we invite the Greek people of Chicago and its suburbs to a big Greek-American assembly to be held on Sunday, May 25, at 2 P.M. in the Garrick Theater at Randolph and Dearborn streets.</p>
   <p>Let us make this a magnificent celebration of the great event which has ushered in a new era for the Greek race in the community of nations. Prominent Americans will participate in this great celebration, for there are some who feel particularly jubilant and proud at the rebirth of Grecian democracy. Therefore representatives of this friendly nation will be invited.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1622.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Matles, the Greek consul, and the Greek clergy and the councils of the Greek organizations will also take official part. A prominent and well-known American will preside at the meeting, and two Americans and four Greeks will speak. Their names will shortly be announced along with the program of this affair. A large orchestra will play American and Greek songs in the intermissions, and a Greek singer will sing in Greek and in English.</p>
   <p>We are sure that the Greeks of Chicago and the suburbs will appreciate the purpose and the value of this Greek-American meeting, and that they will come early to fill the theater, hear the speakers, and express the joy which the Greeks of America feel at the rebirth of democracy in Greece. The good work has now begun over there, and the spirit of democracy will remove the humiliation of the disaster in Asia Minor, investing Greece in the garment of reconciliation, peace, honor, and glory.</p>
   <p>Chicago, May 17, 1924. The Executive Committee:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1623.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Andreas Vlachos, Nikolaos Salopoulos, Constantinos Paleologos, Constantinos Haloulos, Demosthenes Papantoniou, Ioannes Raklios, Spyros Kotakis, George Tsiagoures, Paulos Tzavaras, Ioannes Papanastasiou, Panagiotes Lampros, Vasilios Kotsones, George Bitsapas, Lampros Tsoromokos, Constantinos Salopoulos, Andreas Chrones, Aristomenes Tsikoures, Andreas Karauiannes, Soterios Fasseas, Constantinos Augerinos, Niketas Nomicos, Ioannes Askounes, Tryfon Valos, Georgios Sellas, Theodoros Tsamales, Ioannes Alexopoulos, Stavros Kantzios, Demetrios Alexopoulos, Nikolaos Stamos, Constantinos Terzakis, and D. Eutaxias.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
