<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-07-02">July 2, 1927</date><title level="a">"Mother's" Farewell to the Greeks of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0327</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0327.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-07-02">July 2, 1927</date><title level="a">"MOTHER'S" FAREWELL TO THE GREEKS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.6--Dear Editor:</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as I am leaving Chicago for other American cities to continue my sacred work of securing contributions for the sanatorium, I beg you to print in the columns of your eminent journal this letter of thanks addressed to the Greek people of Chicago.</p>
   <p>I am sure that you will again donate some of the valuable space in your columns, and I beg you, dear sir, to accept the expression of my infinite gratitude.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Anna Papadopoulou,</p>
   <p>Chicago, June 30, 1927.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0328.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dear fellow-countrymen:</p>
   <p>On leaving the hospitable Greek community of Chicago I should consider it a gross omission on my part if I failed to thank you personally. Unfortunately, however, but little time remains, and I beg you to permit me to express my thanks through this newspaper. I wish to thank for the support which they have accorded to my work the Consul General of Greece, the Most Reverend Bishop Philaretos and all the clergymen, the church councils, and the ladies and gentlemen who are members of your various societies.</p>
   <p>It is possible, since I am old, weary, and far away from my own people, that I cannot elicit from the others whom I intend to visit the national enthusiasm which I encountered here. This will, of course, sadden me, but nevertheless such a possibility will not keep me from trying, for my aim is a sacred one, and patience triumphs over all; it will win! Those who do not know me at least know what the army has gone through.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0329.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I realize with all my wearied powers of comprehension that the times are not favorable. My collections might have been a great success, but unfortunately realization disappoints anticipation. Had we in Greece known the present moral and economic condition of the Greeks of America, most assuredly, my dear fellow-countrymen, great as our need is in our own country, we would never have importuned you. Had there been organization, however, or better still, unity in the churches, this matter of making collections would have been much facilitated, and it would have been a joy to those who sincerely sympathize with the fatherland to be told of the help which we are seeking among our compatriots for our invalids. Considering all the service which is being rendered by the Greeks of America to their families and their villages in Greece, I am sure that some day Greek-Americans will realize that all Greece pins its hopes for its future on them, on the Hellenism of America. For that reason I hope that you, like a great family living abroad, will stay together, united, happy and living one another, so as to gladden the great mother-country which watches you from afar. Discord destroys families; harmony preserves them. Do not misunderstand me, my dear friends.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0330.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Again I feel the spiritual encouragement which you gave me, and I set forth to try to succeed elsewhere in my project.</p>
   <p>You are all generous and enthusiastic when you think of your native land. With good organization, united in brotherly charity, you will achieve much.</p>
   <p>And now my boundless thanks! Please accept them, affectionate friends, from one who will never forget you, and who entreats you not to forget her work.</p>
   <p>With love,</p>
   <p>Mother.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
