<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-12-28">Dec. 28, 1929</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">How the Greek Colony in Chicago Could Be Organized.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-12-28">Dec. 28, 1929</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">HOW THE GREEK COLONY IN CHICAGO COULD BE ORGANIZED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To form an educational, social and philanthropic association under the name of Central Greek Association, and united to work for the erection of a residential Greek Educational institution of higher type, including a Greek orphanage, is the subject of this article.</p>
   <p>This institution should be a center for receptions and hospitality for eminent parsonages also a center for the distribution of Charity, in money and goods, to our needy Greek families and Greeks who are poor.</p>
   <p>Members of the Association must be the Greek clergy who are in accord with the ecclesiastical authority, the management and publisher of Greek newspapers and magazines, the professional men the presidents of the various Greek societies and organizations, and contributors of $100 or more.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0144.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The aim should be to bar from membership, person of questionable conduct and those who lack morality. The organization must be composed of healthy and ethical elements in order to acquire the confidence of the people and succeed in achieving the lofty ideals of its creation.</p>
   <p>Means of support will be the dues of the membership,donations and proceeds from social affairs, and other gatherings. The association organized in such a spirit will highly serve the interests of the Greek colony in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Upon such terms and conditions the management of Saloniki is willing to undertake the organization of the association and invites all, who wish to take part, to notify us in order to begin preparations for the preliminary work of the aforesaid association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
