<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-03-30">Mar. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Messinian Benevolent Brotherhood</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-03-30">Mar. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE MESSINIAN BENEVOLENT BROTHERHOOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was about time the Messinians got together for the establishment of a benevolent brotherhood. They have understood that by unity and mutual support they can do much. They can hardly bear the thought that previous efforts to organize and establish strong and lasting Messinian associations have resulted in complete failure. So, two hundred Messinians [Translator's note: natives of Messina, a historic, beautiful, and rich province in the southwestern tip of Greece] came together and vowed that they would work with all their might for the progress and prosperity of the brotherhood.</p>
   <p>We are confident that in a short time the newly organized Messinian Benevolent Brotherhood, composed of members from all five districts of Messina--Kalamon, Messinis, Pylias, Triphylias, and Olympias--will become one of the greatest and strongest Greek organizations in Chicago.</p>
   <p>On March 21 the following members were elected as the governing body for the current year:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0056.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Andreas Petracoyannis, dentist, president; Vasilios Karamitsos, vice-president; Anastasios Tragos, treasurer; S. Poulopoulos, secretary; trustees [Translator's note: there follows a list of ten names of trustees.]</p>
   <p>Saloniki extends to those who took the initiative in organizing the Messinian Benevolent Brotherhood, hearty congratulations and sincere wishes for progress, success, and prosperity.</p>
   <p>The Brotherhood's temporary headquarters will be the office of Mr. Petracoyannis, 600 Blue Island Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
