<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-08-02">Aug. 2, 1930</date><title level="a">Gapa Convention.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1868</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1868.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-08-02">Aug. 2, 1930</date><title level="a">GAPA CONVENTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday morning the Right Reverend Metropolitan Bishop of Corinth, Mr. Damaskenos, arrived in Chicago from New York, to be present at Gapa's convention.</p>
   <p>About 10 A.M. he appeared before the convention and addressed the delegates as follows:</p>
   <p>"I want to congratulate the Gapans for their splendid organization and their sacred aim. Unfortunately, up to this time, the division existing in the church has blocked your progress. But from now on, peace will reign, for the church question has been settled. I wish you full success in the aims of your organization".</p>
   <p>Mr. Mountanos of the committee made a speech of welcome, and the Very Reverend Archimandrite Panos Stamos from Charleston, N. C., addressed the Right Reverend Damaskenos.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1869.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While the convention was in progress, small outings took place. On Tuesday morning more than a hundred delegates and more than a thousand members visited the famous Planetarium. On Wednesday a dance, in honor of the representatives, was given at the Aragon, at which Ambassador Char. Simopoulos was present with the Consul, Mr. Depasta. Mr. Kallimahos, editor-in-chief of the National Herald of New York, who had come to Chicago to attend the convention, was also present at the dances. On Thursday night the ladies of the Chicago lodges, Estia, Kypseli, and Gorgo served tea to the delegates of the ladies' lodges and to the wives of the male delegates at the Edgewater Beach Hotel.</p>
   <p>Tonight on the occasion of the completion of the work of the convention, a dinner will be served at the Medinah Athletic Club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
