<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-10-25">Oct. 25, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us All Work</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-10-25">Oct. 25, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">LET US ALL WORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our colleagues in New York City have been sending us a steady stream of reports describing the national convention of the Panhellenic Order of America, which is holding its deliberations in that city. This is a vital meeting of delegates from all the Greek communities of America, including our own.</p>
   <p>The Panhellenic convention can accomplish great things if it is strongly supported. Its main purpose is unification of, and closer co-operation among, all the Greek communities of the United States. In its efforts to bring together the thousands of Greeks throughout the country, the Order has given the delegates the authority to propose any measure or idea which will promote the common interests of the Greek people.</p>
   <p>The Order does not subject the pocketbooks of our people to a heavy strain; <pb facs="5422062_4_1914.jpg" n="2"/>it does not destroy the freedom of anyone. Every member of the Panhellenic Order can belong to any other organization; everyone can think as he pleases. It has been decided that each member will pay one dollar every six months into the Panhellenic Order's treasury. So, if we suppose that there are 150,000 Greeks in America, the sum of $ 300,000 will be sent to Greece annually. This sum is not to be laughed at.</p>
   <p>It was proposed that every Greek organization contribute five dollars a year to the Panhellenic Order. This is certainly a negligible amount when compared with the hundreds of dollars which the many hundreds of small, local organizations spend for useless purposes and social affairs. In other words, the sum of $300,000 will be sent to Greece for the purpose of helping our families and assisting our fatherland to reconstruct its social, economic, educational, and military life. All this will be done with no serious effort on our part, with no serious strain on our financial resources.</p>
   <p>We know that the good, patriotic, and intelligent Greeks of Chicago are willing to do all in their power to build a national Greek organization whose <pb facs="5422062_4_1915.jpg" n="3"/>immense financial resources, derived from every Greek patriot, will be sufficient to support and maintain all our church, educational, and charitable institutions very effectively and easily.</p>
   <p>We are indeed happy to announce that in the preliminary deliberations of the Panhellenic Order's convention in New York, a motion was passed to the effect that next year's convention be held in Chicago. The convention's decision was telegraphed to Nicholas Salopoulos, the Greek consul general of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
