<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-05-30">May 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Community Pays Homage to the Late Jane Addams</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0838</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0838.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-05-30">May 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK COMMUNITY PAYS HOMAGE TO THE LATE JANE ADDAMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is our duty and obligation as Greek people of Chicago to stop for a moment to pay tribute to a great woman. Since her activities speak for themselves and are known to all of us, we wish to give a brief resume of her life, for the benefit of our own people.</p>
   <p>Jane Addams was born in 1860.....From an early age she displayed philanthropic instincts and concern regarding the fate of the ignorant and oppressed.</p>
   <p>Forty-five years ago she founded Hull House and received the co-operation of many great men who marveled at the courage of the frail girl.....</p>
   <p>Miss Addams's accomplishments are so numerous that it is impossible to refer to <pb facs="5422062_4_0839.jpg" n="2"/>them all in one article. Her greatest attribute was a true and sympathetic understanding of the masses of the poor.</p>
   <p>We shall not even touch upon the honors and renown showered upon her by the entire civilized world. That which we wish to point out is the influence she has exerted upon the growth and development of our own Greek Community.</p>
   <p>At the time when Hull House was founded and during the period of its early development, another great development was taking place. The first Greek community of Chicago was springing up all around Hull House. Much of the progress of our Trinity Church and its parish is directly due to the efforts of Jane Addams. Greek life in this community was firmly bound up with the life in this [Hull House] haven.</p>
   <p>Just as they were to all foreign peoples, the doors [of Hull House] were open to the Greek people. And to Hull House the Greeks went. There they went for <pb facs="5422062_4_0840.jpg" n="3"/>favors, for moral or spiritual guidance, and for rest; there they went to learn English or to get a job. There they went when sons or daughters went astray or when young tots were ill. There they went for protection against unjust labor conditions, or to seek justice. Each one was helped, comforted, encouraged or defended by this brave, saintly woman.</p>
   <p>The first Greek affair given in Chicago took place in 1903 when a play by Sophocles was presented in the Hull House Theater. This was the first public recognition of the Greek people in Chicago. Some of the men who took part are still alive....</p>
   <p>In 1919 Hull House encouraged and was the home of a club for Greek adolescent boys. Later on the Olympic Athletic Club was formed. Thus Hull House to a great extent served Greek youth.</p>
   <p>All of these things seem so easy of accomplishment now, but at that time they were the fruit of much unceasing labor. If they have become realities it is due to the existence of Hull House. All of us who were young men then, considered it our true home, for we all had come over here alone, and had suffered <pb facs="5422062_4_0841.jpg" n="4"/>bitterly from loneliness. Evenings we read from the fine books placed invitingly within reach, and Sundays were spent getting acquainted, resting from the turmoil outside, and gathering courage to face the morrow.</p>
   <p>When the time comes when we shall record the history of our Greek community shall the labor of Miss Addams be acknowledged? She was our best and greatest friend. Some day, I hope our community will make some public gift in honor of Jane Addams.</p>
   <p>As a simple token of our eternal gratitude a huge wreath was sent to the bier of our dead friend. This was contributed by the Halsted Street Merchants. Every Greek store has displayed the color of mourning as a token of respect to the late, great, Jane Addams.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
