<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">"Ahepa's May-Day Ball at Aragon,"</title><title>Ahepa Herald</title>, (Official Organ of District No. 21, 77 W. Washington St., Chicago, Illinois),
<date when="1934-05-01">May 1, 1934</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">"Ahepa's May-Day Ball At Aragon,"</title><title>Ahepa Herald</title>, (Official Organ of District No. 21, 77 W. Washington St., Chicago, Illinois),
<date when="1934-05-01">May 1, 1934</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mayor Edward J. Kelly of the city of Chicago will be the guest of honor of the Ahepa, at the Grand May Day Ball, on Wednesday night, May the 2nd at the Aragon Ballroom, Winthrop and Lawrence Avenues.</p>
   <p>Over five thousand Greek-Americans are expected to greet the highest city official. Office holders of Ahepadom in Chicago, past and present, will be on hand to assist Brother Demetrius Parry, District Governor of the 21st District in the execution of the proper rites for the biggest event in the social calendar of Chicago's Hellenism.</p>
   <p>Former District Governor Arthur Peponis, one of the most loved of the brothers in the District is in charge of the program. Something of exquisite beauty, brilliancy and originality has been arranged and in its glory it will be revealed before the five thousand or more Hellenes who will gather at the Aragon on Wednesday, May 2nd.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1162.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"All roads lead to the Aragon on that night," said Demetrius Parry. And there are reasons for that. And for your information here they are.</p>
   <p>1. The purpose of the dance is high. It is given for the treasury, to establish an orchestra in Chicago by the Ahepa. The "Brain Trusters" of the past never thought of musical institutions for the Ahepans. But Bro. Parry a "New Dealer" so to speak, has thought about it.</p>
   <p>2. Wayne King will play. By that we mean that you will hear music of novel beauty. Bro. Wayne King will play his American compositions that are popular now, numbers of years gone by bringing back memories when George Bambakaris and William Russis were seventeen, and will also play Greek melodies of unique rhythmical attraction.</p>
   <p>3. Gladys Hight, and her nationally famous Greek classic dancers will give Terpsichorian interpretations that we have never seen before. Back to the banks of the Acropolis she will bring us. Spiros Stamos will be <pb facs="5422062_4_1163.jpg" n="3"/>there and there is enough said when one mentions the name of Spiros Stamos "The Modern Orpheus."</p>
   <p>4. The admission is only $1.00 per person and .....................And if you want to get more dope about everything why not tune in on radio Station WLS, "The Prairie Farmer Station" on Monday, April 30th, at 2:15 P.M. and hear the advance broadcast of the Ahepa in connection with this dance. Stamos will be in charge of the program. His Sanduri will be there. His chorus will sing. So why not tune in. Songs galore! Music galore!</p>
   <p>Until we meet again, but it will be at the Aragon, May 2nd, Wednesday night together with the Mayor and the rest of the 5,000 people who will be present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
