<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">With Malice Towards None; with Charity for All</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_0983</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_0983.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">WITH MALICE TOWARDS NONE; WITH CHARITY FOR ALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An immigrant was leaning on the railing of an ocean liner. He was staring at the Statue of Liberty and the forest of skyscrapers silhouetted against New York's horizon. He saw then the realization of his dreams. In the new land, riches and luxuries would be provided by a simple command. He would find kindness, understanding, justice.</p>
   <p>And now he tells his story: "At first," he says, "I found myself bitterly disappointed. I made a mistake in thinking that I was coming to a civilization that would free me of all responsibility. I thought that this civilization was complete and perfect. I thought that all I had to do was to reach and grasp the golden fruit. It is a good thing that I was deceived because my struggle made me strong. I helped build America. America is in the making. What America will become, depends on those who are working as much for her as they are for themselves. The Declaration of Independence mentions that there are three inalienable rights--Life, Liberty, and the pursuit of Happiness. But these are not things which <pb facs="5422062_4_0984.jpg" n="2"/>one may enjoy for one's self only. They are blessings which ought to be shared with one's fellow citizens, with both the immigrants and the native Americans, irrespective of race or creed. if we desire these rights, we must work for them, and work all together.</p>
   <p>"I discovered that the language of the land was the first thing I had to learn. I then studied the customs and the government of the country. I complained about the racial prejudices against other nationalities. When I became acquainted with other people, however, and worked with and for them, my own prejudices started to disappear. I am an American citizen now, and next month I shall vote for the first time."</p>
   <p>For this man, election day has great significance. Not all those who have come from other countries are now citizens. Most of them will become citizens one day. Those who are already American citizens have the opportunity to contribute in the building of America by using their ballot intelligently. No one should vote merely to oblige his friend, or by the <pb facs="5422062_4_0985.jpg" n="3"/>dictation of his supposed leader. He must vote only for those who inspire absolute confidence. He should not vote for platforms favoring the interests of one particular group, but for those that concern the welfare of all classes. In this way, he can help make the America the ideal land of his dreams.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
