<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-02">Apr. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">[Independence Day at Hammond]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1521</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1521.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-02">Apr. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">[INDEPENDENCE DAY AT HAMMOND]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our National Independence Day Feast was magnificently celebrated at Hammond, Indiana, under the leadership of the Ahepa Chapter, there. A sumptuous dinner was served to 500 Greeks at the Women's Club. Mr. Charal Tamparis was Toastmaster and speaker of the day was Mr. Athanasios Pantelis, lawyer from Chicago. Among those who were present was Mr. Dion. Yiannakis, Ahepan of Brooklyn Chapter #41, and a representative of the Chicago Greek Daily, who spoke. It is worth while to make a summary of Mr. Yiannakis speech.</p>
   <p>He said, "The Greeks were under the Turkish yoke, for 400 years, during which time the barbarian conqueror was depriving them of their land, property, and children, taking children to make them slaves. There were two things which he did not succeed in depriving them of, and they were Religion and Language, which were preserved with great sacrifice. The Greek roasted over fire and skimmed alive by the barbarous Turns, still preserved his Religion and Language and when our here ancestors succeeded in liberating Greece, though they were but a handful against a powerful and organized enemy, they handed down to us, Religion and Language, in order that we may hand them down to our children.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1522.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They remained Orthodox Greeks in the midst of fire and sword. In a free Democracy where we have liberty and where nobody has ever prevented us from being Orthodox, or from speaking our language, why should we become infidel, or repudiate our language, our country and our race?</p>
   <p>"It is useless to hold feasts and ceremonies if we do not respect the memory of our fathers and express scorn at those things for which they sacrificed their lives.</p>
   <p>"Let us all, therefore, build churches and schools and let us endeavor to keep our children as Greek Orthodox."</p>
   <p>Mr. Yiannakis received the compliments of his hearers and the ceremony ended with everybody well satisfied.</p>
   <p>(Full)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
