<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">"Tri-Deka Drive a Huge Success,"</title><title>Ahepa Herald</title>, (Official Organ of District No. 21, 1521 N. Clark St., Chicago, Ill.)
<date when="1933-03-15">March 15, 1933</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1806</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1806.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">"Tri-Deka Drive A Huge Success,"</title><title>Ahepa Herald</title>, (Official Organ of District No. 21, 1521 N. Clark St., Chicago, Ill.)
<date when="1933-03-15">March 15, 1933</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of the Supreme Lodge which was held in our city a special drive to get new members into the ranks of our fraternity was launched. The drive was to afford an opportunity to many good citizens to become members at the least possible cost to them. The plan has proven a great sensation. At the last district meeting which was held at the Northshore chapter the presidents of the various chapters reported that the applications were coming in faster in numbers and by far beyond their expectations.</p>
   <p>We know that each member can, if he tried, induce a friend to file an application to become a member. It should not be difficult to convince anyone who is open to conviction that the initiation fee and the dues that are being asked are the cheapest and best investment he has ever been called upon to make.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1807.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Has not the Ahepa the first to conduct excursions to Greece, which has netted to the Greek people in Greece more than five millions of dollars? Has not the Ahepa contributed large sums of money for the maintenance of the Greek Schools and the Greek Church?</p>
   <p>Is it not a fact that in communities where Greek Schools and Greek Churches had not been organized were organized and are now being supported by the Ahepans of those communities? Can it be successfully contradicted that many leaders of our church and school organizations as well as other societies have received their early training of leadership in the Ahepa? Can it be denied that the Ahepa was the first organization that has brought to the attention of the American people that the Greek-American Citizen is as loyal to the American ideals as other loyal citizens and that it deserved the same recognition?</p>
   <p>The Ahepa is an ideal. It represents a distinctive attitude towards the country of our adoption - an attitude that has been wholeheartedly endorsed by Greek and American leaders of all walks of life. Scientists, scholars, explorers, students, statesmen, governors, and mayors of American ancestry have joined the ranks of this fraternity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1808.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Is not the President of the United States a member of the Fraternity?</p>
   <p>What better inducements do you need to convince your friends to join? We cannot think of any. The drive ends the end of this month. Bring in at least one new application and help your chapter win one of the valuable prizes which have been offered by the Supreme Lodge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
