<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>"<title>The Ahepa</title>" Official Program of the First Annual Entertainment and Ball Given Under the Combined Auspices of the Chapters of the District 21 of the Order of Ahepa, Chicago, Illinois,
<date when="1932-05-08">May 8, 1932</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1809</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1809.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>"The Ahepa"</title> Official Program of the First Annual Entertainment and Ball Given Under the Combined Auspices of the Chapters of the District 21 of the Order of Ahepa, Chicago, Illinois,
<date when="1932-05-08">May 8, 1932</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ahepa was organized in Atlanta, Georgia, in July, 1922. It was a great necessity to the Greeks of the Southern states because they were being maliciously treated by a powerful and hostile organization.</p>
   <p>The Greeks who became organized to protect their interests little dreamed that their tiny group would grow to such power and success. They unknowingly laid the foundation for the greatest Greek National organization in America.</p>
   <p>The original purpose of the organization was to uphold Greek rights and preserve Hellenism for the coming generations of Greek descent. At first the group was very small, but immigration from Greece soon corrected this.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1810.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The annual conventions of the Order of Ahepa which take place all over the country emphasize the feeling of brotherhood and cooperation which is not lacking in a single Ahepan. The conventions bring out new progress. They bring exaltation, enthusiasm, and pride to all members. They put other conventions to shame by their order, their regulation, their magnificence and their hospitality.</p>
   <p>The Ahepa aids and contributes to the support of the poor people; it does what it can for the unemployed; it supports the churches and the communities, and it cooperates with all other organizations. Never once has its members been at odds among themselves or with other organizations. System and order prevail in all that they do. A helping hand is always extended to a brother Ahepan. Hellenism in the entire United States is carefully protected from any blemish whatever. Every member has one aim, one purpose, one goal - Hellenic idealization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1811.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Ahepa is proud, but not haughty. It does great deeds but does not crow about them. The work is done quietly and faithfully, and the members are rewarded by the feeling of a duty well done.</p>
   <p>Ahepa is always a champion of truth and justice. The best of ancient Greek civilization is combined with the best of the modern and this gives us - Ahepa.</p>
   <p>G. A. Kyriakopoulos,</p>
   <p>Governor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
