<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-31">Oct. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Various Reports from the Chicago Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_4_1155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-21">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-31">Oct. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">VARIOUS REPORTS FROM THE CHICAGO SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Little by little there comes to light the doings of great organizations that profess to reorganize the unfortunate Hellenism of America.</p>
   <p>Of course there are the well-known tricks with which we are acquainted, and because of which the indifference of the Greek public has grown.</p>
   <p>Even though these secrets are common knowledge we present them to you and beg your pardon, for these small scandals have been publicly discussed for some time.</p>
   <p>And what kind of scandals are these, that are common secrets of all? Simply the disagreements of the high officials of the two big Greek organizations, namely, the Ahepa and the Gapa.</p>
   <p>In the last edition of the Ahepa publication, a letter from its president explains this disagreement of the high officials of the Ahepa. It appears <pb facs="5422062_4_1156.jpg" n="2"/>to be for the purpose of exploiting the brothers and so there will be two excursions to Greece, under two separate groups. One with the Greek steamer, Byron, and the other with the Italian line.</p>
   <p>Let the interested brothers of the Ahepa come to understand and regulate their own interests in regard to these excursions.</p>
   <p>The other organization, the Gapa, was founded to counteract the operations of the former, which has been working against the interests of Hellenism in America. There is not much difference between the two of them.</p>
   <p>This pillar of Hellenism, Ahepa, is nothing but an organization of Greeks, with the usual indication of the troublesome Grecian character, let us look at its deeds here in Chicago.</p>
   <p>On the South side there are two women's organizations fighting for the name of their chapter. There is also a men's chapter which is not recognized by <pb facs="5422062_4_1157.jpg" n="3"/>the central organization. One of these women's chapters is ignored by the central committee, like that of the men.</p>
   <p>According to information from Mr. Christ Christofilos, who is president of the men's chapter, the central committee, for trivial reasons and against the rules of procedure, has outlawed his chapter, so they await the next general convention to assert their rights there.</p>
   <p>Mr. Christofilos asserts that this outlawed chapter is progressing and increasing its membership rapidly taking a leading part in all social movements. It is also helping the schools of its district and does not pay attention to the action of the central committee.</p>
   <p>Mr. Christofilos is one of the most active men in the Parish and enjoys the esteem and confidence of the community for his good social services.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_4_1158.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>While he was president of the Messenians he uncovered the abuses of the finances and discovered the embezzlements of Mr. Eustathios Nestordes and Mr. Demetrios Athanasopoulos, who, like some others, were forced to pay back the money illegally obtained.</p>
   <p>The women's auxiliary does not show a good condition either.</p>
   <p>During the auxiliary election time the hall was transformed into a battlefield for the two factions of the ladies, who were interested in electing their candidate as doctor of the organization.</p>
   <p>The insults and attacks of the faction which lost the election, and the one that won resulted in the resignation of the president and the holding of new elections, in which the winners lost.</p>
   <p>These conditions in the social circles are not only funny but disgusting. For instance, it has been a subject of discussion among some socialites <pb facs="5422062_4_1159.jpg" n="5"/>and a few of the almost educated on how we will help the new Greek generation become Philhellenic! It is very interesting to hear the foolishness passed off as grand ideas and to listen to some people expressing themselves is amazing and disgusting. Is this the district mentality of the Chicago Greek?</p>
   <p>This condition is general, and to illustrate it we report the incident of a woman of the society, who at the celebration of her husband 's name-day, brought performers from a cabaret to entertain the party with their songs, dances, poses and almost nude bodies, even though two priests were among the guests!</p>
   <p>We comment on the dance of the ladies of the St. Andrews Parish, in another section of the paper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
