<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-27">Dec. 27, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The Christmas Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1237</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1237.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-27">Dec. 27, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHRISTMAS FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Christmas festival, with all its joys and surprises, is now a thing of the past. Life and activity on the streets and in the stores--the inevitable concomitant of the holiday--have returned to normalcy and quiet--if such a word as "quiet" can find a place in the description of an American "big city".....</p>
   <p>Although the pleasures of the family circle cannot be surpassed, one is nevertheless seized with the desire to seek companionship among friends and acquaintances. And opportunities to satisfy this desire were not lacking in Chicago. Everywhere, at the Christmas season,festivals and entertainments were arranged; various invitingly-decorated and spacious [turner and singing society] halls were sought out by a gay, motley crowd. One might, for example, mention the following programs:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1238.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>CENTRAL HALL</p>
   <p>Corner Wabash Avenue and 22nd Street</p>
   <p>The Concordia Maennerchor arranged an evening entertainment for the Christmas celebration. Although this organization has arranged excellent musical performances in the past, its outstanding programs have been especially frequent recently, ever since Oscar Schmoll has been the Maennerchor's leader. The society's ambitions and efforts are commendable, and the success attained by Mr. Schmoll is worthy of profound recognition.</p>
   <p>The program chosen for last Saturday evening's entertainment revealed good taste and artistic perception. A varied program was offered. The separate numbers left nothing to be desired; in fact, many of those who took part in the concert were rewarded with especial acclaim. Verdi's overture to "Nebuchadnezzar," played by the orchestra, was the first number. It found unanimous approval, as did the following two selections of the Concordia Maennerchor--one of which, the song "Mein Fruehling," deserves special mention.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1239.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Miss Thomas played a piano concerto by Thalberg. All of this composer's works are very difficult to execute; they contain passages which require considerable exertion for their rendition. In view of this fact, Miss Thomas deserves profound recognition for her masterly performance. The same can be said of Oscar Schmoll. In playing his selection, "Ossian," Mr. Schmoll proved again his mastery of his instrument [the piano]. The other offerings, solos and duets, earned deserved applause.</p>
   <p>A dance was held after the concert, obvious proof that the members of the Concordia Maennerchor not only dedicate themselves to art, but are a jovial lot besides. All enjoyed the terpsichorean pleasures, and at a late hour gay melodies were still coming from the brightly illuminated hall.</p>
   <p>AURORA TURNHALLE</p>
   <p>On the same evening an entertainment was given by the Aurora Turnverein. This was also a very pleasant and gay affair--indeed this Verein has the reputation <pb facs="5418474_10_1240.jpg" n="4"/>of being a center of good-natured comradeship.</p>
   <p>The program was entirely different from that of the Concordia Maennerchor.... While music held sway among the members of the singing society, gymnastics were indulged in by the Aurora Turnverein, and all the gymnastic exercises were performed with precision and confidence. The gymnastic feats performed on parallel bars, horizontal bar, and ladder were excellent. The exercises without equipment were likewise very good.</p>
   <p>The club-swinging exercises met with great acclaim. They provided an opportunity for the fair sex to demonstrate its prowess. Then followed the manifestation of the Christmas spirit--the distribution of presents. This proved highly amusing. Gifts of all kinds were raffled off--some were beautiful and valuable; others were noteworthy for their originality.</p>
   <p>At the end of the festival, a dance was held which lasted until morning. <pb facs="5418474_10_1241.jpg" n="5"/>Joy and gaiety also prevailed at the Vorwaerts Turnhalle on Saturday evening. The Vorwaerts Verein has a certain knack for arranging festivals and entertainments, and so it provided an enjoyable evening. While no speeches were on the program, and no perfectly synchronized gymnastic exercises were performed for the elation of the spectator, the festival was notable for the spirit of genuine sociability which reigned throughout the celebration.</p>
   <p>Here, too, the raffling of presents provided much amusement..... The ball terminating the festival proved to be a very delightful affair.....</p>
   <p>THE CHICAGO TURNGEMEINDE</p>
   <p>The Chicago Turngemeinde celebrated Christmas in its own hall with a concert and raffling of presents.</p>
   <p>The Great Western Band played an overture for the opening number, displaying the precision and self-assurance for which the orchestra is so well known. The <pb facs="5418474_10_1242.jpg" n="6"/>Turner Maennerchor then sang Maehring's "Jagdlied" and it was quite evident that the chorus had made gratifying progress.</p>
   <p>Mr. Schmoll's rendition of Thalberg's "Grande Fantasie De Concert" was excellent, and he received deserved applause. The Turner Maennerchor then offered "Das Deutsche Lied".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
