<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1926-04-18">Apr. 18, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Lutheran Parishes of Chicago and Vicinity</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bethany Community, Pastor August Burgdorf, 2546 Cortez Street</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1926-04-18">Apr. 18, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">LUTHERAN PARISHES OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bethany Community, Pastor August Burgdorf, 2546 Cortez Street</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today the Bethany parish inaugurates its school. Services begin at 11 o'clock. Professor C. M. G. Eifrig of River Forest Teacher's Seminary will deliver the German sermon and Professor Paul Bretscher the English one. Choirs will sing. Coreligionists from near and far are invited to attend the services. The building is at the corner of Narragansett and Wabansia Avenues. On the occasion of inaugurating the House of God, the services of last Sunday were well attended. The building is a handsome, solid structure, taller than the other buildings in the neighborhood. The cellar contains the steam boiler, kitchen, and a few other rooms. On the first floor there are two school-rooms provided with electrical ventilation. The second floor has a spacious hall, furnished like a church. It will at times be used for gatherings of a devotional nature. There is also one other room, which will serve as vestry.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1425.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Jehovah Parish, Pastor Arthur W. Luszky 2310 North Ridgeway Avenue</p>
   <p>Professor A. Beck of River Forest was at the church Sunday with his student choir. The choir pleased the congregation by singing a few songs during services. This year seventy-five children were confirmed, twenty-nine in German and forty-six in English. On April 23, the Senior Youth Club of the congregation will give an evening's entertainment, in which the play "Thirty Days" will be produced. Everybody is welcome. For the time being, John Zitzmann is acting as principal, Walter Wendt, A. G. Ortlip, and C. A. Lehmann as teachers.</p>
   <p>First St. Paul's Parish, Pastor H. Kowert,</p>
   <p>1826 North Hammond Street</p>
   <p>Thursday evening, a banquet was given by the women's club. At 8:15 Pastor F. R. Webber of Cleveland, Ohio, gave a lecture on church architecture.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1426.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Banquet and lecture were well attended.</p>
   <p>Bund of Lutheran Brethren</p>
   <p>The directors of this aid society were we-elected by a large majority. Every pastor and teacher of the Synodal Conference may join it. Please apply to the secretary, C. Franklin Brandt, 2441 Ballou Street, Chicago.</p>
   <p>Concert of Teachers' Choir</p>
   <p>This afternoon the teachers' choir gives its yearly concert at Orchestra Hall on Michigan Avenue. "Elijah" will be performed in English. Tickets are still to be had at the box office at 50, 75 cents, $1 and $1.50. The audience of the concert will be given a unique musical pleasure, soothing to the heart and to the emotions.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1427.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Conference of Pastors</p>
   <p>The northern district of the North Illinois Pastoral Conference met Tuesday, Wednesday, and Thursday at St. Luke's Parish (Pastor Carl J. A. Hoffmann). The officers of the conference are: chairman, C. M. Noack (Pastor Paul Luecke, Pastor Heinrich Kowert); secretary, Pastor W. G. Fechner (Pastor J. E. A. Mueller); chaplain, Pastor F. Zersen (Pastor H. W. Meyer); treasurer, Pastor Daniel Poellet (Pastor W. Bramscher); executive committee, Pastors P. Seils, D. Poellet, and H. Heise; committee for topics, Pastors H. Richter, H. Moldenhauer, and Mueller.</p>
   <p>Concert of the Walther League</p>
   <p>Last Sunday's entertainment provided by the League was crowned with great success. The show "Take my Advice" was played by Georg Heissler, Wilhelm Gratsch, Edgar Elbert, Gertrude Bietzke, Carl Dehlinger, Ruth Schaare, <pb facs="5418474_10_1428.jpg" n="5"/>Elizabeth Bussert, and Dorothy Engelbrecht. The piece was well rehearsed, the presentation masterful. The surplus goes into the cash register of the hospice.</p>
   <p>Independent German Evangelical Lutheran Christ's Parish</p>
   <p>German Sunday School(and, if need be, also in English), will be conducted at 10 A.M. Services with German sermons at 10:30 A.M. Pastor E. M. Lehmann lives at 4411 Dover Street. Private instruction in religion and languages. Morning services will begin tentatively at 10:30.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
