<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-07">Aug. 7, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Festival of the Old Settlers of the Metropolis of the West.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0791</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0791.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-07">Aug. 7, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE FESTIVAL OF THE OLD SETTLERS OF THE METROPOLIS OF THE WEST.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's picnic, arranged by the Turner Community, took place as usual at Ogden's Grove. This is the historical gathering place of the German-Americans of the North Side.... Any one desirous of getting acquainted with the history of Chicago and the reason for its phenomenal growth, should visit the picnic of the Old Settlers.</p>
   <p>Only through contact with these fine Chicagoans, who battled the conflagration and the subsequent hardships, can one gain a real understanding of their excellent work. Due to their efforts, Chicago has become the outstanding city of our great country....</p>
   <p>It was 26 years ago that the officials of the Turner Community conceived the idea of a picnic for men and women whom they called the builders of Chicago. It was a great idea! Yesterday, every guest who inscribed his or her name on the list of honor, and who had resided in Chicago for more than 22 years, was presented with a gold colored silk bow. The black lettering on it indicated the claim of its bearer as a fellow builder of our magnificent city....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0792.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The festive address was delivered by the turner, Emil Hoechster, chairman of the arrangements committee. He said: "Looking at this multitude of people, representing the old settler, we can not but recall the part they have played as builders of this great city, which is among the largest and most important of the world today.</p>
   <p>"Indeed, German culture which our old settlers have brought with them, has been greatly influential in American life, not only in this city, but throughout the country. The Germans can proudly state that they were always ready to obey and respect the laws of their adopted fatherland.</p>
   <p>"They have always been true citizens of this country. As such, their efforts will always be directed against the tyranny of fanatic bigotry. It is partly due to the Germans that America is known as the greatest nation in the world today. To defend this country has always been a sacred duty for the German-Americans. This they have demonstrated whenever the United States was in need of volunteers.</p>
   <p>"The great Bismarck once said; 'The unity of the German people has been welded together with iron and with blood.' The country of our choice has, <pb facs="5418474_10_0793.jpg" n="3"/>likewise, become great only after the shedding of blood. The use of arms has brought about the unity of the nation. A free people we are, and free we shall remain."...</p>
   <p>The distribution of medals then took place. Following are the winners: The oldest German born male settler was Mr. Joseph Miller, a Chicagoan since 1835. The oldest native German female settler of Chicago was Mrs. Barbara Pinter, a resident here since 1840....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
