<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-05-11">May 11, 1907</date><title level="a">German-American National Union. the Local Branch Made an Appeal to the Germans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0750</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0750.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-05-11">May 11, 1907</date><title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN NATIONAL UNION. THE LOCAL BRANCH MADE AN APPEAL TO THE GERMANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago branch of the German-American National Union has its headquarters in Room 912 of the Schiller Building, and the meeting of delegates takes place on the 27th of May. The branch union issued the following proclamation:</p>
   <p>To the Germans: Unity creates strength. The world looks with admiration upon the German people and its achievements. After its example, the Union of German-Americans will unite for mutual action and to reach the aim which hovers before us: Recognition of German merits in our new country; cultivation and maintenance of the German mother tongue, shield of our intellectual treasure; physical education of the youth of both sexes, through the schools; preserving and disseminating German culture all the time and everywhere. Promotion of German sociability under the flag of assured personal liberty. Through the latter gifts Germans will, in spite of rabid fanaticism, become the advocate of true temperance, and will teach the American people to distinguish <pb facs="5418474_10_0751.jpg" n="2"/>between sane enjoyment of life and dissipation. And in the yearly celebration of German day, in remembrance of our belonging to each other, this struggle finds its most beautiful expression.</p>
   <p>The Union has already achieved important results through obstructing those attempts which were intended to abet prohibition, and to put obstacles in the way of immigration, not to mention its other activities and those of its branches in the different states. The Chicago Branch exists already for one year and includes already seventy associations, with a total membership of ten thousand and a number of single members. True to its mission it will spread among the hundreds of German societies and the hundreds of thousands of German population of our city, and help to achieve the position due to it. The eyes of the country rest upon the metropolis of the West, and its powerful German element; we have elected two of our race to the head of the city government and as city treasurer, although they appeared as political opponents before the citizenry. Last year's German day will be remembered by all those who participated at the banquet in the Auditorium, and a similar <pb facs="5418474_10_0752.jpg" n="3"/>worthy festival will take place next autumn even on a larger scale. Our resolution is: Forward with united forces.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
