<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-09-02">Sep. 2, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Swabians.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0927</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0927.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-09-02">Sep. 2, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWABIANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swabians or those Germans who came from that part of Germany known as the Kingdom of Wurtemberg, had a great day yesterday. They celebrated the "Cannstadter Volksfest" for the second time in this city, in a manner that reflects great credit upon the Swabian Society, under whose auspices the festivities were arranged and the ceremonies carried out. Those festivials are very popular in the old country, and judging from their success have this year and last, they will become no less popular in this part of the world.</p>
   <p>The procession was one of the finest and most imposing that ever passed through the streets of this city, and was far ahead of the successful procession of last year. It started at about 10 o'clock from the corner of Desplaines and Randolph Streets and moved east on Randolph to Wells, thence north to Division, thence west to Clybourn Avenue and thence to Ogden's Grove, where the great festival was held. First came a squad of police on horseback under command of Lieut. Baus and then a band in an elegant bandwagon. The Chief Marshal, Ernst Hummel came next, surrounded by a large <pb facs="5418474_10_0928.jpg" n="2"/>staff, all on horseback, then a large squad of horsemen in old, fantastic Swabian costumes following. Then came a large number of Tableau Wagons representing every phase in Swabian history. The most notable among these was a wagon with a tableau representing the organization of the University of Tuebingen. Another representing the Emperor Rothbart in the Kytthauser mountain, and on the summit of the mountain a woman representing Germania. The allegorical tableau "Schiller's Bell" was also finely done. There was also a tableau wagon representing the four Judicial Circuits of Wurtemberg, followed by 64 persons on horseback with standards, on which were inscribed the names of the 64 Judicial Courts in that state. There was another wagon with a tableau representing the return of a Swabian wedding party from church, which was finely gotten up. Besides these there were "a Swabian School", a Swabian Mail-Express and a number of other interesting and amusing tableaux. The whole was finished up with a large number of carriages containing invited guests, members of the Swabian Society, etc.</p>
   <p>The streets through which the procession passed, were finely decorated with flags, garlands, evergreens and mottoes. Particularly conspicuous in this respect was Sedgwick Street, between Division and Goethe. At the corner of Sigel and Sedgwick Streets a garland of evergreens was stretched across the <pb facs="5418474_10_0929.jpg" n="3"/>street, on which was suspended a finely decorated clothes-basket in which stood a man clad in an old German uniform with drawn sword and spy glass, representing Duke Ulrich, reviewing the procession. The bogus Duke was suspended in the air from 9 o'clock in the morning until nearly 1 o'clock in the afternoon, and he was kept alive by large potations of lager-beer, which he drew up in a dinner pail with a string.</p>
   <p>This spectacle afforded immense amusement to about 1000 children. When the poor Duke was lowered to terra firma, he presented a sorrowful spectacle. He was almost overcome by the heat, and from standing in a cramped position so long, his legs refused to act. He had to be carried into a saloon, where a few potations of lager beer soon revived him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
