<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-10-07">Oct. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Celebration of Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-10-07">Oct. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN CELEBRATION OF ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>German-Americans in Chicago celebrated yesterday the anniversary of the founding of the first German colony in America that was established at Germantown, Pa., more than two centuries ago. The celebration at Chicago was in the form of a concert in German at the Auditorium, under the direction of Prof. G. Katzenberger.</p>
   <p>The program included songs by the choruses, which are being trained by Professor Katzenberger for the World's Fair, solos, a prologue by Miss Brehme, and a festival cration by E. F. L. Gauss. Three thousand people had gathered in the Auditorium to hear the folk songs and to listen to the oration.</p>
   <p>On the stage, a rising semi-circle of seats reaching almost to the back of the immense stage was filled with the members of the choruses. On either side were the male choruses, in the middle the women's chorus, and in the front the children's chorus. There were 550 people in the main chorus, and 250 children, making a total of 800 voices in the combined chorus.</p>
   <p>The audience found much to approve in the program rendered, and it was liberal in its applause from the opening number until the united chorus sung in English <pb facs="5418474_10_1205.jpg" n="2"/>"My Country 'Tis of Thee", just before the big steel curtain was lowered.</p>
   <p>The concert opened with the singing of "Welcome" by the mixed chorus, accompanied by the full orchestra. This was followed by the "Jubilee Overture" by C. M. Von Weber and by Wagner's "Tannhauser March", by the mixed chorus and orchestra. "The German Day", a festival prologue written by Fred. Roesch of California, was delivered by Miss Freda Brehme. It was an exhortation to the German-Americans to make the most of their opportunities in the great republic, to love liberty and order, to esteem both the Star Spangled Banner and the flag of Germany, and to be true to the traditions of German Day. This met with long continued applause.</p>
   <p>Following this was a children's chorus in the mother tongue and songs for mixed voices, including "A Frost Fell in the Calm Spring Night", "Fly With Me and Be My Own", and "Oh Mountains High, Oh Dales So Wide". The soprano solo by Mrs. Anna Katzenberger, "In Verdure Clad" from Haydn's "Creation", was warmly received, the audience insisting on an encore. Mrs. Katzenberger then sang, "It was a Dream". The applause which followed lasted for several minutes.</p>
   <p>The program continued with the women's chorus singing "Under Trees and Woods is Rest", by Kuhlan; "The Heavens are Telling", by Haydn, sung by the united chorus; and "People's Songs", also by the chorus.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1206.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The festival oration was delivered by E. F. L. Gauss, who in a fifteen minute talk, told the audience some of the faults of the German race along with their virtues. He said the Germans in coming to the United States should become part and parcel of the great American people, leaving their clannishness behind them, yet being united in all cases where there was necessity for united action. Above all things, they should remember that they were Americans when they became citizens of this great country. They should teach their children English and fit them to fight the battles which must come to them in after life.</p>
   <p>Following Mr. Gauss' address, the musical program was resumed, the mixed chorus singing "The Heavens Resound", by Beethoven. The concert was closed with the singing of "My Country 'Tis of Thee", by the united chorus, accompanied by the full orchestra.</p>
   <p>Prof. Katzenberger's chorus is being trained for German concerts next summer, and also in English. The chorus will be part of the great World's Fair chorus under the direction of Prof. W. L. Tomlins. In speaking of the women's chorus under Prof. Katzenberger's instruction, Prof. Tomlins said it was unquestionably the best women's chorus in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
