<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-09-18">September 18, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Politicians Astonished</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0232</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0232.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-09-18">September 18, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICIANS ASTONISHED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"UNITED SOCIETIES" WILL EXPEAND THEIR ORGANIZATION THROUGHOUT THE STATE. CHAOS IN THE REPUBLICAN CAMP.........MAYOR BUSSE ANNOUNCED, THAT HE WILL NOT CLOSE THE SALOONS ON SUNDAY.....PREPARATION FOR THE SESSION OF THE LEGISLATURE.........TODAY, AFTER ELECTION, CHAOS RULED IN THE REPUBLICAN CAMP, OF THAT PORTION, WHICH IS IN THE CONTROL OF THE POLITICAL MACHINE OF BUSSE-REDDICK-CAMPBELL-HENBERG.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0233.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The victory won by the "United Societies for Social Self-Government," which registered 75,000 voters against the charter, threw the politicians in great dismay, realizing now, that this organization has become a power of incalculble, strength, that will not negligently permit itself to be shoved aside. Add to this, that a series of innovations in Government, which the new charter would have inaugurated, and which the present office holders thought indispensible could not now be procured. So they will endeavor to obtain these innovations from the legislature by means of separate bills. How it will react to this is problematical, and gives the gentlemen in the City Hall a great headache.</p>
   <p>The United Societies for Social Self-Government," will start immediately with its program of expansion through the state. All societies, war veterans, turners, singing clubs, and benevolent societies in the larger cities will be united to participate very actively in elections, especially the candidates to the legislature will be closely scrutinized.</p>
   <p>It does not intend to forget its friends in the legislature, but will deal with our foes more intensely. Till the next election to the legislature, it will <pb facs="5418474_10_0234.jpg" n="3"/>have fully organized a large number of legislative districts, so that it will turn the scale in its favor.</p>
   <p>In the City of Chicago its power will be used to clear the City Hall of a bunch of hypocrites. "We are now a mighty factor in the political life, as we proved yesterday and we will use our influence against all dangerous laws and work for the adoption of good ones."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
