<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-09-19">September 19, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Demonstration. Veterans of the German Wars Parade for Mc Kinley's Death.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-09-19">September 19, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">MASS DEMONSTRATION. VETERANS OF THE GERMAN WARS PARADE FOR MC KINLEY'S DEATH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Alliance of the Veterans of the German army and the German Veteran's Club of Chicagi will meet tomorrow, Thursday the 19th of September at 12:45 P. M. at Jung's Hall, 106 Randolph Street. The veterans will march from there with black-draped flags and their musicians to the rallying point of the 2nd Division, where all veterans' Associations will be directed to their respective places in the parade. All German Military Clubs of Chicago and vicinity, also those comrades, who do not belong to any organizations, are hereby urgently requested to appear at Jung's Hall, for the mourning parade in honor of the departed President, Mc Kinley.</p>
   <p>Turners: Greetings! The Committee desires the participation of all the Turn-Clubs of Chicago at the mourning parade of the late President Mc Kinley, which will be held on September 19th, and asks for the courtesy of an immediate reply. Kindly notify George Alling, chairman of the Parade Committee, Council Chamber, City Hall, whether you can accede to this request and also give the name of your leaders. With Turner-salutation, in the name of the Committee, Max Stern...</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1191.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To the Clubs of The Chicago Turn Districts! Greetings! The Turners are hereby requested to tale an active part in the parade. Concentration point! Michigan Avenue, North of Randolph Street; start 3 P.M., promptly. F. Czolbe, Secretary. R. E. Kaestner:- The Chicago Sharp-Shooters' Club held a special meeting yesterday at the Bismarck Hotel and adopted the following resolution:-"The members( of the above association) feel profound grief because of the premature death of the nation's president, Mr. Mc Kinley, and resolved to participate at the mourning festivities, on September 19th. The President George Kersten is hereby authorized to select a committee of 50 members who shall be at the parade in cabs. On the burial day, the shooting exercises at the Park will be omitted and the flags at the Club house are to be at half mast. The President has also been requested, to nominate a committee of five, for the purpose of drafting a declaration of condolence...A copy of which is to be forwarded to Mrs. Mc Kinley...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
