<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1916-05-03">May 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Tribune and the German American.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1916-05-03">May 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE TRIBUNE AND THE GERMAN AMERICAN.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune has always wisely guarded itself against prejudice. The editorial articles of this newspaper have generally inspired confidence through their thoughtful tone, especially among readers of a differing opinion. In its last editorial it occupies itself with the German American, in which an effort is made to show that they can hardly strengthen their cause by opposing Roosevelt and Wilson, as a man in solid formation. The Tribune is fearful that the German American citizens only invoke suspicion against themselves, that they are not being guided by what Roosevelt and Wilson are doing for the country, but what they are now doing and would do in the future, against Germany. The sympathetic consideration of the Tribune for the German Americans is fully appreciated, but this class does not find its position as ticklish as the Tribune seems to inclined to see it. The German Americans as a whole, have during these two years not once encouraged or carried out one thing that could be harmful to our country, on the other hand, they never omitted anything that would be beneficial to this country. As the Tribune so fittingly observes, these German Americans often, very often, have bitterly protested. Luckily they stood not alone in this series of protests, but even if they would have stood alone in these protests, they should only look back upon their <pb facs="5418474_10_0213.jpg" n="2"/>fulfilled duty during this stormy period of the world's history with the greatest satisfaction and pride, that while American tradition, character, and ideals were threatened in the waves of hatred, they and they alone, had the courage to protest, and to try to rescue our sacred American traditions.</p>
   <p>Is there anything un-American in our protests against the violations of the President's proclamation of neutrality that we have seen in danger in word and deed, in the spirit and in the letter of the law?</p>
   <p>Was there anything un-American about our protests against the inconsistent, unnatural, inhuman, hypocritical, and un-American practice of invoking God for a speedy end of the war in a public proclamation, and tomorrow, before even the fervor of the prayer has died from our lips to bend every effort towards prolonging the war, by permitting thousands of people to occupy themselves with the manufacture of arms? If a protest against this is called un-American, then the President's very peace proclamation was even more un-American, and his claim that an embargo on the export of munitions of war to Mexico was only in line with the practice of civilized nations, was also untrue.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0214.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Because we are Americans, we are opposed to Roosevelt and to Wilson. These two gentlemen seem to know but one ideal, Wilson and Roosevelt! There seems to be only one aim: the White House! We are laboring for an American with a heart that will know how to unite its people; that will be able to regain this country's respect in the eyes of the world; a country that will be able to regain and maintain its reputation in the world according to the high promise and the nature of its birth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
