<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-06-29">June 29, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">Germanism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-06-29">June 29, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANISM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The decision of the Boston Turners to permit the use of the English language at their meetings, has brought protests from the German people. This they consider is "One of the most important grants made to nativism as well as to Americanism", adding that it is "One of the worst blows dealt to the German people and their language". Anxiety is expressed that when the English language will be acknowledged as the official language of the "Turners" along with the German, the latter will, before long, give way to English, which so far has been only tolerated at the Turners activities. The son of the late Munch contradicts by saying: "Permitting the English language to be used in cases where it is called for by good judgment would be, if anything at all, to the advantage of the German people, for giving the directions in English, also, would cause the American children to become interested in gymnastics, and the American public in general could be easily won for this healthy physical sport if it understood what is required. If we invite the American people to participate at these meetings and exercises, they would soon get acquainted with German customs and this, in turn, would create the desire for knowledge of German also. National exclusiveness is a disadvantage in this case, and if we regard gymnastics as a wholesome sport, it would be our duty as good citizens to get the Americans interested too." There is no question but <pb facs="5418474_10_0132.jpg" n="2"/>that every man clings with a certain devotion to his native land, but those of us who over indulge in the noise making for Germanism, are not considered as the most welcome guests to these shores.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
