<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-04-15">Apr. 15, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">Various Services in Memory of the Martyr-President</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1214</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1214.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-04-15">Apr. 15, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">VARIOUS SERVICES IN MEMORY OF THE MARTYR-PRESIDENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Twenty-five years ago on this day, Abraham Lincoln, the most esteemed and revered president since Washington, drew the last breath of a noble life glorified by accomplishment. His death was the result of a murderer's bullet, deliberately discharged into his body on the previous evening by a blindly fanatic assassin, the actor J. Wilkes Booth.</p>
   <p>The Germans, and especially the German Turner societies, have not forgotten what the martyr accomplished for this nation, and the services in his honor on this memorial day give expression to their sentiments.</p>
   <p>Delegations from all parts of the country met at Springfield yesterday to give homage at the President's grave; the Chicago Turngemeinde (Turner District) sent three representatives.</p>
   <p>A memorial meeting is to be held this evening at the Verwaerts Turnhalle. The <pb facs="5418474_10_1215.jpg" n="2"/>Vorwaerts, National, Bahnfrei, and Einigkeit societies will take part, and also the Internationaler Maennerchor (International Male Chorus) and the Concordia Maennerchor (Concordia Male Chorus). Judge Prendergast and Assistant Librarian Gauss will give the official address.</p>
   <p>The Carfield Turner Society will hold a memorial service on Wednesday in its building on the corner of Wisconsin and Larrabee Streets. Lincoln's monument, in the park which bears his name, has been lavishly decorated with flowers and flags through the efforts of the Chicago Turngemeinde.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
