<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-07">July 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">German Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">Express Hope That Germany May Face a Better Future</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-07">July 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Express Hope That Germany May Face a Better Future</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A genuine German festival was held yesterday at Brand's Park, given by the German-American Citizens Alliance. From early afternoon until late at night, new arrivals helped increase the crowd, and few were the men or women of importance in German associations who didn't come. Singers, gymnasts, Pommeranians, Austrians, agricultural organizations, women's societies, in fact, everybody affiliated with the Alliance, was present, which accounted for the great activity that prevailed during the festival.</p>
   <p>Thanks to a very fortunate selection by the Festival Committee, Congressman Henry R. Rathbone was scheduled as principal speaker. He was introduced by Louis J. Link, former president of the German-American Citizens Alliance and its honorary president by unanimous acclaim since this association's last election.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0611.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Rathbone's Speech</p>
   <p>Rathbone spoke of the work of the German-Americans in behalf of the Union, of the great American Lincoln, whom the world loved for no other reason than his true, heartfelt sympathy for the oppressed; he congratulated the German people for their resistance to Poincare, and expressed the hope that the world will face a better future, especially Germany, which still suffers from the aftermath of the war, pointing to an innate sense of common justice which requires that Germany be given full credit for its reparations; also, that all the debtors of the United States, particularly the French, should pay their debts, which all together amount to eleven billion dollars, a stupendous sum. His closing words were:</p>
   <p>"We have just celebrated the Fourth of July. The Declaration of Independence is a true expression of Americanism. I stand irrevocably for a thorough and just revision of the so-called Peace Treaty of Versailles, and hope confidently that the time will come when America will be the moral leader of the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0612.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But as far as the German-Americans are concerned, the creed of old "Attinghausen," in Schiller's William Tell, still prevails: "Let us be a single people of brethren, never separating in danger and distress!"</p>
   <p>True Festival Spirit</p>
   <p>That the young and the aged found such splendid diversion is entirely due to the Festival Committee under the capable leadership of the president, Lorenz Schlegel. There was music and dancing for the younger generation and comfortable places for an exchange of reminiscences between the older groups. Adequate provisions had been made to satiate the hungry and the thirsty. Ice-cream and candy booths did their share in making the youngsters extricate the more or less hard-earned nickles and dimes from their elders; in short, everything was so arranged as to create happiness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
