<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-03-19">Mar. 19, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">[The Platt-German Society Celebrates]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0800</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0800.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-03-19">Mar. 19, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">[THE PLATT-GERMAN SOCIETY CELEBRATES]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Platt-German Society, John P. Altgeld, No. 34, yesterday celebrated its sixth anniversary. It was a double celebration, for it was also the day of the inauguration of the flag. The audience was greeted by the secretary of the society, Mr. Leo Kiewert, taking the place of the president, who was absent because of illness.</p>
   <p>He said: "The day the society was founded the membership subscription was 25, but that number was soon reduced to 19. Now we are happy to announce, that the present membership is 76. The celebration of the anniversary has been a regular feature of our society. Customarily on that occasion, dinner and alcoholic beverages were served free of charge...." Ex-governor John P. Altgeld, an honorary member of the society, expressed his happiness over the steady growth of the organization.</p>
   <p>"It is a well known fact," he said, "That wherever the German people settle, they will, no matter what the circumstances may be, take an interest in their adopted country." The speaker changed his subject then, and severely criticized England, the aggressor in the present conflict with the South African republic, the Boers. He was interrupted many times during the address, by salvos of applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0801.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Very impressive was the consecration and inauguration of the flag performed by ex-grandmaster of the society, Adolph Hoenig. "To every German soldier," he said, "the flag is the symbol of loyalty."</p>
   <p>The flag represents a rare piece of needle work. One side bears the likeness of ex-governor John P. Altgeld, with the name of the society and data of its founding. On the other side, against a red background, a German oak tree, (the symbol of the Platt-Germans) is surrounded by arabesques, with the German and the United States coats of arms.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
