<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-01-18">January 18, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[The Dislike of the "Dutch"]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-01-18">January 18, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[THE DISLIKE OF THE "DUTCH"]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The exaggerated and largely untrue reports of the Tribune and Times have tended very unnecessarily, to arouse the American population still more against the Germans. But no reporter of these papers has sought to inquire into the true cause of the excesses of Monday night...</p>
   <p>At the time when the Aldermanic session was over, and when the bearers of the banners( who had entered the hall not in disorderly fashion, but had been admitted on the order of the police superintendent) were starting to go home- the entrance hall and the upper part of the ataircase were filled with people not only from the demonstration, but many of whom had simply been sitting in the "lobby" to attend, as usually, the happenings in the City Council. Meanwhile the majority of the demonstrators were on their way home, and Schlotthauer's section had already arrived at the ruins of the old courthouse. By and by the rooms of the city hall emptied themselves, and there may still have been about 30 people in the lobby and on the stair, when suddenly the 12 policemen of Sergeant Lull together with the whole team of Captain Hickey pressed to the upper part of the staircase in the lobby(a sign that the crowd no longer can have been very large) and pushed without any warning all the people who stood there with violent force down the staircase.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0175.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The greatest hubbub and excitement was the consequence. Even then the police were not yet satisfied. At the entrance still more policemen were waiting, who had come from the Southside, and who now tried to violently push the people who stood on the very high sidewalk onto the street.</p>
   <p>At the same time they used the most abusive terms against the "Dutch". Only then, as an Alderman who was an eye-witness reports, the people took to self-defense. And this would not have been done with bricks had not a pile of them been lying there- a pile onto which the police, lead by Sergeant Lull, had driven the people like a herd of cattle, without giving them time to go peacefully on their way. Lull, who not for the first time, had been carried considerably too far by excessive zeal, is himself to blame when he was hit by a brick. He is the only policeman who was slightly wounded...</p>
   <p>Last night the conversation in the police-stations resolved exclusively around the "keeping down" and"Killing the Dutch." And Mark Sheridan and Superintendent Sherman left the whole city watch out for itself, while 200 police-men had been ordered to headquarters and into the Aldermanic Council,30 policemen and 3 captains stood on the staircase and in the chanber of the Council, while, the other 170 men were kept in the adjourning police station. But everything was quiet and peaceful in the neighborhood of the city hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
