<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-04">Apr. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Time for Independent Thinking Is Here, Says Dr. Bradley</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mayor Dever Also Speaks at Luncheon of the German Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1926-04-04">Apr. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE TIME FOR INDEPENDENT THINKING IS HERE, SAYS DR. BRADLEY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mayor Dever Also Speaks at Luncheon of the German Club</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's luncheon of the German Club held at the Morrison Hotel was one of the most enjoyable of this season. The program and entertainment were delightful and rich in variety. The two comedians Kolb and Dill, the singer Lydia Lechner, the Fritz Renksch trio, and--last but not least--the well-known orator Dr. Preston Bradley, the pastor of the People's Church, all combined to make the occasion a success.</p>
   <p>The spacious Cameo Hall was filled to the last seat. At the speakers' table were seated the principal speaker of the occasion, Dr. Bradley, and Mayor Dever, Corporation Counsel Busch, Judge Horner of the Probate Court, Postmaster Lueder, as well as other personalities prominent in Chicago's public life.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0560.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While the luxuries of the table were being enjoyed, the two comedians mentioned above provided a welcome spice to the banquet.....</p>
   <p>When the banquet was finished, the chairman of the Club, with a few words appropriate to the occasion, introduced Dr. Preston Bradley, pastor of the People's Church, to the gathering.</p>
   <p>"The Window of the World" was the title chosen by the speaker for his lecture. This title probably was rather misleading to some of his listeners but the manner in which Dr. Bradley treated his subject and the effervescent humor which here and there gave spice to his words, held the interest of his audience from beginning to end.</p>
   <p>"We are living in an age of reactions" [this unusual plural is used in the original], said Dr. Bradley in opening his speech, which was frequently interrupted by applause. "These reactions have opened the gates for a challenge to all ideals of civilization. The government must furnish proof <pb facs="5418474_10_0561.jpg" n="3"/>that it can offer sufficient resistance to these reactions; our educational system must provide such proof; religion must also supply it. Ours is an age of confirmation and verification and not one of experimentation.</p>
   <p>"The peoples of all countries of the world are using their thinking capacities more than ever before in the history of mankind. They do not permit themselves to be misguided by passionate appeals or by prejudices, or to be misled by the mob. The number of those who do their own thinking is larger today than ever before, and the realization of this fact brings forth hope for a better future. People are no longer so easily misled and intimidated; they are trying to solve their own problems by their own efforts. They know how closely their mutual interests are bound up with one another. They know that they live in a world in which a great deal is in need of improvement, and they are striving to secure the triumph of those principles which appear to them capable of making the world better. Mankind must progress as a unified whole, or else its future will be crushed against the rock of hatred and prejudice. Racial hatred and religious prejudices will never <pb facs="5418474_10_0562.jpg" n="4"/>build a world of peace and of truth."</p>
   <p>After the applause occasioned by Dr. Bradley's speech had died down and after a few musical offerings were heard, Mayor Dever, introduced by Corporation Counsel Busch, took the floor for a short address. He expressed his thanks for the honor of the invitation extended him and then spoke about the problems which will occupy him in the immediate future in his capacity as head of the city of Chicago.....His words were likewise received with great applause.</p>
   <p>The musical part of the program was masterfully taken care of by the Fritz Renksch trio and by Miss Lydia Lechner, whose splendid voice beautifully rendered several songs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
