<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-09-11">September 11th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Stoecker's Lecture.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1563.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-09-11">September 11th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">STOECKER'S LECTURE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The announcement, that Ex-court preacher Stoecker will hold his promised lecture over general political questions of the present time, attracted a great number of Germans to the Central Music Hall which was filled to the last place. Nearly 3000 people were present, who followed with intense interest the one hour lecture of the speaker. He has come to America following the call of "Brother" Moody, to help here the work of Evangelization, by which he hopes to find ardent helpers among the Germans, for all the Communicants of the Lutheran faith. The times are hard, and full of responsibility. There are powerful revolutionary circles at work, who endanger the existence of our society. Through the reformation, the moral equality of the people has been reached, and the problem of our time is the restoration of social equality. The task is to straighten out in a Christian-spirit the contrasts between the want of the poor and the luxurious pleasure life of the millionaires. Not alone in higher wages or in shortening of the time of labor does exist the highest aim of the laborers. The better situated ones fail very often in the spirit of brotherly cooperation towards the laborers, for all that, the latter should not give up the belief in an idol, that alone can lead to the true religion. Dr. Stoecker's speech was frequently interrupted by lively applause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
