<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-09-01">Sept. 1, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of a New Church.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1621</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1621.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-09-01">Sept. 1, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF A NEW CHURCH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Twelfth German Methodist Church of this city was dedicated yesterday. It is a wooden structure, neat in appearance, a practical creation which combines beauty and utility, yet produces a symmetrical effect as a whole. The interior is so festively decorated, that the large congregation which is composed of divers elements from many parts of the city, was indeed surprised.</p>
   <p>The sermon was preached in German. The Rev. F. Gottschalk, minister of the German Methodist Church of Wentworth Avenue between 38th and 39th Streets, commenced his Ecclesiastical labors several years ago in the district west of Halsted Street by holding sermons in an English Church and also in private buildings.</p>
   <p>Many of the faithful soon gathered around this nucleus and the demand for a church became more urgent. Since the necessary capital was not available, the Rev. Gottschalk gave lectures. He had traveled extensively in the Orient, Egypt, Greece, Italy, and other European countries. His travelogues included his experiences and the information he had obtained in Palestine. They were very well attended and the proceeds from this venture were used as a building fund. In this manner the ambitious pastor solved the financial question. A well situated plot was bought and the church thus came into existence. During the dedicatory service, <pb facs="5418474_10_1622.jpg" n="2"/>as we have mentioned, a large number of German Methodists from other parish districts were present, as well as the Rev. J. J. Keller, presiding elder of the Chicago district, and four others.</p>
   <p>It was a profound, well thought out, fascinating sermon, highly suited to the occasion and one that reached the heart of the audience, reaffirming the Pastor's reputation, since he is regarded as one of Chicago's greatest preachers. The liberal donors contributed $1,150.00 to pay the balance of the debts. This unexpected gift gives additional proof, that the Rev. Gottschalk's work, who succeeded after many of his colleagues had considered the task a hopless one, has obtained the confidence of his followers. This church, which is located at the Corner of Morgan Street and 53rd Court, will result in the founding of a very promising German community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
