<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-02-11">Feb. 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">R. E. Pattison Kline Lectures at Luncheon of German Club.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1078</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1078.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-02-11">Feb. 11, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">R. E. PATTISON KLINE LECTURES AT LUNCHEON OF GERMAN CLUB.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the luncheon given by the German Club of Chicago in the Cameo Room of the Morrison Hotel, under the presidency of Michael F. Girten, R. E. Pattison Kline, teacher of elocution of the Chicago Chapter of the American Institute of Banking, in the festival speech said:</p>
   <p>"I wonder what would become of Chicago's criminals if every lawyer should fight them, the way Abraham Lincoln did. He declined to defend a case as soon as he became convinced that the person was guilty. Yes, even in the midst of a trial he would withdraw should he find out that his client was at fault.</p>
   <p>"Educated people have many divergent opinions on spiritual matters and very few are willing to repudiate them. Here again Lincoln showed us the way to settle such matters peacefully. Do not always try to discover other people's faults but observe the divine laws."</p>
   <p>He also treated Lincoln's position in regard to the constitution. Lincoln's <pb facs="5418474_10_1079.jpg" n="2"/>ruling principle was that the laws must be observed for the good of the state. He then recalled how Lincoln once walked 12 miles to return four cents to a man whom he had short changed by mistake.</p>
   <p>"To the youth, Lincoln is an example of what a man can and should achieve. And in spite of his high position, he never lost contact with the people. If all the groups of society - Capital and Labor - would cooperate in accordance with Lincoln's spirit, many disputes of social and citizenship nature would be avoided."</p>
   <p>Kline closed his address by pointing out that Lincoln gained the respect of the whole world, as demonstrated by the universal celebration of his 100th birthday in 1915.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
