<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-09-22">Sept. 22, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">Lay Corner Stone of New Turnhalle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0969</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0969.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-09-22">Sept. 22, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">LAY CORNER STONE OF NEW TURNHALLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At ten o'clock yesterday morning, the members of the Chicago Turngemeinde marched in solemn procession from their old hall on Kinzie Street to the site of their new building. The Great Western Band led the procession and was followed by the pupils.of the Turnhalle and the turners, both groups attired in their uniforms. A large crowd accompanied the procession and gathered about the turners when the site was reached. A tin box containing a copy of the German newspapers published in Chicago as well as a copy of the Chicago Tribune and the Evening Journal, several issues of the Turnzeitung, a copy of the minutes of the last meeting of the turners, the last monthly report of the Turngemeinde, a membership list of the Turngemeinde and its pupils, a list of members of the Turner Company of the old Hecker Regiment, a list of turners who died in the service of the United States in the present war, a copy of the Baltimore Wecker in which Washington's Farewell Address appeared, and various coins, were all placed in the cornerstone.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0970.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the Great Western Band had played a patriotic selection, Mr. Wilhelm Rapp made a brief address to the turners, reminding them of the duties they assumed when they decided to erect a new Turnhalle, and also of their obligations to the other German residents of Chicago, who had wholeheartedly and generously supported the enterprise. He pointed out that it is their duty not only to engage in physical exercise and thus keep in good physical condition, but also to develop their minds, to grow in knowledge, thus making the new Turnhalle a nursery of physical strength as well as a temple of noble intellectual attainments, of ardent love toward our country and its freedom and toward their German fellow citizens of Chicago, in whose interest a heroic company of local turners had fought for two years.</p>
   <p>Thereupon the ceremony of laying the cornerstone was performed by Mr. Baetz assisted by Mr. Hein. A patriotic march rendered by the Great Western Band concluded the program.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0971.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thus the cornerstone of the principal pillar of the new Turnhalle has been laid, and the outer walls are rising at a rapid pace. Let us hope that the work will be finished in due time without injury to any of the workers employed in the construction of the building. We are certain that the Germans of Chicago will continue to support this noble undertaking, for the Chicago Turngemeinde has always shown, by word and deed, that it is a patriotic, civic-minded, and charitable organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
