<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-03-01">Mar. 1, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Flag Dedication and Celebration of the Founding of the Bavaria Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0920</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0920.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-03-01">Mar. 1, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">FLAG DEDICATION AND CELEBRATION OF THE FOUNDING OF THE BAVARIA SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The founding of the above mentioned society was first suggested by Mr. William Reisenecker and other fine citizens of Chicago belonging to the older generation. Thus the Bavarian Society came into existence november 12, of last year. All of the one hundred fifty members of the society are natives of Bavaria. Although their preference for this country prompted them to become citizens of the land of their choice, they, nevertheless, cherish a love for the land of their birth.</p>
   <p>The dedication of the society's beautiful white and blue silk flag adorned with exquisite embroidery was the climax of the evening's ceremonies, and when, with the appropriate musical accompaniment the curtains of the stage parted, a lovely scene was presented to the great audience. There stood under the Bavarian coat of arms Columbia and Germania arm in arm, with Bavaria standing at their right, and surrounded by nine demure maidens <pb facs="5418474_10_0921.jpg" n="2"/>all dressed in white, representing the eight districts of Bavaria. On the left side of the stage stood the president of the society, Mr. William Reisenecker, surrounded by the directors and other officials of the organization. The president then received the flag presented to him by Mrs. V. Markham who said: "Mr. president as you are the highest official of the association, I have the honor to present to you the blue and white banner of the society. May it serve as a symbol of our love for Bavaria, the land where our cradle stood. Although far away from the native land, our love for Bavaria has not died.... This banner shall remind us, that we, Bavarians shall always be allied in work and pleasure. Mr. president, I entrust herewith this banner into your care, may it serve and inspire the purpose of this young organization."</p>
   <p>In his reply, President Reisenecker pointed out that it was not the intention of the Bavarian people in this great Republic to display their own flag along with the Star-Spangled Banner. Neither is it their intention to exclude themselves <pb facs="5418474_10_0922.jpg" n="3"/>from the association with other German groups, but only to cherish and preserve the memory of the dear old Fatherland.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
