<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1924-12-08">Dec. 8, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A Worthy Close</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0578</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0578.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1924-12-08">Dec. 8, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A WORTHY CLOSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The festivities on the occasion of the German war veterans golden jubilee, came to a close yesterday evening with a festival dance. All the upper rooms of the Lincoln Turner Hall could scarcely hold the number of guests, who came to celebrate this day in honor of the beloved and respected association, and all enjoyed themselves immensely. The executive committee deserves thanks for not arranging an extensive program. The ballroom, which was especially suited for dances, was used all evening, while in the large hall the older comrades congregated with their friends and exchanged old memories. The singing section, under their able conductor Mr. Waldemar Christof, performed a few songs to great applause. A few more songs humorious performances offered a welcome variety. Unfortunately, the president of the festival, Mr. Wilhelm Schmidt, was prevented from participating through illness. The other members of the executive committee - there are too many to cite their names - discharged their not so easy tasks in a creditable way, so that everything went off smoothly and all visitors enjoyed a pleasant evening. The president of the association, Mr. John H. Schmidt, welcomed the visitors with a few hearty words and later presented the only surviving founder of the association, Mr. Joseph Schlenker. It was an affecting scene, to see this <pb facs="5418474_10_0579.jpg" n="2"/>brave warrior of former great times, in the midst of younger comrades, on the stage surrounded, the imperial standard donated by old Emperor Wilhelm, and the association's banner. Earlier in the evening the golden rail was fastened.</p>
   <p>Elaborate speeches were dispensed with. Besides the president of the association Mr. Schlenker made a short address, in which he referred to the founding and development of the German Warriors' Association and expressed the hope that the younger comrades would follow in the footsteps of the older ones and work diligently in the interest and for the benefit of the association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
