<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-01-30">Jan. 30, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">German-American National Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0757</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0757.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-01-30">Jan. 30, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN NATIONAL UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting took place in the Schiller Building yesterday. The delegates of all associations have joined the branch union of the German-American National Union. The meeting was presided over by the temporary chairman, Max Eberhardt. The constitution and by-laws, which had been worked out for this purpose, have been accepted with very little change.</p>
   <p>The principles of the National Union will be the same as those of the sister union. The by-laws state that all German clubs, associations, brotherhoods, lodges, guilds, communities and their central unions, and all individual German citizens of Chicago and the State of Illinois, which recognize the principles of the German-American National Union can become members. The contributions to be made by the associations is a yearly head tax, which will be fixed at the general meeting but shall not be higher than five cents. No club should pay for less than twenty-five members. Individual members pay the same price as associations - twenty-five cents. All contributions must be paid before the next annual meeting. New associations joining, and individuals, must pay the membership for the first year together with their <pb facs="5418474_10_0758.jpg" n="2"/>applications. Each club is entitled to one representative for each one-hundred members or part thereof, but not less than twenty-five. Individual citizens are entitled to one vote for their paid contributions. The meeting shall take place every three months on the last Monday in February, May, August, and November. The February meeting shall be the annual general meeting. Extraordinary meetings can be called by the executive committee and by the president. Every member has the right to appeal against the resolutions of the delegates' meeting, to the executive committee. Their (executive committee) decision will be final.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
