<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-01-24">January 24, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A Weak Attempt to Organize All the Germans of the Entire Country. Founding of a German-American Citizens Alliance Has Already Begun.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0867</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0867.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-01-24">January 24, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A WEAK ATTEMPT TO ORGANIZE ALL THE GERMANS OF THE ENTIRE COUNTRY. FOUNDING OF A GERMAN-AMERICAN CITIZENS ALLIANCE HAS ALREADY BEGUN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"I hear the news - but I lack the faith" thus will many a German exclaim, after he had noted the activity, last night, at 45 North Clark Street, where an attempt was made to unite all German-Americans. Indeed, a lofty ideal. The plan, at first, shall apply to Chicago. The many local German clubs as well as those which will be organized eventually, shall function only as branches of the great alliance and serve as representatives of the central body. But no ward of the city shall have more than a single branch. Thus, the various representatives form the central committee of the alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0868.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The definite purposes of this encompassing association were not clarified by the chairman and did not appear to be understood by the majority of those present, prospective members. It seems that the chairman regarded this alliance as a great German mutual assistance association which will also be able to express itself politically, in matters appertaining to Germanism.</p>
   <p>The real ideal that is to show the virtues of Germanism, the faithful German heart; to procure recognition among the non-German-Americans; and to stand united when the latter attack us in this New Land; in one word; to create a fortress for the defence of German activities in America, that phase, presumably, did not concern most of those assembled.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0869.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But, the alliance came to life last night, though it was an inconspicuous beginning. A committee will work out the declaration of principles and by-laws. If, at the next meeting, these recommendations meet with general approval and, if Germans, who are known as true and capable representatives of German, take up its leadership then yesterday's embryo association may well develop into a German-American giant.</p>
   <p>The thirty or forty members, delegates from various clubs, selected Carl Wohlfeldt as president, temporarily. He was the originator of the plan.....Other officers, secretary, treasure, were also selected.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0870.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Reisenegger, secretary, then gave a brief address, appropriate and to the point. He said, "Our very leaders among the Germans are not unified among themselves, hence the lack of unity among the local Germans!" He referred to the old inherited evil of the Teutons, envy.</p>
   <p>How powerful we could be if united was proved, last year, when we elected Franz Amberg, a German, as City Clerk. Only when we are united can we achieve greatness! This evening, therefore, let us consider the creation of a German alliance for a lofty cause and forget individuals. That should be the prevailing thought!".......</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0871.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>When the selection of a suitable name was contemplated, there was nearly as much variance as there were members. Beyond doubt, proposals would have continued till after the midmight hour, if Mr. Schcenker's suggestion had not been accepted: German-American citizens alliance, which was amended to include "of North America"........A list of the charter members and contributions towards a general fund, followed. February 6th, and the same address, have been tentatively selected for the next meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
