<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-06">Aug. 6, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Reverend Paul Luecke Celebrates Fiftieth Anniversary of His Officiating as Pastor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-06">Aug. 6, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE REVEREND PAUL LUECKE CELEBRATES FIFTIETH ANNIVERSARY OF HIS OFFICIATING AS PASTOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today the Reverend Paul Luecke, pastor of St. John's Evangelical Lutheran Church in Mayfair, Chicago, celebrates the golden jubilee of his service as a minister, and on this occasion will be specially honored by his congregation and by those with which he was formerly connected.</p>
   <p>Today's religious services will be devoted chiefly to the principal events in the life of the worthy pastor, that the celebration may remain long in the memory of the Reverend Mr. Luecke and of the congregation.</p>
   <p>At the services in German at 9:30 A. M. the Reverend Adolf Pfotenhauer, of Addison, Illinois, will preach the sermon. The songs of the children's choir, of the mixed choir, and of the men's choir, will be chosen so as to harmonize with the significance of the day.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1374.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the services in English at 11 A. M. the Reverend G. Schuessler will preach the sermon. There will then be an opportunity for the congregation to congratulate the Reverend Mr. Luecke and for him to reply.</p>
   <p>The special booklet which St. John's Parish published on the occasion of its pastor's jubilee briefly sketches his life and his blessed works in the service of the Evangelical Lutheran Church.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Mr. Luecke, the son of Christian Luecke, a teacher, was born November 1, 1860, in Howards Grove, Sheboygan County, Wisconsin. He came to Chicago for the first time in 1863, when his father secured a position in the branch school of St. Paul's Parish on the Northwest Side of the city. After graduating from St. John's School he entered the academy in Fort Wayne, Indiana, and in 1880 entered the seminary in St. Louis, Missouri. In 1883, after the completion of his studies, he was called to St. John's Parish in Merrill, Wisconsin, and he was ordained and installed in this position on August 5 of this same year. He then became pastor of the Trinity Parish in <pb facs="5418474_10_1375.jpg" n="3"/>West Merrill, and was then pastor in Pine River.</p>
   <p>In 1886 he was called to the old St. John's Church on the corner of Montrose Boulevard and Sampton Avenue. Since that time the Reverend Mr. Luecke has guided the destinies of St. John's Parish, which has developed from its humble beginnings in a modest chapel into a large and active parish with a modern church. It was November, 1886, when he entered upon his duties. Scarcely a year later the church, built in 1876, was unable to accommodate the congregation. Consequently a parsonage was built so that the newly founded elementary school might be located in the basement of the church. In 1890 the school was enlarged by the building of a transept. In 1915 a special schoolhouse with four classrooms was built, and in 1930 the Reverend Mr. Luecke saw his life's work crowned by the building of a new church, which is on the corner of Montrose and Lavergne Avenues. There is sitting room for almost seven hundred and fifty persons. The church was dedicated on October 5, 1930.</p>
   <p>In 1884 the Reverend Mr. Luecke married Miss Emma Battermaun, with whom he <pb facs="5418474_10_1376.jpg" n="4"/>enjoyed forty-two years of happy married life. She died on October 3, 1926, after a lingering illness. By this marriage there were six children, all of whom are still living. In 1928 the Reverend Mr. Luecke married Miss Adwina Witt, who has been his faithful helpmate since that time.</p>
   <p>The prayer of the congregation, on this day on which their pastor is honored, is that he will be able to continue his blessed work for a long time to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
