<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-03-06">Mar. 6, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">[The German Society]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0885</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0885.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-03-06">Mar. 6, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">[THE GERMAN SOCIETY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Society held its meeting last Friday with the following report read: Collected contributions for last month amounted to $354.00 with outstanding contributions of $335.00. Four new members joined the society: Gustav Schmidt, Schiller Ruske, Constantin Kann and William Thilo.</p>
   <p>The agent reported that there was a drop in immigration during last month. The number not exceeding 2000, most of whom are going further west. But of the large number of unemployed we could place 184 only. During last month we received only 112 calls for workers. The number applying for relief was not as heacy as the previous month. Seven patients were placed in hospitals and four others received pre-medical treatment and medicines. Twelve families received coal and 38 cases were helped with money. Twenty were immigrants. Fifteen more sick persons were helped with money and through the loss of breadwinners, three more families were given assistance. The total sum spent for assistance of the needy amounted to $326.85.</p>
   <p>Consul Claussenius's displeasure over the fact that the "Society of German Women" became independent assuming corporation rights, caused the consul <pb facs="5418474_10_0886.jpg" n="2"/>to appoint a committee of three persons to meet a committee appointed by the Society of German Women to discuss and determine in what relationship the two organizations stand.</p>
   <p>The Treasurer was requested by Mr. Claussenius to invest the net proceeds of $800.00 which a ball given by him yeilded, for the benefit of the German Women's Society with a personal gift of $25.00.</p>
   <p>Messrs. Schwissler and Claussenius were appointed members of a committee of auditors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
