<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-06-16">June 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Governor Fifer's Interview with Representatives of the United German Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1576</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1576.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-06-16">June 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GOVERNOR FIFER'S INTERVIEW WITH REPRESENTATIVES OF THE UNITED GERMAN CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Governor Fifer has had sleepless nights for some time and these are caused by the spector of defeat at the November election. Although he and his friends try very hard to ignore the resolutions of the German Republicans, especially the Lutherans and the United Churches; nevertheless, they are aware of the consequences. They have made every possible effort to make a breach in the ranks of the united Germans.</p>
   <p>Finally the notion occurred to Governor Fifer to have a personal interview with some eminent German church members and to beg for mercy.</p>
   <p>The interview took place yesterday at 106 Randolph Street. Eight German members of the United Evangelical Church took part in the consultation. Among these were the pastors, Kircher, Schaub and Goebel. Fifer's agents, two local so-called Germans, had advised him to seek the aid of the United Evangelical Church and, by doing so, to create discord in the otherwise unified ranks of the United Church and the Lutherans. In the battle against the Edward Law the <pb facs="5418474_10_1577.jpg" n="2"/>Lutherans and the United Evangelical had fought shoulder to shoulder, and the latter deserve at least their share of the glory of 1890. Now Fifer is trying to bring dissensions between these groups without realizing that such methods will avail nothing. For this battle is fought to retain liberty of conscience, and to maintain the mother tongue.</p>
   <p>The gentlemen who granted the interview to Fifer, asked the governor a number of questions, which he answered without hesitation. It is questionable whether he would have answered these questions in the affirmative had they been asked by the American Protestant Association. Fifer as is well known, was nominated by this Association. The Germans who were present at the interview made no promise to Fifer other than to submit this important matter to the synod which will assemble next Wednesday at Freeport. The synod will decide what attitude towards the election the members of the United Church should take. The over-whelming majority of these members are Republicans, and represent a large number of votes.</p>
   <p>Fifer's double-dealings were clearly in evidence yesterday. He promised heaven and earth to the Germans, while his agents, at the same time, tried to undermine <pb facs="5418474_10_1578.jpg" n="3"/>and disparage publicly the strength of the German Lutherans and the German United Church, in order to gain the favor of the native Americans as a substitute for the lost German votes.</p>
   <p>Not all are as honest as A. S. Wright who took part in the conference of the Central Committee. He did not conceal the fact that the Lutherans and the United have declared war against the Republican state ticket. "Something must be done," he declared, "or we are lost. The young people," he continued, "are just as determined in their opposition as the older men, who have for many years voted Republican, and who will vote again for Harrison and Reid, but will not vote for Fifer."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
