<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-25">Apr. 25, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Dewitt C. Cregier's Centennial Proclamation</title><title level="a" type="sub">Hypocrisy in the Mayor's Chair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-25">Apr. 25, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">DEWITT C. CREGIER'S CENTENNIAL PROCLAMATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Hypocrisy in the Mayor's Chair</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our burgomaster released his centennial Proclamation yesterday. The citizenship of Chicago is requested therein, to celebrate the 30th of April by keeping all business closed and assembling in the churches and synagogues in order to thank the creator for all the good, etc.</p>
   <p>One out of two things: either our Mayor is lagging behind the times or he is a hypocrite who finds it more convenient to bend his knee before the religious swindle than to pass it by or oppose it.</p>
   <p>Either Mr. Cregier still believes in a personalized Creator, the famous old man sitting in the clouds and watching his children on this orb jumping and dancing around, or he is a cowardly hypocrite who considers it a clever political move to make concessions to preachers' stuff and mass idiocy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1638.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the latter case, we do not envy the Mayor his loyalty to his own conviction nor his personal courage.</p>
   <p>Anyone without backbone to express his convictions in major questions, regardless of the position he may hold, is no man but only a pitiable person hanging his coat where the wind blows.</p>
   <p>We are blushing with shame to find the religious swindle cared for, well tended, and formally raised by high authorities in this freest country of the world, in these United States founded on an irreligious basis, and only 100 years after the appearance of Thomas Paine, Thomas Jefferson, and Benjamin Franklin.</p>
   <p>It is a shame! Are all achievements in scientific research of the last 300 years passed by the heads of modern Americans without leaving the slightest trace? When reading Dewitt C. Cregier's proclamation, we cannot help but reach this conclusion:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1639.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Cregier speaks in his proclamation of this "preferred" nation. Maybe Mr. Cregier discovered that the smart yankees somehow and somewhere got the best of the peddling Jews by cheating them out of their divine attribute of being the chosen people!</p>
   <p>A nation which is able to manufacture hams and other things out of wood, will certainly succeed to cheat clever Hebrews, and we will not waste any more time with Mr. Cregier's "preferred" nation. This nation certainly has advantages; you only have to know what kind.</p>
   <p>We want to recall Goethe's words to you and your brethren who have remained too far back in time or are professional hypocrites; "He who possesses science and art, also has religion. He who does not possess both, should have religion."</p>
   <p>We further recommend to you the study of Max Nordau's conventional lies of civilized human societies, which should be known to you, Mr. Cregier, from commentaries in the Chicago press.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
