<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-06-15">June 15, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">The Synod-Conference the Admission of New Congregations. Election of Officers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-06-15">June 15, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">THE SYNOD-CONFERENCE THE ADMISSION OF NEW CONGREGATIONS. ELECTION OF OFFICERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting which was held yesterday afternoon, Dr. Schwan, the President of the Missouri-Synod made his report over the financial standing. According to same, the Synod is at present in pecuniary embarrassment, through unwise credit allowances, which, however, can be overcome by economy. To cancel the existing debts, Dr. Schwan recommended to take up collections during the Reformation Festivals. A motion to this effect was made and accepted. Furthermore it was resolved, to induce the Synod, to separate the building-fund from the General money chest. The following congregations were admitted to the Synod league: The Immanuel-congregation in Danville, the Trinity congregation in Geneva, St. Paul's congregation, Chicago Heights, Zions congregation Bunker Hill, St. Petri congregation, Evansville, Immanuels congregation, Broadland, Trinity congregation, Hanson Park. The delegates of above congregations, if they were in possession of credentials, received <pb facs="5418474_10_1536.jpg" n="2"/>seats and votes. Pastor Reinke was admitted to the Synod league. After this the election of officers took place, with the following results: President; H. Guccap, Vice President; I. A. F. W. Mueller, secretary; F. Merbitz, visitors; Northern Illinois: A. Bauer, L. Lochner, H. G. Schmidt, Central Illinois: Zehn Martens, Southern Illinois: Brust Buenger. CAshier H. Bartling, Missionary Commission; L. Hoelter, W. Uffenbeck, H. E. Zuttermeister, Aid Commission; Johannes Grosse, Teacher; Ritzmann, H. Oohlerking, Church building fund: L. Lochner, H. Engelbrecht, Teacher Otto C. F. Wolff, The. Reinhard, Karl Ivern. Pastor Lochner's invitation to hold the next conference amidst his congregation was gratefully accepted. President Succop's congregation was voted thanks for the hospitality, shown to the delegates of the conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
