<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-11-08">Nov. 8, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">German Spirit Building a Museum of Science in This Country.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-11-08">Nov. 8, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SPIRIT BUILDING A MUSEUM OF SCIENCE IN THIS COUNTRY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A typical German with graying whiskers, highly intelligent features, modest in his disposition, that is Dr. Oscar von Miller, one of the spiritually great men of Germany. Important American industrialists brought him over as a guest, in order that he should build a museum of technical science, after the pattern of the one built by him in Munich, which is unique of its kind.</p>
   <p>Dr. von Miller is for the present a guest of Samuel Insull and Rufus Dawes. Yesterday afternoon he was a guest of honor in the German Club. Introduced by president A. F. W. Siebel, he addressed those present in a short speech: "It gives me great pleasure to spend an hour in the company of men and women of German descent. I was in America for the first time 42 years ago, and again 13 years ago, also in the beautiful city of Chicago. But what great progress the latter has made in commerce and industry, and also culturally. Therefore I congratulate you for living in a country where means can be found and the ways are open to make yourselves useful and to participate in its upbuilding. It was difficult for Germans after the war to regain their old position, but I do not doubt that they <pb facs="5418474_10_0567.jpg" n="2"/>will be successful. Forty-two years ago, I was, with Karl Schurz, a guest of Henry Villard in New York, the builder of the Northern Pacific R. R. and at that time there were many Germans to whom the Americans looked up with admiration and I do not doubt that the time will come when this will again be the case.</p>
   <p>"During the war, when we all were starving, and we did not know where we could get bread for our children, you helped us. Should America ever experience hard times, we shall help her, even if not with money, because we are very poor, but with deeds. And in the meantime we prove to the world, that the German culture still exists, and that the whole world must be grateful to Germany for what she accomplished. I only want to mention the German discovery of the remedy against sleeping sickness which will save the lives of thousands of people. Our old enemies, the French and Belgians, were the first who procured this remedy.</p>
   <p>"In many other domains, has Germany won first place, and became a path breaker on the domain of the dirigibles and aeroplanes. Its planes fly from London to Italy, to Sweden, Russia and Persia. The German flying net is spread all over. I only desire to mention one other domain, the building of the museum for <pb facs="5418474_10_0568.jpg" n="3"/>science and technic in Munich. It is the largest in the world, its passages are nine miles long. The whole German nation lent its assistance, all classes. Great scientists like Emil Fischer, Rontgen, great artists, great industrialists supplying all building materials, and even the artisans, because they refused to accept pay for their work on Saturday afternoons and Sundays, and all this in spite of great need! It is German work, and in the small city of Munich, not one third as large as Chicago, 6,000 people visit this museum daily, and 12,000 on Sundays. Of course there are a good many foreigners among them.</p>
   <p>"In New York and Washington, an executive committee has been formed for the purpose of building a similar museum, and I was asked to assist the committee with my experience." The celebrated guest concluded amidst great applause. And still another enjoyment was offered to those present. Mr. Otto F. Reich showed a number of beautiful pictures from his latest European trip like the Steamer Deutschland, Cajutes, landing in Kuxhaven, Alster pavillion, Sans Souci, the Zoo, palaces in Berlin and Potsdam, Dresden, Nuremberg, Munich, Castle of Heidelberg, tower in Bingen on the Rhine, Cologne cathedral, Munich court brewery, promenade square, Innsbruck, Bavarian Alps, the Dolomites, Naples, Rome, Lucerne, etc, etc. And the speaker attested how energetically Germany is <pb facs="5418474_10_0569.jpg" n="4"/>working, how modest and friendly the people are, its love for flowers and music, etc.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wolfgang Wittich, lyric tenor formerly with the Leipzig Opera, at present member of the "Gypsy Love" Operetta troup, sang "Musicians Love", "Ardent Love" and a few more German folk songs accompanied by Messrs. Fritz Renk and Otto Beyer. They were excellent performances, as were those of the Renk trio, who played during the supper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
