<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-05">Mar. 5, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Know-Nothings</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-05">Mar. 5, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">KNOW-NOTHINGS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In one respect, President Hayes' iron will and strength of character cannot be denied. During the last session of Congress, the President appointed a great many people to public office. When the names were submitted to Congress for confirmation, it became quite evident that no position of importance was to be given to anyone who had a Teutonic name. It is true that Hayes' stump speaker, Paul Strohbach, was rewarded with a significant position; the gentleman is now the duly authorized postmaster of Montgomery, Alabama.</p>
   <p>No consideration was shown to German-American citizens in the selection of public officials or the appointment of consuls. This is particularly true with regard to the U. S. consulates in Germany. Some miserable English-American was given the post instead of a capable German-American. The facts <pb facs="5418474_10_0290.jpg" n="2"/>of the story of the consulate at Cologne confirm this charge. The office was given to a messenger boy whose only virtue consisted in the fact that he had hidden some Congressional committee's code telegrams, which, if found, would have exposed very clearly some aspects of Hayes' election and the counting of votes.</p>
   <p>As long as Hayes and Evarts are apportioning consular jobs, German-American citizens will be able to get only those jobs where the jobholder finds it expedient to return home before he starves. Such was the case with Stibolt of Davenport,[Iowa], and the druggist Hoefer of Pekin,[Illinois].</p>
   <p>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung can afford to make such statements; since it did not support Hayes, it has no claims upon him. The newspaper is defending a principle--the right of the Germans who have become citizens to hold public office. This principle is particularly just since there are many German-Americans who have all the qualifications required by civil service.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0291.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Hayes is almost the complete antithesis of the magnanimous Lincoln, although Hayes takes pleasure in comparing himself with Lincoln. But in nothing does he reveal himself to be so completely different from Lincoln as in his discrimination against German-Americans, so far as public offices are concerned.</p>
   <p>Lincoln and his great Secretary of State, Seward, made adequate provisions for placing German-Americans in high positions in foreign countries, as well as in Germany, while Hayes and Evarts persist in excluding all German-Americans from public office.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
