<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-08-12">August 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The "German-American National Alliance" Holds a Special General Meeting.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0704</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0704.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-08-12">August 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE "GERMAN-AMERICAN NATIONAL ALLIANCE" HOLDS A SPECIAL GENERAL MEETING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special general meeting was held, yesterday evening, by the Chicago branch of the "German-American National Alliance" in the Northside Turner Hall, to which a number of societies sent their delegates. After the opening of the meeting, which was presided over by Mr. Ferdinand Walther, Mr. Chas. Christmann pointed to its philantropic objective and made a warm appeal to those present to collect money in their societies and from their friends and acquaintances, for the wounded and to assist the widows and orphans in the old fatherland.</p>
   <p>A resolution, drawn up at the Central office of the "German-American National Association" and which was forwarded to the Chicago branch by Dr. Hexamer in New York, was read and unanimously approved. The text is as follows: "Considering, that about one fourth of the United States' population is either of German birth or extraction of people who have done more than their share to insure liberty since colonial days to preserve the union and help the nation in all branches of industry and commerce, also in cultural projects; be it resolved, that we as American citizens insist that the American press impartially convey the views of these people and that <pb facs="5418474_10_0705.jpg" n="2"/>editorials should, as much as possible, refrain from prejudice and hatred against all American citizens and classes.</p>
   <p>Because these, although an English speaking people, do not form an English nation, it is therefore no other than right, that in these serious times, the American principle of justice should be maintained to promote further good harmony between citizens of all nationalities and creeds.</p>
   <p>And be it further resolved, that a copy of this resolution should be submitted to the chief-editor of every newspaper in the city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
