<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-28">Dec. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Beautiful Christmas Celebration by Swablan Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1269</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1269.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-28">Dec. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">BEAUTIFUL CHRISTMAS CELEBRATION BY SWABLAN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every year the Swabian Society of Chicago celebrates Christmas in the circle of its members and their relatives and, in keeping with the well-established custom of the fatherland, it first of all takes care of the children, and gives them what is coming to them. Well, every year there is not only an enormous Christmas tree resplendent in the bright glow of lights, but there is also "Pelzmaerte" (Martin with the fur coat) who makes his appearance exactly as the Swabian Society has been doing for years, richly laden with gifts--dolls, harmonicas, building blocks, a number of toys of all descriptions, and candies--then follows the singing of German Christmas carols and the usual festive games, which, this year, were provided by Saint Nicholas' workshop and which won enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>The celebration was opened with several selections by Otto Seifert's orchestra. The president, Julius Klein, who, together with the other officers of the <pb facs="5418474_10_1270.jpg" n="2"/>organization and the members of the management, was kept tirelessly at work during the whole evening to see that everything was done right, and everything fit for the occasion. Everyone spent a few carefree and enjoyable hours, and the upper hall of the Lincoln Turnhalle, 1005 Diversey Parkway, in which the celebration was held, proved itself actually too small. Mr. Klein welcomed the festival assembly with words that came from the heart, giving his best wishes for the coming year.</p>
   <p>First came a prologue with a deep meaning, and then came the festive show that was given on the stage with remarkable success, under the talented leadership of Ellen Burhardt-Schmidt. With the sixty participating children, big and small, it brought not only gifts of some special sort, but also flattering ovations. A splendid performance was given in the graceful art dance by Miss Ellen Schmidt. All the other performances of the festive show elicited veritable storms of applause for the players. A particularly favorable impression was made by the fact that, during the entire festive play, only <pb facs="5418474_10_1271.jpg" n="3"/>German was spoken on the stage, and with such distinct pronunciation that no one had difficulty in understanding the text and in following its contents.</p>
   <p>The role of Pelzmaerte was this year in the hands of Anton Iberle, a brother of the popular secretary of the organization, George Iberle, acquitting himself with dignity and skill.</p>
   <p>The fest show came to a close with the well-known Christmas song, "O Tannenbaum," sung by the entire assembly. Then the older folks who participated at the celebration entertained themselves with a good drink or dancing to the strains of German music. It was late when it finally was time to repair for home and for rest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
