<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-25">Jan. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Go Ahead in Spite of It</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-25">Jan. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S GO AHEAD IN SPITE OF IT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his letter to Senator Stone--it would be more correct to say, to the German-Americans and their sympathizers--Secretary of State Bryan also mentions the export of arms and munitions. Of course he talks from the standpoint of the Administration. This letter should not affect in the least the present movement favoring an arms embargo.</p>
   <p>Secretary of State Bryan argues that according to existing international law private arms exports are permitted; that there is no law which binds a neutral nation to curtail its trade in arms and war supplies, or to prevent such export; that it has never been the policy of the United States to do such, except in the case of a neighboring republic (Mexico), and only then because a civil war was raging; that the freedom of the arms trade was maintained and emphasized by <pb facs="5418474_10_0216.jpg" n="2"/>the large shipments German munition makers made during the Russo-Japanese War [1904], and during the Balkan wars [1912]; and that the German Government itself had issued the statement December 15 [1914] through its ambassador in Washington that, according to generally accepted international concepts, it could not object to arms and munitions shipments by neutral countries or through neutral territory for the benefit of Germany's enemies.</p>
   <p>That is all, and it is nothing new; that the Administration was in no position to prohibit the export of arms was a well-recognized fact and was generally admitted. The purpose of the present movement is either to obtain an arms embargo or to give the President the power, with Congressional consent, to decree such an embargo. The movement demands additional legislation; it asks the representatives of the American people to elevate this Republic to a higher moral level and to break with "International Law," which, as the case shows, can not only lead to a grave injustice toward one belligerent nation, but also has a tendency to prolong a murderous war which does considerable damage to neutral nations as well.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0217.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That is why Mr. Bryan's arguments against the demand for an arms embargo do not hold water. Because of that, and because the demand for an arms embargo has been labeled a German-American movement, it is imperative now for the German-Americans, for the Austrian and Hungarian Americans, and all their sympathizers, to continue to write letters to senators and representatives, asking them to vote for the arms embargo bills. The Administration has maintained that it could not do anything under present circumstances. It did not say that it would not suppress arms shipments if it had a legal right to do so! Our slogan should be: Let's go ahead in spite of it! Let us exert the strongest pressure on our legislators to provide the Government with the legal means of prohibiting arms shipments. Let us induce every neighbor and acquaintance, regardless of nationality, to write letters to their congressmen. That's the duty of every loyal and high-minded citizen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
