<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-09-16">September 16, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Ignorant Foreigner</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-09-16">September 16, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE IGNORANT FOREIGNER</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because there are many "ignorant foreigners" in the United States, a judge not very well known - in the State of New York; sharply refused all the citizenship applications, which lay before him. He explained, he would not grant any more citizenship to anybody who does not know the constitution of the United States so as to be able to cast his vote intelligently, and who has no knowledge and understanding of our form of government, so as to share in patriotic duties. Only too readily could an ignorant voter be bought and a thoughtless use of the franchise is a danger for any government.</p>
   <p>Whosoever is seeking citizenship according to the New York paper "must know" what it means, and desire it not solely for paltry material gain, but from conviction. If he lacks this, if it is only to be a means to escape prosecution at the hand of the law in the land of his birth, when he may go there on a visit, or to more readily acquire some property, or for a "job," then he had better remain what he was. Nobody forces him to become a citizen. But it is time that in the interest of the country and its institutions, it be required that the applicant must also use some thought when he swears allegiance to the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0084.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To think a little "is fine." Properly speaking, a little thought and reflection should be required about everything that is being done, even when writing an editorial. Regarding the case cited, it must be mentioned that the right to American citizenship is no protection against "the hand of the law" of the old fatherland in case one wishes to live there and puts himself in its power; therefore, no one ever sought citizenship for these ulterior motives. It must be remembered that civic rights alone do not give everybody a right to vote. The New York judge, as also his newspaper defender, must know that citizenship is bestowed by the federal government, while the franchise comes from the states. One may possess one without the other.</p>
   <p>Where the state finds it expedient to divide the population into the intelligent and the ignorant, and to debar the latter from voting, it also excludes the "ignorant foreigner," which the possession of citizenship papers cannot reverse. Every state has the right to make the grant of franchise depend on a possible educational test. Where such a condition prevails, the uneducated foreigners are in the same position with the uneducated natives, though being citizens. This order of things proves that the foreigner is made to suffer something for which the natives do not.</p>
   <p>With reference to "some thinking," to truly consider that one does some thinking, depends on what he thinks. How can the examining judge make sure as to <pb facs="5418474_10_0085.jpg" n="3"/>what the applicant really thinks? The New York paper forgets to state further, that the applicant must prove that he is able to make judicious use of his ballot.</p>
   <p>What does "judicious use" mean? In every election contest, the people are divided, and one-half accuses the other of poor use and judgement in voting for the right side. We will have to wait many thousands of years till every faction of society will make "judicious use" of his vote. To think and to know judgment and wisdom are nice ideas, also patriotic unselfishness, but it is not possible to use these as proof in examining for fitness for citizenship. To leave the decision to the judge is to grant him arbitrary power in place of established law, on pretense that the foreigner does not think right; and tends to deprive him of his vote, which he needs to protect himself from oppression and unjust laws. The judge, by making his own laws to refuse citizenship, is not following law, but his own unlimited private opinion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
