<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-27">Aug. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Large Crowds at District Meeting of Friends of New Germany</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-27">Aug. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">LARGE CROWDS AT DISTRICT MEETING OF FRIENDS OF NEW GERMANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two halls of the Germania Club turned out to be too small to accommodate the crowds of people who came, on Saturday night, to attend the district meeting of the Friends of New Germany. Long before the district meeting was officially opened, the two halls were filled to the last seat. Many had to content themselves with standing room at the entrance or in the galleries. The great ballroom was richly draped with the colors of New Germany. The front rows were reserved for the delegates from the individual local groups of the district.</p>
   <p>To the solemn strains of the march from "Tannhaeuser," the flag orderlies from the local groups entered the hall. The public rose to its feet to greet the flag. After a brief address by the leader of the local groups, T. Miller, there followed the singing of the American national anthem by all. Hitler's pet march, the "Badenweiler," was played as a prelude to the speech made by the new district leader, Fritz Gissible, who was inducted into <pb facs="5418474_10_0453.jpg" n="2"/>office on that occasion. The speaker touched upon the aims of the movement in his speech. This movement has taken it upon itself to unify the Germans of America on a nationalistic basis, and to be instrumental in fostering and maintaining good relations between the two countries. Notwithstanding the difficulties which congressional investigation has laid in its way, the Bund will continue in the pursuance of that aim.</p>
   <p>The first verse of the Deutschland song was sung with vigor at the end of his address.</p>
   <p>The local groups of Cincinnati, St. Louis, Milwaukee, Detroit, Cleveland, and Hammond sent greetings from their organizations through their group leaders. They gave reports of experiences in their circles of activities; these reports were quite interesting. Then followed a few more pieces of orchestra music, and a piano recital by Dr. Klumm. The official part of the meeting came to a close with everyone singing the "Horst Wessel" song. Although the hall was overcrowded, those who wanted to dance found room and opportunity to do so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
