<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-07-01">July 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Work Is Done</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolutions and Election of the German Roman-Catholic Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-07-01">July 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORK IS DONE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Resolutions and Election of the German Roman-Catholic Alliance</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Looking backward upon the two years which have elapsed since our country entered the World War, we cannot but express our feeling of utmost contempt for the suspicions and insults to which we have been exposed because of our origin. On the other hand, we are satisfied with the knowledge that it is now generally admitted that we have done our full duty to our country, the United States of America, not only by subscribing to our allotted quota of Liberty Loan bonds, but also by having sacrificed our sons to the service of our country--though our hearts bled when they left us. And we here make the solemn promise that we shall maintain this patriotic attitude in the future, and show the loyalty which our oath of allegiance demands.</p>
   <p>We Catholics of German origin know full well that English is the language of <pb facs="5418474_10_1458.jpg" n="2"/>our land, and that no other language will have a permanent place in America. We use and foster the German language only because we are convinced that it is absolutely necessary for the spiritual welfare of immigrants and their descendants. We do not wish to see the parents' mother tongue neglected in families, because such neglect would serve to detract from parental authority. We maintain the use of German and other foreign languages in our churches for the sake of those who do not yet understand English sufficiently to obtain spiritual knowledge and comfort for their souls. We are certain that the language question will be solved best if we insist that our children learn the English language. However, we are opposed to using any force in the solution of the problem, and we stand upon our right to speak the language which we know best and in which we can best make ourselves understood.</p>
   <p>In the afternoon, election of officers was held. Mr. Michael Walsdorf, of Chicago, was elected president.....George Stoecker, of Chicago, was elected financial secretary.....and Fred A. Gilson, of Chicago, was elected <pb facs="5418474_10_1459.jpg" n="3"/>recording secretary.....</p>
   <p>After the Alliance voted to thank the members of St. Benedict's Church for acting as host to the convention, a general meeting was held in which Father Albert Muntsch, of St. Louis, lectured on the subject of the program of the National Catholic War Board; he made special reference to social reconstruction. Adjournment followed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
