<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-08-04">Aug. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">German Catholic Old Settlers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1574</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1574.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-08-04">Aug. 4, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN CATHOLIC OLD SETTLERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>German Catholic old settlers assembled at Oswald Grove, 52nd and Halsted streets yesterday, for a picnic. A large sum of money was collected for the erection of a building for a school connected with St. Paul's German Catholic Church at Ambrose St. and Hoyne Ave. The picnic was held under the auspices of the Society of St. Paul's Church. There were 1500 people present, and the merriment was kept up from 9 A.M. until late at night.</p>
   <p>In the afternoon, Washington Hesing delivered a speech and the Rev. Father C. D. Heldman, rector of St. Paul's Church, also spoke. Among other things, Mr. Hesing said: "It is hardly possible with these remarks, to give even an approximate idea of the marvelous development of our church in this city. The best opinion can be formed when we consider how small was the beginning and how great is the material welfare of the church today."</p>
   <p>There are at present twenty-six German Catholic churches, mostly prosperous, in this city. An orphan asylum, which is financially in better condition than any other in America, provides a home for three hundred unfortunate little ones. Two beautiful and successfully managed cemeteries furnish a last resting place for the dead. But a short time ago, 325 acres were bought for a German Catholic <pb facs="5418474_10_1575.jpg" n="2"/>old people's home. Three German Catholic hospitals administer to the sick without regard to religion."</p>
   <p>"Statistics prove, if we consider the children of German parents, that the German population of this city is rather more than less than 400,000. If we take as a basis of our calculation the percentage as usually figured in the German empire, where out of every 10,000 inhabitants, 2580 are Catholics, we find that the number of German Catholics in this city is about 143,000. Another way of figuring is equally convincing."</p>
   <p>After the speech-making, the entire assembly led by the St. Ambrosius chorus, joined in singing a festival song composed for the occasion by Father Heldman. A number of prizes were awarded to the oldest settlers, the largest families, etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
