<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-08-13">August 13, 1909</date><title level="a">Appeal to the Germans!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0741</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0741.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-08-13">August 13, 1909</date><title level="a">Appeal to the Germans!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We wish to be a united nation of brothers. No trouble and danger shall separate us. With these words of our great poet, Franz von Schiller, whose 150th birthday we shall soon celebrate, we call on you to join our National League. What Germany, in its might and culture, means for the Germans at home is represented inthe National League, which was formed eight years ago in Philadelphia for Germans in the United States. Under the Stars and Stripes, to which we have pledged obedience and proven our faithfulness so often, we will find a permanent place for the best of German culture. The foundation of our work is the maintaining of the national sentiment among Germans in this country, whether immigrants or natives.</p>
   <p>A few years ago it looked as if German ties, which bound the Germans to their fatherland, were loosening considerably, and today an honest, impartial, American historical research is active, to put the history of the Germans in this country in its proper light. We follow the principle that accomplished duties compel acquired rights. Taking first place is the mother tongue, superb treasure, which we must maintain now and for all time. We Germans in <pb facs="5418474_10_0742.jpg" n="2"/>America must help ourselves, and the League with its branches all over the United States and its Two and one-half million members, should be the best mediums. The Illinois branch was formed October 3rd, 1908, at Chicago, and it already has acquired a great number of Clubs in various towns. The second State Convention will take place September 11th, at Peoria, Illinois. We call on all Clubs and Associations in the State of Illinois, which are not as yet affiliated with the League, to join us and send representatives to the Convention.</p>
   <p>Towns with several German Clubs can form a local branch. One hundred members can send one delegate, and each additional fifty to one hundred members can send an additional delegate.</p>
   <p>Unity makes strength. Remember the force laws, which the fanatics have imposed upon us. Remember your individual liberty, which only a united German sentiment can preserve for you. Join the German-American National League.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
