<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>St. Paul's Bote</title> (English-German Monthly Magazine),
            <date when="1933-12">Sept. to Dec. 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Founded in 1843 by the Methodist Church History of St. Pauls Since 1871</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The Fire</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>St. Paul's Bote</title> (English-German Monthly Magazine),
    <date when="1933-12">Sept. to Dec. 1933</date>.
<title level="a">FOUNDED IN 1843 BY THE METHODIST CHURCH HISTORY OF ST. PAULS SINCE 1871</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The Fire</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On October 9, 1871 (Monday morning), the old St. Paul's Church suffered the fire which spread to its section at Ohio and La Salle Street. By evening the Pastor Joseph Hartmann lost his home, library, and other belongings; and five-sixths of the entire membership of the church gazed upon the wreck and ruin of all their earthly possessions.</p>
   <p>"One of the wealthiest congregations of Chicago had suddenly become the poorest of all, none of the other churches founded by the Mother Church having been damaged by the flames. Immediately after the fire had been placed under control, relief poured in from all parts of the country, expecially the Eastern states. Within a few weeks $5,000 was sent from sister churches as a fund for rebuilding purposes. In the spring of 1872 it was definitely resolved to rebuild the new church on the old foundation. The same architect, Mr. A. Bauer, who 20 years before had made <pb facs="5418474_10_1369.jpg" n="2"/>the plans and specifications for the first church, was again engaged to rebuild the new church. Messrs. F. Letz, H. Muhlke, Conrad Fuerst, William Knoke, A. Kroeger and J. K. Jarmon, were appointed as the building committee. Steer and Turner, organ builders at Westfield, Mass., received the contract to build a larger and more beautiful instrument. On February 16, 1873, the new church was dedicated and meanwhile the membership had also erected its new homes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
