<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>.
<date when="1908-02-13">February 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Practical Advice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>.
<date when="1908-02-13">February 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">PRACTICAL ADVICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Very often you hear our Chicago Germans say that American Courts and American Judges are not just and not honest.</p>
   <p>Without doubt, the understanding of right and wrong is all over the world the same. And still there is a remarkable difference in the meaning and handling of laws in all countries. As a rule, all Germans, coming to this country, will find it hard to get accustomed to our American laws and American courts, which are giving plenty of time and opportunity to both sides (accuser and defendant), to produce and demonstrated their arguments.</p>
   <p>We dare to say, that in many court cases even clever Germans were not quick witted enough to grasp the situation in one nut shell, to counteract at once the arguments of the opponent.</p>
   <p>In other words, our German citizens must acquire the ability to think American and enter the courthouse with an American mind. This will help enormously, to understand more profoundly the American judge and to cooperate <pb facs="5418474_10_0082.jpg" n="2"/>more effectively with the court proceedings towards a just solution and fair trial.</p>
   <p>Our Germans still have the old country habit, of entering a court case, finally will seek legal advice. Up till then valuable time had been lost, while the opposite side of the case was able to build up powerful arguments and testimonials. In most cases like this, our Germans are unjustly inclined to believe, that all available evidence is against them. And still, the judge himself would decide probably the other way, if the standpoint of the German client would have been made sufficiently clear to him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
