<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-01">May 1, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[Peace Festival Planned]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0949</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0949.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-01">May 1, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[PEACE FESTIVAL PLANNED]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon a mass meeting took place in Concordia Hall to discuss the planned Peace Festival. Mr. A. Schoninger was elected chairman. The proposition to have a public parade was unanimously adopted. (Translator's footnote: About two months earlier the Staats Zeitung was particularly vociferous in urging that public parades should be left to the Irish, and were "un-German" - but now she makes no mention of any opposition). The program of the festival was adopted by all against one vote.</p>
   <p>One committee that drew up the plan for the festival started with the idea that this must become the grandest celebration that ever took place in the West and must correspond to the incomparably great events of the immediate past. The parade shall demonstrate both the numerical and the intellectual strength of the Germans, their solidarity and union. The fifth float will represent German literature through the following figures: Schiller, Goethe, Lessing, Klopstock, Wieland, Herder, Uhland, Heine, etc. The eighth float will glorify the repossession of Alsace-Lorraine by the German Reich.</p>
   <p>Mr. George Schneider was elected president of the festival. Four committees <pb facs="5418474_10_0950.jpg" n="2"/>each of seven members, were formed - a finance committee (Adolph Schoninger), a parade committee (Robert Thiem), a place committee (Lorenz Mattern), and a celebration committee (Franz Arnold).</p>
   <p>Herr Carl Proebsting was elected secretary general, and given the task to get in contact with all German associations. There were present at the meeting about thirty members of the growing German militia in full Prussian uniform. When they left, their erect posture and regiment-like marching earned them loud applause from those present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
