<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-09-05">Sept. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Great Demands on German Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-09-05">Sept. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT DEMANDS ON GERMAN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday, September 4, the administrative council of the Deutsche Gesellschaft (German Society) of Chicago held a meeting under the chairmanship of the president, Mr. Michael F. Girten. The following gentlemen were also present: A. F. Madlener, G. F. Fisher, H. Wollenberger, R. Seifert, F. A. Lackner, P. S. Theurer, E. Kusswurm, Wm. Mannhardt, and F. von Wysow.</p>
   <p>The report of the business secretary for the past quarter year gave a vivid picture of the wonderful work done by this, the oldest of Chicago's charitable institutions, which has to meet greater demands than ever during these turbulent times.</p>
   <p>During this period 227 families with 675 children, and 508 single persons, including 54 females, received cash relief. Unemployed and homeless people were given 1688 free meals and 202 nightly shelters. For these purposes $2,188.38 was disbursed, more than double the amount spent during the same <pb facs="5418474_10_0701.jpg" n="2"/>period last year. On recommendation of the Society, 17 persons found free admission in hospitals, 12 in County institutions and 19 were given free medical treatment.</p>
   <p>Work was found for 994 people, a comparatively small figure for this time of the year. In comparison to the number of job seekers, which increases daily, the opportunities for employment are decreasing at an alarming rate, and it is extremely difficult to provide jobs.</p>
   <p>The influence of the war on the work of the Society is remarkable. During the first few days after the outbreak of the war the number of job seekers declined almost eighty percent only to shoot up suddenly far above the average, and to increase steadily. One of the reasons was that thousands of men of military age, in their eagerness to join the colors, went to New York with or without means, in order to get back to their native land as quickly as possible. Disappointed in their hopes, only a few had the means to come back here, and the others found themselves up against it without a job.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0702.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On the other hand, thousands of men have arrived here from the west, hoping to get transportation east, but have had to be disappointed.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, among these men are many professional hoboes who are trying to capitalize on present conditions by pretending to have lost their papers. They enact the role of [German] patriots in an attempt to arouse sympathy and to secure a few dollars at the expense of honest people who really deserve the money. We cannot warn a good hearted public enough against these cheats.</p>
   <p>We want to call special attention to the fact that the German Society will celebrate its sixtieth anniversary during the first days of October.</p>
   <p>With the kind co-operation of the local branch of the Deutsch-Amerikanischer National Bund, this anniversary will be celebrated as German Day. The net profits will be used to relieve destitution of German and Austro-Hungarian families who have lost their provider in the war. Details will be <pb facs="5418474_10_0703.jpg" n="4"/>announced in a few days.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
