<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-04">Oct. 4, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">News from the German-American Citizens' Bund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-04">Oct. 4, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE GERMAN-AMERICAN CITIZENS' BUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Presided over by William Joern, a general meeting of the committee for the fall festival of the German-American Citizens' Bund was held last Friday, in conjunction with a membership drive. It was decided that all present should function as a committee for the fall festival.</p>
   <p>Present, were the following gentlemen: William Joern, Chris Clausen, Gust Gross, Emil Rapp, Theo Schlichting, Fred Rixmann, Gust Scheel, Henry Neumann, Wenzel Wiese, Fred Brumund, John Beierwaltes, Herman Joern, Eugen Klomfass, and Otto Lausar.</p>
   <p>The Schiller Liedertafel is expected to take part in the program, as reported by Secretary Clausen. The Schleswig-Holstein Singers' Bund will be asked to participate, so that a mass chorus may be heard. John Beierwaltes and Emil Rapp will call on the former and Ernst Brosius on the latter to extend the invitation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0481.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A committee was appointed to take care of further entertainment. It is composed of John Cremer, Ernst Brosius, Gust Scheel, and Fred Rixmann. Contact should be made with the ladies' squad of the Illinois Turn District.</p>
   <p>Hartwig's orchestra is to provide music.</p>
   <p>The following additional committees were named:</p>
   <p>Reception: Fred Rixmann, Ernst Brosing, and William Joern.</p>
   <p>Tickets: W. Thiel, Herman Joern, and Henry Neumann.</p>
   <p>Bar: Emil Rapp and Gust Scheel.</p>
   <p>Finances: Alfred Clausen, Charles Bischoff, Otto Lausar, and Theo Schlichting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0482.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Publicity: Ernst Brosius.</p>
   <p>Arrangements were made for a radio broadcast and other publicity, as well as for invitations to officials and political candidates. The latter, however, should only be introduced. Only the city's representative, if present, should be permitted to speak. [Editor's note: How nice!]</p>
   <p>The next meeting is to take place on Monday, October 17.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
