<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-10-07">Oct. 7, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Peace Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-10-07">Oct. 7, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEACE CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Richard Bartholdt of St.Louis, one of the speakers at yesterday's celebration of German Day was, during the past month, one of the representatives of the United States, at the Peace Conference at the Hague. He came back from Europe only a few days ago. To a reporter of the Abendpost Mr. Bartholdt expressed the following opinion about the Congress:</p>
   <p>"In my opinion the most important part of the peace conference lies in the fact that it has taken place at all, for in this way the Governments will get used to talk at the green table also about important affairs in place of being always ready with their fist in the pocket. By such discussions a danger of war will be substantially diminished. Another of the acquisitions of Congress is the resolution to arrange further meetings and to make agreements to settle by arbitrary treaties in a peaceful way controversies among nations that always will turn up again. Also, if the idea of a foundation of a Court of Justice with permanent judges should not succeed, the Tribunal of the Hague will still remain in existence and the present conference made the powers more willing to appeal to it in the future and to make it by this action an integral part of the international justice apparatus.Personally I rejoiced most that the United States and Germany went along hand in hand <pb facs="5418474_10_0231.jpg" n="2"/>in many questions and this created the best impression in both countries.</p>
   <p>"My personal activity, in Berlin, as well as in London, consisted in making propaganda for a Model Arbitration Treaty that was proposed by the United States and by the latest reports it seems that my mission was crowned with success. I believe that a general arbitration Treaty between all countries will be created, but the German Empire and probably other countries as well will present the questions in which it will recognize the Court of Arbitration. The theorists and dreamers who saw in the conference already the dawn of an overlasting peace will be disappointed as could be seen in advance, but this proves only how impractical they were in their demands and how optimistic in their plans. Personally I must say that the peace conference did about what I had hoped for and expected."</p>
   <p>Mr. Bartholdt arrived today again in St. Louis. During the last few years he has been frequently mentioned in connection with high offices, such as national senator and governor of Missouri.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
