<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-05-11">May 11, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Twenty Five Year Peace Memorial Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0808</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0808.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-05-11">May 11, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTY FIVE YEAR PEACE MEMORIAL CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large number of patriotic clubs and parties assembled Saturday in the festive decorated Northside Gymnastic Hall, to celebrate the 25th year memorial of the Frankfort pease of the German Empire. The Weege Music Choir opened the celebration with Webers jubilee overture and the various Veteran Clubs marched their standards and flags to the stage and united them in a festival group. Mr. George Buettner, President of the German Veteran's Club, introduced Judge Brentano as the festival chairman. In a short speech the President reminded the public of the peace festival, celebrated by the Germans of Chicago 25 years ago and stated that the United Germany not only as soldiers, but also in the culture of art and science takes first place among the nations of the world. Several patriotic songs were enthusiastically sung by all parties, and Mr. E. F. L. Gauss recited a prologue composed by him, "The Song Of The Germans," in which every one participated, followed by a superb orchestra play "The Torch Dance." Dr. Karl Buentz the German Consul held the festival speech and said, that the position of Germany in the heart of Europe forces the nation to keep the National defense in accord with the times. The German people at home seem to forget their great tradition in party fights, and therefore it should <pb facs="5418474_10_0809.jpg" n="2"/>be duty of the Germans outside the fatherland, to honor National ideas and principles. The Germans in the United States of America well know their duty and responsibility and a splendid toast was drunk in honor of the United Germany and the German Emperor.</p>
   <p>Pres. W. Meyer of the Platt German Central Association spoke about the scattered German states before the war with France. After several more patriotic songs, the orchestra played the Paris entrance march and Mr. Emil Hoechster spoke about "real unifiers of Germany." He finished the toast with a cheer for the old chancellor, Bismarck, among the stormy enthusiasm of all guests, who demanded a telegram to be sent to the hermit of Friedrichsruh. Justice of the peace, Max Eberhardt, spoke about the Germans in America, their support of the menanced union, their quiet work for civilization, industry, art and good fellowship. His speech ended with the appeal to give the new fatherland the same support which made the old fatherland strong and great. Several other speakers as Mr. George Buttner, Dr. J. A. Schmidt followed and a number of German patriotic songs were played and sung. The celebration ended as a real patriotic one, and everybody was conscious of the National ideas and success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
