<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-02-14">Monday, Feb. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Central Association of the German Warriors Celebrate "Emperor's Birthday." the Imperal Flag. the German Reservist Club Will Carry It.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-02-14">Monday, Feb. 14, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">CENTRAL ASSOCIATION OF THE GERMAN WARRIORS CELEBRATE "EMPEROR'S BIRTHDAY." THE IMPERAL FLAG. THE GERMAN RESERVIST CLUB WILL CARRY IT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Somewhat belated but more animated and enthusiastic because of it, amid generous participation, the Central Association of the German Military Clubs of Chicago and vicinity celebrated the birthday of their former war-lord. Schoenhofen's Hall, at Milwaukee and Ashland Avenue was barely large enough to accomodate the surging crowd, and during the various parade numbers, jubilant enthusiasm manifested itself. This was especially noticeable during the presentation of the flag to"German Reservist Club," in whose care this standard, loaned by Wilhelm II, will remain during the ensuing year. Association President, Martin Gass who gave the flag presentation address, added an extra number. An uniformed division of the recently organized Red Cross Auxiliary Corps, wherein Mr. Gass functions, as major, was present during the festivities and showed how capably they were instructed in military movements. Also the Amazon March presented by the ladies of the Club, wives of the <pb facs="5418474_10_1187.jpg" n="2"/>former soldiers, of the army and navy was given adequate commendation.</p>
   <p>Most musical numbers were similarly received. The program contained orchestra selections, choral singing, a duet by Mr. Maja Gloersen-Huitfeld and Mr. Max Bing. The committee on arrangements was confronted with arduous labors but fulfilled them faithfully and without dissenting. Mr. Traub and eight others co-operated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
