<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-11-11">Nov. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Impressive Schiller Celebration of the Chicago Swabian Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-11-11">Nov. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">IMPRESSIVE SCHILLER CELEBRATION OF THE CHICAGO SWABIAN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swabian Society of Chicago, celebrated a Schiller festival yesterday, in the North Side Turner Hall, which was very successful in every respect, as a dignified and imposing demonstration by Chicago Germans, in honor and in memory of the prince of poets, Frederick von Schiller.</p>
   <p>Music by and orchestra and by the Men's Choir of the Swabian Singing Society introduced the program, after which the president, Wilhelm Jauss gave the welcoming speech. The speech of the evening was given by Carl Kotthaus from Munich, who has been on a lecture tour in America. After a few illuminating remarks about the German spiritual importance of Schiller, as a poet, as well as a personality, Mr. Kotthaus, with the assistance of stereopticon pictures, explained the connection, which existed between Schiller's spiritual life and personality and his head formation. Mr. Jose Danner, who is well known in German circles of America, as a director of the German theater, presented the <pb facs="5418474_10_1081.jpg" n="2"/>"Rutli," scene from Schiller's "William Tell." The ardor of Schiller's language, was faithfully reproduced by the art of Mr. Danner. With the enthusiasm of a young soul he filled to over-flowing all the hearts of his listeners, through Schiller's forceful poetry and they felt themselves free and in a defiant mood, conscious of their Germanism.</p>
   <p>The Swabian society proved anew through this festival, that the German element in America, has liberated itself from oppression and as in the rest of the world, is becoming stronger day by day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
