<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-07">Sept. 7, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">The Shepherds and Their Flock.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-07">Sept. 7, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">THE SHEPHERDS AND THEIR FLOCK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held at Battery D, last night, called by the delegates attending German Catholic Day, to which the prominent followers of the Catholic religion of this city were also invited. The right side of the speaker's platform where the delegates of the clergy were seated, resembled a cabbage patch with their round and shiny bald heads. Seated on the platform were, besides the speakers of the evening, the most prominent catholic citizens of Chicago, amongst whom was Anton Caspar Hesing.</p>
   <p>The Rev. Father Jessing of Columbus spoke of the "Deutsk Katholiske Skule in Amerika", and expressed his opinion that our public schools are nothing but a nusiance. A good many people hold that schools are here to impart knowledge to our children; but this is wrong. Religion ought to be taught in these schools. Too much knowledge is creating evil, Chicago boodlers are giving a good exhibition of that! (Obviously, this Reverend does not seem to know that the most contemptible scoundrel among the boodlers is a pious Catholic. Lynch, the "squealer, is a <pb facs="5418474_10_1660.jpg" n="2"/>member of the Board of Directors and one of the pillars of the Catholic church. The rest of the boodlers are all good christians, although theirs is a different form of idol worship.) The priest then asked the assemblage to encourage and build parochial schools. This honest westphalian clergyman closed his speech with these words: "Erect parochial schools, and religion will be thriving." (Stupidity would be thriving.)</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. Miller, the publisher of the Detroit newspaper, The Truth. Mr. Miller's subject was: "The Press, expecially the American-German Catholic Press." Very little of what he said could be understood, for his immense nose interfered with the clarity of his speech. He raved furiously against the Turners and secret leaguers, who have no consideration for any authority, etc. The chairman who noticed the unpleasant effect his speech produced on the audience, caused him to withdraw.</p>
   <p>The Rev. Father Robbers of Covington, Kentucky followed as speaker. He was supposed to have as subject: "The Social question". Nobody could have exhibited more <pb facs="5418474_10_1661.jpg" n="3"/>ignorance than he did during the half hour allowed him. It was astounding to hoar that social economist of the German catholic church ask: "Is there really a social question, does poverty and misery really exist among working men?" We communicated with the Holy Father and according to his instructions the church has to remain neutral, but we are not restricted as private individuals in the expression of our opinions, and mine is, that we have to block the activities of the now existing labor societies in which followers of Marx and other Jewish defenders of social economy are leaders. Those labor societies are working toward a revival of slavery, trying to dictate to their bosses. They are bound to revive the Roman and Grecian barbarism thorugh their insistence upon eradicating the religion to which we owe our civilization. The working men have to be won back to the church, peace of mind of which they were robbed by the socialistic agitators can be theirs once again, if they attend church instead of attending public meetings or Sundays. But they need the leadership of their employers." At this point he felt jokingly inclined and related an anecdote to the amusement of the listeners.</p>
   <p>Anton Caspar Hesing, who applauded the joke so loudly, must have forgotten that he <pb facs="5418474_10_1662.jpg" n="4"/>made his fortune through the whisky ring and, furthermore, that he transferred the money into his wife's name, thus escaping his obligations toward his creditors.</p>
   <p>The proposed point of the resolution, to forbid a catholic to join the Knights of Labor, was not passed, fearing this to be a false move.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
