<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-05-04">May 4, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">The German Building.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A c a</item>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-05-04">May 4, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN BUILDING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We herewith give you an illustration of the new German Building reproduced from Der Westen (The West, a German paper, Translated.) The object of this creation is to produce an edifice, whereby the higher ideals of the German population may find stimulation and satisfaction from a social standpoint and at the same time construct the building in such a manner, that the proceeds therefrom will defray the maintenance expense, which is considerable. It was a very difficult problem for the administration.</p>
   <p>The main purpose of the building is to provide a "German Theatre" where performances will be given daily; this required considerable space, not only on the ground level but it included five floors and, as there are many more assembly halls, it was found necessary to resort to sky scraper construction, in order to add sufficient rooms, so that the income from rents could defray the expense.</p>
   <p>This made it inadvisable to select one of the academic historic styles for the facade. Neither antiquity, the mediaeval age nor the present period, only the ultra modern time has succeeded in perfecting vertical transportation to its present <pb facs="5418474_10_1610.jpg" n="2"/>degree of excellence which was most essential, because of the ever increasing congestion into the preferred (?) districts of a city and this system was unknown to the ancients. To the classic styles and the Renaissance which developed therefrom with its serene, deliberate treatment, its strong horizontal lines, with the definitely prescribed proportions for the various dimensions, this competition to scale the sky is simply something atrocious when architectural appearance is considered, and all attempts to combine these unfriendly elements into an harmonious whole, have failed. Even if the Gothic, vertical lines have developed structures of the highest artistic merit, these were always strictly monumental buildings, which were not required to serve a useful purpose. In our case it was not desired to build a high tower in honor of the Lord, something lofty that reaches towards heaven, but it was demanded to erect an entire building, 165 feet high, on an area of 1,000 square feet. (Translator's note: Subsequent dimensions in the same article, quote an area of 3,000 square feet on the 10th floor.) Yet the sense for beauty had to be considered and it must not be forgotten, that the building has been dedicated to a communal spirt, to a longing towards an ideal, by citizens of a free city, adherents of a people who advanced far in culture and in conforming to all this, the utilization of every conceivable space was something which could not be ignored. Besides, one <pb facs="5418474_10_1611.jpg" n="3"/>is confronted with Chicago's swampy soil, which imposes further limitations. That made it impossible to make the plan of the building conform to the definite patterns of some historic style. Just as the masters of the classic Greek, the Roman, Romanesque and Gothic architecture, and just as the artists of the Italian, French and German Renaissance added to the bequeathed wisdom, by bringing to it new thought and phantasy, in order to fulfill the demands of their contemporaries, had to consider available building materials, the dexterity of the obtainable artisans and trades, which brought a gradual architectural development throughout the centuries, and just as in by gone ages the epochal builders, perhaps even unawarely, founded new styles slowly, subtly,by alterations here and there so also it became the task of the Administration of the "Chicago German Opera House Company" and the architects, to add their share in creating the new archictural style of the twentieth century.</p>
   <p>No heavy quarried stone or brick was to be used for walls, and arches, instead steel beams and rods, riveted together formed a skeleton, which was clothes with hollow tile. Economic reasons demanded many windows and precluded large wall surfaces.Sunshine and air should be available to all parts of the building. The gigantic <pb facs="5418474_10_1612.jpg" n="4"/>pillars of the Greeks, the arches... of the Romans, the umbrageous, romantic colonnades of the romanesque, the Norman and Gothic designs with their ornamental and admirable treatment of each motion....were not to be copied...We intend to give a more detailed account later....</p>
   <p>The plot of ground is 80 feet on Randolph Street, a depth of 181½ feet towards the alley, the latter is 18 feet wide.</p>
   <p>The basement contains the necessary, large assortment of machinery, dressing rooms, meeting rooms, storage rooms for the stage and a restaurant fashioned in the manner of a German Rathskeller where beer is also available.</p>
   <p>On the ground level is the forty feet wide entrance, next to it on each side a space to be rented for restaurant purposes. The theater, similar to the auditorium, can be reached from the main floor, likewise the second floor. It will have 1,257 seats and rises to the fifth floor which allows a considerable grade for the floor level and galleries, it enables every one in the audience to have an unobstricted view of the stage. It is also one of the characteristics of this theater, that the galleries are supported by iron posts, which eliminates all pillars inside of the theater.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1613.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>On each side of the theater, exits will be provided which lead... into the alley. On the main floor are two foyers, each gallery has one... Iron, steel, marble, slate and concrete are used on the stage, for stairways, the loft above the stage, galleries, etc., to prevent serious fires. The stage will be supplied with the artificial horizont, which our readers probably know from the auditorium. It was copied from German theaters...Mechanical methods shall be the best available and, aside from the auditorium, it will be the only nearly fireproof stage in America.</p>
   <p>The area of the stage will be 40 x 80 feet. Height of stage from procenium to attic which contains the scenery, 71 feet. Illumination for theater and audience requires 1,400 electric lamps. Fresh air, steam heated by coils, is supplied by two fans, having a capacity of 2½ million cubic feet per hour; distribution is obtained without noticeable draft....</p>
   <p>Other public halls are on the 12th floor, one with 600, the other 250 seats. Both can be used as dance halls, large reception and dressing rooms are provided. The 11th floor, will be used entirely by a German business men's club, which will be organized in the near future. This space provides for dressing, reading, play, billiard and dining rooms, etc., the 10th floor will be used solely for a restaurant <pb facs="5418474_10_1614.jpg" n="6"/>of 3,000 square feet and a number of smaller, private dining rooms and kitchen.</p>
   <p>For hotel purposes 131 rooms with 38 baths and 10 rooms for the personal are also available. Besides these the reception and business rooms found customarily in hostelries of the first rank.</p>
   <p>For ventilation throughout the halls and rooms, kitchen, bathrooms, etc, and the saloon in the basement, five fans are used which are electrically driven. 2,500 electric lights... excluding the theater will be used. Steam heat is used.</p>
   <p>The foundation calls for 900 piles 30 feet long, to be driven into the ground... steel and concrete above this.</p>
   <p>The theater proper is surrounded by a wall, three feet thick. On it the 25 foot high, steel supports are mounted, on which the remaining eight floors rest. The balance of the construction consists of riveted steel pillars and beams. All connections are riveted. The vertical and horizontal sections are filled with hollow tile. All stairs are made of marble, slate and iron. Four passenger and one freight elevators connect all floors.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1615.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The artistic embellishments and the difficulties of construction will be treated in a separate chapter later; illustrations will be included.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
