<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1903-12-08">Dec. 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">New Difficulties in Obtaining Citizenship</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1903-12-08">Dec. 8, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">NEW DIFFICULTIES IN OBTAINING CITIZENSHIP</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If President Theodore Roosevelt and his attorney general Knox have their way, then all who intend to acquire American citizenship papers will meet with considerable difficulty in the future. That our nationalization law is faulty in many respects is true enough. It is undefined, contradictory, incomplete planless, and unscientific. It is so defective that a certain question which has arisen thousands of times a year for over a century can not be adequately answered. Thus, the query, if a child were born in the United States by parents of foreign birth who are not American citizens, what is the status of the indigenous youngster? One day a court answered: Yes, he is a citizen; another day it proclaims: No; until some years ago, the supreme court ended the controversy.</p>
   <p>Worse chaos exists where the nullification or loss of citizenship is concerned. There is no rule whatever. An American, a bonafide citizen, may travel to a foreign country and so conduct himself that he actually becomes a subject of another nation, so that he finds it necessary to give an oath of allegiance to such a power: for example, he obtains a public position or serves in their army, as many of the southern army officers have done after the Civil War and later they returned, <pb facs="5418474_10_0095.jpg" n="2"/>appearing and acting as full fledged citizens, as if nothing had happened. Already, President Grant has emphasized the necessity of regulation for the voidance and procural of citizenship; a new and comprehensive law should be drafted. He cited logical reasons which showed that he was well versed in the subject, but it was of no avail.</p>
   <p>What Theodore Roosevelt proclaims at present shows plainly that he has only a casual knowledge of this problem. About the loss of citizenship he is absolutely mute, and in regard to the declaration or intention of prospective citizens, he confines hinself to a lamentation about crookedness which existed to a staggering degree and the "unfathomable evil" which created thereby. He concludes this with a recommendation of the proposals contained in the attorney general's annual report.</p>
   <p>No one will argue that obtaining citizenship by fraud is a serious offense which should not be tolerated. However, the matter is not as dangerous as Mr. Roosevelt would have us believe. Evidently he has been misled by the account of a snooping official whose gross exaggerations we mentioned in these columns months ago. Among other items he claims that a Chicago judge naturalized three thousand people in one evening, an alleged incident nobody ever heard of and which in itself, is <pb facs="5418474_10_0096.jpg" n="3"/>is a physical impossibility... In the main, "the despicable evils" are confined to an occasional immigrant who votes illegally, but this is much more prevalent among the "hired repeaters" paid tramps etc., who did not come to our shores recently; and, secondly, there are some poor souls, comparatively new arrivals, who, with the aid of improperly obtained citizenship papers, have become city street cleaners before the alloted lustrum, and have held similar jobs which a constricted, heartless, native legislation reserved in the interests of the political bosses, who dole them out to citizens and voters.</p>
   <p>Now we face a more serious peril; just this, that the majority, or at least a large fraction, will not be admitted to citizenship, which causes an ever increasing quantity of foreigners, who cannot obtain citizen rights, which precludes any possibility that they may become imbued with patriotic sentiments: of "foreigners" in the true sense of the word, whose troth belongs to another government, and their presence may lead to grave international complications. Mr. Roosevelt and his attorney general do not mention this calamity. They probably never thought about it. If they did, then they hardly would have advocated laws, which, when passed, would make such a contingency an inevitable reality. Consider the proposal, for instance, whereby the citizenship applications and grants, etc., must be confined <pb facs="5418474_10_0097.jpg" n="4"/>only to a United States court. What this means, we can understand by perusing these facts. Throughout the 45 states of the union there are about 70 United States courts; in most cases, a state has only one. Therefore the great mass of prospective citizens would be compelled to make long and expensive journeys, often for hundreds of miles, and then, after arriving, they may have to wait for days or weeks, before the busy court finds time to concern itself with their case. We might just as well deny citizenship rights to thousands and hundreds of thousands.</p>
   <p>This single thoughtless proposal does more harm then all the good which is contained in the rest of the recommendations.... All the dire consequences of emigration which excites so many people, are but a sequence to our natural growth.... If we proclaim that we obtain many an undesirable alien by the citizenship route, then we can make the identical statement of our preferred native inhabitants,.... we know from experience that many are not exemplary citizens....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
