<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-02-19">Feb. 19, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The German Literary Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-02-19">Feb. 19, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN LITERARY SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If a small number of people congregate, in order to do pioneer work for the purpose of establishing German literature and German culture, then we must admit that it is both a very laudable but also a difficult task. It is there-fore very gratifying to note that such precursors, under the name of "The German Literary Society," are now able to review their successful accomplishments. After working unobtrusively, they have obtained a secure foot-hold and may now face the public. The purpose of the Association has already been mentioned, but we must not forget to give especial credit to its leader, Henry Cohn, who endeavors not only to attract the German element with its unified sentiments on this subject, but also wishes to create interest in the German language amongst the Americans. "The French language is fashionable amongst Americans," Mr. Cohn said, "and our Society intends to make German the fashion." That would be a progressive step. That the Club is capable of accomplishing something may be readily ascertained by visiting its meetings. The women and men supply sagacious wit for diversion and erudition; <pb facs="5418474_10_0860.jpg" n="2"/>literary compositions and humorous recitations give a diversified program, and music has by no means been forgotten. Yesterday's evening proved most entertaining and we especially recommend that the younger German element should become affiliated with the Society. Guests, or, we might say, visitors, are welcomed every Tuesday, 8 P.M., Room D, Central Music Hall. A very promising program has been announced for Tuesday, Feb. 25, at Emerson Hall. The officials of the Literary Club are: W. T. Underwood, President; A. Woodcock, Vice-President; Miss A. E. Crocker, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
