<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Fackel</title>,
<date when="1881-03-06">March 6th, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Anniversary of the Foundation and Flag Inauguration of the Society "Bavaria."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0918</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0918.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>DIE FACKEL</title>,
<date when="1881-03-06">March 6th, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Anniversary of the Foundation and Flag Inauguration of the Society "Bavaria."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Society "Bavaria" was founded on November 12th of last year, and has already a membership of about 150 who gathered last Monday evening at Brand's Halle, to spend a few hours, in the real German manner of sociability. The Hall was decorated with garlands and flags and through its beauty impressed everyone present. It is Mr. Aug. Lang, the well known turn teacher of the North side, who has been entrusted with the decoration of the Hall, and he also directed the tableau's presented, which were "Die Schlacht bei Muhldorf" (The Battlefield of Muhldorf) "Die Sendlinger Schlacht" and "Die Schlacht bei Weissenburg." All three presentations enjoyed so much acclaim, that it was deemed necessary to repeat these numbers.</p>
   <p>The finale of the evening, was the presentation of the beautiful silk flag, with heavy rich embroidery, made by Mrs. Mitchell, and presented to the President by <pb facs="5418474_10_0919.jpg" n="2"/>Mrs. Victoria Markham. Mrs. Markham, earned the Society's gratitude; her costume for this occasion, was one representing Bavaria. The President, Mr. Reisencker, in a lengthy speech, extended a welcome in the name of the Society.</p>
   <p>The flag presentation scene was heightened in effect by the artistic setting of large Oak trees on the stage under which shadows, a group of eight ladies, dressed in national costumes, represented the eight districts of Bavaria. In the center, under the Bavarian coat of arms, stood Germania and the Goddess of freedom, with the President and Mrs. Markham, each at one side of the stage.</p>
   <p>Much praise for the great success of the evening goes to Messrs. Reisenecker, Miller, Baus and Fols, members of the committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
