<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-01-10">January 10, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">Der Westen Sunday Edition</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Administration of the St. Sonifacius Cemetey and of the Orphan Home in Pose Hill. Anaual Meeting of the Boare of Directors.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-01-10">January 10, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">Der Westen Sunday Edition</title><title level="a" type="sub">THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE ST. SONIFACIUS CEMETEY AND OF THE ORPHAN HOME IN POSE HILL. ANAUAL MEETING OF THE BOARE OF DIRECTORS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the refectory of the Franciscan Convent, the yearly meeting of the Directors of the Catholic Orphanage and the Catholic St. Bonifagius Cemetery was held under the chairmanship of the Rev. Father Fischer. The priest of every German Catholic parsonage and two members of each parish participated as representatives. Rev. Father Fischer made a speech in which he related that at the time of the foundation of the cemetery only four German parishes existed in this city and that it was a hard struggle before the Catholics, who were then hated received a permit to found their own cemetery. This was in 1863. Today the parishes share the cemetery. Four small parishes founded the cemetery in the belief that it would provide resting places for the dead for an endless number of years. Today, with more than 80,000 German Catholics in Chicago, new cemeteries soon will have to be established. The same is true of the Orphan home, but in an even more pressing way, 183 children have found a good home there, thanks to the unselfish service of twelve servants of Christ. During the last year, 1,132 Catholics found their last resting place at the St. Bonifacius Cemetery.</p>
   <p>A sum of $1,000 was received by the Orphan Home from the Katholischer Jugend <pb facs="5418474_10_1671.jpg" n="2"/>Freund which represents the net profit of this publication edited by the Rev. Aloys Thiele at 1 North Clark St.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
