<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-11">Nov. 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Turnverein Vorwarts (Forward Athletic Club) Commemorates Schiller, the Poet of the People.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-11">Nov. 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">TURNVEREIN VORWARTS (FORWARD ATHLETIC CLUB) COMMEMORATES SCHILLER, THE POET OF THE PEOPLE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The season of pleasant intellectual entertainment was introduced by the Turnverein Vorwarts last night in a most fitting manner, namely, by commemorating Schiller. The Vorwarts Hall was well filled, when at 8:30 o'clock the orchestra played the overture. The choir section of the club rendered a composition "Free and Unshaken," with great enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the committee for intellectual programs welcomed the guests very cordially. He stated that the duty of Turners (Gymnasts) is not to parade in political affairs, but to solve modern educational problems; namely, the symmetrical development of mind and body. Although this aim is pursued by our public schools, yet their efforts are entirely too inadequate. The intellectual development often turns out to be in the realm of religion only.</p>
   <p>The speaker then criticized the employment of female teachers in public schools. The shaping of the future depends upon the training of youth, the speaker stated, and the Turnverein must be a rock of liberty in the ocean of public life.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1211.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. H. Huhn of Milwaukee delivered the speech of the occasion. "Schiller and His Time," was the topic of his address. "Three men," he said, "who are unforgettable today, were all of them born on November tenth, namely, Luthor, Schiller, and R. Blum. They all were sons of the people, and their names will never be forgotten by liberty-loving people. All three of them were striving to elevate humanity and increase human value and dignity.</p>
   <p>"Only those who live with the people and among the people, understand its needs and its problems. There is no help for the people to be expected from above; the people must help themselves. Those three men live in the memory of all who strive to attain a higher human dignity."</p>
   <p>The speaker then expounded the dramas and poems of Schiller from the standpoint of the humanists and the friends of liberty, and he succeeded in fascinating his audience for one hour....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
