<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-10-10">October 10, 1907</date><title level="a">The Rest of the Deceased Representatives of the Concordia League Protest against Baseball Park.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-10-10">October 10, 1907</date><title level="a">THE REST OF THE DECEASED REPRESENTATIVES OF THE CONCORDIA LEAGUE PROTEST AGAINST BASEBALL PARK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Concordia League has taken a position in the name of 80,000 Lutherans of Chicago and Chicago's suburbs against the new plan for the creation of a baseball and exhibition part near the present location of the Concordia, Waldheim and other cemeteries in Harlem, for which the Town Council of Harlem gave permission to certain operators by decree. On the same ground a few years ago was intended the erection of a Pleasure Park in the style of Riverview Park. The Concordia League and the various cemetery companies protested so decidely that the undertaking had to be stopped; the business affairs of the "Beach Amusement Company" were finally attended to by the federal courts. Partners of the "Beach Amusement Company" will now hide behind the new plan, and they have found support in the Township Council of Harlem according to the testimony of City Council Member Beilfuss.</p>
   <p>Yesterday evening the representatives of the Concordia League discussed the plan at the Schiller Building and presented in resolutions the attitude of the League. It says this:</p>
   <p>"Be it resolved that we, the undersigned members of the Concordia League who <pb facs="5418474_10_0749.jpg" n="2"/>represent the Lutheran parishes of the City of Chicago, decided to enter a protest against the insult that is done against the peace-loving and law-abiding citizens, and that we express our abhorrence against those who have lent them their land to enable the above said undertaking on that territory, and that we are herewith asking the public for their assistance to preserve the quietness and the peace that shall surround the last resting place of our loved ones. We further call public attention to the respect that even heathens pay to their dead ones in their interment places."</p>
   <p>These protest resolutions are signed by Albert W. Beilfuss, William Busse, Henry Utpatel, Otto Doederlein and Robert Schoenfeld.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
