<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-09-09">Sept. 9, 1928</date><title level="a">Foundation Festival of Schiller Lodge a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-09-09">Sept. 9, 1928</date><title level="a">FOUNDATION FESTIVAL OF SCHILLER LODGE A GREAT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A fine musical program and lovely dance sponsored by the Schiller Lodge found great approbation.</p>
   <p>For weeks, an active Festival Committee made it their object to prepare for the fourth Foundation Festival of the Schiller Lodge, I. O. F. A., which preparation extended into the smallest details, in order to offer all visitors and music lovers a program which should surpass all expectations.</p>
   <p>The Festival began at 8 o'clock in the large room of the Turner Hall, under the leadership of the conductor, Hugo Jung, the Schiller Orchestra, consisting of thirteen musicians, opened the concert with the old, but always new march, "Old Comrades." Several other compositions were played which were all heartily applauded by the audience. The prologue by J.C. Hoch, recited by Miss Fanny Geip, deserves special mention.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0540.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Splendid singing by the Orpheus Men's chorus, interspersed with solos and group dancing, executed by pupils of the Huntinghouse academy for dancing, were on program.</p>
   <p>The festival speech by Mr. Hoch closed the program. He expressed his pleasure and satisfaction about the celebration and the exceptionally large attendance. The festival committee consisted of the president, Erwin A. G. Schnurpfeil, treasurer, Hans Schmidt, and the secretary, Erich Paschky. After the concert, dancing began, which lasted until the early morning hours.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
