<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-22">Feb. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Carnival of the Gymnastic Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-22">Feb. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">CARNIVAL OF THE GYMNASTIC ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the main features of this year's carnival festivities was the great masquerade of the Chicago Gymnastic Association. The celebration had been eagerly expected for weeks, and the dance-craving crowd made the customary preparations long ago. All the chambers in the spacious Turner Hall were filled, the jovial throng manifesting a true carnival spirit. The quality and originality of the masks excelled, and according to the judgment of old-timers, nothing better was ever witnessed before. As if preconceived by all the participants, the usual hackneyed and monotonous costumes were conspicuous by their absence, a very fortunate occurence. Variety reigned supreme and many original masks were to be seen everywhere. The cooks carried huge posters, announcing in bold letters that their soups were free from ptomain poison and arsenic. [Allusion to the recent banquet in which Mundelein, and others became violently ill shortly after partaking of food. Trans.] Women with braids in rococo style and modern dresses, Harlequin and Columbines, Knights and ladies, slender pages and clowns of all kinds, and naturally, the doubles of Charley <pb facs="5418474_10_0645.jpg" n="2"/>Chaplin, were to be found all over the place. In conformity with this traditional Turner festival, all made merry in prolonged and lively dancing. A large orchestra was untiring in its efforts to provide Terpsichorean amusements.</p>
   <p>In addition to the regular orchestra, one of the adjacent halls, where dancers and partners were enjoying invigorating, cool wines tete a tete, boasted of a Hungarian band. All in all it was a successful affair, designed to "lick the blues," and as such it fulfilled its mission to a dot.</p>
   <p>[A list with the names of the members who made the carnival possible is given.Trans.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
