<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-09-11">Sept. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Central Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-09-11">Sept. 11, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE CENTRAL ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a preliminary to the fifty-sixth annual convention of the German Roman Catholic Central Association, a mass meeting at Orchestra Hall, took place yesterday. Despite adverse weather conditions, an audience of about 1,000 persons were present when the former Judge Michael Girten, president of the festivities, called the meeting to order, while a large choir composed of several hundred members of various church organizations of German Catholic communities of Chicago took their places on the stage. These excellently trained voices, supported by an orchestra equally as excellent, presented songs of unusual beauty and accomplishment.</p>
   <p>For stage decorations, the American and the papal colors were used. The papal coat-of-arms occupied the center of the stage. After the choir and the audience sang the "Star Spangled Banner", Judge Girten rose to deliver his short opening address.</p>
   <p>He said: "The annual meeting of people of German descent, whose reputation <pb facs="5418474_10_1320.jpg" n="2"/>as good Catholics and respectable citizens is well established, gather once every year for the purpose of deliberation. Since 1855, when this custom was established, the Central Association has been aware of the fact that real patriotism is not expressed solely by shouting "hurrah" and such exhibitions, but in the continuous sacrificial spirit, working for the good of the people and for the country. During the long years of its activity not a single instance can be cited in the program of the Central Organization when it succumbed to a tendency of attacking its fellow-citizens. But this association always did, and always will in the future, defend and fight for the principles upon which it was founded.....</p>
   <p>"Reviewing the activities of the Central Association, we can feel proud of its accomplishments; the founding of numerous parochial schools as well as the establishment of branch societies throughout the United States are the products of this organization.....</p>
   <p>"The honor of being host to the Central Association has been bestowed upon Chicago for the third time. Men from far and near have come to attend the <pb facs="5418474_10_1321.jpg" n="3"/>convention. I look upon this audience with great pride because it consists of those who have remained true to its high ideals, regardless of the change of the times and that which follows in its course. I herewith extend my hearty welcome to you...."</p>
   <p>Mr. J. B. Oelkers, of Newark, New Jersey, president of the Central Association welcomed the delegates in a short address, reminding them of the difficult task which they face if through their ambition and efforts the program is to be realized.</p>
   <p>The chairman then presented Mr. Nikolaus Gonner, of Dubuque, Iowa, as the first official speaker. Mr. Gonner, who is the editor of the Katholischer Westen, chose the subject: "What We Do Want." He said that Baron Wilhelm Emanuel von Ketteler, the former Archbishop of Mains was the originator of the program upon which the German Catholic Central Association is based. It deals primarily with social reform towards the realization of which all the efforts of the organization must be united. The economic, political, and social changes are the results of the trend of liberalism now sweeping the world, especially noticeable in the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1322.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Gonner's address: "What is the purpose of this meeting and what is the task before us? It is, no doubt, to familiarize ourselves with the program of our organization. And I do not hesitate to say that the efforts of realization by this society must be favorably received by every farseeing Catholic of this country....The program put into practical use is patriotic in all its phases.....</p>
   <p>"Neither can the very interesting political situation be disregarded. There are three important political parties in the United States: the Democratic, the Republican, and the Socialist. But the political parties which exclude Christianity from its program are not parties with which we would affiliate; they would be all too willing to work hand in hand with the Socialist Party. We will support no political party that disregards Christianity, the strong pillar upon which it rests. The doom of the Democratic as well as of the Republican Party is preferable to the ill fate of our nation.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, to unite our forces for the successful outcome of our program is essential to every German Catholic. It is a task well worth a lifelong <pb facs="5418474_10_1323.jpg" n="5"/>struggle. This program of the Central Association and its eventual realization, shall build the monument which will be the heritage of the future German generations of America."</p>
   <p>The brilliant orator, Dr. C. F. Bruehl, teacher at St. Francis, Wisconsin, was the second speaker. He, too, pointed out the importance of social reforms....The high points of his impressive address - interrupted quite frequently by outburst of applause - were as follows:</p>
   <p>"We offer our assistance to a movement intended for the furtherance of humanity's happiness without first going through the dismal experience - the dawn of an overthrow. The illuminating minds of Christianity are leading this movement. The problem of the leaders of the present century is to introduce new blood into the stream of economic life and to bring forth the warmth, laying dormant in the cold and unbending industry. The world is seeking the key for the solution of its difficult problems; a task terribly complicated. The world is also quite amiable and very willing to accept any assistance to ease its difficulties. The social policy of Christianity is <pb facs="5418474_10_1324.jpg" n="6"/>is not to teach or advocate class hatred; its aim is directed towards the improvement and furtherance of human happiness. Our people must be made to realize that Christianity is steadily trying to better the nation's fate, which will otherwise undoubtedly embrace the anti-social principles. America is probably the most fertile field upon which Socialism would thrive. The thing that can save us from that calamity is the widespread knowledge of the social principles of Christianity and its national policy based upon the happiness of the people. This organization is endeavoring to inspire society with the sense of conciliation and the spirit of peace; but to do this we must be certain that we, ourselves, are thorough devotees of this teaching. And thus we continue to pursue this great aim, namely, the attainment of social peace through justice. The Church is too enormous to indulge in class politics, moreover, we join the Church in expressing our profound wish for real progress and happiness for all...."</p>
   <p>The convention is being held in the large hall of the school building of St. Michael's community.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1325.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Federation, an oak tree with the inscription; - "Acquired rights, accomplished duties". It was resolved to have the next convention in Moline.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
