<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-24">Feb. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Reverend John's Jubilee</title><title level="a" type="sub">Spiritual Leaders of St. Paul's Parish for Thirty Years</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-24">Feb. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">REVEREND JOHN'S JUBILEE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Spiritual Leaders of St. Paul's Parish for Thirty Years</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past thirty years Reverend [Rudolph] John has followed his calling in a faithful manner, building a splendid new church and successfully solving all its problems. Reverend John is always present during baptisms and marriages, and he may always be counted on as a consoling friend when death pays a visit. No wonder that the congregation availed itself of this opportunity to express its appreciation for this good pastor.</p>
   <p>The Women's Aid Society prepared the food for the occasion, providing culinary masterpieces for about three hundred and fifty members and friends of the parish. A good orchestra, led by Joseph A. Schwickerath, provided music during the banquet, which was financed by the Men's Club. Speeches were in order. F. J. Haake, president of the club, spoke impressively and declared that the eminent position of the parish one of the most outstanding in the city, is <pb facs="5418474_10_1470.jpg" n="2"/>chiefly due to Reverend John's consistent efforts throughout these many years.</p>
   <p>Alfred A. Kanberg sang an air from "Martha" and was given great acclaim. Mr. A. P. Humburg gave a short biography of the celebrant.</p>
   <p>Reverend John was born in Washington, Missouri, and became assistant pastor to his father in St. Louis. Later, fate brought him to Du Quoin, Illinois; then to Sedalia, Missouri, and Richmond, Virginia, where he married Miss Emilie Wenzel. Finally he was called to the St. Paul parish in Chicago.</p>
   <p>An illustrated poem, the literary work of Louis G. Thoene, which not only immortalized Reverend John's life and efforts but also gave a graphic account of the parish development and history, was enthusiastically received.</p>
   <p>The next number on the program was reserved for the minister's address. The enthusiastic reception appeared unending. Reverend John's contemplated theme <pb facs="5418474_10_1471.jpg" n="3"/>was "How Much German," but he preferred to postpone this subject; he said that he would like to speak according to the dictates of his heart, and thus the subject revolved about faith, truth, love of God and fatherland, and affection for the German Church.</p>
   <p>"That these form my inspiration, that I am intensely religious", averred Reverend John, "is directly due to my German origin." He then spoke about the present reform movements which have manifested themselves throughout the land, and he said that their lack of success is attributable to the Anglo-American Church, which is not big enough for the task. The St. Paul community, however, proceeds with German thoroughness, as he pointed out.</p>
   <p>It is also true that our children are under the influence of their parents and therefore we face no child problems. He also mentioned the prohibition question, saying that all good Germans favor moderation. He stated that there has not been a single drunkard in the St. Paul parish within the last thirty years.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1472.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"A truly 'good' man is not one who abstains totally from drinking or smoking," said Reverend John, he must be fortified against temptation."</p>
   <p>Reverend Pister, assistant pastor of St. Paul, made the closing remarks, and so the joyous festivities came to a glorious end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
