<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-07-07">July 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Truly German Work</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-07-07">July 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TRULY GERMAN WORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hospitality and considerate attention for the welfare of German-American teachers which has made their attendance to the convention possible, through the sacrifices of Chicagoans, deserves commendable recognition. This embraces the fact that they realize the importance of the German teachers in America. But the support for their endeavors is only half the German work. Something really worthwhile will be achieved by supplementing the effective schooling by home work of the parents, for without their assistance, the endeavors of the teacher cannot bring a lasting result. But the language itself is not sufficient. Where else, can the youth, knowing their language gain enthusiasm for German culture, when his own parents are continually aping foreigners, banishing the spirit of that culture from the home, excluding German book and papers, and although supporting the German theatre with a few paltry dollars, yet cannot make their attendance at plays coincide with the plays importance.</p>
   <p>Why should they pose as Germans at banquets and on other festival occasions, <pb facs="5418474_10_0072.jpg" n="2"/>when ordinarily they disdain to "carry on" in their own home and fail to implant a monument to the durability of the German race and its cultural attainments. The sacrifices of the Chicagoans should not be depreciated, but the German problem has the right to call for something else than money.</p>
   <p>German youth should carry on real German work and make their homes temples of German culture. They should not only support German literature and art with dollars, but also with a sincere love which is far more fruitful in its results.</p>
   <p>Only then German aims will have been accomplished, and the success will not be swept away by the strongest waves of native antagonism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
