<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-30">May 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Teed and the Spiritualists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1580</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1580.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-05-30">May 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">DR. TEED AND THE SPIRITUALISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The First German Spiritualist Society, which had its meeting yesterday afternoon at 116 Fifth Avenue consulted about the sensations, which have been aroused about Dr. Teed. After P. Knauer had given a short lecture about the meaning of Decoration Day from the spiritualistic standpoint, several concert numbers were rendered, and then the following resolutions were discussed and accepted with a considerable majority:</p>
   <p>"In view of the recent persecutions of the so-called Koreshites and their leader Dr. Teed, the First German Spiritualists Society makes the following declaration: Every movement has the right to make propaganda for itself as long as it is not carried on in connection with illicit actions. No person and no class of people can be threatened and outlawed upon mere assertions without actual investigation.</p>
   <p>Regardless of their teachings, whether true or not, we find that these people have been treated by certain elements of the population in a manner which is in direct defiance of the 'equal rights of all citizens, irrespective of race and religion'. This persecution was originally instigated by fashionable and fanatical church members under false pretenses. The Germans have no reason to cooperate <pb facs="5418474_10_1581.jpg" n="2"/>with this element.</p>
   <p>In the name of justice, of fairness, of equality before the law, we protest most emphatically against such conduct. No class of citizens has the power to deny others such rights, which are granted to others in a most extensive measure. We protest against the condemnation of any person without an unbiased investigation. It is in the interests of all to join this protest, who are not inclined to fall in line with the whims of the dominating movements and cliques.</p>
   <p>These resolutions shall be turned over to the press."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
