<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-04-10">April 10, 1877</date><title level="a">German in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-04-10">April 10, 1877</date><title level="a">GERMAN IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Westliche Post received this letter from New York:</p>
   <p>The growing youth of German descent here in the East prefers to converse in poor English rather than to use good German. This was the reason why one of our leading German Societies resolved that in future in their reading rooms German should be spoken exclusively. The success is of course questionable....</p>
   <p>In connection with it, the Baltimore Wecker remarked:</p>
   <p>What was said for New York could be said also of many German Societies elsewhere, in some instances youth even scoffs at the German-speaking person... All German Societies should insist that German should be spoken exclusively while making use of the Society's rooms...If this kind of German spirit prevails in the East, we in Chicago cannot complain, or at least not to any great extent. The native-born children of German parents are not ashamed of their German descent; moreover they take pride in speaking both languages equally well and use each one in its proper place....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0160.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Here in the West where the growth of national life is still in process - unlike the East where it has grown and has hardened - the Germans are a much more important and influential part of the political and social life. Here they do not feel themselves as strangers in a strange country and among strange people....They are Americans speaking German, and English as well when conversing with their non-German fellow citizens, but do not consider the English language as a special cause for pride. It is a fact that in the large cities of the West - Chicago included - the number of the Germans not exactly belonging to the educated classes, but with self-confidence in their English who make use of it on any appropriate occasion, is ten times as large as that of the large cities in the East....</p>
   <p>This discussion of the Westliche Post and the Baltimore Wecker as mentioned in the beginning of this article, inspired the Chicago Volkszeitung to these remarks: "Considering the factors mentioned, there does not seem to be a rosy future in store for the Germans. But a new factor has developed lately giving rise to great hopes; this new factor is the German Socialists, who <pb facs="5418474_10_0161.jpg" n="3"/>are furthering the mental life and aspirations, who are endeavoring to make effective what is good in the German character. In this they differ vastly from the Teutomaniacs who, regardless of the merits or demerits of the Germans, are bound to introduce it here. Our motto is: The good shall stand, the bad shall fall. We do know, the future belongs to our youth and he in whose hands youth is entrusted now, is the actual molder of the State's future, which means that he will determihe the political, social and religious trend. Because of this, we will support free schools and prepare a reform of general pedagogy. We know furthermore, that through nothing else the German cause can be helped as much as through mental stimulation, meetings and debates. And without boasting we may say that nobody has done more in this direction in late years than the Socialist organization. May they go on, grow and thrive, then the things German, worthy of preservation, will not be in danger."</p>
   <p>This contains many empty phrases, for the furthering of "mental life" in America through the copy of boresome tape worm articles from the German Social Democratic newspapers has hardly been very striking. We are willing <pb facs="5418474_10_0162.jpg" n="4"/>to admit that the German Socialist's influence in America as a leaven might be of just as much importance as that of the 48-ers a quarter of a century ago....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
