<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-06-29">June 29, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[Political Matters]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0944</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0944.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-06-29">June 29, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[POLITICAL MATTERS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Times is seeing ghosts. It thinks that the United States Germans stand in danger of committing the same mistake as the know-nothings fifteen years ago. In New York, it says, they already have formed a National Association for political purposes, and here the formation of one is imminent. This is a dangerous thing to do. No political party on the basis of national differences can endure in the United States. It would immediately call forth the resistance of all the other nationalities and would be smashed by them, and so on.</p>
   <p>In the logic of the Times "There is only one flaw - and it is that the supposition on which it rests does not exist." The National Association that was founded in New York on occasion of the Peace Festival, and that the Germans in Chicago plan to found, is not an association with political aims, but an organization for the promotion of German education, art, and science, for the purification of the German language and morality, and for the founding and maintaining of benevolent and other public institutions for Germans. If it should be perverted to the promotion of political aims it would soon collapse, and justly so. The dream of a German party, that was dreamed by some, fifteen or twenty years ago, has long since evaporated, and no reasonable man thinks of dreaming it again. One might just as well found a separate German religion, as a German party. The common extraction, indeed, <pb facs="5418474_10_0945.jpg" n="2"/>produces a certain conformity of sentiments, customs, and habits, but not of political and religious convictions. Would it not otherwise have to be possible for Karl Heinzen and Pater Oertel, for the Reverend Schabehorn, and Gallus Hoch to agree on a common German religion?</p>
   <p>What the National Association wants not only stands in no contradiction with the duties that the German speaking citizens owe to their adopted fatherland, but it aims on the contrary at making them better citizens of the Republic. Because daily experience teaches that those who cannot quickly enough renounce their own nationality (either out of simian imitativeness of foreign ways, or out of lack of mental independence) usually become very poor citizens of the new country. The German Associations in America want to make America a true home of the Germans by preparing a congenial atmosphere for the German mind and heart. But to coordinate the political and religious opinions of the German-Americans they do not intend to do. For one simple reason among others - they know that they would make themselves ridiculous if they tried.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
