<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-25">May 25, 1871</date><title level="a">[The Postal System]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-25">May 25, 1871</date><title level="a">[THE POSTAL SYSTEM]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In no other country of the world do new machines, new technical procedures, new means of locomotion find quicker acceptance than in the United States, provided always that the idea is home-grown.</p>
   <p>...It is hardly threeyears since an Austrian post official spread the idea that many millions of letters which are sent into the world every year contain only short communications of slight importance that neither the sender nor the addressee really wants to keep secret. He proposed that the post should sell stamped cards of fitting size (five inches long, three or three and a half inches broad) on the from of which the address should find room, while on the back would be space for communications of moderate length. The Austrian Post Administration entered on the proposition, and the result surpassed the boldest expectations. The cards were sold for half of the common letter postage. Because one did not need anything but a pencil - neither stationery nor envelope, neither wafer nor sealing wax; - because one could send one in a few moments time from anywhere, be it even the post window on the street -they (the postal cards) came immediately into the most widespread use, and <pb facs="5418474_10_0306.jpg" n="2"/>where formerly one letter would have been sent there now three or four postals were written. The income of the post did not decrease, but increase. So obvious was it that inside of one year almost all the States of the European Continent introduced the cards. Their use grew to colossal proportions during the Franco-Prussian War, and there they became a real blessing... A collection of postals from the front (Feldpostkarten") brought together intelligently would perhaps constitute the most interesting and true-to-life history of the great war.</p>
   <p>Even England which is so reluctant to accept innovations from the Continent in this case has come around quickly enough and presently the postal cards have been introduced even in our neighbor Canada. Only in the United States nobody has tho't of making the proposition, neither the Postmaster General nor any member of Congress. And yet the cards would in no country of the world be more useful than here.....A special advantage that the postals have in common with telegrams is that through their use the longwinded time-consuming letter style would become simplified.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0307.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now that all this has become apparent to the rest of the world we can hope thar during the next session of Congress the American Post Administration, too, will come hobbling after. The price of the postals could very well be fixed at one cent a piece. No reduction of the income of the post needed to be feared.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
