<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-02-10">February 10th, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A New German Church. Pastor Merz and His Congregation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1633</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1633.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-02-10">February 10th, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A New German Church. Pastor Merz And His Congregation.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The number of German Churches of the Evangelical faith has been increased again,-by one, situated on Addison, between Clark Street and Sheffield Avenue, surrounded by woods it presents a quaint picture. It was founded after 2 1/2 yeats of missionary work by the aforesaid pastor, who built it with his own funds, but prior thereto the philantropic minister, Dr. Passavant of Pittsburg donated the ground. Yesterday the festive, ceremonial dedication was conducted by Rev. Merz in the German language, while Dr. Passavant preached the sermon in English. Thus far, parish members number only 25 but how generous they were, is attested by the fact, that the mortgage which still hovers over the little church, is of a very small proportion. During the evening, Dr. Roth of Vickers Park, held the pulpit; he spoke in English. As to the location of the church, in this sparsely settled environment, in a sylvan forlorn neighborhood, it makes a lonely, forsaken impression, yet it has been erected with a thought to the future, when this district of Lakeview will be interspersed with fair streets. After untiring effort, Rev. Merz succeeded in spreading the Evangelical gospel and secondly, to obtain the sympathetic esteem of the inhabitants. His Sunday School boasts of a sizeable number of students, boys and girls.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
