<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-05-31">May 31, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Legal Protection for Foreigners</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-05-31">May 31, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">LEGAL PROTECTION FOR FOREIGNERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A bill was introduced in the Senate recently by the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations. The purpose of this bill is to summon criminals, who committed crimes against foreigners in any one of the states, before a Federal Court, thereby declaring each violation of the treaty rights of foreigners, which constitute a crime according to the law of the respective state, likewise a crime against the United States. In such cases the legal proceedings shall take place at a Federal Court, but such proceedings as well as the penalty shall be in accordance with the respective state rules and regulations.</p>
   <p>Obviously, the bill is aimed to prevent in the future such occurrences as took place in New Orleans, where the murderers of the Italians were exonerated. The Senate's action is, undoubtedly, the dirct result of that unfortunate, and, for the United States, disgraceful event.</p>
   <p>The United States does not wish to be again forced to admit that it is unable to protect the life and property of strangers or foreigners, who live here, or are visiting here, and that it is also unable to prosecute the criminals in such <pb facs="5418474_10_0258.jpg" n="2"/>instances, even though it has signed treaties with other nations, granting their respective citizens such liberties as are necessary to carry on their trade and commerce, and while thus engaged, to be able to enjoy the same protection and priviledges as the citizens of this country.</p>
   <p>It is evident that a change of the present situation is urgently needed for the prestige of the United States in foreign countries. It is very doubtful, however whether such a change can be effected by the present bill, which is the product of Senator Morgan's mental activities. This bill is first of all rather faulty, because it speaks of protection of the "treaty rights" of foreigners only. Hence citizens of those countries which have no signed treaties with the United States, in as far as the protection of life and property is concerned, would apparantly be outlawed. The protection of the citizens of all civilized countries who may be guests in the United States is recognized by an unwritten law as an internationally sanctioned responsibility. If such were the case, than any country refusing to accept these responsibilities, would of its own volition withdraw from the ranks of civilized nations.</p>
   <p>The important question in this connection is whether or not a simple law could extend the jurisdiction of the United States over such cases, and whether or not <pb facs="5418474_10_0259.jpg" n="3"/>an amendment to the constitution would be required.</p>
   <p>For if the rights of the foreigners are beyond question, than the rights of the citizen are likewise indubitable. Under such a law a criminal, who is accused of having committed a crime against a foreigner, will raise the question why he is summoned before an United States Court, while another defendant, accused of a similar crime against a citizen, is brought before the criminal court of the state.</p>
   <p>Not quite so weighty appear the objections which others are raising. They point out that the bill speaks only of such crimes against foreigners which are likewise considered as such by the laws of the respective states where the crimes have been committed. Although murder, robbery, plundering, theft, etc., are classified as crimes in all states, yet there are a number of treaty violations, which are not recognized as criminal offences by the laws of individual states. This objection, however, seems untenable, because the chief objective of the bill is the protection of foreign citizens against violence.</p>
   <p>A debate in both houses of Congress may clarify the point in question. It is gratifying indeed that our legislature endeavors to extend justice to foreign <pb facs="5418474_10_0260.jpg" n="4"/>citizens, and also to enable the United States Government to meet its international responsibilities. May we hope that Congress does not adjourn until it has made a law which is unimpeachable and satisfactory in every respect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
