<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-25">June 25, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">German Free Masons</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0879</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0879.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-25">June 25, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN FREE MASONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The amusement committee of the six German Free Mason lodges of Chicago made a wise choice, when they selected the Northside park of the rifle club for their midsummer festival this season. This decision made it possible for a larger crowd to enjoy the very desirable privilege of participating in the successful and merry St. John's or midsummer festival of the German Free-Mason lodges.</p>
   <p>Because of improved transportation facilities, and many noticeable improvements at this shady park, it was to be expected that large crowds would find their way to this memorable festival yesterday. Since some of the best elements of the German Americans gathered together it was natural that the festival made the impression of a family feast. The refreshing cheerfulness, the gayety, and the pleasing cordiality, which prevailed among the visitors, made this occasion one of the most enjoyable festivals ever held at this park.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0880.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The men's choir "Orpheus", whose majority of membership belong to the Free-Masons, contributed in considerable measure to incite and stir the fire of cheerfulness and enthusiansm. They rendered a great many appropriate songs.</p>
   <p>For the small and the bigger children many amusing games and plays were arranged and about 400 useful prizes were distributed among them.</p>
   <p>Late during the afternoon, Mr. W. Vocke delivered the speech for the occasion, in which he made a comparison between the American Puritanism and German sociability; the latter so beneficially and refreshingly demonstrated at this festival.</p>
   <p>In connection with previous remarks it may be mentioned here that according to influential members of one of the Free-Mason lodges the erection of a large hall is planned by the German lodge members, and it is supposed that very few difficulties will stand in the way to proceed with this estimable endeavor.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0881.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It must be mentioned at the close that the amusement committee, consisting of three members of each of the six lodges, deserve a well earned compliment because the festival was a splendid success due to persistent efforts in planning and preparing for the same.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
