<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-07">Aug. 7, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The United German Societies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0794</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0794.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-07">Aug. 7, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED GERMAN SOCIETIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2 - At yesterday's meeting held at the Schiller building, the proclamation of the newly constituted society took place. That association will be henceforth known as the United German Societies of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The constitution which was drawn up and submitted to the meeting, by an especially appointed committee, was accepted after a short debate. Following is the text of the constitution:</p>
   <p>The name of the association will be henceforth the United German Societies of Chicago. Aim: A closer contact between the existing German societies. By uniting their forces they will be able to fight attacks upon the German instruction in public schools. Furthermore, this society's aim is to prevent further curtailment of singing, gymnastics, drawing and <pb facs="5418474_10_0795.jpg" n="2"/>kindergarten work. This association will go even further, because it insists on a more thorough study of these subjects in the public schools. It also aims to unite the Germans more closely and thus create a mutual interest in all the questions of public life.</p>
   <p>Those German societies which are in accord with this association's policy are requested to be represented by two delegates each. A meeting shall be held once a month unless some unforeseen occurrence should require immediate action. An annual report concerning the association's activity, as well as the revenue and expenditures, will be sent to every society connected with this organization.</p>
   <p>After the acceptance of the constitution the election of officers took place. Elected were:Jacob Ingenthron, chairman; Leopold Saltiel, second-chairman; E. J. Stockhoff, treasurer and Chas.Alvin, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
