<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-08">Dec. 8, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">For German Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-08">Dec. 8, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">FOR GERMAN DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The general assembly of the German Day organization takes place tomorrow night. German Day is the only public declaration of Chicago's German element. It is an institution in which all but a few German tribal organizations participate and is, for this reason, noticed by the entire press and by our non-German fellow citizens. It is, therefore, the duty of the German Day organization to make the celebration bring distinction to the German element.</p>
   <p>This, in the final analysis, depends upon the delegates and the superintendent. It is, therefore, incumbent upon the organizations to send delegates to the meetings of the German Day organization who, unselfishly and conscientiously, will give themselves to the service of the good cause. But good will alone is not enough. The delegates must, before all, be fitted for their task; <pb facs="5418474_10_1061.jpg" n="2"/>they must be familiar with parliamentary rules and be able to defend their views with clear, convincing words.</p>
   <p>In this sense the office of a delegate to the German Day organization is undoubtedly one of the most important offices which could be given by an organization. This should be kept in mind by each organization before they elect a delegate.</p>
   <p>The delegates, on the other hand, have it as their duty to frequent the meetings regularly, to defend their views openly and with decision, and to elect a chairman (superintendent) in whom all of Chicago's Germans may have confidence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
