<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of the Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1924-06-29">June 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">From Lutheran Parishes of Chicago and Vicinity</title><title level="a" type="sub">Pilgrim Church, Reverend H. C. Steinhoff, 1840 Cuyler Avenue</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1451</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1451.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of the Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1924-06-29">June 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">FROM LUTHERAN PARISHES OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Pilgrim Church, Reverend H. C. Steinhoff, 1840 Cuyler Avenue</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This relatively young sister congregation owns beautiful church property, a church, and a school. A few years ago, Teacher Rumsfeld started the school with nineteen children. The number has in the meantime risen to 104 who are instructed by Teacher A. A. Rumsfeld and two women teachers. The school enjoys a good reputation and has recently again been accredited by the city's school authorities. Eight of the pupils graduated this year; they are the first ones who may enroll in a public high school without any examination.</p>
   <p>St. Mattaeus Congregation, Pastor</p>
   <p>Theodor Siemon, 2116 West 21st Street</p>
   <p>The St. Mattaeus school was closed with the commencement exercises held on <pb facs="5418474_10_1452.jpg" n="2"/>Tuesday evening in the hall of the Union League Boys' Club on Leavitt and Nineteenth Streets. Thirty pupils graduated. Two plays were staged at the commencement exercises. "The Man without a Country" and "Calendar Days", an historical play. The large hall was well filled. Arthur Keil made the welcoming speech and Loretta Obereiner the farewell speech. George Nottke and Miss Klara Krause played a duet on the piano. The songs interspersed here and there in the program were accompanied by the teacher of the class. Professor A. Miller of the teachers' college at River Forest made the principal address which was received with great enthusiasm. Pastor Siemon delivered a brief address to the graduates and distributed the dipolmas.</p>
   <p>On Friday, July 4, the congregation will make an excursion into the open. It will celebrate in a pleasant manner the annual school festival. All coreligionists who can get away are cordially invited. At eight in the morning there will be a parade in which young and old should participate. Then a special elevated train will stand ready for the excursionists at the Hoyne Avenue <pb facs="5418474_10_1453.jpg" n="3"/>station. Tonight the students' quartet will present a concert in the church to which all are invited. The church is located at West 21st Street and South Hoyne Avenue.</p>
   <p>St. Paul's Congregation in Maywood, Pastors Reverend E. Zapf and Reverend P. F. Kluender</p>
   <p>The commencement exercises of the school took place on Thursday, June 19. Thirty-seven pupils received their diplomas. The welcoming address was delivered by Walter Bussert and the farewell address by Margaret Schuett, the principal speech being made by Reverend Kluender. On the Saturday following, June 21, the community celebrated the annual school festival. The band of the Daily News provided the music. The construction of the new school building is progressing well. They expect to have the new building ready for occupancy in September.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1454.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Gnaden Congregation, Reverend H. Boester, 2751 South Karlov Avenue</p>
   <p>Twenty-eight children graduated Friday night, June 20, and received their diplomas. The speakers were Arthur Jochens and Bernice Topel. The address to the graduates was made by Teacher C. W. Linsemann, rector of St. John's School in Forest Park.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
