<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-04">Aug. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[Mass Meeting at Auditorium]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0706</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0706.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-04">Aug. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[MASS MEETING AT AUDITORIUM]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The appeal of the board of directors of the local branch of the Deutsch-Amerikanischer Nationalbund has met with the approval of the Germans of this city, and the meeting to be held at the Auditorium tomorrow evening should prove to be a memorable one. However, those who attend will not only have to discuss the cause of the War and its present status, and take measures necessary to force the English-language press to be unbiased and just in its reports and statements concerning persons and events connected with the War, but they will also have to take initial steps to support those who have been wounded or who have suffered material losses. At this meeting the board of directors of the Deutsch-Amerikanischer Nationalbund will propose the names of members of a committee which is to take charge of this charity work and solicit funds. Each society participating in the meeting may select a representative, who shall then be eligible for appointment to the committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0707.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From the ranks of the German, as well as the Austro-Hungarian societies, we have received many suggestions that the German-speaking societies refrain from taking part in entertainments or festivities during the War. These suggestions appear to be in keeping with the seriousness of the present time, and it will be the duty of those present at this meeting to decide whether or not they wish to adopt this suggestion and recommend that other societies follow their course of action.</p>
   <p>The following speakers have been announced for the meeting: Reverend Alfred Meyer, of Saint John's Lutheran Church; former Judge Michael F. Girten; H. O. Lang, president of the Germania Maennerchor; Karl Zwanzig, editor, of Ottawa, Illinois; and Ferdinand Walther, chairman of the board of directors of the local branch of the Deutsch-Amerikanischer Nationalbund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
