<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-04-18">Apr. 18, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The Heart of the Germans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-04-18">Apr. 18, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">THE HEART OF THE GERMANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everywhere the Germans in this country have commemorated the anniversary of Lincoln's death, but with the Americans it has been the exception. This seems to be new evidence of the fact, that the German Americans are better friends and supporters of true Republican liberty than the others.</p>
   <p>Wherever something thoughtful and beautiful has been done on April 15, in memory of Lincoln, it was done by Germans. The decorations of flowers and wreaths, at Lincoln's vault and monument at Springfield, were presented by Turners of Chicago, St. Louis, New York, Pittsburg, San Francisco, Cincinnati, Connecticut, Wisconsin, Ohio, and other states.</p>
   <p>Even in Chicago, nearly all commemorations in honor of Lincoln were held by Germans, and the decorating of the monument was done by Germans, only. The native Americans appeared indifferent, and even the many negroes did not manifest the least sentiment of gratitude.</p>
   <p>What was true in the west, was also true of the east. There also chiefly Germans commemorated the immortal restorer of the Republic on the twenty fifth <pb facs="5418474_10_1213.jpg" n="2"/>anniversary of the martyr's death.</p>
   <p>The heart of the Germans beating most affectionately for Lincoln is, at the same time, the best American heart. If America would face grave danger, again, the experiences of 1861 to 1865 would repeat themselves, and out of the ranks of the Germans would come many of the loyal defenders of this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
