<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-08">Apr. 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">A Magnificent Religious Service</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1519</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1519.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-08">Apr. 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">A MAGNIFICENT RELIGIOUS SERVICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Classical secular music is being upheld by St. Paul's Church,of which Pastor Heldmann is the spiritual leader.</p>
   <p>In the service of religion the great art of music remains triumphant. This is just the way one feels inclined to describe the Easter festival held yesterday in Pastor George D. Heldmann's St. Paul Parish. Although the impressive ceremonies observed in this place of worship on Easter Sunday were not at all unusual, the musical program, however, sparkled with vocal and instrumental brilliancy.......</p>
   <p>Such charm and deep pathos was exhibited by the choir boys in the execution of their songs. These young voices have received excellent training as the result of strict discipline in the parochial schools. This choir is composed of fifty young boys, known as Pastor Heldmann's model choir, a predicate quite justified.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1520.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, the opinions may differ about the introduction of the cecilianic secular music in Catholic churches of this country, but one thing remains beyond dispute, namely, the fulfillment of its service in ecclesiastical affairs, because of its dignified form and because it is unpretentious, without pomp or sentimentality. This does not imply, however, that the gorgeous compositions of sacred music by the world's oldest masters are not duly recognized and appreciated by the faithful flock, as well as by the church itself.</p>
   <p>One of the outstanding compositions is the "Terra Tremuit" by Greith. The sound effect of this piece of music is both thrilling and striking...A masterpiece of equal importance is the "Mass" by Brosig. Especially, the "Kyrie," "Benedictus," and "Agnus Dei" are excerpts of rare classical beauty. This work enjoys the distinction of being of gracious style and serenity. The instrumental program of the Easter Sunday church ceremony was directed by the youthful choir leader and outstanding organist Mr. Otto A. Singenberger, who-considering his extreme <pb facs="5418474_10_1521.jpg" n="3"/>youth-may indeed be congratulated upon his exquisite accomplishments. The incomparable orchestra, which was composed of members of the famous Theodore Thomas musical organization, contributed greatly to the success of the beautiful, divine services. The resounding tunes of the grand pipe organ added to the almost overwhelming grandeur when rolling through the stillness of that sanctuary. Like waves upon the ocean they rolled and resounded in the souls of the devout who came to share in the spiritual beauty of the ceremony of the Resurrection. It was indeed an unusual divine service, which justifies here the citation of Beethoven's exclamation in regard to Klopstock: "He is great and a unique uplifter of the soul besides."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
