<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-17">Oct. 17, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Autumn Ball of the Club Heimat</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-17">Oct. 17, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">AUTUMN BALL OF THE CLUB HEIMAT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The social club Heimat held its annual autumn ball at the Germania Clubhouse last Saturday. The club spared no expense in its efforts to make the occasion a success.</p>
   <p>This club, with 114 active members, had an attendance at its party which might well arouse the envy of other clubs in German circles. The young people came by the hundreds, so that both halls were filled to the last seat. While dancing was in progress the crowding was unpleasantly noticeable.</p>
   <p>The program of the evening--so far as there was a program--was directed mainly toward pleasing the young people who made up the larger part of those present. There was dancing and music almost without a pause. In the great hall the Johnk orchestra took over and had plenty to do to satisfy the wishes of the dancers for more music. During intermissions pianist Harry Koenigsmann played popular songs, thus doing his bit toward keeping <pb facs="5418474_10_0478.jpg" n="2"/>the audience in a pleasant mood. His playing was often drowned out by the loud singing of the guests, which showed that everyone was in boisterously good humor and was having a good time.</p>
   <p>The ladies present were all decked out in party dresses. They conducted a beauty contest, but no prizes were awarded. The moving spirit of the entire festival and of the club as well was Mr. Walter Muhr, who acted as maitre de plaisir and supervised all diversions. This is the custom at all German parties. Mr. Muhr occupies the position of vice-president of the club. He has repeatedly alternated between this position and that of president. He is the only one of the present members who has belonged to the club from its foundation, and we owe it to his persevering efforts that the club has survived its periods of crisis and has been preserved to this day.</p>
   <p>Because of the active co-operation of the other members, the party was brought to a harmonious close, and the guests were held together to the <pb facs="5418474_10_0479.jpg" n="3"/>early hours of the morning.</p>
   <p>The preparations for the party lay in the hands of a committee composed of the following gentlemen: Julius Kruse, president; Walter Muhr, vice-president; Fritz Baner, secretary; Herbert Vollmeister, treasurer; Robert Fesenmeier, bummel president; Herbert Moldenhauer, steward; Otto Mansei, scientific adviser; also Herbert Medrow and Harry Miek, ex-presidents of the club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
