<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1870-10-10">Oct. 10, 1870</date>.
<title level="a">Report of Agent of German Society of Chicago, April 1, to October 1, 1870</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0952</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0952.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1870-10-10">Oct. 10, 1870</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF AGENT OF GERMAN SOCIETY OF CHICAGO, APRIL 1, TO OCTOBER 1, 1870</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Requests for employment</cell>
     <cell>1,273</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Employment secured for</cell>
     <cell>579</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Advice or information given to</cell>
     <cell>1,818</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Aid secured from County Agent or Relief and Aid Society for</cell>
     <cell>43</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured free or reduced fares for</cell>
     <cell>38</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Secured medical care for</cell>
     <cell>31</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Located lost baggage for</cell>
     <cell>30</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Located relatives for</cell>
     <cell>8</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Letters received</cell>
     <cell>244</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Letters written</cell>
     <cell>368</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Money recovered from swindlers amounted to $542.45; 146 persons <pb facs="5418474_10_0953.jpg" n="2"/>received $324 from the support fund of the Society.</p>
   <p>These figures describe as accurately as possible the activity of the Agent of the Society during the past six months.</p>
   <p>The number of those who sought employment is very large in proportion to the number of those for whom employment was secured. This condition is not unusual. It is not due to a lack of effort on the part of the Agent, but partly to the fact that there are certain recurrent periods when labor is plentiful but jobs are scarce, and partly to the fact that most employers do not apply to the German Society when they are in need of workers, while the unemployed all flock to our office; and finally, partly to the fact that applicants for work frequently are not suited to work that is available. In most instances your Agent was able to give advice or imformation that was sought; aid was always rendered, unless too great an expenditure of money was involved, as for instance, when an indigent immigrant family required a <pb facs="5418474_10_0954.jpg" n="3"/>home, furniture, clothing, food, etc., or when a family that had resided here for some time needed repeated and continuous help, or when free transportation to a far distant destination was asked. The means of the Society are much too limited to meet such demands.</p>
   <p>Free medical aid was rendered whenever it was applied for, or appeared to be necessary. We take pleasure in acknowledging that Dr. E. Best and Dr. R. Seiffert were always willing to serve the needy, gratis, and that their help was generous. However, it was more difficult to secure help, that is, admission to the County Hospital, for those persons who had no home. As everybody knows, the County Hospital is so limited with respect to space, that persons who should be admitted, often are refused. And, to make matters worse, the Board of Supervisors has ruled that nobody may be received for treatment unless he or she has been a resident of Cook County for at least six months. Although this rule is justified, if it is applied to needy sick <pb facs="5418474_10_0955.jpg" n="4"/>persons who are brought to this city from other parts of the state or country, it cannot be defended, and is everything but humane when applied to indigent immigrants or other persons who take sick in Chicago while they are enroute to some other place. A change of this illiberal policy appears to be just as necessary as an extension of the County Hospital. The Board of Supervisors has voted to add to the capacity of the institution by erecting another building and expects the addition to be ready for occupancy late this year. Several needy immigrants who had been rejected by County Hospital authorities gained admission to Alexian Brothers', Hospital through the mediation of Dr. Seiffert.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
