<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-05-08">May 8, 1877</date><title level="a">The German Language in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Philadelphia Democrat)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0157</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0157.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-05-08">May 8, 1877</date><title level="a">THE GERMAN LANGUAGE IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Philadelphia Democrat)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whenever the German immigration to America slows down, the ebb and flow of human affairs in the life of the German population of this country becomes noticeable. Then the question always arises, whether there is really a future for the German language, here, or whether it will be doomed to die out. For the consolation of those interested in the cultivation of the German language, here be it said, that during the last two centuries this question has been asked many times. Pastor Brobst, a man of great merit, whose death occurred recently and whose family immigrated to this country two hundred years ago, used to reply to this fear:</p>
   <p>"Did not my family stick faithfully to the German language through the last two hundred years? Is this not proof enough that this language is not a stranger in America, but a heritage like that of the first English settlers and fathers of our country? And there are thousands of families living in Pennsylvania who fully agree with me. How often I had to hear during the <pb facs="5418474_10_0158.jpg" n="2"/>last fifty years that the German language in America is just about on the wane. The fact is that it lived and still lives, and has become even more powerful, acknowledged, appreciated and advocated by educated and influential men now more than ever before."</p>
   <p>Pastor Brobst was aware of the fact that the existence of the German language is due to a large extent to the rapid growth of the German-American press, but the very life of the language is preserved by the unceasing stream of German immigration....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
