<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-07">Jan. 7, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Complacent Warriors</title><title level="a" type="sub">Installation of Officers at the Veterans Club of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0788</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0788.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-07">Jan. 7, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">COMPLACENT WARRIORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Installation of Officers at the Veterans Club Of Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The officers of the German Veterans Club of Chicago were inducted into office yesterday at the first meeting of the New Year, held at the North Side Turner Hall during the afternoon. Two former presidents, Joseph Forcher, and Joseph Schlenker, inducted the new leaders. During the course of the proceedings, Martin Gass, treasurer of the German Veterans Alliance of North America, made the encouraging announcement that the treasury of the Alliance has $16,000 available for death benefits. The relatives of deceased members receive $300. The per capita rate is $6 per year. He added that three German Veterans associations have been affiliated with the Alliance since the last general session, and that a substantial increase may be expected in the near future.</p>
   <p>After the business session, the meeting turned into a social affair <pb facs="5418474_10_0789.jpg" n="2"/>under the guidance of Mr. Tanzer, the new president. He suggested that a special chairman be elected for the occasion, and the well-known "Barbarossa," Fritz Lindemann, was selected on the strength of his often-proven capacity. Then followed dancing, lively and jovial, to say nothing of the homage paid to barley brew. There was no lack of humorous recitations; such exponents in the art as Albert Luettke, Franz Damske, Stein, and many more, took good care of that.</p>
   <p>Other clubs sent delegates, among them police officer Max Heidelmeier, a former German cavalry captain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
