<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-12-07">December 7, 1876</date><title level="a">"Spanish Bestiality"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-12-07">December 7, 1876</date><title level="a">"SPANISH BESTIALITY"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As little as the leopard can rid himself of his spots, just as little can the Spaniard master his inborn nature of a bloodthirsty beast. Aside from the shooting of the hostages by the Paris Commune, the history of the 19th Century has no greater horror than the butchering in Havana of eight boys who had broken the windows of a burial vault. The details of this atrocity which are now reported are likely to make the blood congeal in the veins of every feeling human being....</p>
   <p>Shudderingly the civilized world views a spectacle that reenacts the most terrible horrors of the Sixteenth century. And one asks ones self; are there no means with which to put an end to this slaughter in Cuba that dishonors humanity? Are there no bounds to that heartless neutrality, that coldly looked on while in the neighbors' houses crimes without number are committed? Does not humanness demand an armed intervention against the godless deeds of a people that have sunk to the level of a pack of wolves? "Blood is thicker than water", exclaimed the American Commodore Rodgers when English ships were shot to pieces by Chinese forts; he steamed forth against the forts and <pb facs="5418474_10_0298.jpg" n="2"/>shelled them into silence. All America and Europe applauded. Has not the time come when it is a duty of honor to the United States, similarly, to intervene in Cuba?</p>
   <p>This question has nothing in common with a demand for an annexation of Cuba. Such an annexation we have fought as pernicious to the United States and our opinion in this respect remains unchanged. But to drive the Spanish beasts of murder from Cuba is something else. May Cuba, delivered from them, then become a republic of the uninviting type of Mexico, or of the more attractive one of Chile,--that needs not concern the United States....No European power would raise the slightest objection, if the U.S. would revenge the outraged honor of humanity, and if one really should try to protest, the U.S. is strong enough to ignore it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
