<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-20">Oct. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">St. Peter's Evangelical Parish Celebrates Sixty-Fifth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1403</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1403.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-20">Oct. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">ST. PETER'S EVANGELICAL PARISH CELEBRATES SIXTY-FIFTH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The St. Peter's Evangelical Parish will celebrate its sixty-fifth anniversary today at Cortez Street and Oakley Boulevard. Religious services will be held in the morning and evening; Pastor J. Kircher giving a sermon in German, and Pastor G. A. Kienle a sermon in English. A combined chorus, consisting of six choirs of the community, will provide the sacred songs.</p>
   <p>The morning service begins at half past ten, the evening service at a quarter to eight; Pastor H. W. Dinkmeyer being the festival speaker during the latter period.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1404.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the jubilee week, a banquet has been scheduled, and a special program for Tuesday, under the auspices of the young members. The men will have their celebration on Wednesday, and the ladies on Thursday afternoon and evening.</p>
   <p>The Development of the Parish</p>
   <p>The parish was founded in 1864 by Pastor Joseph Hartmann, former pastor of St. Paul's parish. The co-founders were: Nikolaus and Wilhelm Schoeneck, August Gudehus,.... [Altogether, twelve names are listed. Translator].</p>
   <p>The first small church was built on Noble Street and Chicago Avenue. A larger church was built three years later on the same location. It</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1405.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>is in existence even today, being used by a Lithuanian congregation.</p>
   <p>The first ministers were the Reverend Johann Schmidt, Hans Albert, and Johann Bond, and under the latter's leadership, the parish developed rapidly. Finally, disagreement manifested itself and Pastor Bond's successor, the well-known Reverend Gotthilf Lambrecht took the helm. His splendid guidance brought such profound growth that at the time of his demise, after forty-eight years of continued activity, the congregation had attained a membership of three thousand families. As a result of his labors, eight additional Evangelical parishes were founded in the Northern and Northwestern part of the City. A branch Sunday school was established at North Central Park and Costello Avenue, the building representing an investment of twenty-five thousand dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1406.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The present spiritual leader, H. E. Lambrecht, continues the work in a successful manner..... One of the great events during the last eleven years was the acquisition of the Timotheus Mission district, on George Street and Lavergne Avenue, and its incorporation with the Peter's Church in 1928. Owing to increasing labors, it now became necessary to obtain assistants, resulting in the procurement of Reverend G. A. Kienle, well-known superintendent of the Evangelical Hospital.</p>
   <p>Others functioning in this extensive work are: John A. Michel, teacher, organist, and choir director of the main parish, as well as general parish worker; at one time principal of the abandoned parochial school. Miss Dorothea Flottmann, secretary.... and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1407.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The following capable consistorial members deserve particular mention: President Ernst W. Schumacher;.... H. O. Paschke, secretary;..... [altogether eighteen names. Translator].</p>
   <p>Within the last sixty-five years, the pastors officiated during the following ceremonies: twenty-six thousand Christenings, 9,350 confirmations, 11,375 marriages, and 14,750 burials.</p>
   <p>The beautiful large church on Cortez Street and Oakley Boulevard with the adjoining rectory and all modern improvements, is valued at a quarter million dollars; the Sunday school building on North Central Park Avenue and the chapel on George Street with their equipment,</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1408.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>represent an outlay exceeding sixty thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The three divisions of last year's Sunday school had 1,039 members, representing scholars, teachers, and officials. The Home department had three hundred, and the Cradle lists 422 members. The Ladies Club and Ruth Circle have 698 members. The Men's Club and Men's Aid Society comprise 235 members. A Scout troop and orchestra are being organized now. Opportunities to develop one's vocal gifts are provided by six choirs, who participate in the regular services and on special occasions, giving solo and ensemble selections.</p>
   <p>The St. Peter's parish is a member of the Evangelical Synod of North America, and supports the various institutions in a most liberal</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1409.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>manner, having expended $4,342.84 for benevolent purposes last year. This amount includes the salary for an active missionary in East India, Miss Anna Schichi, a daughter of this community.</p>
   <p>Every Sunday: Religious services in German, at 11:15 A.M., Sunday school: 9 A.M., Services in English, at 10 A.M. The Branch Sunday school at 9 A.M. In the Chapel: Sunday school at 9:45 A.M. and church service at 11:15.</p>
   <p>C. A. Kg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
