<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Westen</title>,
<date when="1914-07-05">July 5, 1914</date>,
<title level="a">Supplement of Illinois Staats Zeitung</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Discourse.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0073</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0073.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Westen</title>,
<date when="1914-07-05">July 5, 1914</date>,
<title level="a">Supplement of Illinois Staats Zeitung</title><title level="a" type="sub">A DISCOURSE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the arranged festival for the unveiling of the statue of Goethe, Professor Hugo Muensterberg of Harvard University, mentioned in his address how the German Americans are finally taking courage and are recognizing their social worth, achieving the aim and striving of the noble minded. So only are they to hold their leading place, rightfully theirs, by virtue of descent, and always in advance, of all other mixed nationalities of America. The longing period for the fatherland that used to exist is now past, yet it need not leave the heart bare of love for our birthplace, the pride for our German fatherland and its great and wonderful achievements. This would not be natural and would be unworthy of a German, man or woman, and would merit ample criticism.</p>
   <p>All that is good and excellent, speech, manners, inherent nobility should also be planted here, that it pass not away with him, but will remain a valuable possession for posterity in perpetuity. We, who came from Germany to America are, in a sense, not in a foreign country, since the nation of the United States is not a single homogeneous race and the land was not inherited or guaranteed to a single race of ancient origin. If the contrary would have been the case, it could have been expected that the immigrant subscribe to established conditions and seek no special liberties. It is evidently different in this country. It <pb facs="5418474_10_0074.jpg" n="2"/>was, and is yet, the right of the strong to decide which of the immigrated race should exercise the greatest influence here. This long belonged to the German Americans, because of numerical strength and other significant physical and mental attributes, but the weakening effects of homesickness retarded their activity and bereft them of courage.</p>
   <p>The German population must take strong roots here. America is now our country and the home of our children and we must learn and teach them to know and understand the history of the country, its famous men and women, who have contributed to the making of this land and it must be told in speech and writings of our native language. To create results for our German attainments we must feel at home here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
