<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-06">July 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Lutheran Parishes of Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-06">July 6, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">LUTHERAN PARISHES OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Parish of Peace in a convention assembled, extended its hospitality to the District of Northern Illinois, a branch of the General Synod of Missouri, Ohio, and other States. The convention was opened on June 21 with a prayer by Doctor Kretzmann, of the St. Louis Seminary. The teachers' chorus sang a psalm-motet, led by Hans Biedermann. The session ended on July 1, at 4 P.M., Chairman Brunn officiating during the closing ceremonies. More than six hundred pastors, teachers, delegates, professors, and guests, attended the convention which lasted for ten days. Pastor Heise von Area spoke about the Kingdom of Christ. Pastor A. Ullrich was elected secretary, and pastors R. Miessler and Brauer were chosen as assistants. Pastor Wangerin of Lombard functioned as chaplain. Several <pb facs="5418474_10_1447.jpg" n="2"/>reports were accepted, and thousands of dollars were granted for local and foreign missions. Missionary Meyer, who is on furlough at present, gave a very interesting and encouraging report about the missions in China. Professor Eckhardt of St. Louis, financial secretary of the General Synod of Missouri, Ohio, etc., spoke about the monetary status.</p>
   <p>St. Matthaeus Parish, Reverend Theo.</p>
   <p>Siemon, 2116 W. 21 Street</p>
   <p>The 148th birthday of our Nation was celebrated by the community. After a parade of about half an hour, the school children and the other excursionists boarded a special train of the elevated Railroad which brought them to the end of the Douglas Park Line, and there they continued by truck to Bergmann's Grove. Delightful weather prevailed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1448.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Attendance exceeded all expectations. At half past one, several patriotic airs were sung by all the school children, accompanied by Theis' band. The guests were then regaled-with diverse entertainment by the teachers and pupils. Everyone spent a most enjoyable day in God's glorious nature. The festival left nothing to be desired.</p>
   <p>Altenheim (Home for the Aged) At Arlington</p>
   <p>Heights</p>
   <p>The annual festival of the Altenheim will be given at Arlington Heights. . . .</p>
   <p>Festival of the Children's Home in Addison</p>
   <p>Regardless of the unfavorable weather, the festival at the Children's Home in Addison was well attended. An extra train brought many of the <pb facs="5418474_10_1449.jpg" n="4"/>guests, but most of them came in automobiles. Pastor Hoeckler, president of the Friends of Children Society opened the religious service, and Pastor Karl Schmidt delivered the sermon in German at half past two, while Pastor Kowert spoke in English later. Walter Wendt's Male chorus sang two suitable selections. The children of the Home also showed their vocal accomplishments. The institution cares for eighty children at present. Forty applicants could not be accepted for lack of space. The Society decided to build an addition as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>Bethlehem's Parish, Pastor Arthur L.</p>
   <p>Reinke, 1514 N. Wood Street</p>
   <p>The closing festivities of the school were held on July 25, and thirty-five children received their diplomas. Professor Albert Miller of the <pb facs="5418474_10_1450.jpg" n="5"/>Teachers' Seminary of River Forest gave the festival address. An interesting program was offered, and the attendance proved that the community appreciates and is grateful for the Christian education which is being offered to our youth.</p>
   <p>R. F. Nimmer</p>
   <p>Free Association of German American Lutherans, corner Garfield</p>
   <p>Avenue and Mohawk Street.</p>
   <p>German Sunday school with English classes, if desired. German religious services at 10 A.M., for all who still think and believe, or would like to believe, in German.</p>
   <p>E. M. Lehmann, pastor. Residence: 4411 Dover Street; phone: Edgewater 2409.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
