<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-13">Feb. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Lincoln Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">Lincoln's Birthday to be Observed as Founding Day by Club of Americans of German Descent</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-13">Feb. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">LINCOLN CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Lincoln's Birthday to be Observed as Founding Day by Club of Americans of German Descent</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was a good idea of the directors of the Chicago Lincoln Club to observe Lincoln's birthday as its founding day, since the organization chose the Great Emancipator's name for its own. More than two hundred members and their wives and guests took part in the festivities. The tables in the large hall were draped with American flags. Several veterans of the Civil War, wearing uniforms and displaying medals, occupied places of honor, as did the chairman and the speakers. The first part of the program consisted of a banquet at which the guests enjoyed good wine and food while an orchestra and a male chorus rendered appropriate and well-received musical selections. After the banquet two addresses were delivered, while President Ernst Kruetgen acted as chairman. Professor George L. Scherger of Armour Institute was the first speaker. His topic was "Lincoln, the Man and Statesman". He called Luther, <pb facs="5418474_10_1094.jpg" n="2"/>Goethe, and Bismarck the greatest Germans, Napoleon the greatest Frenchman, and Washington and Lincoln the greatest Americans. He said: "Lincoln was truly a typical American, whereas Washington bore the stamp of the English businessman. Lincoln sprang from the common people and was so poor that he was obliged to borrow money to purchase his first suit of good clothes before taking up his duties in the state legislature in Springfield and again, later, before entering upon his Presidential duties at Washington, yet he became the foremost American. He had but few books but he knew them well, especially the Bible and Euclid's Mathematics. Lincoln was a man who was used to facing facts squarely. He was nominated because the Republican party would have neither Stewart nor Chase, and after his election he made both these men members of his cabinet. He possessed a splendid sense of humor. The difference between Lincoln's greatness and that of Frederick the Great consisted therein, that, while both ruled in the interest of their people, Frederick the Great received his authority by inheritance, whereas Lincoln's authority emanated from the will of those over whom he ruled.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1095.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Lincoln's rule was typical of America's ideals, "Liberty, regulated by the law and equality of all before the law". In the world of today a battle is raging between democracy and a movement to destroy individualism. The world should act according to Lincoln's principle, "After the conclusion of war there are no enemies".</p>
   <p>After a quartette had rendered a selection the Reverend Rudolph A. John addressed the assembly....His topic was, "Abraham Lincoln and the Americans of German Descent". He said that Americans of German descent respect Lincoln so highly because they value his character and his keen mind, and that Lincoln also esteemed Americans of German descent very highly.</p>
   <p>"America has been good to German immigrants, but was also repaid by them," Reverend John exclaimed, "We of German origin point with great pride to the German-sounding names which appear on the casualty lists of the recent war.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1096.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Americans of German descent should place a wreath upon the monument of the great Emancipator, who was so dear to them--laurel for his fame, oak for his loyalty, and roses for his love."</p>
   <p>Upon conclusion of the addresses the guests enjoyed dancing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
