<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-05-08">May 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Centennial Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-05-08">May 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE CENTENNIAL CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Turners of Chicago honored the memory of Friedrich Ludwig Jahn with a celebration held at the North Side Turner Hall yesterday. Turners from every part of the city came with their families and, shared in the great success of the festival.....</p>
   <p>After the orchestra finished playing the festival overture, which opened the second half of the program, the stage curtains parted upon a beautiful living picture, arranged by Mr. Emil Rothe, Jr., the turn teacher of the La Salle Turn Society. It represented a gymnasium, with female athletes in action. A large portrait of Jahn was visible in the background, while aged Germans, scattered about on fur rugs in the foreground, represented the symbol of the nation. A festive prologue followed, in which Mr. Martin Drescher explained the athletic art and aims of the gymnastics.</p>
   <p>He commenced the prologue with this line: "A healthy body produces a <pb facs="5418474_10_0715.jpg" n="2"/>healthy mind."....The curtain fell upon that scene, while the highly spirited audience joined the Turners in singing "The Song of Songs." The festive address was delivered by Turner Jakob Willig,....he reminded somewhat sarcastically, that Jahn's idealism was not understood, therefore, not appreciated, but he said the determination of the Turners brought them final recognition.....The United Turn Societies went even further. They played a prominent part in the cultural promotion of this country, the credit for which goes exclusively to the German people. Neither did the United Turn Societies of North America neglect, regardless of their manifold pursuits, their interest in the progress of healthy social and political activities. Consequently, as long as the Turn Societies continue to devote their work and energy for the benefit of the people, their right to existence can not be disputed.</p>
   <p>The choir of the Turn Society, "Oak," joined the male choir of the "Chicago Turn Community" in presenting songs, which helped to make the evening an outstanding event.....The arrangement Committee was composed of Messrs.: Emil C. Rothe Jr., Leopold Grand, Fred A. Kruse, Jac. Schneider, Balthazar Rau, Chas. Cobelli, Jacob Willig, Otto Schmidt, Otto Kahle, August Weigund, <pb facs="5418474_10_0716.jpg" n="3"/>Alfred Wild, Arthur Schiffer, A. Schachenmann, and Walter Neumann.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
