<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title><date when="1891-08-28">August 28, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">May Be Two Turner Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0839</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0839.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title><date when="1891-08-28">August 28, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">MAY BE TWO TURNER ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the quarrels between a few individuals, members of turner societies in Chicago, commenced some years ago members were inclined to belittle the matter and laughed down those who predicted a split in the national organization. The Vord Amerikanische Turnerbund, since the Chicago Turngemeinde, the oldest and largest society in Chicago was expelled from the organization by the Executive Committee of the Chicago district the matter has assumed a more serious prospect and now the split has become an accomplished fact. The Turngemeinde is no longer the only society in Chicago outside of the National organization. At their last meeting two other societies adopted resolutions placing them outside of the organization. These are the Central on the West Side and the Germania on the South Side. The resolutions by which they with-drew from the Turnerbund refer to the quarrels which began four years ago over the anarchist question, and recite at some length the circumstances of the trial of the Turngemeinde before the District Board, at which a man presided who was himself under charges involving issues similar to those for which the accused society was to be tried. "We see in these actions," the resolutions say, "shameless and infamous as they are, the execution of a plan that has long become apparent, namely: to attract the lawless element and to supplant the genuine turner-like reasonably progressive efforts of the Turnerbund by brute force and to make way for reactionary chaos. We <pb facs="5418474_10_0840.jpg" n="2"/>recognize this with an undeniable feeling of shame at our blindness which some years ago led us to believe that the Bund would be the gainer by our concessions. But being unwilling to longer bear the responsibility for all these infamies, we hereby declare our withdrawal from the Bund as a proof of our esteem for the Chicago Turngemeinde as an expression of detestation of the conduct of our District Board, from consideration of self esteem and for the protection of our members who are true to their country and to the Bund, also as an expression of esteem for the North American Turnerbund and its lofty, ideal aims." The South Side Turngemeinde will have a special meeting to take action on a similar proposition September 2. The seceding societies will try to organize an independent District organization and endeavor to secure admission to the national organization as the recognized representatives of the Chicago District to the exclusion of the radical societies and those which fail to declare their position in the matter, "I would not be surprised if two national bodies of turners were formed," said Max Stern, one of the leaders of the conservative elements of Turners. "The quarrel really handed down from the fight of four years ago, was opened afresh by the Turngemeinde expelling Vahlteich, because of his intense anarchistic sentiments. Then the Turngemeinde was expelled by the District Board because it expelled Vahlteich. Appeals were taken and a great deal of technical business gone through with and now we of the Turngemeinde have appealed to the National Board. The chances are it will do nothing. The Central <pb facs="5418474_10_0841.jpg" n="3"/>Turnverein and the Germania Turnverein have withdrawn from the order because the Turngemeinde was expelled. Several other Turner Societies in the City, in the district outside the city and in this and other States outside the district will doubtless withdraw on this account. The fight between the anarchistic and conservative elements of the order has been in progress for some years. It is now coming to an issue. The Turngemeinde represents the conservative element of German Turners and the result of this fight over Vahlteich will doubtless be the formation of two national bodies of Turners. It is stated that turners at Freeport, Mendota, Ottawa and LaSalle will withdraw this week in sympathy with the Chicago Turngemeinde.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
