<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-11-26">Nov. 26, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of Evangelical Pastors of Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-11-26">Nov. 26, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF EVANGELICAL PASTORS OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An extraordinary meeting of pastors of the Evangelical churches of Chicago and vicinity will be held tomorrow afternoon and evening at the First English Evangelical Church, 3062 Palmer Square, where, Reverend L. W. Goebels is pastor.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the meeting was given in a message by Rufus Jones, and repeated by Reverend F. W. Schroeder, chairman of the Chicago Pastors Organization, and pastor of the Tabor Lutheran Church; and Reverend Joseph George, chairman of the Advancement Committee, and pastor of the Salem Evangelical Church. The message follows:</p>
   <p>"The world has been jolted from its slumber and made to realize clearly its financial chaos. Until now, no such awakening to or realization of moral and spiritual chaos has been shown. Neither has there been evidence of an urgent desire to discover what is missing in our lives, nor how to rebuild the foundations of our deteriorated spiritual lives. The method by which this awakening <pb facs="5418474_10_1396.jpg" n="2"/>is to be quickened and realized will have to be discussed and decided upon at this meeting."</p>
   <p>The speakers at this meeting are to be Professor John Biegeleisen from the Theological Seminary in Webster Grove, Missouri, and Professor Robert Stanger of the Eden College of Elmhurst, Illinois. Reverend L. W. Goebels, vice-president of the Evangelical synod, will sum up the discussions at this meeting, and will offer suggestions on the execution of proposals made. A number of other pastors will participate in the debate, and a resolution will be made to call a similar meeting of church officials for January 8, at Reverend Fruechte's Bethlehem Church, at Diversey Boulevard and Magnolia Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
