<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-05">Oct. 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Doctor Boess Given Reception by German Clubs of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0531</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0531.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-05">Oct. 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">DOCTOR BOESS GIVEN RECEPTION BY GERMAN CLUBS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's guests from abroad, Doctor Boess, mayor of Berlin and other members of the Study Commission, will leave Chicago this evening to visit Milwaukee, from where, after a short stay, the party will visit several cities on the Pacific coast.</p>
   <p>Prior to the departure, the German Day Committee had arranged an informal reception at the Hotel Atlantic for the Mayor and his party, and although time was short for the necessary preparations, about five hundred German-Americans, representatives of local German organizations, filled the Winter Garden of the Atlantic Hotel. German and American flags, as well as many club banners which ornamented the place, did much in giving a festive appearance to the occasion. The reception was arranged in accordance with Doctor Boess's wish, who desired to become familiarized with our Germanism, even in its remoter aspects.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0532.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Doctor Boess and his companions were greeted in the hall of the hotel by Dr. J. W. Kobalter, president of the German Day Committee, who escorted him to the Winter garden, where the Concordia Male Chorus sang "This is the Day of the Lord."</p>
   <p>Here Doctor Kobalter gave the welcoming address, greeting Doctor Boess and his associates in the name of Chicago's German clubs. He referred in terse words to the history of the German Day and the ambitions connected therewith. It is on this day that Chicago Germans, as well as their clubs and organizations, meet every year in overwhelming numbers so as to impress our American co-citizens by the realization of the importance of the Germans.</p>
   <p>Digressing, the speaker mentioned the demise of Doctor Streseman, German minister of foreign affairs, to whose family, as well as to Hindenburg, Germany's president, telegrams had been sent by the German Day Committee. In connection therewith, he also expressed the conviction that Chicago's <pb facs="5418474_10_0533.jpg" n="3"/>Germans will always show the profoundest interest in all untoward or happy events befalling their old homeland.</p>
   <p>In closing his address, the speaker requested Doctor Boess to submit the assurances of our sympathy for the fate of the Fatherland to President Hindenburg, and expressed the hope that the Mayor may visit Chicago again during the World Fair of 1933, adding also that the Berlin Club of Chicago had nominated Doctor Boess honorary member.</p>
   <p>The Reply of Doctor Boess</p>
   <p>Heartily thanking the assembly for their cordial reception, Doctor Boess assured his listeners that he would gladly take the proffered greetings to the president of Germany. Germany is thankful to America because the latter, one of the great powers, was the first to withdraw its army of occupation from German soil, and therefore Germany is fully convinced now and has confidence in America's peaceloving attitude.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0534.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>City treasurer Peterson spoke a few words in German, stressing the racial relationship of Germany and Sweden, and then followed more or less lengthy speeches by various club members, giving assurances of their faithfulness towards their former homeland, even in their capacity as American citizens.</p>
   <p>The various speeches were interspersed with songs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
