<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-09-05">Sep. 5, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">German Methodist Conference.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Added transcription of 5418474_10_1604, which had mistakenly been put in separate file.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-09-05">Sep. 5, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN METHODIST CONFERENCE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Methodist Episcopal Conference at the Maxwell Street Church lasted but a short time yesterday morning, transacted a small amount of business, and adjourned to meet again at 8:30 o'clock this morning.</p>
   <p>Two members, the Rev. Drs. Sepert and Keck, were passed by their presiding elders and continued on trial, and the Rev. Dr. Abels and Scholt were put on trial by a majority vote of the conference. The remainder of the session was taken up with the election of delegates to the General Conference at Omaha next May.</p>
   <p>The Rev. C. Hedler and the Rev. C. Iwert were elected as such delegates, and the Rev. Dr. Saulus and Lambert were made reserve delegates.</p>
   <p>The seesion was closed with short addresses by the Rev. Dr. Dreyer and the Rev. Dr. Hamilton of the New York Conference. Dr. Dreyer speaking on behalf of the deaconessess and Dr. Hamilton on behalf of superannuated ministers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1603.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The adjournment was taken to allow the various committees to prepare reports for today's session.</p>
   <p>At 8:30 o'clock yesterday morning the sixty odd ministers composing the German Methodist Episcopal conference were in their seats at the Maxwell Street Church for the third day of the session Bishop Newman presided as before and at the conclusion of the opening exercises he delivered a short lecture on the duties of ministers.</p>
   <p>The question "Where shall the next conference be held?" was taken up and Kenosha was chosen as the next meeting place.</p>
   <p>The Committee on Temperance submitted its report. When the English copy had been made to express the exact meaning of the German copy it was adopted. The report of the Orphan Asylum was adopted, with the understanding that the distribution of the collection for the cause be incorporated in the published report.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1604.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Bishop Newman then introduced the Rev. H. Jacoby, Treasurer of the Warrenton Orphan Asylum, to the conference, and he gave a short address in regard to the orphan cause closing the morning session. At 2 o'clock the conference was again at work. After the devotional exercises a number of statistical reports regarding the work of the various churches of the last year were read and approved. The Bishop made a short address, and after singing a hymn the ministers made way for the laymen, who had been in session in the Sunday school room below. The laity filed down the front aisle, and the Chairman, Mr. G. A. Seefeld, addressed the Bishop, telling of the work that had been done in their meeing. Bishop Newman made an interesting address on Methodism, closing by saying that Methodism was marching on to make a conquest of the earth, and hoping that the laymen would do all in their power to make pleasant the duties of the ministers who have been assigned to the various churches for the next year.</p>
   <p>The laymen formed about the altar, and while all sang "Nearer My God to Thee," the ministers passed by in line, shaking hands and saying a few words to each.</p>
   <p>The conference adjourned to meet again Monday morning at 8 O'clock, to listen to the reading of the appointments.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
