<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-01">Mar. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Attention Please!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Concerning the Appeal for a 1915 Bismarck Celebration Committee Members Decline</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-01">Mar. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ATTENTION PLEASE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Concerning the Appeal for a 1915 Bismarck Celebration Committee Members Decline</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[The editor of the Abendpost received the following communications]</p>
   <p>Chicago, Feb. 27, 1915.</p>
   <p>To the Committee for the Bismarck celebration of 1915. Horace L. Brand, 24 South Fifth Avenue.</p>
   <p>Paul F. Mueller, c/o Abendpost Co., 225 West Washington Street.</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>The Chicago Turngemeinde [Gymnastic Association] has adopted a resolution at <pb facs="5418474_10_1137.jpg" n="2"/>its Feb. 24 meeting, not to participate at a Bismarck celebration, and has instructed its officers not to take part officially at any such celebration.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Turngemeinde adheres to its traditional point of view that those who have taken the oath of American citizenship should refrain from celebrating in public any birthdays or anniversaries of foreign political leaders, regardless of their prominence.</p>
   <p>For this reason the Turngemeinde cannot participate in your preparations [for a celebration].</p>
   <p>I must ask you, therefore, to strike out my name, which by mistake appeared on the committee list in your appeal, and to take note of the Turngemeinde's attitude.</p>
   <p>Ernst G. Kusswurm</p>
   <p>President of the Chicago Turngemeinde.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1138.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To the Committee for the 1915 Bismarck celebration, c/o Paul F. Mueller, Abendpost, 223 West Washington Street</p>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>I must ask you to remove my name, which erroneously was put on the committee list in your appeal [for a Bismarck celebration], in order to keep the members of the Zentralverband Deutscher Militaer Vereine [Central Association of German War Veterans' Societies] straight in this matter. At the last meeting, when this affair was being discussed, most members agreed with me that during the present times such a demonstration is entirely uncalled for and that we should first wait and see how things would go with our dear fatherland; then, maybe a victory celebration, in connection with a centennial celebration for our revered Iron Chancellor, would be proper. There is no suggestion of a Bismarck festival being made in the old country and since, our relatives over there can do without such a demonstration during these difficult times, we here in our adopted country can do likewise. Eventually, when the time is <pb facs="5418474_10_1139.jpg" n="4"/>ripe, we should do everything to show America that our hearts are German, even though we are good American citizens.</p>
   <p>C. G. Geleng</p>
   <p>President of the Central Association</p>
   <p>To the editor of the Abendpost!</p>
   <p>The directorate of the Chicago branch of the German-American National Bund has been requested in writing, to participate officially at a meeting which allegedly was to make preparations for a great Bismarck celebration. The directors decided unanimously not to participate in this meeting in their official capacity as directors of the Chicago branch of the German-American National Bund, and have instructed Ferdinand Walther, president of the branch that, in case he would go to the meeting at all, not to do so in his capacity as <pb facs="5418474_10_1140.jpg" n="5"/>president.</p>
   <p>Yours truly,</p>
   <p>J. Danziger</p>
   <p>Director of Chicago Branch of German-American National Bund.</p>
   <p>As to the above, we want to say that a short time ago invitations were extended to the presidents of Chicago's German Vereine [clubs] to come to the North Side Turner Hall on Feb. 18, at 8 p.m., to discuss plans for a Bismarck centennial celebration. The meeting took place with about thirty persons present, of whom twenty-five proved to be Verein presidents. Among the latter was Mr. Paul F. Mueller, editor-in-chief of the Abendpost, who is also president of the Verein Deutsch Presse [German Press Club]. He argued against a noisy celebration because, he said, the times were grave and not favorable for celebrations; <pb facs="5418474_10_1141.jpg" n="6"/>because demonstrations of the German element were uncalled for at present and might do more harm than good, etc. A majority of those present were of a different opinion, and favored a Bismarck celebration for April 1. All details were to be discussed at a later meeting, to be called together by the directors of the German-American National Bund or by a committee.</p>
   <p>An appeal which has been published since, "To the German element and the German Vereine," to participate at a Bismarck celebration on April 1 bears the names of fifty persons, among them the editor-in-chief of the Abendpost, who did not have any more to do with the composition of the list than the president of the Turngemeinde or many others whose names were included in the list. Our editor was not asked for his approval of the appeal. Naturally he was somewhat amazed to find his name beneath it. His opinion on the question was well known to the gentlemen who had suggested this great Bismarck celebration.</p>
   <p>The times are so grave and the demands being made on the German element are so <pb facs="5418474_10_1142.jpg" n="7"/>tremendous at present--to say nothing of the future--and the political situation is so difficult that the Abendpost does not feel justified in urging the German element to stage a large demonstration or a large German festival and picnic, because the Bismarck Celebration naturally would either have to be one or the other. The Abendpost rather feels called upon to ask for caution and discretion and would advise the German element to "keep their powder dry", as the saying goes.</p>
   <p>If Chicago's Germans, and the German Vereine in particular, want to stage a large, popular Bismarck celebration, we say O.K. But a great and important affair like that should not be undertaken hastily. Naturally all Germans in the city would like to honor their Bismarck, but that does not mean that they favor a large and noisy demonstration.</p>
   <p>An Explanation</p>
   <p>As secretary of the committee for the proposed Bismarck celebration permit me <pb facs="5418474_10_1143.jpg" n="8"/>to direct a few words to your newspaper. First of all, I want to state here that, for the time being, nothing definite has been arranged regarding a Bismarck anniversary celebration; no demonstration is planned either. The program committee has worked out two tentative arrangements. The first one includes a celebration in the Medinah Temple with music, songs, two speeches (one in German and one in English), and moving pictures. The committee has in mind Dr. Julius Hofmann, pastor of the Zion Congregation in Baltimore, to be the German speaker, and a prominent American scientist or statesman to speak in English. The second arrangement would be a sort of banquet [mostly beer] at the North Side Turner Hall, admission to be one dollar per person. The speakers would be the same, but no moving pictures would be shown and the number of participants would be limited to about 800 people because of limited space.</p>
   <p>Today's session will decide on these two proposals and whether a Bismarck anniversary celebration is to he held at all.</p>
   <p>Now, I should like to reply to the letters sent to the Abendpost. First, to the <pb facs="5418474_10_1144.jpg" n="9"/>Chicago Turngemeinde. Not only I, but many readers of your esteemed newspaper regret the attitude of the Turngemeinde. It seems to me that there is nothing left of the spirit of the founders of this venerable institution. Or maybe the members have never grasped the meaning of Goethe's words:</p>
   <p>"Wohl dem, dez seiner Vaeter gern gederkt!</p>
   <p>Der froh von ihren Taten, ihrer Groesse</p>
   <p>Den Hoerer unterhaelt, und still sich freuend</p>
   <p>Ans Ende dieser schoenen Reihe sich geschlossen sicht!"</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: which means something like:</p>
   <p>"Oh happy, who his forebears does remember,</p>
   <p>Who gladly tells the tale of their great deeds</p>
   <p>And proudly takes his place in their succession!"]</p>
   <p>It was no "mistake" that Mr. Ernst G. Kusswurm's name appeared on the appeal.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1145.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>It was suggested by a committee member, and the name was subsequently put on the list. Mr. Kusswurm should know from experience how committees [and lists] are made up. Anyway, no harm was intended.</p>
   <p>Regarding the communication of Mr. C. G. Geleng, all I can say is that, at the first meeting, on Feb. 18, 1915, the War Veterans' Vereine evinced the greatest enthusiasm of all, and one member even announced that in case the meeting could not come to a decision on the Bismarck celebration, the war veterans would hold one by themselves.</p>
   <p>The name of Mr. Geleng, just like Mr. Kusswurm's, was suggested and sponsored by a member of the program committee.</p>
   <p>It is true, to be sure, that Mr. Paul F. Mueller, editor-in-chief of the Abendpost, came out against a demonstrative Bismarck celebration, but after it was decided that the German-American National Bund was to handle the affair, the program committee had reason to assume that Mr. Mueller had given up his <pb facs="5418474_10_1146.jpg" n="11"/>opposition, and especially when the chairman, Mr. Ferdinand Walther, appointed him to the program committee we could not help but believe that Mr. Mueller would be pleased if we put his name on the invitation committee.</p>
   <p>[signed] G. F. Hummel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
