<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-05-08">May 8, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Ninth Foundation Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">Foundation Festival of the Club Heimat in Germania Clubhouse Took a Brilliant Course</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0467</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0467.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-05-08">May 8, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">NINTH FOUNDATION FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Foundation Festival of the Club Heimat in Germania Clubhouse Took a Brilliant Course</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With a successful festival, which drew a large following from the circles of the young German element, the social Club Heimat celebrated its ninth anniversary in the Germania Clubhouse.</p>
   <p>During the nine years of its existence this Society has developed to the extent of becoming a factor in the preservation of German customs and the cultivation of sociability, a fact which was evident from the large attendance that came to this affair.</p>
   <p>The festival committee devoted the larger part of the evening to dancing, which was made enjoyable by the music of Henry Johnk's orchestra. The intermissions were filled by violin and piano selections.</p>
   <p>In a small room, a violinist, accompained on the piano, started a round of <pb facs="5418474_10_0468.jpg" n="2"/>German songs and asked the audience to join the club members in singing old home songs.</p>
   <p>The performance was opened by the orchestra with the overture to Weber's "Freischutz."</p>
   <p>With a soft and pleasant voice, Mrs. Charlotte Arnold sang "On the wings of song," by Mendelssohn, and "Violets," by Mozart. She was rewarded with great applause. "The Wanderer," by Schubert, sang by Mr. Otto Bauer, a member of the Club Heimat, gave him an opportunity to show his beautiful voice.</p>
   <p>The president of the club expressed his pleasure at seeing so many people present at the festival. His words were followed by Mr. Bauer, who sang "The two Grenadiers," by Schumann. Miss Anne Marie Gerts concluded the song offerings with "Moon night," by Schumann, and "Spring," by Hildach, which were given great applause.</p>
   <p>A musical piece, "Piazza del populo," was played by Henry Johnk's orchestra.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0469.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The singers were accompained on the piano by Mr. Robert Felsenmeyer.</p>
   <p>The preparation of the festival was in charge of a committee which, not including the president, was made up with the following persons: Justin Schneemann, vice president; Adolf Guenther, cashier; Fritz Bauer, secretary; George Laukemann; Gerhard Moltenbauer, Walter Muhr, and Robert Felsenmeyer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
