<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-08-10">Aug. 10, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Successful Festivals</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0493</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0493.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-08-10">Aug. 10, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S SUCCESSFUL FESTIVALS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Plattduetsche Grotgilde of the United States held its 42nd annual picnic yesterday. Favorable weather conditions brought large crowds of German-Americans to Riverview Park, where the festival was held. John Kractus' band and orchestra, supplemented by the drum and whistler's corps of the Central Organization of German Warriors, and of the Social Turn Society, kept the animated spirit of the public alive by making their regular rounds on the picnic grounds.....</p>
   <p>The football game played between Plattduetsche Grotgilde and the German Sport Club of Chicago ended with a score of 4 to O in favor of the German Sport Club. The game was followed with intense interest. Mr. William Sack, the Grand Master of the Plattduetsche Grotgilde, who was also president of the festival, presented the beaming victors with miniature silver footballs. The rope pulling contest in which a number <pb facs="5418474_10_0494.jpg" n="2"/>of men of the World War Veterans Organization, and members of the sport club, Hansa, participated, was also followed with great enthusiasm. The World War veterans emerged victorious, although their opponents put up a fine battle. A silver loving cup was the victors' reward. This was the veterans third trophy won in similar contests during the current year.....</p>
   <p>Fred Lindner, president of the German World War Veterans Organization, in a short address, expressed the gratitude of his men and of the organization. He praised the veterans' opponents for playing an excellent game. Preceding the picnic in Riverview Park, a short commemoration speech was held at the monument of Fritz Reuter, in Humboldt Park. The laying of a wreath at the foot of the statue by Mr. William Sack, Grand Master of the Plattduetsche Grotgilde, was followed by a short speech, delivered by Professor E. von Schroetter..... Represented at the festival were the following organizations: Branches <pb facs="5418474_10_0495.jpg" n="3"/>of the Plattduetsche Grotgilde of Milwaukee, Racine, Kenosha, Hammond, Michigan City, and Elgin. Strongly represented also was the Schwaben Aid Society, as well as various local military and Warriors Societies, and the Schiller Liedertafel. The last mentioned society, under the direction of its assistant conductor, Fritz Rathert, sang songs to the delight of the listeners.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's festival introduced the 34th convention of the Platt-duetsche Grotgilde of the United States which opened today. Nearly one hundred delegates are expected to attend the session.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
