<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-11-05">November 5, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">A New Church. Dedication of the Evangelical Lutheran Emanuel Church at Ashland Avenue.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1646</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1646.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-11-05">November 5, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW CHURCH. DEDICATION OF THE EVANGELICAL LUTHERAN EMANUEL CHURCH AT ASHLAND AVENUE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opening of the Emanuel church proceeded in conformity to the report we published in the Western, (a separate issue, Trans.) on Oct. 28th. The festive tolling of the new bells brought a pious multitude to the new church at Ashland Blvd., and about 2,000 persons waited impatiently for the opening of the portals. At 10 o'clock, the pastor, Mr. Hoelter appeared at the new rectory, accompanied by his assistants, Rev. Seidel and Pastor Wagner, the latter of the Zion parish. They were greeted by the assembly with the sacred song "The World Praises the Lord!" Thereupon Rev. Hoelter gave a short address, and in response to the joyous congregation's exclamations, replied, "The Lord gave us great blessings!" Then he proceeded with the dedicatory prayers and unlocked the doors. Every place in the church was filled, so that a part of the vast throng <pb facs="5418474_10_1647.jpg" n="2"/>stood in the street. From the interior emanated the strain, "God alone, deserves all praise!" Standing before the altar, Pastor Hoelter opened the service by singing the Psalm, "How lovely are your environs, God Zebaoth"; kneeling before the altar, he offered the first prayer, in unison with the congregation, then read from the Epistle of John, to which his listeners intoned the credence song,"Trinity".....Chapters from the scriptures and choir singing under the direction of Instructor, Rusch, helped to round out the program. To the strains of the melody, "We all believe in God," he mounted the pulpit. His topic consisted of resume of the church's progress. It is the third dedication in the parish since its founding in 1854, with 11 members. The St. Paulus community at that time held its services in a private home, out on the prairie, the S. W. part of the city, now known as Blue Island Avenue church, school and rectory, all were represented in a single dwelling, and this modest beginning represented greater difficulties than the subsequent creation; the present, magnificent structure.........</p>
   <p>It is now the nucleus of a thriving district,....with 8 branch churches.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
