<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-04-29">Apr. 29, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Lively Pace at the Preliminary Work for the German Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">Advance Sale of Admission Cards Is Main Point</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-04-29">Apr. 29, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">LIVELY PACE AT THE PRELIMINARY WORK FOR THE GERMAN DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Advance Sale of Admission Cards Is Main Point</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An important step forward in the preparations for this year's German Day celebration was made at the meeting of delegates held yesterday evening at the banquet hall of the Atlantic Hotel, under the presidency of Bernard de Vry. During the meeting several propositions of the president were read. The offer of 3,000 propaganda buttons by the German group of the Exposition was accepted with thanks, and it was agreed to sell them at the price of one dollar apiece. The money thus collected, together with the proceeds derived from the sale of admission cards, will be used to cover the expenses of this year's festival.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0471.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the details of the festival came under discussion, it was agreed that there should be a large parade followed by a short act in the Exposition Building, where, under its present seat arrangement, the lions share will undoubtedly fall to the singers, a reason why the speeches should be short. In the matter of speeches, president De Vry said that he will look around for suitable personalities.</p>
   <p>A Good Beginning</p>
   <p>The substitute financial secretary, Hermann Loesicke, reported that over one thousand dollars has been collected by twenty societies from the advance sale of admission cards. He stressed the necessity of selling at least twenty per cent of the admission cards before May 15, the deadline, <pb facs="5418474_10_0472.jpg" n="3"/>so that the money thus collected may be used to cover parts of the expenses of the association.</p>
   <p>In connection with this, an urgent request is made for all societies to order the admission cards from Mr. Loesicke before May 12, including cash with order since all sales are to be paid in advance.</p>
   <p>The different committees are working hard on this matter and hope to be able to make a favorable report at the next meeting of delegates.</p>
   <p>Missing Fire</p>
   <p>From delegate Jacob L. Leimann, who signed himself as "Leader of the <pb facs="5418474_10_0473.jpg" n="4"/>Central Union of Russian-German Unions and member of the Germanic Union," a written proposition was received that only "Germans or Americans of Aryan-German descent be allowed to participate in the meetings, because otherwise the German Day Association will lose its importance as an organization." The motion was rejected by a large majority. A long debate followed the question whether it was necessary that the Austrians should celebrate on another day, August 27. Vice-president Waldherr, and Dr. Kobalter, president of the Austrian group, gave the necessary explanations, stating that this is done at the special request of the World's Fair management, which claims that all countries having a consular representative in the city may reserve one day for this purpose. Delegates of the German Day Committee, representing Austrian societies, pointed out that they are working diligently for the success of both organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0474.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Welcome Present</p>
   <p>The Women's Section of the German group made a contribution of $100 to help defray the expenses of the German Day, a gift which was gratefully accepted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
