<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-01">Jan. 1, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">New Year's Eve Festivities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1192</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1192.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-01">Jan. 1, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">NEW YEAR'S EVE FESTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Twelve o'clock. A small droning church bell proclaims the midnight hour; its knell stops the jovial Thespian pleasures and silences the orchestra. Thus we live, thus we live; we all live that way.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Gymnastic Association was celebrating at the North Side Hall. Sudden darkness, music come to a dead stop, dance steps come to a halt, as an unearthly pandemonium reverberated in the hall. From every nook and corner, galleries, stage, and the smaller meeting halls one heard the terrific whistling, honking, megaphone calls, concussions, the sibilant exclamations of an enthusiastic assembly, and other unclassified noises. In this manner, the Gymnasts greeted the New Year and the new century.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1193.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last night's Sylvester ball was a genuinely friendly affair, wherein the tide of joy mounted to transcendental heights. A large crowd was present and the arrangements perfect. The committee which functioned so commendably and made the affair a success, consisted of eleven Turner members.</p>
   <p>The Turner Pioneers made up the reception committee. The singing division of the Gymnastic association appeared in full numbers and regaled the gathering with several selections.</p>
   <p>At The Frohsinn</p>
   <p>Contentment reigned last night; true happiness in conformity to the Sylvester custom among German singers, a delightful, exceedingly merry crowd, the like of which has not been witnessed for many a day. The singing club Frohsinn [Contentment], which celebrated at the South Side <pb facs="5418474_10_1194.jpg" n="3"/>Turnhall, attracted many celebrants, and regardless of the multitude, it was a very sociable affair. The program was arranged by the members Charles Hartung, Charles Luedecke, and Adolph Hook. The gentlemen offered excellent selections; they provided humor, took good care of the occasion, and complied with the social character of the event.</p>
   <p>The main attraction, undoubtedly, was the allegorical group "End of the 19th, beginning of the 20th century." At the midnight hour thousands of small cards, bearing good wishes from the Frohsinn, were scattered over the crowd.</p>
   <p>At The Germania</p>
   <p>Adhering to custom, the members of the Germania Male Chorus celebrated the event at their club house. A splendid ball and banquet were on the <pb facs="5418474_10_1195.jpg" n="4"/>program to commemorate the approach of the new century. The principal speaker of the evening was Joseph Brucker "The old succumbs; times change and new life sprouts among the ruins. A few more fleeting moments ere the iron-mouthed chimes and steam whistles proclaim the new century, the approaching period of another historical era. What may it bring, this new-born child's destiny,which reminds us of Schiller.</p>
   <p>"'With festive melodies of hapiness,</p>
   <p>It greets the beloved child,</p>
   <p>In life's first venture,</p>
   <p>Repose and sleep;</p>
   <p>Obscure and joyful fate</p>
   <p>Still rests in the lap of time.'</p>
   <p>"Schiller, at the beginning of the 19th century, wrote to a friend: 'Precious Friend: Where are the portals leading to peace,and the haven of security? The past century was enshrowded in storm, the new commences with murder.'"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1196.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The speaker then continued, expressing his own views. "After a hundred years," he said, "France's sword lost its power and thereby Germany acquired might and recognition. This rebirth of a nation is one of the outstanding deeds of the century which will imprint its mark also in the coming hundred years.</p>
   <p>"' How inspiring to behold thee, with thy palm branch,</p>
   <p>On the brink of the century!'</p>
   <p>"When Schiller spoke these words he thought of the land which broke the despicable, enslaving shackles of despotism. We Germans, at least the older men, were present during Germany's rebirth and our future generations will envy us. We shall never witness a repetition of such monumental splendor, our examplary poets at the turn of the century, the liberation from the Napoleonic yoke, its gigantic struggle against the hereditary enemy in 1870, and our re-creation through Bismarck, the <pb facs="5418474_10_1197.jpg" n="6"/>great Chancelor. Verily, in retrospection we Germans may look with pride and satisfaction upon the last century. Justified confidence, fortified with the knowledge of the present, strong will power, as well as unflinching diligence, should enable us to traverse the threshold of the coming hundred years.</p>
   <p>"Simultaneously, as Germany forged its destiny in Europe, a titanic empire grew on this side of the Atlantic ocean. Emerging from a small beginning, it developed into the North American Union, with which we are affiliated as citizens. Only a hundred years ago, the territory west of the Mississippi did not belong to the Union; nor Flordia and other lands on the Gulf of Mexico. The most reckless prophets never would have ventured to predict that the Union banner might flutter on the Pacific coast within such a comparatively brief span of time.</p>
   <p>"I shall not recite history. But this is definite. What the 19th century <pb facs="5418474_10_1198.jpg" n="7"/>shaped so well with blood and iron, the German nation and the American Union will strengthen for the protection of right, liberty, art, sience, progress, and culture.</p>
   <p>"Fortune helps the strong," an old, proven proverb. But where is a race stronger than the American? What nation has a more intriusic and intensive spirit?</p>
   <p>"Here, at the threshold of the 20th century, I predict that our country will be the leader among the people of the world. America is destined to become the great connecting link between the old world in Europe and the still older continent of Asia.</p>
   <p>"It is but natural that we are exulant in being a part of this gigantic nation and we may look towards the future with serene confidence. We <pb facs="5418474_10_1199.jpg" n="8"/>did our share in building and embellishing it in the German manner, that our offspring may bless the day when we landed on these hospitable shores.</p>
   <p>"But finally, let us quote the poet: [Ten verses, 80 lines follow. Transl.]</p>
   <p>Whatever the future may decree, nothing can make us submissive.</p>
   <p>"The call, the year begins anew</p>
   <p>Drones from resonant bells;</p>
   <p>But the hour finds us</p>
   <p>Unified, joyful, and faithful."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
