<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-02">Nov. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Vote as an American Only</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0200</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0200.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-02">Nov. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">VOTE AS AN AMERICAN ONLY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From an editorial which appeared under the above title in the Milwaukee Herald, a strictly Republican publication, we quote the following:</p>
   <p>"If any politician or association of politicians (regardless of what political party or what political attitude) should ask you to join an organization, a club, or a union based on racial affiliations, for no reason other than that you are of German or some other descent, then say: 'No!'</p>
   <p>"We advise everybody, and beg each one of our readers, to act in each case as an American citizen only, and under no circumstances as a German-American or any other hyphenated American, in politics or in social life. Let us adjourn politics altogether for the time being. That means we want to remain independent of affiliations with political parties. Just the same we can <pb facs="5418474_10_0201.jpg" n="2"/>pay attention to what the politicians have to say. But think it over first, then act and vote!</p>
   <p>"But--perhaps you would like to know for whom you should vote.</p>
   <p>"Our answer is very simple: Vote for any candidate running for office (particularly for the office of Representative or Senator), who stands behind the President and his policy for world peace and world democracy openly and honestly. Vote against all other candidates, even those seeking state and county offices, if they show any tendency to imagine themselves smarter than the President, and think they know more than he about international affairs. In the majority of cases you can be pretty certain that most of them know nothing about the situation. It is not even necessary to enter into any argument with them; just do not vote for them. The way world politics are being shaped right now, a citizen who uses his common sense should not only take sides with the President but also vote in a way to give him the best support.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0202.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"That does not mean that you always have to vote for a Democrat, although we are of the opinion that the President, at present, should have a majority of his own party in both houses of Congress. What we wish to make clear is: Vote in any case for a candidate whom you know to be sympathetic with the President's policy regarding peace, democracy, and reconstruction after the war. If you have to choose between two men of this sort, vote for the one who belongs to the President's party."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
