<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-02-10">February 10, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A New House of Worship. Dedication of the Evangelical Lutheran Mission.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1631</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1631.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-02-10">February 10, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW HOUSE OF WORSHIP. DEDICATION OF THE EVANGELICAL LUTHERAN MISSION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new church has been built on Addison street between North Clark street and Sheffield avenue. Only a few residences are in the neighborhood which at first glance gives the impression that the location is not a fortunate one. The church has been built for the future. Where the frigid North wind now howls through the leafless trees, a populated district will appear. Pastor Merz is the founder of this parish district and its chapel. About two and one-half years ago he started a mission in that part of the city by holding services in a schoolhouse. To this he added a Sunday school and so obtained a fair number of supporters. He progressed slowly but consistently and eventually found his quarters too small. He then rented a store in the vicinity. Finally conditions became more auspicious and the chapel was planned. Funds were low but it so happened the Reverend Passavant owned eight acres of land contiguous to Addison street and he contributed a part of it for this purpose. The building dimensions are 32 x 63 ft. The front, 32 x 43 ft. constitutes the church proper. A two story, practically arranged addition in the rear serves as the pastor's home. On the other vacant part, Dr. Passavant intends to build a seminary and a deaconess' hospital. The dedication was held yesterday - a splendid festival with a flower covered rostrum and floral wreaths ornamenting the interior, artistically arranged by loving, intelligent members. The liberal donations by the few members, a <pb facs="5418474_10_1632.jpg" n="2"/>veritable sacrifice, succeeded in the collecting of $2,500, which almost paid the mortgage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
