<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-12-31">Dec. 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">We German-Americans</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-12-31">Dec. 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">WE GERMAN-AMERICANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are of German blood and heritage, but we are also citizens of the United States. We call ourselves German-Americans.</p>
   <p>And every day we become more proud of this name. To us, the designation German-American seems proper and fitting. Nothing else would do. But other people do not agree with us. They deny us that right. They scoff at the implication of Germanism contained in the expression and call us "hyphenated Americans," which is to say, Americans with a mental reservation, or "grade B" Americans. Others pretend not to know us when we call ourselves German-Americans. They say there ain't no such animal. We are prone to regard people in the first category as our enemies, and the others--? Well, the German Kaiser made this remark some years ago; "I don't know any German-Americans. I only know Americans". And Dr. Bernhard Dernburg, former German minister [cabinet member], <pb facs="5418474_10_0051.jpg" n="2"/>and at present Representative of the German Red Cross--one may even say, of the German people--when stopping in Chicago recently, remarked during a conversation in which the expression "German-American" was mentioned, "I don't know any German-Americans; to me they are Americans. At best they could call themselves Americans either with a German inclination or of German extraction".</p>
   <p>We don't mention this as a criticism of Mr. Dernburg or anybody else. We just want to elucidate our own position. Neither friend nor foe cares to recognize us as "German-Americans," but here we are just the same; and not merely since today or yesterday, but for generations. And we know what we are and remain what we always have been. It is only that we have become stronger and lately have developed more self-confidence. We hope to acquire still more confidence and influence. And the name "German-American" will stick, too, if we wish to remain what we are. Because if we should drop the "German" which stands in front of the "American," we would also lose our characteristic nature, just as if we were to abandon our German native tongue. And that is what we would have to do, if we just called ourselves Americans. Maybe we should, considering <pb facs="5418474_10_0052.jpg" n="3"/>that even representatives of the German people speaking at a "German-American" meeting, feel called upon to speak nothing but English, because they are guests of this nation. If hospitality granted to a guest obliges him to speak the language of the land, how much more so does the citizenship to which we were admitted?</p>
   <p>Even this is not meant to be a reproach or a complaint. It merely explains the situation in which we find ourselves, and points to the difficulties which we have to overcome in order to preserve our ways and habits, and at the same be regarded as good citizens, who intend to have greater influence in politics and the social development of our country than heretofore. This is what we want. It is our main objective. And in spite of the precariousness of our position we should be able to succeed by employing German courage and perseverance, efficiency and honesty, diligence and sincerity in words and actions, magnanimity and thoroughness in tackling all problems, and, above all, unanimous determination!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0053.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>These are the German character traits which people admire today, even though they don't admit it. These are the properties which already have secured a moral victory for our homeland over the enemy and which will be followed by a victory of arms if there is any justice in the world, and if mankind is to make progress instead of slipping back. Throughout our lives, in our speech and in our actions, we must express these [German] characteristics if we want to be successful in our efforts. That is why we want to retain our "Germanism" along with our Americanism and earn the recognition and respect we are entitled to. It will not always be easy, but we must do it if we want to reach our goal. We believe on a final victory of the German arms, which will usher in a German era. But let us not delude ourselves by believing that we could participate in the harvest without having done our share. We have to do our part to gain respect and influence, otherwise, if the German Era should arrive, we would still be regarded as "hyphenated Americans" or, at best, as "Americans of German descent."</p>
   <p>What to do? Our duty will be to prove ourselves model citizens; to fulfill <pb facs="5418474_10_0054.jpg" n="5"/>diligently all duties and obligations of citizenship, and above all, to exercise our franchise at all times to our best knowledge and ability in order to take part in politics and maintain interest in all the great problems that confront our country. By demonstrating that we make the best citizens, we can command recognition and influence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
