<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-08-27">Aug. 27, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Organization for D. A. Convention Oct. 24-26</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-08-27">Aug. 27, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZATION FOR D. A. CONVENTION OCT. 24-26</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Committee of three to whom was entrusted the management for the preparation of the convention for the founding of a German-American National Union, will, according to a resolution accepted at yesterday's meeting in the Bismarck Hotel, call another meeting, the date of which will be published in the newspapers, for the purpose of submitting further propositions, if they become necessary.</p>
   <p>The festival banquet, which will close the meeting is to be held on Oct. 25. The respective committee, has to work out the lowest price for each plate, so that as many people as possible can attend the banquet. The number of guests will decide where the banquet is to be held. Otherwise the Bismarck Hotel was selected as headquarters.</p>
   <p>The hotel management placed itself at the committee's disposal, free of charge. It is of great importance that the committee resolved, to extend the meeting, <pb facs="5418474_10_1310.jpg" n="2"/>till all business is finished. The official roundup of the delegates from other states, would also have to take place Monday, Oct. 26th.</p>
   <p>After a lengthy debate, the meeting, at which about seventy delegates of different societies participated, resolved that President Rixman should appoint the members of each committee, City treasurer Edward J. Kaindl is president of the finance committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
