<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost, (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title><date when="1926-04-11">Apr. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation</title><title level="a" type="sub">To all German-Speaking Inhabitants of Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1082</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1082.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost, (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title><date when="1926-04-11">Apr. 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">To all German-Speaking Inhabitants of Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In September of last year, the Germans of Chicago once again appeared before the public united and in closed ranks--they celebrated German Day in the Stadium, gaining recognition and respect among all other nationalities who make their home in the metropolis of the West.</p>
   <p>Turners and singers, speakers in the German and English languages called forth joy and enthusiasm from the 35,000 visitors of the Stadium for German customs, German habits, and German efficiency in the new homeland. Its aftereffect is still felt among all those who stem from Germans. Therefore, German Day--June 13-- will be celebrated again this year in the Stadium; it will be greater and more impressive, and will inspire still more enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>Thus we call upon all, no matter whether their cradle stood on German soil or whether they were born here, whether they came here from the Rhine or from the <pb facs="5418474_10_1083.jpg" n="2"/>Danube, from the Volga or from the Adriatic, whether Austria, Hungary, Switzerland or Russia had been their old home; we call upon all who are of the same kinship to co-operate and to be on the spot when "The Star-Spangled Banner" and the German song are heard.</p>
   <p>Every organization should report for duty, should take part in the parade, should send its flag to the front and thus demonstrate that it is composed of Americans of German descent, that it has contributed to making the new homeland into what it is today. Time is short. Send your representatives to the meeting of delegates which takes place in Gill's Hall, 169 North La Salle Street, the first and second Friday of each month. Get admission tickets, sell them, and do your share in preparing for a German Day which we shall be proud to talk of. The German master athletes--the best turners from Germany's provinces--are coming to the turnfest of the Bund, and will show their prowess in the Stadium on German Day.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1084.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On returning to Germany, they should be able to announce that the Germans of Chicago and its environs were there by thousands, standing in the city of parks to proclaim that German ways, German customs, and German habits shall not be forgotten.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
