<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-06-21">June 21st, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Germany's Revolution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1188</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1188.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-06-21">June 21st, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANY'S REVOLUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Club of old '48 celebrated the reminiscences of the revolution of the German people in the year 1848 at Anbachs Garden yesterday. The festival speech was given by Mr. Joseph Rudolph, who pointed out that after a 58th year celebration, the members again have been reduced in numbers. Three have died during the last year and some are too old and sick to be present.</p>
   <p>The present generation has little understanding and interests in the happenings of 1848 and it is very regrettable that for years it has been tried here in America and more so in Germany and Austria to discredit the Revolution of 1848. The objectives at that time were not Socialist or Anarchist, but solely the intellectual product of the liberty and freedom of Germany.</p>
   <p>The failure has proved that the German Nation had not been sufficiently prepared yet. It also had been demonstrated that the Germans with their high respect for <pb facs="5418474_10_1189.jpg" n="2"/>general human rights and their soft heart, were bad Revolutionist, on the pillars of the 48 Revolution the German Empire of today had been built. It is however, not perfect and united by a long way; as there are still vast German sections especially in Austria exposed to the hate of other Nations, and they are longing to be united with the German Empire. The speaker told about the immigrations of the many political refugees who for the greater part came to the United States of America, the distrust and contempt, which they met at first, how they obtained a hearing from various associations and newspapers and how they participated fully in the Civil War and the development of the United States of America. It must also be recognized that the work of the Revolution of '48 has brought about a better understanding between both nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
