<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-11-28">November 28, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of the New St. Paul Church.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-11-28">November 28, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF THE NEW ST. PAUL CHURCH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new and beautiful church of the Evangelical St. Paul's Congregation, at the corner of Orchard Street and Kemper's Place, has been dedicated yesterday to its noble purpose in an appropriate and up-ligting manner. It was a day of honor for the faithful congregation whose self-sacrifices had made the erection of a house of worship possible. It is a worthy monument of German aspirations and power of faith.</p>
   <p>The members of the congregation participated in the dedicatory ceremonies during the morning service. Services were held during the afternoon and in the evening. There was an extensive program arranged for every evening during the following week, exclusive of Saturday.</p>
   <p>The new St. Paul church has been built by the architects, Hill and Woltersdorf, at a cost of $135,000.00, of which sum $27,000.00 only is unpaid. The Church is built in the Romanic style. A 230 foot high tower rises above the building. At the main entrance a plate bears the following inscription: "First German United Evangelical-Lutheran St. Paul's Church.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1527.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Established in 1843. The first Church was built in 1844, at La Salle and Ohio Streets. The second Church was built in 1854 and destroyed by the great Chicago fire in 1871. The third Church was built in 1872 and sold in December, 1897. This property was bought in March, 1896; the corner-stone laid on August 8, 1897, and dedicated on November 27, 1898. "The inside of the Church is artistically and elegantly arranged. Scenes from the life of Christ on the beautiful windows effect a dignified appearance for the whole.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
