<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-24">Dec. 24, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Evangelical Parishes of Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-24">Dec. 24, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">EVANGELICAL PARISHES OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The religious editor requests pastors to let him have bulletins by Friday morning at the latest, so that they may be entered in the Saturday edition of the Abendpost.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow the Christmas festival will be celebrated at St. Paul's Church in an old-fashioned, solemn manner. The German choir, having been augmented, will offer beautiful German Christmas carols; Mrs. Rosa Kloepfel will sing a Christmas choral from the seventeenth century. As a conclusion, the orphans' choir of the Uhlich Home will march in a procession of candles to the strains of the old children's song: "Alle Jahre wieder kommt das Christus-Kind". The German festival services will wind up with the Holy Supper.</p>
   <p>The English services are to be conducted at the altar by Pastor Pister and the orphan boys, together with those recently confirmed, will march in a <pb facs="5418474_10_1386.jpg" n="2"/>second candle procession into the House of God, singing the Christmas carol: "Herbei, o ihr Glaeuligen". The church choir will sing special Christmas chorals and a mass choir of 300 voices will give Christmas melodies. At these services Herr Harold Rensch will play a violin as only he can do it. The children, as well as their teachers, will receive gifts at the conclusion of the services, and the Holy Supper will be solemnized again.</p>
   <p>At 2:30 P.M. the orphans will repair to Rosehill Cemetery where they will sing songs of faith at the graves of their benefactors, Edouard Abel and Carl Buehler, letting their voices resound in the midst of Winter's ice and snow.</p>
   <p>Sunday, December 25, Christmas Day, German services with special festival music will be held at 9:30 A.M., Pastor Pister will deliver the sermon. At the conclusion of the services the Holy Supper will be celebrated. At 11 A.M. there will be English services, with the celebration of the Holy Supper.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1387.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The sermon is to be given by Pastor Scherger.</p>
   <p>Monday, December 26, at 2:30 P.M. Christmas will be celebrated at the Uhlich Orphanage. December 27, the Christmas celebration of the Sunday school will take place at the church hall. Your children are invited there, along with their parents, and the entire parish should be present at the celebration. Thursday, December 29, will be German Night (7 P.M.). German Christmas, music, Christmas carols and addresses fitting the occasion are on the program on which the children of the German Sunday school will celebrate Christmas.</p>
   <p>At the Evangelical Bethlehem Church there are to be a number of services and celebrations on Christmas. Saturday afternoon the children of the lower and kindergarten grades will have their Christmas. At 7 P.M. Christmas will be celebrated at the church. The older grades and the children of the confirmation class will participate. On Christmas two services are to be held, the English at 8 A.M. and the German at 10 A.M. The great choir will sing <pb facs="5418474_10_1388.jpg" n="4"/>various Christmas carols, and the pastor will preach at both services. On the second day of the Christmas season, generally regarded as a holy day, two services are to be held, the German at 10 A.M. and the English at 11 A.M. At these services the youths' choir are to sing Christmas carols.</p>
   <p>Tuesday at 2:30 P.M. will be marked by distribution of gifts for the members of the Cradle, their parents, and friends. All kinds of Christmas plays will come on the stage. On Friday the Penny-a-Day Club will meet. The ladies will find pleasure in the beautiful Christmas program. On the second Christmas Day, Holy Supper is to be celebrated in English. Sylvester Eve is to be celebrated in a quiet manner with German services beginning at 7:30 P.M. It will be followed by the Holy Supper. On Christmas morning, Miss Bertha Wiedman will be accepted as member (sic).</p>
   <p>We wish, for all our members and friends a Christmas festival blessed with abundance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1389.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Sunday, Dec. 25, at the Evangelical Friedenskirche German Christmas services will be held at 9 A.M. You fathers and mothers will come, won't you? Enough of the day will remain for celebrating at home.</p>
   <p>After these German festival services on December 25, no other celebrations will take place at our church, not even in the Sunday school.</p>
   <p>Monday, December 26, at 3 P.M. Christmas for the little children of the Sunday school will be celebrated,with distribution of gifts and collection for the benefit of the Sunday school.</p>
   <p>Monday, December 26, at 7 P.M., there will be a Christmas celebration for the Sunday school, with two Christmas performances, distribution of gifts, and a special collection for the benefit of the Sunday school.</p>
   <p>We invite the whole parish to these festivities of the Sunday school, and ask the adults to take seats in the balcony, if possible. Saturday, December <pb facs="5418474_10_1390.jpg" n="6"/>31, being Sylvester evening, there is going to be the concluding service of the year at 7:30 P.M. with a sermon and celebration of Holy Supper.</p>
   <p>Sunday, January 1, at 8:45 A.M., will open the New Year with festive services. at 10 A.M. both Sunday schools, as usual. Sunday following New Year, January 8, at 2 P.M. the parish will hold its annual meeting. The officers will read their reports, and election of officers will take place. All members entitled to vote are asked to devote two hours to the business affairs of the parish on January 8. One should discharge his duties as a voting member.</p>
   <p>The festival of Christmas is being celebrated at the church of St. Stephanus with three services on Christmas Day. At six o'clock in the morning there will be Christmas mass with candle light. From 9 to 10 A.M. the Sunday school is to celebrate its Christmas festival with a beautiful program. Regular English services are to be held at 10 A.M. and Christmas services in German at 11 A.M.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1391.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>On New Year's day there will be English services at 10 A.M. and German services at 11 A.M. Beginning January 8 of next year, and in future, there will be evening services every Sunday. Christmas time is quite a special time of the year, and no member of the parish should stay away from services without a good reason.</p>
   <p>The Evangelical Lutheran Church of Epiphany begins Christmas celebrations for the Sunday school by presenting a beautiful program. German services are to be held on Christmas morning with a German sermon and German choir and community singing. English services are arranged for 11 A.M. That a Christmas tree belongs to every Christmas festival is proved by the beautiful Christmas tree which stands at the altar of the church. The Sunday school and the meeting hall are decorated with pine branches. In the old fatherland of the founders of the parish, the second day of Christmas was likewise celebrated, and the custom is cultivated by us too. For this reason, on Monday, December 26, there will be two services in which the Holy Supper will be celebrated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1392.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The first services will take place at 10 A.M. in German, and the second at 11 A.M. in English. No member of our parish must miss these beautiful services. At 2 P.M., the choir of our church will broadcast a program of various carols over station WMBI under the direction of Professor Lucke. Do not forget to turn on your radio.</p>
   <p>Evangelical Gethsemane Church will begin its Christmas celebration with the Holy Supper at 6 A.M. At 10:30 A.M. are to be the main services, together with the celebration of Holy Supper. Christmas celebration of the Sunday school will take place at 7:30 P.M. Whoever wants to enjoy a merry Christmas with singing, rejoicing children must not fail to come to this celebration. We, too, will celebrate the second day of Christmas on Monday, December 26, with German services at 10:30 A.M.</p>
   <p>To all pastors and their parishes are extended the wishes of a merry and blessed Christmas from--the Religious Editor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
