<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-24">Dec. 24, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Turner Christmas</title><title level="a" type="sub">On Monday Chicago Turnverein holds its Christmas Festival and Giving of Gifts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-24">Dec. 24, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">TURNER CHRISTMAS</title><title level="a" type="sub">On Monday Chicago Turnverein holds Its Christmas Festival and Giving of Gifts</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the auspices of the ladies' department of the North Side Turnhalle there will be, on Monday, the second day of Christmas, the annual Christmas celebration of the Chicago Turnverein, 820 North Clark Street.</p>
   <p>The celebration begins at 8 P.M. The girls' and boys' classes and the orphans will perform under the supervision of the gymnastic teachers, Albert E. Teuscher and Alfred O. Diete.</p>
   <p>A very rich program is provided for so that all friends of athletics will get enough out of it. The program will conclude by bestowing gifts upon the children which, as usual, is done by the ladies' group.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1276.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Following the celebration there will be dances played to by an orchestra at which young and old will have a hearty good time.</p>
   <p>The Christmas celebration of the Social Turnverein in conjunction with show turning by boys' and girls' classes and bestowing of gifts to children takes place tomorrow, Sunday, in the Social Turnhalle, Belmont Avenue and Paulina Street.</p>
   <p>The celebration is scheduled to begin at 8 P.M. Various grades (of children) will show gymnastic performances under the supervision of the gymnastic teacher Bernhard Brockmann.</p>
   <p>Bestowing of gifts to children will terminate the official program. Following it the Beisse Orchestra will provide music for dancing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
