<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-08-08">Aug. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Old Settlers Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0711</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0711.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-08-08">Aug. 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD SETTLERS FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Turn Community arranged the thirty-seventh annual Old Settlers' festival in accordance with its custom yesterday, the success of which surpassed any previous year. The large Brand Park, the scene of the gayety, could hardly accomodate the multitude of people who came to share in the fun awaiting them.</p>
   <p>The very active arrangement committee provided fun and pleasure for young and old...The women marathon runners created the center of interest. The first prize was won by Mrs. Lizzie Rohde, the second by Mrs. Klara Koepke, and the third by Mrs. O'Brien. The number of contestants which were entered exceeded all previous years. But the Registrar's Committee with its years of experience was well prepared to handle the situation....Then followed the announcement of the winning contestants, whom Mr. Emil Hoester presented with medals, the emblems causing so much pleasant excitement.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0712.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The winners:</p>
   <p>1. The oldest German settler was Charles Rehm, a resident of Chicago since March 15, 1842.</p>
   <p>2. Mrs. Marie Meyer, living here since 1842.</p>
   <p>....5. Michael Meyer, for the distinction of being an employee of the Illinois Central Railroad since 1862.</p>
   <p>6. Sylvia Dennis, for her record of thirty-five years as an employee in one family.</p>
   <p>7. Mr. William and Mrs. Marie Nicolai, as the oldest couple of German settlers, their ages 84 and 78 years respectively...</p>
   <p>9. William Ohr, the oldest living veteran of the Civil War. He was a member of the 30th Illinois Regiment of Volunteers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0713.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>10. Mr. &amp; Mrs. Christ. Heckenbach, who are proud of the distinction of having the largest number of living descendants....</p>
   <p>Plaudits to the committee which was in charge of the highly successful entertainment......</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
