<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-03-27">March 27, 1899</date><title level="a">Germans, Come Forth! Today's Meeting of Protest at the Auditorium. a German Answer to the Propaganda of the Jingos and Anglophiles.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-03-27">March 27, 1899</date><title level="a">Germans, Come Forth! Today's Meeting of Protest At The Auditorium. A German Answer To The Propaganda Of The Jingos And Anglophiles.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tonight, - in the gigantic hall of the Auditorium, the Chicago German-Americans will hold their great Protest Meeting! Its purpose is to give a typical German reply to those malicious attempts and miserable insinuations now being circulated by the subsidized press of England, and our yellow Press, which is so desirous of destroying our friendship and adherence to our adopted fatherland, to which we have been faithful for a century. Above all, the local German - Americans wish to proclaim and prove to the world, that they are bona fide - loyal citizens of this nation; in unity they voice their demand to be recognized and enjoy equal suffrage; - with stentorian tones of warning, which shall reverberate like thunder, we will protest against a perfidious alliance with Albion.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt, the meeting will be a grand demonstration and will not fail in its purpose. All those, who wish to obtain cards of admission, may procure them at William H. Jung's hall, 106 East Randolph Street, or from Mr. E. H. Plautz, Room 1135, Stock Exchange Building. <pb facs="5418474_10_0100.jpg" n="2"/>The mass chorus consists of more than 500 singers, and the enthusiasm they showed during yesterday's rehearsal at Haendel Hall was most inspiring.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
