<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-02-19">Feb. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Tactless Inquisition</title><title level="a" type="sub">Federal Officers Embarrass German Applicants for American Citizenship with Humiliating Questions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-02-19">Feb. 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TACTLESS INQUISITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Federal Officers Embarrass German Applicants for American Citizenship with Humiliating Questions</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Germans look back with regret to the good old times when the German immigrant, after getting acquainted with the language, the laws, and the customs of this country, received the final papers which made him a proud American citizen. Without being embarrassed by insidious questions, without coercion, with gladness in his heart, he fought for his self-chosen country in the hour of need, leaving his family behind him.</p>
   <p>Unquestionably those times are gone, not because the German feels differently toward his adopted country, but because from high authorities a certain pressure is applied which makes it difficult for him to retain that youthful enthusiasm which he had on the day of his naturalization.</p>
   <p>The highest national virtue of the German, next to loyalty, is gratitude.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0043.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Gratitude to the country of his birth, where he spent his youth and received his education, is what he cannot and will not forget, although his loyalty and gratitude to his adopted country will endure to his death.</p>
   <p>Therefore every American with the least bit of sympathy for the Germans, must agree that the questions addressed to several Germans at the examination for citizenship, such as "In the case of war between the United States and Germany, what would you do?" were embarrassing and humiliating, aside from the fact that from the ethical viewpoint such inquiries are absolutely superfluous. For although every decent immigrant is proud of his descent, yet if the hour of danger comes, he will undoubtedly do his duty toward his adopted country; and it already has been proved that the German immigrant is earnest and sincere in his intention to become a loyal American citizen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
