<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-05-01">May 1, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">The Centennial Noise.</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Ill-fated Demonstration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-05-01">May 1, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">THE CENTENNIAL NOISE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Ill-fated Demonstration.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All in all, yesterday's centennial celebration was a real miserable affair. It is a good sign that people begin to realize that they have absolutely no reason to be proud of the results achieved since the inauguration of the first president, that the intention of the founders of the United States to assign to posterity a treasure in the constitution which should guarantee to the people a liberal development for common wealth, for common education, and common security has been wrecked by the perfidy and bad intention of the "upper ten thousands," who by and by succeeded in complete domination.</p>
   <p>It is true, that almost all business people were showing flags, even if only penny flags, in order to protect themselves from anything disagreeable on the part of the American rowdy-elements, - but one could see on the decorations as a whole, that "joy and love for the thing itself" was lacking.</p>
   <p>Attempts for decorations were also made on public buildings, but also failed dejectedly for the biggest part. The enthusiasm of the dear public, which was <pb facs="5418474_10_1219.jpg" n="2"/>milling in the main streets of the city yesterday, was not so great. The mob on the streets consisted chiefly of two elements: the native rowdies, who were lacking enthusiasm because the wealthy failed to fill them up with brandy as e. i. at election-demonstrations, - and secondly the newly immigrated, who wandered around in the streets and vainly looked for something which would appear to them more beautiful and grand than similar things in their respective home-country.</p>
   <p>Many American workers undisturbed tended their business. M. W. Doty, a wood-turner at 76 Lake Street, was the only man in Chicago yesterday who had the courage to show that his demonstration was somewhat different from that of the "sovereign citizens" and imported slaves. He hung a big red umbrella and a working-apron outside of his window indicating that only under the colors of liberty is work able to endure. But what does the dear mob know about the "flag of Bunker Hill?"</p>
   <p>When about 2,000 persons gathered and threatened to storm the house, a firecaptain, whose patent patriotism felt annoyed, threw the umbrella and apron down on the street.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1220.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A scoundrel, a thick, fat camel of a German knocked Mr. Doty down. Mr. Doty is a native American and not an imported "Foreigner," who did not quite understand our magnificent constitution.</p>
   <p>In all prayer-stables, in all schools, and in eight mass-meetings on all public squares large quantities of patent-patriotism were tapped. There was singing, programs and preaching, but real enthusiasm was lacking. No great animation could be created by the sermons of patriotism of bartenders, preachers or laymen. They were a collection of phrases, compiled more in the order of sounds than sense and were therefore mostly not understood.</p>
   <p>Special stress was laid yesterday on stuffing the brains of our dear youth with patent-patriotism. This also proved a failure. The teachers and other speakers lacked the feelings which could have been transmitted to the little ones only directly, and by that the celebrations became ceremonious and stiff.</p>
   <p>The most pitiful impression in yesterday's celebration was doubtlessly created by the procession. There were about 300 grand army members and 200 discharged German mercenaries. So far, the grand army people were all right. At least they did something during the Civil War, which was in direct violation of the peace-ordinance of the constitution.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1221.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They showed themselves as living, discouraging examples, but the German, discharged mercenaries - what were they looking for in that parade? Perhaps they intended to serve as an advertisement for the foundation of an American Bismarckdom? Well, was the impression of their herds imposing? Certainly not!</p>
   <p>The majority of the members of the Krieger Verein and Militar-Verein were smart enough not to participate in the whole humbug. They looked rigid enough, only there was something wrong with their music-band, for when reaching market square the band ran away, but was later caught again.</p>
   <p>In the evening hours there was a "commers" in "comrade" in Vogelsangs place, during which much war-like drinking and very un-war-like ingratiating took place. A similar program was on in #246 S. Halsted St., furnished by the "Deutsche Militar Verein." There were also, of course, patriotic orgies in different places by prominent Americans during the evening.</p>
   <p>Hundreds of thousands went to see the fireworks. Wonderful things were promised but only moderate ones were delivered. The fault of all accidents, which happened in such great numbers yesterday, chiefly rests without any <pb facs="5418474_10_1222.jpg" n="5"/>doubt with the police, who neglected to take the necessary precautions and, more especially, did not prohibit the numerous buggies and coaches, from which the "prominents" observed the fireworks, to close the streets with an impenetrable barricade of wagons. Chief Verkes' pull-boxes added their utmost to these street blockings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
