<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-07-22">July 22, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Arbeiterverein and Conscription</title><title level="a" type="sub">Loyal Germans Condemn Rioting and Violence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0980</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0980.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-07-22">July 22, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHICAGO ARBEITERVEREIN AND CONSCRIPTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Loyal Germans Condemn Rioting and Violence</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>July 20, in a meeting of the Chicago Arbeiterverein, the most active society in the city and with a membership of more than one thousand, Mr. S. Schoenemann proposed that the organization, which is rightly considered to be representative of the Germans in Chicago, voice its stand on conscription and enforcement of the conscription laws, elect a committee to draw up pertinent resolutions, and declare itself ready to organize for the preservation of peace and order.</p>
   <p>This proposal was unanimously adopted and Mr. Leon Strauss, Mr. George Schneider, Mr. S. Schoenemann, Mr. J. Mechelke, and Dr. Ernst Schmidt were elected to serve as a committee on resolutions. They immediately withdrew for a conference, and after some time returned and submitted the following resolutions which were not unanimously accepted, but were hailed with loud and prolonged cheering.</p>
   <p>"We, the members of the Chicago Arbeiterverein, assembled in special meeting <pb facs="5418474_10_0981.jpg" n="2"/>July 20, 1863, make the following declaration:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The sovereignty of the law must be upheld above all else if anarchy is to be averted and the lives and property of our citizens protected and preserved; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Especially the Conscription Law, though it contains some faulty provisions against which we have protested and which we have vainly attempted to have changed, must now be upheld and enforced if our army is not to be halted on its victorious course, and peace is to be deferred for a long period of time; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we would be ashamed of Chicago if its citizens did not possess enough prudence and courage to prevent a repetition of incidents like those which occurred in New York. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we would not permit a violation of the sovereignty of the laws <pb facs="5418474_10_0982.jpg" n="3"/>under any circumstances. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we, members of the Chicago Arbeiterverein, are ready to organize to nip mob violence in the bud. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we entertain and are ready to defend the view that in a possible uprising by a mob, the humblest as well as the most prominent, the black as well as the white, are entitled to, and should receive, the full protection of the law. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That it is our hope, therefore, that all good citizens will not be tardy in taking the steps necessary to protect the life and property of all those who live within the confines of this city, and to preserve the honor and the good name of the Republic. Be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we will resist any eventual rebellion against law and order with sword and bullets. Be it further</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0983.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Resolved, That these resolutions be published in all English and German newspapers of Chicago."</p>
   <p>It was also voted to hold a special meeting of the Chicago Arbeiterverein Wednesday, July 23, for the purpose of laying the foundation of a protective organization.</p>
   <p>Theodor Hilscher, President,</p>
   <p>Gottlieb Brauning, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
