<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-29">Sept. 29, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The New Decorations of the North Side Turner Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_0887</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-20">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_0887.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-29">Sept. 29, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW DECORATIONS OF THE NORTH SIDE TURNER HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Turners [Gymnasts] were quite contented, to judge by their singing, which could be heard even on the street, and they had good reason to be elated. They were celebrating the completion of the wall decorations of their large hall. The work, fresco painting, was done by the firm of J. B. Sullivan and Brothers, 266 North Clark Street, lowest bidders..... [Translator's note: Since Sullivan was an Irishman, and these translations are concerned only with German endeavor, I must omit the greater part of the description.] They were exceedingly successful in their treatment as a whole, particularly of the large ceiling, and here they created a veritable masterpiece. The work is impressive, shows good taste, and is free from gingerbread effects. A cupola about twenty feet in diameter forms the approximate center of the large ceiling, 69 by 96 feet.....The portraits of Humboldt, Goethe, Schiller, Shakespeare, Liszt, Beethoven, Mozart, and Wagner, each on a separate shield, appear on a gray background. A reddish <pb facs="5418474_10_0888.jpg" n="2"/>ribbon, interspersed with rosettes, forms a connecting band for the pictures, indicating continuity, and this effect is enhanced by garlands of flowers.....[Translator's note: Detailed description omitted.] The other rooms also were decorated.....The stage wall of the great hall is no longer of cloth; it is now a solid wall and will undoubtedly improve the acoustic qualities. Indeed, the Turners might well enjoy yesterday's banquet.</p>
   <p>The hall will be shown to the public next Sunday afternoon, and in connection therewith Orchestra Leader Rosenbecker will give a concert, in which forty members of Thomas's orchestra will appear. A dance and other entertainment will constitute the evening program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
