<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-06-07">June 7, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Bishop Henninghaus He Intends to Make a Number of Interesting Speeches Here.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_10_1499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_10_1499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-06-07">June 7, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">BISHOP HENNINGHAUS HE INTENDS TO MAKE A NUMBER OF INTERESTING SPEECHES HERE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bishop Henninghaus, born in Munsterland in Germany, who was a missionary for 20 years in South Shantung, China, arrived in New York on March 25th. As in Germany, his lectures about the religious situation in China, found here also great acclaim. In all dioceses of the East, which he visited, he was received with great friendliness. He is an eloquent speaker and linquist. The Bishop arrived here yesterday, to go afterwards to Techny, Illinois to visit his brothers. He belongs to the Society of the Divine Words, which is conducting the St. Joseph technical school there.</p>
   <p>He is accompanied by the young Chinese priest, Peter Ischang, who besides his mother tongue, also speaks Latin and German, and in accordance with his country's habits, wears a cue and serves as secretary to the Bishop. Today the Bishop will celebrate high mass in Techny, his attendant, in the Catholic Church, of Niles Center, Pastor George Thiele, will sing high mass <pb facs="5418474_10_1500.jpg" n="2"/>and the Bishop will preach. Tonight at 8 o'clock, Bishop Henninghaus is going to lecture about conditions in China, in St. Michael's Church, and his attendant will make a German speech. Tomorrow, Whit Monday, the Bishop will confirm a number of boys of the St. Joseph technical School, also several children of the Shermerville community.</p>
   <p>The following days and weeks, he proposes to lecture in different German and English churches. The Bishop intends to make the return trip to China, by way of Vancouver and Japan, after a little while.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
