<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. III, No. 1,
<date when="1909-12-25">Dec. 25, 1909</date>
<title level="a">Jesus Christ Son of a Proletarian. the Great Teacher Who Sacrificed His Blood and Life</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0410.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. III, No. 1,
<date when="1909-12-25">Dec. 25, 1909</date>
<title level="a">Jesus Christ Son of a Proletarian. The Great Teacher Who Sacrificed His Blood and Life</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>He was born nearly twenty centuries ago. He suffered all his life from manger to his crucifixion, He, a proletarian. He died as a criminal between criminals. He suffered for a principle. His principles as well as his teachings were the fruits of the surroundings in which he lived. His environment was slavery and cruelty. In those times the lords threw their men, slaves, to wild beasts as fodder and enjoyed to see men torn and massacred. The people were without rights and oppressed. Jesus saw in the slave his brother, his counterpart, his equal. From that came his teaching about brotherhood of men, love and justice; the fight against the oppressor and holder of power.</p>
   <p>His teachings were the seed of Socialism.</p>
   <p>His words about justice and equality he spread relentlessly.</p>
   <p>He went to towns and villages, to temples and markets.</p>
   <p>His words were full of love for the oppressed and robbed, sharp against the rich and the Pharisees.</p>
   <p>The governing classes got sick of his teachings soon. The rich and the governing declared him to be a rebel. The hypocrites, the philosophers and the priests, called him a troublemaker, an atheist, who was revolting against laws of God and man, against order. They crucified him. Gave him the most shameful punishment.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0411.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The masses stupid, without conscience, spat on him.</p>
   <p>Nineteen hundred years have passed from the death of martyred Christ, who waged war for humanity, while humanity enslaved still suffers untold sufferings, injustices and pain. Dumbness and ignorance weigh down the human mind. Vampires drink from human brains and blood.</p>
   <p>Aeons went by; but tyranny, crookedness, ambiguity dominate alongside proud palaces, alongside luxury - how much of undeserved misery, pain and sufferings. A hell close to an earthly heaven.</p>
   <p>But the priests - the Pharisees of today - say it must be as it is, because God wants it is. You have to suffer hunger - they must have plenty.</p>
   <p>When those in power send you to war, the Pharisees bless the arms. And yet did not Jesus Christ say: "Do not Kill." Did Jesus Christ teach that some folks become rich at any price, the rest stay poor and in want. Did he teach that all the misery is God's will? No! Jesus Christ did not teach those things. But the Pharisees misused his noble sufferings for the benefit of the rich.</p>
   <p>We Socialists - who are atheist rebels the same as they called Jesus Christ - understand his teachings.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0412.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He preached liberty, brotherhood, equality. To secure these things, all the oppressed workers in the world must unite, become brethren and cooperate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
