<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. X, No. 50,
<date when="1917-11-21">Nov. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Memory of November 11, 1887.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0314</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0314.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. X, No. 50,
<date when="1917-11-21">Nov. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MEMORY OF NOVEMBER 11, 1887.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thirty years have passed, on November 11 of this year, since the day when a capitalist judiciary committed a brutal injustice over working men who asked for their rights and better living conditions.</p>
   <p>A dreadful tragedy was enacted thirty years ago when a governing class used force to stifle in blood the voice of the laboring men, to degrade them to slaves who must be silent, having no demands.</p>
   <p>In 1886 the workers asked for an eight-hour working day. The capitalistic class became scared by this demand as well as by the determined action of the workers. The capitalist class became frightened by the workers' movement, and not knowing what to do, used force to suppress that movement, but to do that, used means which did not only suppress but did strengthen said movement and spirit of resistance.</p>
   <p>Thirty years ago, on November 11, it happened that August Spies, Albert <pb facs="5420779_1_0315.jpg" n="2"/>R. Parsons, Adolph Fischer and George Engel had to die a death in Chicago the way vicious criminals must die. Louis Lingg ended his life by suicide in jail.</p>
   <p>The sentence by which these labor leaders were sent to death belongs among the greatest judiciary crimes of the world. The workers were accused of different crimes without being given an opportunity to defend themselves.</p>
   <p>Governor Altgeld of Illinois commuted the sentences for Michael Schwaba, Samuel Fielden and Oscar Neebe. The governor himself was exposed to accusations by the capitalistic class, but he was a just man, knowing that he did what was right. He considered the sentence against those workers and injustice in which they tried to send to death all those who did not approve the conditions of work imposed by the capitalists on labor.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0316.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In Chicago the memory has remained of those victims who perished for a just cause.</p>
   <p>Thirty years passed since. The capitalistic class is just as brutal as it was in those times. But stronger now and has servants at her disposal who will act against the working class at all occasions.</p>
   <p>But the workers' movement became also stronger, and a struggle is conducted which will end in the defeat of those who defend an unjust cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
