<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VI, No. 7,
<date when="1913-01-30">Jan. 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Take Care of Your Pockets</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VI, No. 7,
<date when="1913-01-30">Jan. 30, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">TAKE CARE OF YOUR POCKETS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From many sides we receive printed circulars in the Croatian language, sent to addresses of our Croatian nationals by the Peruvian-Chamyro Rubber Corporation of New York. In these letters and circulars the receiver, in tempting words, is assured of getting rich quick if he buys shares of the said corporation. The more he buys the better.</p>
   <p>"We want to give the opportunity to our Croatian people to gain, without work or trouble or sweat, 25% to 50% per year. To double their cash positively after four years." The above is said in the circulars. Further, that the corporation acquired land in the Republic of Peru, where trees grow, out of which rubber is made. In the forests there is hidden so much wealth that anybody can become wealthy who puts his money in that enterprise, that is, if he buys shares at $5 each.</p>
   <p>In short, that is the content of their circulars, and we are able to tell instantly that some speculators are bent, not to help the Croatian <pb facs="5420779_1_0167.jpg" n="2"/>people in America, but to empty their pockets and fill up their own. Such enterprises grow in America like mushrooms, to disappear quickly after the crooked speculators gained the money of the poor whom they rob.</p>
   <p>Why do such swindlers appeal to the workers? Why do they sell shares for as little as $1, $5, or $10? Why? To help the workers to get rich? No, because the rich will not put his money where it does not bear profit. Gold mines, rubber plantations, and etc., offered for sale to the poor, do not even exist. If they exist, they are not accessible, or are worth less than nothing. The worker who invests his money loses in the end. There were thousands of cases like that. For that reason take care of your pockets.</p>
   <p>But there is something more of interest in this case. There is talk that two brothers work for the Peruvian-Chamyro Rubber Corporation.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0168.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Two Croatians, known all over America. They want to help the Croatians. One resides in Peru, the other in Chicago, just to catch fools.</p>
   <p>We will investigate and deal with such patriots. Once more, take care of your pockets!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
