<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. XI. No. 7,
<date when="1918-02-20">Feb. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Miserable Position of Workers in Slaughterhouses</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. XI. No. 7,
<date when="1918-02-20">Feb. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE MISERABLE POSITION OF WORKERS IN SLAUGHTERHOUSES</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The workers in Chicago's slaughterhouses were exploited for years in the most inhuman way, the owners were using every means that this exploitation might not become public, and that the workers do not react against it. Finally this exploitation reached the extreme; it came before a court last week, where the litigation between workers and company had to be decided.</p>
   <p>Last Monday, a conference was held between the company representatives and the workers' delegates. The workers are represented by the president of the Chicago Federation of Labor, Fitzpatrick, and Attorney F. Walsh, president of the well known industrial commission.</p>
   <p>The workers submitted to the companies a list of questions to which they must answer. Among other things it is asked, How big is the invested capital, what connections exist with other big firms in similar business and banks, to name affiliated plants, the number of employed workers and their wages.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0175.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To these questions the following companies are required to answer: J. Ogden Armour, L. F. Swift, N. Morris, Cudahy and Thomas Wilson.</p>
   <p>If the companies refuse to answer the above mentioned questions, the workers' representatives will request the court to force them to do so.</p>
   <p>Tuesday was the first hearing before a court of arbitration, where Fitzpatrick portrayed the miserable position of workers in slaughter houses, what was very disagreeable to hear for the company representatives. However, they were forced to hear the accusations, which could not be minimized.</p>
   <p>Fitzpatrick proved that the workers receive wages on which they cannot get along. Then he touched upon the corruption used by the companies to keep their workers out of the unions. "There were," he said, "many union men who did not mention to their own wives that they belonged to a union, from fear this fact would be made known, and the workers fired from their jobs." Not only that, but the companies watch that such a worker is not employed in any other place.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0176.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Very often workmen had to change their nationality and name to escape the revenge of the company to obtain work in some other place.</p>
   <p>At these words the companies' attorney jumped at Fitzpatrick, claiming that this statement offended his clients. Fitzpatrick did not mind that. He continued calmly his revelations. From which it was seen that the companies treated their workmen like slaves. What will be proven later on in hearings of workers, men and women?</p>
   <p>In the slaughterhouses are employed workers belonging to nearly all of the different trades. Consequently many organizers were examined at the hearing, who corroborated the fact that the companies persecuted in the meanest way, all those who tried to organize their workers.</p>
   <p>At the hearing, J. Kennedy, president of the butchers' union gave the information that the companies played a dual role. They have slaughterhouses in New York, where they were forced to sign with his union. The same union asked several times to be recognized in Chicago but was always refused.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0177.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The workers in New York work shorter hours, have a little higher wages, but as soon as they ask for something the company tells them that workers in Chicago are getting less and it is only right that those in New York should not get more.</p>
   <p>Of the working women examined we will mention Cecilia Sula. She declared in court that her father was hurt last week and is sick now. When her father does not work, our mother must go to work, said the girl. "We drink coffee with bread in the morning and coffee and bread at noon." For supper the same with some soup. We all live in one room, where we dry our washing. In that room are eight of us: father, mother and six children."</p>
   <p>The above is the statement of this girl. Such statements were many. The working woman, Rosie Babeck, stated in court that her husband was buried last Saturday. The union paid burial expenses. The poor woman had no money to buy bread. Her husband was injured at work and died at the County Hospital. She is left on the street with three children. Her late husband earned 27 cents per hour. They lived in one room, paying eight and a half dollars per month rent.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0178.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Albina Stupien is the mother of six children. Her husband works in the slaughterhouse. If he works all week, he gets $15. But he is often sick, then hunger reigns in their house. Also this family has just one room, two children on the floor in the kitchen. The family has no bed sheets nor blankets. Everybody covers himself at night with his own clothes. Their food consists of coffee and bean soup. If the husband is sick, the wife goes to work in his place. Her job is then to clean killed hogs.</p>
   <p>One woman declared that what the other women said was true, that she knew the conditions under which the slaughterhouse workers were living. She continued that the workers have been organized only six months, the women two months. But the employers are great enemies of the unions.</p>
   <p>The attorney for the Wilson firm refused to give any explanation about wages paid by that firm. Pressed by the judge, he declared that it is forbidden him by his firm to talk about this matter. It was proven that all firms act in accord on how much to pay their workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0179.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Because the arbitration will take few days, the court asked both parties to decide how many hours daily the hearings should last. The workers' representatives asked for eight hours, the companies' representatives declared five hours were enough.</p>
   <p>During the hearings, the organizer of the American Federation of Labor, Kitulski, revealed how brutally the workers are treated in the companies' work shops. The companies have private spies and police and maltreat their workers. Kitulski said: "I protest against the acts of the private police of the companies who beat up workers if they are late for work. I protest against the treatment of foreign laborers who are subjected to abusive language of vilest kind. Just because these workers do not understand English, they must not be treated like cattle. They were lured by agents from Europe to make slaves of themselves in the slaughterhouses.</p>
   <p>The other day I came to the house of a workingman. He had not yet come from work and his wife was also away. In the house were seven children without shoes and stockings or socks. The children were compelled to stay inside. Fifty per cent of the workers in the slaughterhouses, who are foreigners, are starving. The company officials handle women just as brutally as men."</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0180.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Agnes Nestor from the Women's Trade Union League stated that men who are getting 21 cents per hour are laid off, in their place are hired women, who are paid 20 cents per hour. These women must work just as hard as men do. Even in the killing department women are employed. Though the women do there the same work as men, they get just 20 cents per hour.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Nestor protested because women are employed in the killing department. Women must do work, which is not fitted for them, while the men must rot without work.</p>
   <p>The workers' representatives requested that the state take over the slaughterhouses. The party which wants to come into power in the future will have to see that this is done.</p>
   <p>In the above manner workers are handled in shops of great American patriots and fighters for democracy and freedom.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
