<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 6,
<date when="1915-01-20">Jan. 20, 1915</date>
<title level="a">The Hunger Army and Barbarism of Chicago's Police</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0232</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0232.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 6,
<date when="1915-01-20">Jan. 20, 1915</date>
<title level="a">THE HUNGER ARMY AND BARBARISM OF CHICAGO'S POLICE</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday,January 17, the League of Unemployed called a meeting in Hull House, Chicago, Illinois. About eight hundred people assembled in the hall and a great many stood outside because there was no room for them inside.</p>
   <p>After the speeches delivered in different languages, the assemblage moved out on the street to demonstrate against the unemployment.</p>
   <p>In the parade the workers carried signs with many inscriptions. At the front four girls carried a black flag with the inscription "Hunger." Other signs bore inscriptions of "We do not want charity. Give us work!" "Give us our daily bread today!"</p>
   <p>Already in the hall among the throng were some plainclothes police-men. They wanted to halt the parade on the claim that there was no permit issued for it. Indeed, there was no permit because the police refused to issue one.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0233.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Plainclothes men and the uniformed police wanted to break up the parade. They beat up the paraders with their clubs. A riot call brought five hundred more policemen. Many men and women were arrested. Among them Reverend Tucker, a priest and editor of the Christian Socialist. When Reverend Tucker saw the inscription "Give us our daily bread today!" he said that that was a passage from the Lord's prayer and he took up the sign to carry it.</p>
   <p>Miss Jane Addams, the most sympathetic being in America, declared that there was nothing in the speeches that would incite the people to riot. The meeting and the parade were quiet; the workers did not do anything against the law, but the Chicago police, who could be teachers for the Russian Cossacks, did not care for the law, right or justice. They showed that civilization was dead in the center of America, and that this state is a nest of crooks who exploit and oppress the working class.</p>
   <p>The miserable poor thrown on the street - who has neither bread nor lodging-wanted to demonstrate in this manner, to show that in this great capitalistic city of Chicago hunger reigns, received a policeman's club over his head.</p>
   <p>Where is liberty? Where is law? Where is the Constitution which supports the lazy ones and permits them to be our bosses? Do we find culture just in the <pb facs="5420779_1_0234.jpg" n="3"/>millions of a Rockefeller or a Carnegie, in the depraved justice of the courts, in policemen's clubs?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
