<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VIII, No. 27,
<date when="1915-06-16">June 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Few Words to Socialist Married Couples</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VIII, No. 27,
<date when="1915-06-16">June 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A FEW WORDS TO SOCIALIST MARRIED COUPLES</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>You complain that your wives are against Socialism, that they grumble when you speak at a Socialist meeting or spread propaganda among workers.</p>
   <p>It is too bad to be disturbed by a person with whom you are obliged to live. Yes, your wives bother you, they want to trouble you, to take you out of the Socialist Party. You resent that. Instead of remaining in your home, you flee from it; you go to saloons and find your home there.</p>
   <p>I do not say that your wives hate your principles with reason, but I must also tell you that you, husbands, are to blame.</p>
   <p>Try to answer these questions: (1) What do you do to inform your wife that Socialism is a new form of human progress, that the foundation of its teachings are as indestructible as are the needs of life. (2) In what way do you show her that Socialism is teaching love and equality;</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0318.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>that it means you must regard her as an equal and love her. (3) How is your behavior in your family? What do you do to discredit the statements of the clergy that Socialism kills family life? (4) Do you respect the religious feelings of your wife just the same as you expect her to respect your Socialist views? (5) In what manner do you want to prove to your wife that the greatest enemy of the working class is the clergy because they are always allied with the powerful? (6) Do you not waste your Sundays in saloons, while your wife and children are left to themselves? No wonder that they must turn to church and the priest. (7) Can you assure your wife that a Socialist, according to his mode of living, is better than those who are kneeling before the church altars? Do you think you will be able to win your wife for Socialism by your gambling and drinking? (8) Do you think that your wife will believe that gamblers and drunkards are able to lead humanity in the right path? (9) Do you care for the betterment of conditions for the working women? To make them intelligent, to organize them? Do you influence your wife and children to attend public meetings of the workers?</p>
   <p>There are very few Socialists who could answer these questions in the <pb facs="5420779_1_0319.jpg" n="3"/>affirmative. Very few of them try to lead their wives and children in the true path, the path of Socialism. However, if there are very few today, there will come the time when there will be more of them. It is in the interests of the working class that each Socialist makes a comrade of his wife, because then he will have in his own home a friend and co-worker and not, as it is today, an enemy of his principles. To reach that goal comrades must excel in the mode of their living within and without their families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
