<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1928-08-09">Aug. 9, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Eight Commandments for Parents</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1928-08-09">Aug. 9, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">EIGHT COMMANDMENTS FOR PARENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. Do not "show off" your children. Children were never intended to feed the vanity of their parents. The latter must forego any excessive pride in their children.</p>
   <p>2. Don't push your children too rapidly. Maturity cannot be forced upon a child; it is the result of growth, a growth whose processes are highly important. You cannot make children conform to a pattern; they must be permitted to grow.</p>
   <p>3. The emotional displays, the temperamental outbursts which you would not indulge before adults should not find expression in the presence of children. What may offend adults will likewise affect children unfavorably.</p>
   <p>4. Stern commands cannot take the place of friendship and love for the child.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0095.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. Don't lie to your child, and don't let others lie to him. Your ideas and beliefs may be beyond a child's comprehension, but the lie direct is fraught with great danger: it is easy to repeat, and hence should be carefully avoided.</p>
   <p>6. Don't use fear as a whip. Fear creates slaves, and slaves, at best, are not human beings.</p>
   <p>7. Don't harp on the weaknesses of your child; he may take the matter seriously, and slowly develop a feeling of inferiority, a submissive attitude. Or it may well happen that the child will concentrate his thoughts on your faults, and will lose all respect for you because of your hypocrisy.</p>
   <p>8. Don't tell your child that he cannot think, and don't call him stupid. Every normal child can and does think; it is your duty to help him along.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
