<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> (Worker) Vol. VII, No. 134.
<title level="a">To the Jugoslav Proletarians of America</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0248</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0248.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> (Worker) Vol. VII, No. 134.
<title level="a">TO THE JUGOSLAV PROLETARIANS OF AMERICA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Workingmen and Women:</p>
   <p>The situation confronting the working class of all the world and of the United States, as well as the Jugoslav proletarians, is becoming worse every day.</p>
   <p>The economic crisis grows, the abyss between the classes becomes wider; the political struggle is sharpened; the capitalistic class prepares assaults, not only against the proletarians, but against all the oppressed peoples.</p>
   <p>In the United States the situation for immigrant workers, like the Jugoslav proletarians, is more plighted by special violence of the ruling classes of America.</p>
   <p>Our movement, the revolutionary and Communist movement, was for you, <pb facs="5420779_1_0249.jpg" n="2"/>workingmen and workingwomen, clear and open like the pages of a book; all the time you heard the truth, which was proved to you. You were not misled by statements brought before you; all were proved and correct.</p>
   <p>We inform you now that a united front of reactionaries is organized against our Communist movement. That front is in action; the offensive starts against the Labor Party and its Jugoslav section.</p>
   <p>The duty of the Jugoslav proletarians is to resist this offensive of reactionaries and opportunists, who want to assault them. It is your duty, Jugoslav workers, with more faith and more enthusiasm to follow the ranks of the revolutionary movement--the Labor Party and its Jugoslav section.</p>
   <p>Up to the present you have given resistance to a divided enemy; from now on your resistance must be greater, because the enemy has united.</p>
   <p>We call on you to stand as one man for the idea of getting the working class <pb facs="5420779_1_0250.jpg" n="3"/>free--that means Communism.</p>
   <p>You must stand united like a wall against the assaults of our enemies. After their assaults you must take up the offensive. For success you must assert discipline in your ranks, strengthen your organizations for more work in all fields; of propaganda, agitation, organization, enlightenment, not only of members but also of sympathizers and other fellow workers. The slogan of the Communist Internationale is "In masses!" This slogan must become alive among the Jugoslav proletarians of America.</p>
   <p>As Russia for seven years has repulsed the assaults of the world's capitalists and social traitors, so must we repel our enemies, who are numerous.</p>
   <p>The voice of the Russian revolution, the voices of the oppressed workers all over the land, the voices of the Jugoslav proletarians of America call us to work and to fight. Today, on the seventh anniversary of the Russian revolution, we must declare that we will fulfill our duty and come out victors of that <pb facs="5420779_1_0251.jpg" n="4"/>struggle. We owe that to the ideas of Lenin.</p>
   <p>Central Committee of the Jugoslav Section of the American Labor Party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
