<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VI, No. 4,
<date when="1914-01-07">Jan. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Milan Glumac-Nurising, Dead</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0330</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0330.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VI, No. 4,
<date when="1914-01-07">Jan. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MILAN GLUMAC-NURISING, DEAD</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the fifth of January at 4:30 P. M. came to end the life of one of the first fighters and one of our most devoted comrades, Milan Clumac. He died, worn out by the proletarian sickness called tuberculosis.</p>
   <p>Since his 18th year he worked faithfully with all the fire of his heart, sacrificing all his powers of mind and body for the labor movement. Wherever he worked, either as typesether or Social Democrat, he won unsurpassed merits for the workingmen's cause.</p>
   <p>Finished is the life of a great fighter: a life full of misery, devotion, and self-abandonment.</p>
   <p>The funeral will be at the Montrose crematory. The body will be cremated according to the will of the deceased, the 11th of this month at 1:30 P. M.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0331.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Milan Glumac Jurisic was born in 1884 in Bosansnki Samac. He attended public school in his birth place. When 12 years old he left for Zagreb to learn the typesetters' trade, where be contracted the disease to which he finally succumbed. From that time he was interested in the most pitiful of human classes: the workingman. As a boy he started to read books which told him of the tragedy of the working class and at the same time showed him the way for the betterment of these conditions. His thoughts, his philosophy of life, he disclosed in the paper Narodna Rec, at Budapest, where he worked. For his freethinking, for all the good he did for the working class, he was persecuted.</p>
   <p>From Budapest he went to Novi Sad, where he worked for Narodni Glas. Then he became secretary for the Socialist Federation of Agricultural Workers. Soon his name became known and feared. He was denounced as an instigator of riots, an organizer of unions, which it was said, were dangerous for society in general. He was arrested and when released went to his home town.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0332.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In Zagreb he organized the leather workers, and in spite of many persecutions he worked continually in the Socialist direction. They drafted him for military service, which he hated. At that time there came to him a call from Allegheny, Pa., to come there to start to organize Socialist branches for a future federation.</p>
   <p>In 1907 he escaped military service and came to America where be worked continuously to spread Socialist teachings. In Chicago he became the first editor of Radnicka Straza.</p>
   <p>On account of his malady and overwork, he was obliged to have some rest and went to California. But it was too late. His eagerness for work brought him back to Chicago to our newspaper Badnicka Straza, again as <pb facs="5420779_1_0333.jpg" n="4"/>editor. Here he worked until one evening his condition became so bad that he was carried from the office to his bed to die.</p>
   <p>The working class lost in Milan Glumac an energetic and hard worker for its liberation.</p>
   <p>A lasting memory of the indefatigable fighter and sufferer!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
