<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1913-07-30">July 30, 1913</date><title level="a">Knightly Deeds of Serbian Patriots</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1913-07-30">July 30, 1913</date><title level="a">KNIGHTLY DEEDS OF SERBIAN PATRIOTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Visiting Chicago these days is Vaclav Klofac, a Czech representative. Mr. Klofac was for a long time in the Balkans. He came to America to make himself better known among the Czechs of Chicago, telling about the glorious Balkan war.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday he came among the Serbians of Chicago's Northside, to give a talk at a meeting, where he was invited by the Serbian patriots.</p>
   <p>He related how he saw the war with his own eyes. How he was greeted and embraced by Serbian dignitaries; what heroes the Serbian officers are, and geniuses the Serbian generals. That minister Pasic outranks them all and how each Serbian should be proud of such a splendid statesman.</p>
   <p>Klofac spoke as a man who wants to flatter the audience and inflame national fanaticism.</p>
   <p>After Mr. Klofac finished his talk the platform was given to comrade V. Bornemissa, <pb facs="5420779_1_0153.jpg" n="2"/>editor of Narodni Glas (People's Voice). Conrad Bornemissa declared that he is wondering how Mr. Klofac is able to glorify the fratricidal Balkan war, which the genial Pasic helped to start. The Balkan war is not for the benefit of the people.</p>
   <p>Pasic took advantage of the war to speculate on the bourse and fill his pockets. Klofac also omitted to tell how the minister of war, with his drunken subordinates, gave over Serbian soldiers to firing squads and how Serbian peasants were beaten up.</p>
   <p>When comrade Bornenissa started to prove his talk by reading from Belgrad newspapers, the president of the Serbian Sokol Popovich jumped up and pushed comrade Bornemissa from the platform.</p>
   <p>After that comrade M. Polovina mounted the rostrum. But before he was able to talk the Serbian "patriots" him with blackjacks. The same procedure was used on comrade <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Both comrades received several injuries before they were thrown from the hall onto the sidewalk.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0154.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Czech representative Klofac was sitting quietly with a smile on his face when the Serbian "patriots" perpetrated said atrocities.</p>
   <p>That is the way freedom of speech is respected at "patriotic" meetings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
