<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title/>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0105</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0105.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>future ought to keep in closest touch with Millions of their own nationality who have emigrated from their native lands.</p>
   <p>He also recommends that children of foreign parents learn their mother tongue besides English, as they have an opportunity to know, at leant, two languages. We also thinks that children should accept all the good things their parents have brought from the old country - such as poetry, music, charming dream, high ideals, - and acquaint the American public with them. In that way we would accomplish a twofold purpose: our children would know two languages and to the richer in culture as well as language, and we would contribute to American civilization.</p>
   <p>Editor's comment: -- We are not always in accord with too much idealism as sometime the Englishman thinks himself superior and the German most enlightened - "uber alles." In this way we would tear down prejudice held by chauvinist Americans against foreigners. The good side of foreigners would we recognized as adding to cultural wealth. From all this higher culture can gradually develop.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0106.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Cotton was especially anxious to arouse listeners to enter a discussion, in which he succeeded. Some agreed with his views, others expressed their opposition. Some said that it is impossible to accept his philosophy because of the school system and American public opinion.</p>
   <p>A well-known leader among us, Mr. George Mamek, spoke briefly and sharply criticized the cruel materialistic philosophy of life of most Americans who think most of their dollars and forgot their souls. In that spirit they raise their children, and foreigners slowly become imbued with the same philosophy, especially those who have come here to improve their material condition. His speech was enthusiastically acclaimed by all.</p>
   <p>Many others participated in the discussion. A few questions were asked and satisfactory answers received.</p>
   <p>Eventually he introduced a resolution as follows:</p>
   <p>1. We believe a variety of peoples releases cultural creativity.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0107.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>2. We believe children should be brought up to be distinctive and different.</p>
   <p>3. We believe they should know at least two languages and two cultures.</p>
   <p>4. We believe organizations of foreign-born people are the best medium of cultural transformation.</p>
   <p>5. We believe children should join their parents in the foreign-born organizations.</p>
   <p>6. We believe this philosophy best for our children and our new country-America.</p>
   <p>This lecture surely must have been of benefit to all. It awakened many to think, and that, in itself, is big gain.</p>
   <p>We regret, only, that there were not more people at the lecture, especially young people, as it was mostly concerning youths and they could have profited by it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
