<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VI, No. 4,
<date when="1923-04-30">April 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The American Face of Communism</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0292</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0292.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VI, No. 4,
<date when="1923-04-30">April 30, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN FACE OF COMMUNISM</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two main lines can be discerned at the big Communist trial in Michigan: (1) This trial gave an opportunity to bring out Communism before the American people. (2) That trial showed for the first time in the United States that Communism was extolled by a typically American working man, a trades union fighter.</p>
   <p>The capitalistic press, together with the government, succeeded in linking the name of Wm. Z. Foster with Communism. He became known as such to the American working masses. A prospective juror, when asked what is a "Red," answered: "An ignorant foreigner." At the end of the trial, American public opinion had to admit that a "red" was nothing else than a fighter in American trade unions, armed with scientific Marxism and Communistic teachings.</p>
   <p>At the moment when Foster was put on trial as a Communist, Communism received American citizenship. Communism before bore the sign of an alien.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0293.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Before this trial cartoonists in capitalistic papers could put Communism under cover of the "Jew from the East" or "the ignorant alien hired by Russia," but at the trial in Michigan to the working class was revealed the true face of Communism, by the charming, typical character of the American worker, of an Irish-American union man, Wm. Z. Foster.</p>
   <p>The accusers baptized Communism as "American" when the prosecutor read from Foster's book that simple, masterful sentence: "To me it was not hard to understand the Russian revolution. That is our own movement, conducted to a logical conclusion."</p>
   <p>Wm. Z. Foster is a typical representative of American fighters of the working class. He pictured his life during the trial. That description was a real portrait of a working proletarian who, eager <pb facs="5420779_1_0294.jpg" n="3"/>to see everything, went from one trade to another. Slowly he worked himself up to become the leader of the working masses.</p>
   <p>He himself was always sincere and of a fighting spirit. Before the court, he could say with utmost assurance: "Since I started to work for the working class I tried to put the power of government in workers' hands."</p>
   <p>At the trial in Michigan we go through characteristic events. In front of our eyes the leader of American working masses is borne. It is a great historical trial. For the first time before American masses steps a man who is of the blood and flesh of the American working class, a worker himself, a leader of the masses, a union man, a revolutionary, a Marxist, a Communist.</p>
   <p>Foster is a representative of American labor hailed before the court.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0295.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A farmer jury will render the verdict. Here are presented three classes of American society: the worker, the capitalist, and the farmer class.</p>
   <p>The workman is accused; the capitalist is the accuser, the farmer will be judge.</p>
   <p>We do not yet know whether the worker will be convicted by a farmers' jury or not. But Foster in prison or out of prison will be recognized as the revolutionary leader. The Labor Party salutes in his name the red banner of revolution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
