<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VI, No. 3,
<date when="1913-01-02">Jan. 2, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">After the Congress</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VI, No. 3,
<date when="1913-01-02">Jan. 2, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">AFTER THE CONGRESS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Second Jugoslav Socialist Congress which adjourned in Milwaukee, Wis., last week, was a bright turning point in the history of our Socialist movement in America. During three and a half days this congress finished matters which had to be taken care of.</p>
   <p>We want to mention here just the main things which the congress accomplished to the satisfaction of all our comrades and making our enemies sorry.</p>
   <p>The new organization of the old Federation will permit more success in the future. This congress adopted complete centralization without division according to nationality, or division of financial means to separate central committees.</p>
   <p>The necessity of such strong united organization was felt everywhere. The realization of this is the guaranty that our Federation henceforth <pb facs="5420779_1_0358.jpg" n="2"/>will have successful progress.</p>
   <p>The second next important question was the question of our press. The best intentioned proposition was to merge both of our newspapers Radnicka Straza and Narodni Glas into a new newspaper printed in the Latin and cyrillic alphabets. But the congress decided that there will be no merger and the paper will be issued separately as before. This resolution is in accord with the progress of our Socialist movement.</p>
   <p>All the resolutions of the congress will be submitted to the members of the whole Federation for approval. We are certain they will meet acclaim by the members.</p>
   <p>The Second Jugoslav Socialist Congress clearly proved that our Federation has the moral vigor, consciousness and discipline necessary for such a great movement as the Socialist.</p>
   <p>There is much fighting spirit, much resoluteness, much good will for work in our ranks, Accordingly, our Federation stands not behind the <pb facs="5420779_1_0359.jpg" n="3"/>other legions of the Socialist Internationale.</p>
   <p>This Second Jugoslav Congress of America created by its work a far greater possibility for progress by eliminating things which prevented our advance. There is no doubt that our comrades will work with more and greater zeal for the awakening and encouragement of the weak and for the enlistment of new fighters in a big army, the aim of which is the liberation of the proletarians from capitalistic slavery.</p>
   <p>Long live the Jugoslav Socialist Federation of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
