<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title>,
<date when="1920-04-26">Apr. 26, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Latest in Patriots</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title>,
<date when="1920-04-26">Apr. 26, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE LATEST IN PATRIOTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago a new patriotic organization was formed, the "United Americans". The membership of this blue-blooded organization is confined to the wealtheir element, which believes that America must be kept safe for American--capitalists.</p>
   <p>We will mention just a few leaders of the organization, and that will suffice to give an idea of it. One of them is Otto Kuhn, of Kuhn, Loeb, and Company, a firm closely connected with J. P. Morgan and Company. This firm's business is concerned with railroads, money, and foreign investments.</p>
   <p>Kuhn is a true adherent of the American Constitution, which is flaunted by his class at every turn.</p>
   <p>There is also John H. Kirby of Houston, Texas, president of the wood manufacturers' organization and the inventor of the Ku Klux Klan, of which the aim <pb facs="5420779_1_0164.jpg" n="2"/>is to destroy workers' institutions.</p>
   <p>Finally there is H. H. Merrick, president of the Chicago Chamber of Commerce, well known by his speech about the strikers, in which he said, "Treat them rough." On the same day when he said that, four strikers were killed in Hammond, Indiana. That same Mr. Merrick was decorated not long ago by the self-styled Jugoslav crown prince Alexander. We do not know whether he was decorated for the speech in which he advised rough treatment for the strikers--of whom a great number were Jugoslav workers--or for something else of equal importance.</p>
   <p>The papers printed a picture of four heroes of the Jugoslav monarchy, Jurica Biankini, the famous Palandacic, the priest Uskokovic, and Dimic, handing to Mr. Merrick the decoration sent to him by Alexander.</p>
   <p>As we see, the organization "United Americans" consists of great capitalists. After they have forced their employees to join the organization, we shall hear <pb facs="5420779_1_0165.jpg" n="3"/>through the capitalistic papers that the American people support this society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
