<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VIII, No. 52,
<date when="1925-04-30">April 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Our Word to the American Working Class</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VIII, No. 52,
<date when="1925-04-30">April 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">OUR WORD TO THE AMERICAN WORKING CLASS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first of May, 1925, found the American imperialism as a governing power in questions of the world.</p>
   <p>Even Great Britain, the financial boss, is negotiating with Wall Street for a loan of $250,000,000</p>
   <p>The Dawes' plan bound Germany to the House of Morgan. France is suffocated by Morgan's loans.</p>
   <p>In every corner of the capitalist world, agents of American imperialism enlarge the activity of their bosses.</p>
   <p>On the Pacific coast the greatest fleet in history is assembled to attend maneuvers in the East. War is near.</p>
   <p>Two private soldiers,Crouch and Trumbull, were sentenced to 40 and 20 <pb facs="5420779_1_0277.jpg" n="2"/>years each. Their crime was that they organized a Communistic Youth's League and declared solidarity with the workers of Russia.</p>
   <p>In the United States the coal barons and owners of the textile industries wage war against coal miners and textile workers.</p>
   <p>Laws for criminal syndicalism are on the statutes of twenty-eight states. In Michigan, Idaho, Illinois, Pennsylvania, California and New York, workers are accused and jailed for syndicalism and subjected to deportation laws. The persecution of immigrant workers is continued, they are traced by an army of spies. The negro race is subjected to lynchings and beatings.</p>
   <p>In Europe there are bloody regimes. Military governments slaughter working men wholesale. In the colonies, working masses suffer under the strokes of imperialism.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0278.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Labor (Communist) Party of America invites the workers and poor farmers of the land to celebrate the First of May, the international mass holiday, so that they can organize in the fight against the reducing of wages, against lowering the standard of living, against theft and looting by bankers and capitalists, against the persecution of workers.</p>
   <p>The Labor Party invites the masses to fight the Dawes' plan, accepted for international slavery. We must join the struggle against white terror, which is aimed at workers and peasants of Asia, Africa and Europe.</p>
   <p>We must unite against the financial oligarchy of Wall Street. Join the ranks of millions of workers and farmers who fight against world capitalism.</p>
   <p>Only through a revolutionary struggle will capitalism be destroyed and the liberation of enslaved workers accomplished.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0279.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Long live the union of workers, farmers and colonial peoples! Long live the workers' and farmers' government!</p>
   <p>(Signed) Central Executive Committee of the Labor Party of America.</p>
   <p>The National Executive Committee of the Youth's Labor League of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
