<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. II, No. 26,
<date when="1919-09-29">Sept. 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Big Strike of Stell Workers in America</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. II, No. 26,
<date when="1919-09-29">Sept. 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">BIG STRIKE OF STELL WORKERS IN AMERICA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Monday, September 22, 1919, started a bitter straggle of the organized working classes against organized capital.</p>
   <p>The fight of the steel workers against the gigantic trust which sucks the blood out of hundred of thousands of workers in America. The struggle is hard because there are among the workers many foreigners whom they try to extricate from this struggle and make them slaves of American capitalism in the name of thankfulness, for the benevolence of American capitalists who are willing to exploit these workers.</p>
   <p>The capitalistic press started with lies to discredit the American worker. If there is nothing to report we are informed how workers return to work, how factories open, how workers are tired of strikes. All such news has the tendency of making the workers weak, to break up the strike.</p>
   <p>It seems here the people know the lies of the capitalist press and nobody believes them. Some paper will bring the news that this strike is <pb facs="5420779_1_0210.jpg" n="2"/>the work of Russian bolshevicks, but that turns out to be a lie.</p>
   <p>The organizers of this strike are without exception of Irish extraction, which can be judged by the names J. Fitzpatrick, E. J. Evans, J. E. McCadden, J. L. Beaghan, J. McGraig, J. Williams, H. Young, H. M. Runsee, De Young and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Foster. If there would be just one Russian name it would be a help to capitalistic lies. But because that is impossible, the papers report that bolshevick agitators appeared some place and were dispersed.</p>
   <p>One day we will hear that this strike is the work of the Irish Sinn Feinn. The number of strikers is not known. There are around 300,000 of them.</p>
   <p>If the trust insists on killing the workers as it was done in 1892 at Homestead and McKeesport, some other trades may join the strike and the other industries will be paralyzed. The coal miners of Pennsylvania, the seamen and railroad workers are ready to strike.</p>
   <p>Saturday, before the strike started, the Wisconsin Steel Company at South Chicago closed its doors. This was considered the real start. That same <pb facs="5420779_1_0211.jpg" n="3"/>day twenty-five organizers of the American Federation of Labor held a conference. They declared this will be a one-hundred-per-cent strike. In Waukegan the union secretary asked that one hundred workers be sworn in in order to keep order.</p>
   <p>The company swore in 300 sheriffs, whose duty it is to provoke the strikers and beat them up.</p>
   <p>In the State of Pennsylvania the companies swore in sheriffs by the thousands, who will be ready to kill each worker who is fighting for his interests.</p>
   <p>Statistics show that in all factories the number of strikers is 518,000. At South Chicago there are about twenty factories on strike, in Gary, Ind., six factories, at Indiana Harbor, Ind., eight factories, at East Chicago, three; Hegewish, two; Hammond. six.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
