<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 46,
<date when="1921-02-19">Feb. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Conference of the Unemployed</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 46,
<date when="1921-02-19">Feb. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE OF THE UNEMPLOYED</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, February the 6th, a conference was held of unemployed workers, or rather, delegates of different unions, to debate the Question of unemployment.</p>
   <p>The conference, which started at 10 A. M. and ended at 1 P. M. was attended by 200 delegates, who represented 84 trades, or 35,000 workers.</p>
   <p>The president of the Chicago Federation of Labor presided. In opening the meeting, he remarked that it looks bad for the Chicago trade unions if of 300 unions, only 84 sent their delegates to the conference.</p>
   <p>It looks as if these unions are either content with the situation or do not take interest in the question of unemployment. The committee worked for six weeks to prepare the conference but the response is very small.</p>
   <p>It was brought out that the cost of living fell 9%, while workers' wages <pb facs="5420779_1_0302.jpg" n="2"/>went down 20%</p>
   <p>In some instances wages were lowered from 7 to 4 dollars.</p>
   <p>The building laborers pointed out how renting profiteers are to blame for high rents.</p>
   <p>Between the contractors and banks exists a conspiracy to build up a great army of unemployed to destroy the unions.</p>
   <p>The bribed press supports the speculators and blames the workers for the unbearable situation in the country.</p>
   <p>The other unions brought similar complaints, declaring that never before were the unions exposed to such brutal attacks from capitalists.</p>
   <p>All delegates, who were class conscious, accentuated the fact that crises and unemployment repeat themselves under the capitalistic system, and that they will stay as long as the workers want to keep up the capitalistic <pb facs="5420779_1_0303.jpg" n="3"/>system of profit and exploitation.</p>
   <p>One of the delegates said: "Many times in this country we have had such a situation of unemployment. The workers became discontented, but as soon as they received anything and filled their stomachs, they forgot the past misery. These workers must be informed how to work in order to destroy this system.</p>
   <p>The discussion lasted three hours. Resolutions were read and adopted. In the adopted resolutions it was requested to start trade with Russia; to start with public works; to shorten working hours; to abolish profiteering. It was advocated to organize and to instruct workers to oppose open shops. The authorities have to be allowed to inspect books of companies which stop production; to obtain the reason why production was stopped. At the inspection of books, representatives of unions have to be present. The conference closed with the appeal to help the workers' press.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
