<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. IV. No. 2,
<date when="1910-12-30">Dec. 30, 1910</date>
<title level="a">Chicago and Milwaukee</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. IV. No. 2,
<date when="1910-12-30">Dec. 30, 1910</date>
<title level="a">CHICAGO AND MILWAUKEE</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is in Chicago a strike of garment workers. About 50,000 workers are in the fight for betterment of living conditions.</p>
   <p>The working class as a whole sympathizes with the striking working slaves, out of whose blood and sweat the capitalists did squeeze many, many millions.</p>
   <p>During the strike in Chicago a few workers were killed. The police beat up the workers. The police shoot the workers like wild beasts. The workers are handled by the police like mad dogs.</p>
   <p>That happens in Chicago. Because Chicago has a capitalistic administration. A capitalistic mayor, who is obliged to the capitalist class. The same can be said of police officials as well as policemen.</p>
   <p>Milwaukee shows another picture. In Milwaukee, too, there was a strike of garment workers.</p>
   <p>The first few days of the strike things looked serious. Chief of Police Janssen, held over from the previous administration, was showed to be the tool of capitalists. He wanted to emulate Chicago. But he made a mistake. The Mayor, Emil Seidel, is a Socialist, and instructed the Chief of Police not to bother about the strike of the garment workers.</p>
   <p>To the strikers Mayor Seidel said: As long as you do not disturb order; As long as you do not commit violence; the police has no right to interfere.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0220.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>You may say to a scab that he is a scab. "That is no crime."</p>
   <p>Mayor Seidel brought about a conference between manufacturers and workers. As long the bosses thought that the police will shoot and beat up the workers, they refused to reconcile.</p>
   <p>But when the manufacturers were convinced that the Mayor would not tolerate terror against the workers, they signed an agreement. The strike was closed. Nobody beat up the strikers. Nobody shot them, as it happens in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Is that not a nice example for the workers in all the cities of these United States of America?</p>
   <p>Imagine if Seidel were mayor of Chicago? How soon Schuettler, the Chief of Police, would be fired.</p>
   <p>In time the workers will become sane, and will elect the true servants of the people -- Socialists -- for public offices.</p>
   <p>But be sure, before that occurs, the police will smash many a skull.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
