<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1908-02-06">Feb. 6, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Forward! Appeal Forward! Stand Up! Croatian Workingmen of Chicago!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1908-02-06">Feb. 6, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Forward! APPEAL Forward! Stand Up! Croatian Workingmen of Chicago!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lack of work is extending, devastating workers' ranks like a monster.</p>
   <p>The man eaters - the capitalists - threw out their slaves into the snow and cold. In Chicago only there are over 150,000 jobless worker slaves.</p>
   <p>The misery is becoming bigger every day. The distress worse. The last saved nickels escape through the fingers. Thousands of workers cannot pay rent. Many workers are without coal and wood. Many a workers wanders driven by hunger and cold, like a dog without a master.</p>
   <p>Is that true? O it is, it is! It is even worse. Thousands of workers suffer from want, impossible to describe. Is there no way out of this distress? Can we not alleviate that misery? Can we not stop this wretchedness from growing?</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0236.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We can, we must. It has to be better.</p>
   <p>The Socialist Party of Chicago started a fight to abolish this evil. This fight must be supported by us Croatian workingmen.</p>
   <p>We too, with thousands of other workers have to exclaim and shout:</p>
   <p>Give us work! Give us bread! For that reason The Croatian Workingmen's meeting will be held Sunday, February the 9th, 1908 at 9 A.M. in the great hall of Fr. Mladic 587 Center Avenue for the benefit of unemployed workers.</p>
   <p>The Committee of the Croatian Workingmen's Union for Education and Politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
