<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VI. No. 43,
<date when="1913-10-08">Oct. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Scientific Exploitation</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VI. No. 43,
<date when="1913-10-08">Oct. 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">SCIENTIFIC EXPLOITATION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Socialist papers (Radnicka Straza wrote about it also) much is written about a so-called Taylor System. That is a way by which capitalists, through a scientific method, try to extract out of a worker as much as possible.</p>
   <p>All the motions of a worker are studied at any kind of work; all "unnecessary" motions must be eliminated so that every second motion will bring profit to the capitalist. Of course, the capacity of the worker is strained to the utmost, for that reason the capitalistic profit is growing bigger.</p>
   <p>This scientific method of exploitation is used in the United States Arsenal in Watertown, Mass. But a few days ago the workers of that Arsenal sent a petition to the Secretary of War to abolish that system because it is to the disadvantage of the worker and his health.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0336.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>General Grozier opposes the petition because, as he says, that system benefits the worker and the employer, in this case the government.</p>
   <p>The worker during the same working time earns 20 to 35% more than before; the government makes 60% more profit than as under the old system.</p>
   <p>It is clear from what we said that the employers may be satisfied with the new "scientific" system of exploitation. The worker gets more, but the employer's profit doubles.</p>
   <p>The extent of exploitation is much bigger.</p>
   <p>The Taylor System means an increase in the working man's exploitation;</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0337.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>weaker workers are not able to stand the strain at work, and those who are able worked, exhausted beyond the limit. The worker's strength is extracted sooner, he becomes incapable for work so much faster and is stricken with the poverty that becomes the let of any worker out of whom no more work can be extracted.</p>
   <p>Capitalism makes inventions to make bigger profits by skinning the workers. Therefore, the workers must organize and determinedly fight against capitalistic institutions which want to degrade the worker to the standard of an animal or machine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
