<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. II, No.37,
<date when="1919-12-15">Dec. 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Root of Evil</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. II, No.37,
<date when="1919-12-15">Dec. 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE ROOT OF EVIL</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American bourgeois press admits that the general situation is unfavorable in this country. Life left its normal tracks; on all sides there is disorder.</p>
   <p>But the bourgeois press is not in a dilemma to find the cause of all this evil. It says: "Agitators are to blame." That claims a press which backs profiteers and usurers.</p>
   <p>"The agitator," says the bourgeois press, "disturbs the lower classes of the population, appeals to their passions, while these classes on account of lack of education are an easy prey for them. The lower classes are infiltrated with hate to make them believe their fate is dependent on the capitalists."</p>
   <p>Since the bourgeois press thinks that it has found those who are guilty of the social chaos, then it is easy to find a remedy for that. That remedy is to deal harshly with the agitators. Take away the agitators and the discontent will be gone from among the masses.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0311.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We wonder if the bourgeois society is indeed so naive as to believe such arguments.</p>
   <p>If we admit that the larger part of the discontent is created by agitators, then the question arises: Whence came those agitators? There must exist causes which create them.</p>
   <p>Today every worker is an agitator because he has come to realize that he produces all and gets little from his production. The workers feel that they are poor and neglected, and that creates discontent among them.</p>
   <p>If society would be reasonably organized, if all would have employment, sufficient food, clothing, and other conveniences of life; if all would have opportunities for education in order to participate in cultural achievements, would it be possible for one agitator to disturb the people and create so much discontent?</p>
   <p>If agitators succeed in appealing to the masses, that is a sign that they speak about what the people feel, but the cause of which they are unable to find. Through the mouth of agitators the misery of the people is revealed.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0312.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If it is true that the agitators create disorder and discontent, there arises the question, Are the agitators to blame because people suffer from want and high cost of living? Did the agitators make thousands and thousands as usurers and profiteers who keep products off the markets and keep prices high? Are the agitators to blame that many things cost 500% more today than years ago?</p>
   <p>Did the agitators make the existing disparity in society, that in America are so many hungry, ill clothed people while at the same time there are 25,000 millionairs. Are the agitators to blame that there is in public life so much corruption?</p>
   <p>Reporters of capitalist newspapers ought to go to the housewives and ask them who make them discontent.</p>
   <p>Do agitators trouble them or are they troubled and discontented on account of high prices?</p>
   <p>These women will tell what makes them bitter. They will tell who is the real agitator and cause of disorder in society.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0313.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But this answer will not please the press of profiteers. That press dislikes to talk straight to the people about the economic situation. It is much easier to shield capitalists through newspaper columns and blame the agitators.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
