<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1915-11-03">Nov. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Answer to Those from Hicktown</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1915-11-03">Nov. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWER TO THOSE FROM HICKTOWN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In number 248 of Hrvatska Zastava, Dr. Biankini declared that my writings about Jugoslavia are "a psychopathological case." That is about all he can say in his defense. One of us is surely not of a sane mind. For that reason I propose a psychopathic examination.</p>
   <p>If Dr. Biankini is so sure of his brains, why doesn't he accept my challenge?</p>
   <p>Through ten issues of Radnicka Straza I brought out the facts that those gentlemen--Biankini and company--are either fools or paid by some government. Because I am convinced of that, I will not revoke it until said gentlemen do not prove it to the contrary.</p>
   <p>They are a bunch of characterless cattle who never did regard the interests of the people, but just their own. For their own sake they divided our people not only in nations but in provinces, in tribes, in factions. They created hate and dissension among the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0141.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last year we condemned German militarism in our paper. We predicted that the kaiser's barbaric attempts will cause the ruin of Germany, Austria-Hungary and Turkey.</p>
   <p>But we cannot commend this war or the imperialistic aims of the Allies either. In principle we are against any war politics, much less can we approve the foolish lies, chauvinistic hate, robbery, and anti-national politics caused and conducted by our Jugoslav dollar patriots in America.</p>
   <p>Dr. Biankini holds fast to his statement that this is a war between the German and Slavic races. For that reason he accuses me of being the friend of the Teuto-Magyars. That is an infamous slander, considering the sacrifices my family made for Serbia and Jugoslavia.</p>
   <p>Today, looking back at the graves of my beloved family, I want to speak as a Serbian or Jugoslav. I have to ask permission of Biankini and of his dogs--of men who, till yesterday, licked the plates of Austro-Hungarian consuls in <pb facs="5420779_1_0142.jpg" n="3"/>America, and by their spying, kept up the darkest reaction of the Austro-Hungarian oligarchy.</p>
   <p>Today, King Peter, his ministers, generals, and the rest of the bourgeoisie, pushed Serbia to the edge of ruin. The whole Slavic South is a shambles; the country vibrates from death groans, bloodshed cries to heaven, while Dr. Biankini and his dogs praise the allies all over America at banquets and parades.</p>
   <p>Forward, Serbian sons, if you have to die, die gloriously! Do not fear, Serbian sons, the allies will grant us liberty! Long live Jugoslavia! Long live King Peter and Tsar Nikolas.</p>
   <p>I have to be quiet. I have to approve any of their misdeeds. I have to hide their lies, I have to help their blunders, if I want that Biankini and company consider me an honest Serbian or, still better, a good Slav. Isn't that a fateful irony? Down with you!</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0143.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I fight for life and progress, not for the death and ruin of my people!</p>
   <p>B. R. Savic</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
