<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. III, No. 18,
<date when="1910-04-22">April 22, 1910</date>
<title level="a">From a Meeting in Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. III, No. 18,
<date when="1910-04-22">April 22, 1910</date>
<title level="a">FROM A MEETING IN CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday was held a great public meeting in Chicago, The important outline of same, brought all earnestly thinkingworkers together and the referees explained our socialistic standpoint toward the situation in the old country as well as here.</p>
   <p>The socialist idea penetrates little by little in the workers' ranks. The best proof of it is thesocialist victory in Milwaukee.</p>
   <p>Mr. Maston concluded that the only way to liberate the working class consists in spreading class consciousness and leading workers in political and economical organizations of the socialist type. (Applause)</p>
   <p>Mr. Milan Glumac concluded his report saying: salvation and progress of all the Jugoslav peoples depend on the close union and concerted fight of the Jugoslav proletarians organized in a revolutionary international democracy (Stormy applause).</p>
   <p>Comrade Ivan Masten referred to the Socialist movement in America. He spoke about difficulties and hardships which the said movement has to overcome on one side from the ruling capitalistic class, which is bound under all circumstances to break that movement, oppressing the workers newspapers, taking away rights from workers, which rights the workers do have in all other countries, that is the right: to strike and of boycott. From the other side difficulties arise from workers themselves, who are not aware of the importance of class <pb facs="5420779_1_0398.jpg" n="2"/>struggle, who are misled by different false "leaders." These leaders are in contact and in the service of capitalists and this is the main cause for lack of success to gain economical advantages by the laboring class. Nevertheless there are signs of going forward by the laboring class.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
