<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. II, No. 16,
<date when="1919-07-21">July 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Fear of Unions</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. II, No. 16,
<date when="1919-07-21">July 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FEAR OF UNIONS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our misled Jugoslav workers fear unions. With contempt do they look upon people who are organized politically or economically. From what one hears they distrust unions even more than the companies by which they are employed. They agree with the company in everything because they are not independent. The company would rather close the factory than recognize the union. The action of the company can be understood but not the inaction of the workers.</p>
   <p>On July 14 a few strikers came with an organizer to a factory to explain to the workers the need of organization. The misled and uncomprehending workers commented on this proceedure in the same spirit as the employers, saying, "Why are these bolshevicks here to disturbe us peaceful workers." One of them stated: "The union wants us to work only eight hours. Who is able to stop me from working longer if I so desire? If I work longer hours I earn more. The union wants dues to be paid but wants us to work shorter hours."</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This false impression prevents many workers from finding out the truth. The union, it is true, wants shorter hours, but at the same time it wants an increased pay. The union wants more humane working conditions for the workers.</p>
   <p>Many of the poor simpletons make the unions responsible for the high cost of living. They do not understand why the working class must rise nor why it wants a change of living conditions.</p>
   <p>Indeed, the misled, unorganized workers are helpers of the capitalistic class. They are the ones who make the struggle hard and prevent its fulfillment. They do not read the workers' press but read patriotic newspapers that write for the benefit of capitalistic companies.</p>
   <p>Among that kind of newspapers belong those Jugoslav newspapers that like a dollar more than they do their people. They preach the principle of "everybody for his own kin," when they need help from the working class. If the worker needs them, then they forget their own "kin" and work for the companies. Jugoslav workers, leave the patriotic press. You belong among workers. Be smart at least. Organize! Help humanity to freedom!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
