<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1914-11-18">Nov. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Divorces</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0082</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0082.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1914-11-18">Nov. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">DIVORCES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The courts of Chicago are occupied daily with a very serious problem--the divorce evil. The chief reason for so many divorces in America is that people consider marriage a contractual relation, which endures just as long as the two parties care to stick it out. In most cases, no deep feeling unites the couple; no attempt is made to know and understand each other, and thus provide the foundation for a lasting union.</p>
   <p>The notion that the husband has to support his wife is a legal right to which the latter clings tenaciously. If the husband is unemployed, the wife will seldom make sacrifices: she insists on her right to be supported. This egotism repels many a husband; he loses his illusions about married life, and leaves home because he sees in his wife, not a friend but a partner who sticks with him as long as life is agreeable. Marriage in America today is not a union of souls; it is a matter of "joining hands," and for that reason the marriage tie <pb facs="5420779_1_0083.jpg" n="2"/>is very loose, so that divorce results easily.</p>
   <p>Statistics show that most divorces are granted in the first years of married life; divorce is considerably less frequent in subsequent years. Often, the children are the tie that keeps their parents together.</p>
   <p>The great number of divorces in America is an evil that is rooted in the present-day [economic] system. The worker is a slave to need and to economic conditions. This oppresses his spirit; it is difficult to be in love when one is hungry. When a woman is driven into marriage by hunger, she cannot choose:she will accept anybody able to provide her with a better life, a life free from worry. The worker's lack of security is also a cause of marital strife,and he is driven to alcohol instead of endeavoring to improve his lot.</p>
   <p>The courts and the moralists deplore the large number of divorces, but do nothing to prevent them, to change the capitalistic system, the principal source of this evil.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0084.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Workers! Fight to save your family! Fight to save the future generations!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
