<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 15,
<date when="1937-04-14">April 14, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">John L. Lewis, Leader of American Workers</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 15,
<date when="1937-04-14">April 14, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN L. LEWIS, LEADER OF AMERICAN WORKERS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I will try to make it clear to the leaders of the Zajednicar who is John L. Lewis, director of the Committee for Industrial Organization.</p>
   <p>John L. Lewis was born in Iowa, in a small mining town of Luces, Lucas Country, 60 miles south of Des Moines.</p>
   <p>His father came to America from Wales and started to work at Lucas in 1880, for the White Fuel Company.</p>
   <p>At that time coal was screened at a big lose for the workers because the screans were too wide.</p>
   <p>John's father, Thomas Lewis, called on the workers to strike. The workers responded immediately. For that Thomas Lewis was put on the black list of the coal companies and could not get work after the strike in Lucas county. Thomas Lewis moved with his family to folfax, Iowa, and secured <pb facs="5420779_1_0187.jpg" n="2"/>a position as night watchman, at the same time trying to get employed as a miner. He went to the mine but was dismissed as soon as his radical record became known. In 1889 Thomas Lewis requested collective bargaining for the workers and was forced to move to Des Moines and was put to jail there. This was the first lesson for John L. Lewis as to what happens to a worker who insists an his right.</p>
   <p>John started to go to public school in Des Moines, after that to junior high school. While John went to school for eight years, his father's name was taken from the black lists and the family returned to Lucas County.</p>
   <p>John L. Lewis, who was 16 years then, worked with his father in the mine.</p>
   <p>After getting older he felt and understood the sufferings of his blacklisted father. He left the mine to engage in business and continue studying. He was also theater manager and manager of the local baseball team.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0188.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In his 27th year he decided to enter politics and run for mayor but with no success. The same year Lewis married a school teacher, Myrtle Edith Bell. In 1908 they left Iowa, came to Illinois, and John L. Lewis became active in labor movements. He became agent for the Mine Workers of America, the American Federation of Labor. He also became vicepresident of the United Mine Workers of America and in 1920 their president.</p>
   <p>He severed connection with the American Federation of Labor and organized the Committee for Industrial Organization (OIC).</p>
   <p>Croatians and the rest of Jugoslavs, if you are not in a union, join at once because that is the only salvation for the working class. There is better opportunity to join a union today than ever before. President Roosevelt is on the side of the workers. Your organizations, like the Croatian Fraternal Union, is and up for you. You are advised by your political organization to join unions.</p>
   <p>The newspapers write and instruct you for your benefit. Why then be <pb facs="5420779_1_0189.jpg" n="4"/>afraid to join a union?</p>
   <p>The Zajednicar has touched the question of why if organizations are injurious for the workers, why are the employers against them?</p>
   <p>There are some employers who pay more than others, but they do not want to recognize a union. Why? Because they are able to drop you from the payroll at any time. If you are in a union they cannot do it without good reason.</p>
   <p>For these facts join the union, which will represent you and your family in hard times.</p>
   <p>Kazimir Kruzich</p>
   <p>Vice President Local 2485.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
