<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title>,
<date when="1920-04">Apr. , 1920</date>.
<title level="a">And </title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.E.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title>,
<date when="1920-04">Apr. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, 1920</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> AND <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From statistics of the year 1918 we see that out of 18 American-born citizens one is a criminal. Among the residents who were born abroad, comes one criminal out of 66 persons.</p>
   <p>If we would count as criminal any common law breaker, the number of criminals among born Americans would be still bigger.</p>
   <p>Indeed, if we watch the newspapers, we will see that leading in crime are Americans born here and not immigrants.</p>
   <p>If these facts were clear to the Americans they would renounce their hate and contempt against foreigners." From a pure scientific standpoint, we all are foreigners, because our residence on earth is very short. Why then not try to live this short life in brotherhood and love, why be divided in classes, nations, races, besides in an artificial division, which is expressed between American-born and foreigner.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0128.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This would not happen but for the plutocrats who want to distract the attention of the people from misery and injustice by calling their attention to the exaggerated dangers coming from foreigners.</p>
   <p>There is no reasonable cause why Americans ought to have contempt for foreigners. They also, or their forebears, were foreigners once. Besides, the foreigners elevated this country to prosperity. Foreigners do the heavy work today. If they would leave for their hope country abruptly, there would be a crisis here.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, the foreigners are the most peace-loving element in this country, more peaceful than the Americans themselves. This is shown by said statistics of crimes.</p>
   <p>The situation in America is not brilliant. That is understood by deciding factors, who are afraid of reaction and resistance. They have many reasons to explain the situation, for which they try to blame the Socialists, the communists and foreigners, but the robbers from Wall Street are never blamed for anything.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
