<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 150,
<date when="1924-12-16">Dec. 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Who Was Gompers?</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 150,
<date when="1924-12-16">Dec. 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">WHO WAS GOMPERS?</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to news dispatches Samuel Gompers died December 13, 1924, at 4:30 A. M.</p>
   <p>Gompers was president of the American Federation of Labor for 44 years. By right he was one of its first founders. There is no doubt that he had organizing talent. His aim to organize separate unions by trades was fulfilled. From its start the A. F. of L. grew. But Gompers was by his education, by his nature, by his social position,not only a conservative but a reactionary.</p>
   <p>His organizing talent was not for the creation of militant workingmen's unions to lead an uncompromising class struggle, but it was for cooperation, like his colleagues Legien, Thomas, McDonald, etc.</p>
   <p>Gompers hated Socialism as well as all progressive ideas. Also he was the greatest enemy of Communism. No led a bitter fight against industrial unionism when it became a necessity in this country after the great <pb facs="5420779_1_0171.jpg" n="2"/>industrial expansion of America. He also hated those who wanted to make the reactionary A. F. of L. a tool of a class conscious struggle in the labor movement. Among them was Comrade W. Foster, one of the greatest enemies of Gompers.</p>
   <p>During the war Gompers was with Wilson and his fourteen points, the most faithful servant of capitalism.</p>
   <p>If there was a strike, Gompers was the first to end this strike in favor of capitalism. Through his efforts many strikes were lost, many workers' lives sacrificed on the altar of Wall Street. Gompers was even against the name of Socialism. He watched to see if there was any danger to capitalism in order to warn it in time. For the same reason he went to Mexico. Gompers did not travel there for the benefit of the working class, but to protect the interests of American capitalists who were after the natural wealth of Mexico.</p>
   <p>Gompers was born in a capitalistic society and reared there; in working men's ranks he was a faithful servant of capital; for it he lived, <pb facs="5420779_1_0172.jpg" n="3"/>traveled and served to the end.</p>
   <p>The American capitalists will mourn Gompers because another Gompers will not be born in these times. Many working men will mourn Gompers because they think of him as a great leader.</p>
   <p>The class conscious worker will not grieve Gompers, knowing that he was against revolution and the liberation of the working class.</p>
   <p>The reactionaries will clamor: Hail to the memory of Gompers; the revolutionaries: Hail to the death of Gompersism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
