<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title>,
<date when="1920-04-26">April 26, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The </title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title>,
<date when="1920-04-26">April 26, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago a new patriotic organization was formed, the United Americans. The membership of this blue-blooded organization consists of rich elements only, who believe that America must be kept secure for American capitalists. We will mention just a few leaders of this organization. That will suffice to get an idea of it.</p>
   <p>There is mentioned Otto Main, of Kahn and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Company, which is in close connection with J. P. Morgan Company. This company controls railroads, money, and foreign connections.</p>
   <p>Kahn is a true follower of the American Constitution, which is flaunted by his class at each step. There is John H. Kirby, from Houston, Tex, president of wood manufacturers, who founded a Ku-Klux, which has to destroy <pb facs="5420779_1_0125.jpg" n="2"/>workers' institutions.</p>
   <p>Finally, where is H. H. Merrick, president of the Chicago Chamber of Commerce, well known from his speech about the strikers, in which he said: "Treat them rough." The same day he said that, four strikers were killed in Hammond, Ind. That same Mr. Merrick  was decorated not long ago by the self-styled Jugoslav Crown Prince, Alexander.</p>
   <p>We do not know whether he was decorated for the speech in which he counseled to treat the strikers brutally, of whom a great part were Jugoslav workers, or for something equally important.</p>
   <p>The papers brought a picture where it was shown how four heroes of the Jugoslav monarchy, Juricabiankini, the famous Palandacic, the priest Uskokovic and Dimic, are handing over to Mr. Merrick the decoration, sent to him by Alexander.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0126.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As we see, the organization United Americans consists of great capitalists. After they will force their employees to join this organization, we will hear, through capitalistic papers, that the American people supports said organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
