<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VI, No. 28,
<date when="1923-08-28">August 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Red Danger in America</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VI, No. 28,
<date when="1923-08-28">August 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">RED DANGER IN AMERICA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About the 'red danger' in America and talks of revolution that we can read in all capitalist newspapers today. Editors of the bourgeoisie have utopian ideas of how to counteract this danger in America, to preserve life, liberty and happiness in this country, which means private ownership.</p>
   <p>A proverb says that "where there is smoke there is fire." Why comes smoke down capitalistic chimneys?</p>
   <p>The cause is that political life in America has changed in the past few years. The working class is lined up against the government now, while before the government was considered as something holy, not to be touched.</p>
   <p>Farmers are on the border of revolt, representatives of the middle class are up against the imperialistic policies of plutocracy. The main thing is that revolutionary workers are not split and isolated today, but are consolidated in dense workers' world organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0291.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today is the most opportune time to spread ideas about Communism among American workers.</p>
   <p>Old tales that the American worker cannot grasp the teachings of Communism are contradicted. Revolutionary ideas are not a national problem, but international and acute under present conditions and everywhere there is misery and exploitation. The American proletarian showed in many instances that he is willing to fight for the workers' cause, the way he sees fit. He defended with gun in hand his workingmen's organizations, as it was in West Virginia and other places. In critical moments we are sure, he will be in his place. The Labor Party of America has the task of imbuing dissatisfaction in American workers and farmers. To lead both in the fight for power, the dissolution of the present order of society and the creation of a workingman's regime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
