<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1928-10-17">Oct. 17, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Youth and Election</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1928-10-17">Oct. 17, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">YOUTH AND ELECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What is the position of the young workers in industry today? We find that we have eleven million young workers in industry and the number is increasing. The young workers are the most exploited section of the working class. The average wage of a young worker is about $13 weekly. Working conditions are terrible and particularly so in the textile mills and chemical works. No attempt except that made by the young workers of the Young Workers (Communist) League, has ever been made to organize these young workers for a fight for full economic and political rights. What are full economic rights? Membership in trade unions, equal pay for equal work, etc. Only recently has their been a tendency among young workers to fight for their rights in the political and economic fields. That is the position of the capitalist parties in regard to this question. They disregard this question entirely. Not in any of their platforms have they even hinted at this question. Not one of the capitalist parties desires to have the youth vote or receive full economic rights.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0191.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is no surprise, for we realize very well that all capitalist parties, the Socialist, Republican and Democratic, are the parties of big business and they are not for less exploitation, but insist on more.</p>
   <p>What had the Workers (Communist) Party and the Young Workers (Communist) League to say on this important question confronting the young workers?</p>
   <p>(1) No economic discrimination! All young workers must be permitted a membership in trade unions on an equal basis with the adult members. Equal pay for equal work!</p>
   <p>(2) For young workers a six-hour day, five day, five days a week.</p>
   <p>(3) Youth protection. Abolition of night work, and work in dangerous occupations. Establishment of a system for accident compensation and to have the young workers regulate it.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0192.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>(4) Two dollars a day, state benefits, for all unemployed young workers, under trade union supervision. Millions are today walking the streets unemployed. These are but a few of our demands. We do not contemplate, however, the joys of these improvements, even though a Communist gets a majority vote, because the capitalists will exercise every means to crush that power. Therefore, capitalism must be completely wiped out before either youth or adult can expect those things which rightfully belong to them.</p>
   <p>Join our ranks in a fight for the immediate needs of the young workers and for the fight against capitalism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
