<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. IX, No. 85,
<date when="1926-06-09">June 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Organization of a Workers' Club in Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. IX, No. 85,
<date when="1926-06-09">June 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZATION OF A WORKERS' CLUB IN CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The organization of progressive workers' clubs is in order in all settlements where a greater number of our people live. Such organizations are existing among other nationalities because there is felt a necessity for the enlightenment of the working class.</p>
   <p>The capitalist class has its different clubs and organizations in all towns, and gathers in them youths and workers, because such clubs are a good instrument in capitalistic hands to teach workers bourgeois ideas. To make them for a certain length of time not dangerous for the capitalist order, which is based on extortion, exploitation and oppression of the working class, such is the basic purpose of bourgeois clubs.</p>
   <p>The workers until lately did not have their own clubs to gather their members and educate them. That means to educate them in the ideology of the working class.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0269.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The progressive workers of Chicago took steps to organize in Chicago a working men's club, which will take into its circle a greater number of workers and improve their culture. For that purpose a meeting was called to make preparations for the organization of such a club. The chief speaker at that meeting, Comrade Zinic, explained the economic and cultural necessity of the workers to have such a club.</p>
   <p>At the meeting, a committee of eleven was elected to organize a great club, while all those interested would help the committee in their task. After the preparations are made, the club will begin to function.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
