<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. VIII, No. 34,
<date when="1931-03-04">March 4, 1931</date>
<title level="a">Fascism on Clybourn Avenue</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. VIII, No. 34,
<date when="1931-03-04">March 4, 1931</date>
<title level="a">FASCISM ON CLYBOURN AVENUE</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the inception of the Jugoslav Workers' Council and since the council sent their famous invitation to all cultural organizations of Jugoslav origin, for the purpose of suppressing black reaction in this country -which of late is rapidly spreading by an effort of our reactionary element--The Serbian Fascist element on Clybourn avenue raised a fuss against Jugoslav Socialist organization No. 20, especially comrade Kokotovic, who signed the invitation. When some Serbian lodges received the invitation and read it to their members a few members jumped to their feet and started to curse and swear.</p>
   <p>They attacked all who are not in accord with dictatorship in Jugoslavia or are opposed to the consul, the priest, or any other chauvinist element.</p>
   <p>In some lodges they resorted even to fist fights. Especially arrogant were the World's War heroes who fought for the democracy and freedom of the dear old fatherland but after freedom was saved they had to leave it and come to <pb facs="5420779_1_0240.jpg" n="2"/>America, because their dear old fatherland wouldn't give them bread and now they are loafing here with no job, no bread, nor health, which they lost in war.</p>
   <p>They think that every person who dares to oppose the regime is a traitor.</p>
   <p>We Socialists don't believe in any dictator. We are for liberty and un-spoiled democracy. While we Jugoslav Socialists, during the Austrian rule, held protest meetings against Austrian tyranny, we were good then. When there are protests against Italian fascism and their oppression and crime against our people of Austria and Julian Venetia, that is also good. When you needed our support for strikes that was good. too. But when we dared to raise our voice of protest against military tyranny in Jugoslavia, against the ignorant type of plotters in America, then we are the traitors of our own people.</p>
   <p>They want to take away our right to lead in the struggle of our oppressed people in the old country.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0241.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Serbian people are by nature troublesome and radical; they had five hundred years of experience under the Turkish yoke and the majority is against dictatorships, although there are expeptions. There are a few districts in Croatian and Bosnian soil that can be classed among the reactionary. Those districts supply most of our reactionary and ignorant element on this side of the Atlantic.</p>
   <p>But our task, as in the past, will be to open our youth's eyes so they will not remain eternal slaves to capitalism.</p>
   <p>Clybourn Avenue Socialist.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
