<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1928-08-23">August 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">For Justice and Humanity (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1928-08-23">August 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">FOR JUSTICE AND HUMANITY (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This euphonious motto, which was used in the 18th century by the then new bourgeois against the feudal system, also serves the capitalist politicians of today. Just think: who dares rise against justice and humanity with this motto, - which is a good wish to all mankind, in mind! So thought the bourgeois politicians of the 18th century when they led the bourgeois revolution against the feudal lords; and capitalist politicians of today think likewise.</p>
   <p>This same motto has been raised by our intelligentsia in this country ever since the death of St. Radic (a Croatian peasant party leader who was shot by Punisa Pacic, Serbian nationalist, in the Jugoslav parliament in July 20, 1928, in Belgrade).</p>
   <p>And under which sentiment they are trying to form their reactionary and chauvinistic circle, the immigrant workers. Regardless of how melodious their motto is, and how much our upper crust boast that it made St. Radic <pb facs="5420779_1_0253.jpg" n="2"/>a genius, we openly declare that behind this phrase deceit and confusion are hiding. Justice! For whom? Is it justice for workers and peasants or justice for capitalists and landlords? Before we Jugoslav workers follow this confusing motto, they should ask the foregoing questions. Justice is an abstract word. What is justice for one class is injustice for another. That which is justice for capitalists and landlords is injustice for peasants and workers, and vice versa. When one baron or lord owns more land than ten villages together that is justice for the owners, but great injustice for the peasants.</p>
   <p>We can prove facts and write volumes on the question whether justice is a relative term in a class society; and the word justice is a dream with which servants of the capitalist class want to confuse and poison the minds of workers and peasants.</p>
   <p>Humanity! An abstract word again! At a recent gathering of about 300, in commemoration of the death of the late St. Radic,here in Chicago one of the speakers said Radic's greatest service and genius was due to <pb facs="5420779_1_0254.jpg" n="3"/>the fact that he always had a longing in his heart to emancipate humanity. What Radic carried in his heart we don't know. We know only that of which he spoke and what he did, and from this basis we make our deductions and form our conclusions. But if for the sake of argument we allow that he did, then what? We know know that mankind is divided into two classes: poor and rich, exploiters and exploited, tyrants and serfs. Longing for the emancipation of all humanity doesn't mean emancipation of only those who need freedom and are struggling for it. The capitalists and landlords have no use for the emancipation of humanity. They are not enslaved nor exploited, but they are that part of mankind which lives off the great majority of mankind: the workers and peasants. These are the ones that wish for their class to be relieved of the yoke of capitalist and land-lord slavery. We Communists, however, think differently than Mr. Radic and his followers. We workers demand freedom for workers and peasants, from Belgrade's bloody regime, and freedom for all workers of the world who are enslaved by the capitalist tyrant system. This is in plainly spoken language what the working class should undertake. We don't call our program a motto as some pseudo emancipators do, who, under their various-cloaked phrases and words, such as justice, equality, freedom, humanity, etc., hide their policy of class serfdom for the working people.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0255.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But emancipation from the capitalist regime will not come with magic words (hocus pocus), as our pseudo-intelligentsia want us to believe. Emancipation for the enslaved class, workers and peasants, colonial people and various national minorities, comes by way of organization, relentless struggle against capitalist tyrants and their cause. There is no other way out but to fight, and we contend that various patriots and chauvinists who come to the workers with their words of justice and humanity, are interpreting justice in the interest of the capitalists' and landlords' class, under misleading phraseology.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
