<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. V, No. 44,
<date when="1912-10-17">Oct. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">For Whom Will You Vote?</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. V, No. 44,
<date when="1912-10-17">Oct. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">FOR WHOM WILL YOU VOTE?</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Workers, do you not feel each day how your backs bend more and more? How your bones are getting tired, your bodies weaker? Think over the condition in which you live. Each day you have to run to the factory or shop, or wherever on the ground or underground you work and toil like worms.</p>
   <p>From dawn to night you work for miserable wages. Behind your backs all the time stands a capitalist or some of his helpers, who bawl: "Work, toil faster, faster!"</p>
   <p>They are never satisfied. If you were able to work 24 hours a day, not asking for any wages, then, brothers, you would be considered the best workers in the world. But if you say to them: "We also are human beings, we want rest, take a walk, have some fresh air or light. We want to spend some time with our families, wives, children, sweethearts, or we want to be with our comrades," then the capitalist exclaims: "Out you go from my factory, you are lazy, you are not workers for me."</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0366.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If you ask for more pay in order to buy proper food or decent clothes for yourselves, your wives or children; or to buy presents for your girls, or to rent healthy, airy flats, there you have the capitalist crying: "You are full of haughtiness, out you go again." The capitalist is only concerned about giving you the smallest pay possible, that you let him alone to enable him to amass his fortune and to work as little as possible or not at all, that his wife is dressed well, that his children have a carefree life Just like himself, while you slave, starve and suffer.</p>
   <p>All these things, oh workers, are done at your cost, by your permission, because you are fools; because you believe that he is not able to shorten your working time; because you believe that he pays you enough; because you believe that all must be just like it is, and not different; because you, yourselves, give him the power to be your boss, and because when elections come you vote for the capitalistic candidate, you make a capitalist a president, you put a capitalist in as vice-president, you put a capitalist in as congressman, as governor, as judge, in a word, as bosses.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0367.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Socialist Party is the only one which says that the fortune of the rich is your work, your toil; his thousands are your money which he stole from you. The Socialist Party is the only one which says that you, too, are a human being; that you, too, have to live and should get all that you earn; that you are cheated and robbed.</p>
   <p>The Socialist Party only is able to work for the benefit of the workers because it is the workers' party. For that reason, workers, do your duty on election day and vote Socialist, for the workers' candidates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
