<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1928-08-16">Aug. 16, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">What to Expect from the Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0089</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0089.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1928-08-16">Aug. 16, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT TO EXPECT FROM THE CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great majority of parents show a selfish feeling when they expect their children to support them some day and repay with material things that which they did for them as parents.</p>
   <p>These feelings are natural and well understood, but the irony is that when the children grow up they rarely re-imburse their parents this way. Every father and mother has an indispensable responsibility towards their children, whom they brought into the world. That responsibility requires that the children be fed and raised the best way possible.</p>
   <p>Most care should be directed toward the development in children of love for their parents. And where parental love exists, natural consequences may be expressed in the material assistance. But where there is no parental love, one can not expect much from the child during the time that one is unable to work.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0090.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In place of all this, the best method is to develop nobleness, unselfishness and sobriety; respect for all and all other virtues, and when this takes root in the child's heart, then it is almost sure that the child will be good when it grows up.</p>
   <p>The child should also be asked to do some work occasionally, so that it does not become lazy, for then he would be useless for himself and others.</p>
   <p>Do all you can for your child. Clothe him and feed him. Send him to school, and care for him in every respect. Under normal circumstances this will bring good results. But if it happens otherwise, you may be reasonably sure that you did the best you could and your conscience will be free.</p>
   <p>If the child is sensible and good, he will know later how to appreciate <pb facs="5420779_1_0091.jpg" n="3"/>all that his parents did for him. Then be will know his duty and will repay, out of love for them, out of natural and sincere gratitude, not because society demands it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
