<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. Iv, No. 12,
<date when="1921-06-25">June 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Evident Partiality</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. Iv, No. 12,
<date when="1921-06-25">June 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">EVIDENT PARTIALITY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It seems that the United States Supreme Court is a great protector of the capitalistic system.</p>
   <p>Whenever capitalists encounter trouble they believe justice in the Supreme Court will come to their relief. In many cases that happens.</p>
   <p>Much was written about how Senator Truman H. Newberry by corruption and graft came to be elected to the Senate. He spent $100,000 for his election, buying votes and election officials.</p>
   <p>Afterwards he was indicted and sentenced to two years in prison and $10,000 fine.</p>
   <p>A monied man convicted of a crime can usually stay out of prison for an indefinite period.</p>
   <p>Senator Newberry appealed to the higher courts. His case came before the <pb facs="5420779_1_0299.jpg" n="2"/>United States Supreme Court and he was freed. The reason was some lack of formalities by the lower courts.</p>
   <p>Newberry goes to the Senate again, although everybody knows what corruption and felonies he committed. And yet the Supreme Court ruled that his sentence is unconstitutional. Not to say more, this was a sure proof of partiality by the Supreme Court.</p>
   <p>But let us see the other side. In America many are in prison who did not offend the Constitution, but only performed their civic duties. They reach a few hundreds, and they are in prison for their strong beliefs during the war. Their cases do not depend on formalities, but on clear words of the Constitution, which gives them the right for freedom of thought and speech.</p>
   <p>Yet, today Tom Mooney is in prison, although there is no evidence that he committed a crime. Some witnesses repudiated their testimony because they were paid to testify against him. Mooney is still in prison. The Supreme Court never reached a decision on that unjust sentence. If there <pb facs="5420779_1_0300.jpg" n="3"/>is a millionaire in question, then justice just blinks, not to the right but to help wrong.</p>
   <p>The times are such that neither the Supreme Court nor Newberry will be ashamed for said decision.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
