<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 72,
<date when="1924-06-17">June 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Struggle and Death</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 72,
<date when="1924-06-17">June 17, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">STRUGGLE AND DEATH</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the World War we can say that we entered a new social epoch, an epoch of clashes between the class of exploiters and exploited. The World War, like a giant machine, plowed the world over.</p>
   <p>Instead of the old bourgeois democracy, fascism, the power of black shirts, raises its head and submits the workers to the interest of capitalism. The workers went to war and during four years fought in the belief that they were fighting for humanity's progress, a better life, a more perfect world, but after they returned to their destroyed homes they discovered the enormous fraud perpetrated on them.</p>
   <p>In Europe terror reigns alongside misery and hunger. Human imagination is not able to think about the difficulties which the working class suffer as a result of the politics of idiotic rulers.</p>
   <p>The situation in America is not much better. The fight for an open shop has been going on for years, and the employers openly try to fasten the <pb facs="5420779_1_0288.jpg" n="2"/>yoke of slavery on the workingman's neck.</p>
   <p>"Selective immigration" became a law. The workers coming here will be fingerprinted and photographed, and under police surveillance. That is the first step of plutocracy to change the law so that all foreign workers will have to register with the police and report, like criminals, at certain times. These are measures of the greatest reaction.</p>
   <p>What will be the outcome of this? We see the outcome in the common fight of foreign and native-born workers against capitalistic reaction; in a bond between workers and farmers against capitalistic domination. The workers must join workers' unions as the first trenches of defence. They have to join the political struggle of the working class to get their rights.</p>
   <p>The Farmer-Labor Party is getting organized and every workers' organization, be it political, economic, benevolent, athletic or cultural, must join this movement for an independent political action for the <pb facs="5420779_1_0289.jpg" n="3"/>defence of workers and farmers. If the by-laws of some of the organizations do not approve of such a struggle, they must be changed in favor of it.</p>
   <p>The only salvation of the workers is struggle and fight, not lamentations. The slogan must be: Men fight; cowards lament - beasts of burden suffer silently."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
