<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1928-07-26">July 26, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Read to Learn</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_1_0043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_1_0043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1928-07-26">July 26, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">READ TO LEARN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If you are so unfortunate as to think that you know everything or that you need not, or that you cannot absorb any more knowledge, see to it that you free yourself from these thoughts.</p>
   <p>Some people read to learn, to develop their minds, to gain knowledge to guide their work and life. Others read as a habit or to amuse themselves. One who looks for amusement in a newspaper or a book will not learn, and one who reads because he sees others read, loses his time. Only those are on the right track who read to learn something.</p>
   <p>The first step toward a profitable reading is curiosity. This has to be satisfied. By satisfying our ouriosity we learn and gain new thoughts. By studying various things we become richer in mind. One needs not know very much, needs not be a great thinker or a student to be able to judge the life and things with which he comes in contact. Enough is to have a will and to be able to think. If you don't take a book or a newspaper with a prejudiced mind, only to see the views of your opponent without <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> or hate, you will profit by the reading. In other words, the purpose of reading is not <pb facs="5420779_1_0044.jpg" n="2"/>fault-finding, but the sincere wish to find material for new thought.</p>
   <p>You will not get far in your education if you become a prey of some foolishness and believe in it blindly and firmly.</p>
   <p>Read to know, to learn and gain material for thought: to realize and enjoy your spiritual growth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
