<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-10-23">Oct. 23, 1908</date><title level="a">The Presidential Election</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1026</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1026.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-10-23">Oct. 23, 1908</date><title level="a">THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>American politicians are now busily engaged in a bitter campaign to elect the next president of the United States. The election will take place next month. The candidates are traveling from state to state, explaining and praising their respective platforms. However, judging from the past, it is understood that the candidate elected will not adhere to, nor fulfill his platform. Opposing candidates are accusing each other of real and imaginary defects. This has occured during all past elections and it is happening again. There is nothing new about the behavior of politicians who are seeking public office.</p>
   <p>The democrats and candidates of other parties are accusing the Republican party of preparing a field in America for a monarchy. It is possible <pb facs="5423970_1_1027.jpg" n="2"/>that this accusation is not without foundation. William Howard Taft, the present Republican candidate for president, stated many times when he was Secretary of War that it is not essential for America to adhere to the Republican form of government. The incumbent, President Roosevelt, is most interested in increasing the Army and strengthening the Navy; it is a well-known fact that for their existence, all monarchies depend upon the bayonets of soldiers.</p>
   <p>The presidents of the United States have a much greater power over the Army and Navy than the presidents of France. It is much easier for a president of the United States to declare himself king, with the support of Army and Navy officials, than it is for a president of France to do so. In France, before a president can attract the support of the Army and Navy he must have at least some very important accomplishments to his credit. In America that is not necessary. Here everything is done not with principles, but with money.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
