<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>, Vol. VI,
<date when="1925-01-13">January 13, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Our Answer to Them</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>, Vol. VI,
<date when="1925-01-13">January 13, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">OUR ANSWER TO THEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the last issue of the Vilnis, the Chicago Taylors' Union gave an answer to the Mensheviks' clerics and the nationalists' attack and lies. This answer shows what kind of ugly methods those nationalists, etc., are using in their struggle with the conscious workingmen. And this is not only in Chicago. Whenever our friends have a deal with the capitalists, they always learn that there is nothing too low that can serve our enemies' purpose.</p>
   <p>Why? Why now, as never before, are they using the vilest methods to damage our movement? Because they cannot withhold the struggle for principles and ideals. In reality, they themselves have no ideals. Their main principle is profit. And to cover this fact they are covering themselves with nationalistic or socialistic camouflage, but whenever it happens that we meet them in our labor organizations, it is easy for us to unmask them and show their real face. They have learned that even in their combined <pb facs="5423970_1_0772.jpg" n="2"/>action against Communists - they cannot withhold the development of organizations, and that is why they use lies and similar methods in their fight against labor.</p>
   <p>But for how long can they fight with such methods? Of course, not for very long. They can fool perhaps some of the workingmen, but this will be only temporarily. Whenever the truth comes into light, it costs them plenty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
