<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-05-10">May 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The I. W. W. on Trial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-05-10">May 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE I. W. W. ON TRIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois--the much publicized trial of the Industrial Workers of the World, or the I.W.W., has finally begun here. The United States Government is pressing the charges.</p>
   <p>Among the defendants there is only one Lithuanian, Joseph Laukis, former editor of the Darbininku Balsas (The Voice of the Workers), the organ of the Lithuanian members of the I.W.W. Laukis was arrested with the others some time ago.</p>
   <p>Frank K. Nebeker of Salt Lake City, chief prosecutor for the Government in this case, is an assistant prosecuting attorney of the United States. In his opening speech to the jury he explained why the 112 I.W.W. members have been put on trial and what the Government intends to prove. Among other things, he said:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0785.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"All of the charges are for certain misdemeanors committed between April 6, 1917 and August, 1917. These men not only refused to join the army but attempted, in all sorts of ways, to hinder military preparations.</p>
   <p>"These men consider themselves a government within the Government. They do not acknowledge any other authority except their leader, who sits as their king. You all know whom I have in mind when I speak of this foreign lord--William D. Haywood. These men seemingly work for the benefit of the workers as a class. In order to do this they spoil and destroy property and threaten and even agree to murders.</p>
   <p>"They use force to prevent the execution of the country's laws. They are opposed to all the laws, though they are passed by the majority of the citizens."</p>
   <p>Nebeker explained that one of the counts in the indictment charged that the accused were guilty of an illegal conspiracy to prevent ten thousand young <pb facs="5423970_1_0786.jpg" n="3"/>men from registering and to help five thousand other men attempt to desert the United States army. He stated further that the center of I.W.W. activity was in Chicago and that the I.W.W. lieutenants in secondary cities received their orders from here. The secondary centers, he charged, are located in Philadelphia, Minneapolis, Cleveland, New York, Duluth, Spokane, Seattle, Salt Lake City, Scranton, and Great Falls, Montana.</p>
   <p>"The contagious poisons of the I.W.W.," Nebeker continued, "have reached the members of enslaved nations who have come here from Europe seeking freedom. They penetrate our groups with their poisonous and illegal doctrines. The membership of the I.W.W. is composed of representatives of almost every nation of Europe. Among the are Finns, Russians, Italians, Spaniards, French, a large number of Germans and Austrians, and representatives of Balkan nations."</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0787.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Charges</p>
   <p>In summary, the prosecutor made the charges, thus:</p>
   <p>"We," he said, "will prove beyond a doubt that this organization was a criminal organization from its very beginning.</p>
   <p>"We will prove that it started its anti-war propaganda a year before our war began.</p>
   <p>"We will prove that many persons who did not want to fulfill their obligations to this Government became members of the organization.</p>
   <p>"We will prove that these men (the members of the I.W.W.) come in groups to cities where legal strikes are in progress, with the intention of 'making trouble' and soliciting for membership in their organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0788.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"They are proud when they are thrown into jail and they attempt to recruit members there.</p>
   <p>"The testimony will prove that they forced conscientious workers to become members of the I.W.W. They desire to do away with the wage system and the right of one person to bargain with another.</p>
   <p>"The purpose of their strikes is not to win shorter hours, better conditions, or higher wages; they want to fight until the employer, driven by desperation, will shout, 'Take everything I have!'</p>
   <p>"We will prove to you that, whenever this organization came into contact with honest workers, it always attempted to lead them off the right path.</p>
   <p>"We will prove to you that the connection this organization has with graft is so large as to be almost beyond belief."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
