<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 22,
<date when="1908-05-29">May 29, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">From the "Zinycia" (The Temple) Society</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 22,
<date when="1908-05-29">May 29, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE "ZINYCIA" (THE TEMPLE) SOCIETY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "Zinycia" Society held its meeting on May 24, in the office of Lietuva and elected the new administration.</p>
   <p>J. J. Hertmanavicia, president.</p>
   <p>Just. Jakavicia, vice-president.</p>
   <p>M. M. Juska, first secretary.</p>
   <p>Aleksandra Olszewskis, second secretary.</p>
   <p>Nicefor Zilevicia, reasurer.</p>
   <p>A. Olszewskis, the publisher of Lietuva, general manager.</p>
   <p>The "Zinycia" directors:</p>
   <p>Povylas Rymkevicia.</p>
   <p>Antanas Knistautas.</p>
   <p>Moteijus Cernikas.</p>
   <p>Antanas Draugelis.</p>
   <p>Konstantinas Draugelis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0477.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Stanislovas Milleris.</p>
   <p>Vladislovas Milleris.</p>
   <p>Povylas Juska.</p>
   <p>Adomas Pocevicia.</p>
   <p>Antanas Juska.</p>
   <p>Julijonas Juska.</p>
   <p>At the meeting the following decisions were made:</p>
   <p>(1) The sale of the land should be started at once in Clark County, in the town of Thorp, Wisconsin. This is necessary in order to be able to establish the Lithuanian farmers, before the end of the summer in a colony, situated near the Central Wisconsin Railroad and the Black river, and to start to build the Lithuanian church, school, etc.</p>
   <p>(2) To sell the farm land to the people cheaper than the company is selling it.</p>
   <p>To sell on easy payments for the term of five years or longer, as the case may be.</p>
   <p>(3) The excursions to the colony should take place every Friday. Those, who will <pb facs="5423970_1_0478.jpg" n="3"/>buy the land, will have their expenses refunded.</p>
   <p>(4) To construct the buildings and drill the well on the installment plan, if the buyers of the land cannot afford in the beginning to undertake this work themselves. The "Zinycia" society believes that it can erect the buildings and drill the well cheaper than the farmer himself.</p>
   <p>(5) To sell the "Zinycia" stock at twelve dollars per share, until one-half of the "Zinycia" land is sold. When one-half is sold, then the price of the stock will be fifteen dollars a share.</p>
   <p>(6) It was decided that those, who have subscribed for the "Zinycia" stock and have not paid in full, must pay for all the subscribed stock before the meeting, which will be held on June 28, 1908, at the office of Lietuva. Those, who up to that time have not paid for their subscribed stock, will have their shares sold to others, and the money will be refunded to the former subscriber.</p>
   <p>(7) Decided, that those, who having changed their mind, do not want to buy the shares, should return their receipts at once in order that the money already paid by them can be refunded, and the stock sold to others.</p>
   <p>(8) At this meeting one member returned three of his shares, and at once other <pb facs="5423970_1_0479.jpg" n="4"/>members of the Society bought them.</p>
   <p>The "Zinycia" Society members are glad that the value of their stock doubled in one year. Last year they paid ten dollars per share, this year the price of the share is twelve dollars. The price of the land, which the "Zinycia" has bought, also doubled this year, that is why the value of the stock doubled.</p>
   <p>Now then, those, who want to double their money, can buy a few shares of the "Zinycia" Society stock, and you will have a much better profit, than in any other business. The business of the "Zinycia" is to buy the land in large tracts at a low price and to sell at higher prices or the same prices as other companies are selling. Every one knows, that the money invested in land will not be lost, fire will not destroy it, nor will a theif steal it.</p>
   <p>When a man buys property in the city, he pays a high price, say $3000, during prosperity, but when an industrial crisis comes, millions of people are out of employment, and the value of city property falls to one-half or less. The price of the <pb facs="5423970_1_0480.jpg" n="5"/>farm land, however, remains the same regardless of industrial crises. During the present industrial crisis, people are buying land in order to protect their savings and the future of their own. The price of the land is going up. The "Zinycia" Society for saw this, so the society bought farm land before the prices became too high. Many of the American large farm land companies have bought the land at a low price, now they have and still are making millions of dollars in profit.</p>
   <p>If the companies made millions of dollars profit, then we see no reason why the "Zinycia" Society cannot make a profit by buying and selling farm land.</p>
   <p>When the "Zinycia" Society will have one thousand members or more, its budget will be at $100,000. Then the Lithuanians with $100,000 can buy as large tracts of land as the American companies and make the same profits. For this reason many people are joining the "Zinycia", instead of joining other business propositions in cities, where the investments are always in danger.</p>
   <p>Therefore, do not hesitate, join the "Zinycia" Society, come to the meeting, which <pb facs="5423970_1_0481.jpg" n="6"/>will be held on June 28, 1908, at the Lietuva office.</p>
   <p>Those, who want to see the Lithuanian farm colony of "Zinycia", call or write to A. Olszewski, 3252 S. Halsted Street, and he will give you information gladly.</p>
   <p>The "Zinycia" Administration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
