<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 12,
<date when="1906-03-23">March 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Lithuanian Organizations, Newspapers and Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0495</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0495.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 12,
<date when="1906-03-23">March 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO LITHUANIAN ORGANIZATIONS, NEWSPAPERS AND SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Committee of Zinycia (The Temple) will hold a convention for the discussion of various problems. They have decided to invite to this convention the Lithuanian organizations, newspapers, societies, and individuals who are well known because of their activities in the scientific and national field. Not having the addresses of many Lithuanian societies, we have decided to invite them not by letters but through the medium of the press. We hope that the Lithuanian Alliance of America, the Roman-Catholic Alliance of America, the Lovers of Fatherland Society, the Lithuanian Science Society, the newspapers Lietuva,Katalikas (Catholic) Vienybe (Unity), Saule (The Sun), and Zvaigzde (The Star), and all other societies of Chicago and of other cities will send delegates in order to make the convention more important. That will bring benefit to all of us.</p>
   <p>Writers, teachers and other men of science, Just let us know that you are coming; you need no other credentials.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0496.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To avoid unnecessary expenses, the organizations can appoint their delegates from their local branches, the newspapers can appoint their local (Chicago) reporters.</p>
   <p>If any society has no time to elect a delegate, the president or secretary of such a society can be sent.</p>
   <p>The convention will be held on April the 8th, at 1 P. M., at the Northwestern University Settlement, Augusta and Noble streets, Chicago.</p>
   <p>The names of the delegates, organizations, societies and newspapers, must be sent to the Zinycia secretary, M. Januskevicia, 137 Augusta St., Chicago, Ill., before the fourth day of April, so that a list of the delegates could be prepared.</p>
   <p>J. Hertmanavicia, President</p>
   <p>M. M. Januskevicia, Secretary.</p>
   <p>Among the guests we are expecting to have many ladies and American visitors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
