<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1923-01-25">Jan. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Politics and Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1923-01-25">Jan. 25, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS AND LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By viewing the economic and Industrial situation in America in a general way, we notice that there is a large amount of discontent among the workers. They appear to be aware of the fact that they are being very severely exploited. While the press of the capitalists and their servants in Washington are continually boasting of the present "greet prosperity," the workers notice how their standard of living is constantly going from bad to worse. Insecurity and uncertainty of the future is tormenting millions of workers. Many workers know that the are victims of social injustice, but very few know what must be done to correct the situation. The American working class is influenced largely by the union <pb facs="5423970_1_0675.jpg" n="2"/>bureaucracy, such as the American Federation of Labor, However, the officers of these unions serve only the bourgeoisie and are continuously misleading the workers.</p>
   <p>The hypocrisy of the union bureaucracy was clearly illustrated at the last Ohio State convention of the American Federation of Labor, at Columbus, Ohio. No one at, the convention denied the fact that the American workers are being exploited; no one even attempted to hide the fact that the laws of the land are being drafted and enacted without giving any consideration to the welfare of the American working class. Even President Frey, of the Ohio State Federation of Labor, explained to the convention that the American workers are being inhumanly exploited.</p>
   <p>It is very obvious that after such discussions as stated above, the most <pb facs="5423970_1_0676.jpg" n="3"/>logical conclusion would be to recognize the fact that the workers bust fight for their rights in the industrial field, and at the same time organize a political party of their own. However, instead of taking the above logical steps, it was decided at the convention to a there to the traditional "non-political and non-partisan" policy. The leaders of the convention then had a motion passed to from a committee for the purpose of finding political candidates who are "competent and friendly towards labor," regardless of party affiliations, and then urge the union membership to vote for them as their own candidates.</p>
   <p>It is very clear that the scheme of the labor leaders is the sell the votes of union members to those candidates who will pay the highest price and will not be too lazy to make a few promises to benefit the working class.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0677.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Anyway, it is interesting to note that the discontent among the workers, and the resultant desire for better conditions is a sign that the workers are becoming increasingly class-conscious.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
