<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol.2. No.43.
<date when="1894-10-27">October 27, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Politics</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0911</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0911.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol.2. No.43.
<date when="1894-10-27">October 27, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Politics</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In politics, there are two great political parties, the Democratic and the Republican. From the misunderstanding of workers who voted for Democrats, the Democratic party got in control of country and city. As soon as the Democrats took control of the government, factories were closed, thousands upon thousands of workers were thrown out of employment, and now are starving.</p>
   <p>Lithuanians, you ought to remember, that during the Republican national administration, nobody worked for seventy-five cents a day; nobody in Chicago worked for a dish of soup, that even dog would not eat. But now, under the Democratic control, the workers must work for only a dish of dirty soup. Under the Democratic administration the factories are closed, stores are vacant, hundreds of people in the city of Chicago lost their homes. When such a horrible condition exists Democratic politicians are begging for votes, to elect themselves again.</p>
   <p>Under the Republican administration nobody was working like a slave for a dish of soup, as is being done now under the Democratic rule. Therefore, Lithuanians vote for the Republican ticket. Elect the Republican administration national and local, then again everybody will have work and will be happy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
