<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-06-03">June 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Socialist Alliance United with Socialist Party</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0832</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0832.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-06-03">June 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN SOCIALIST ALLIANCE UNITED WITH SOCIALIST PARTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of joining the Socialist party was decided by direct vote. The results of voting were as follows: 755 votes were given in favor of joining the Socialist party and 696 votes were against joining. The majority was small according to the results, however, it showed that a larger number of the members were in favor of joining the Socialist party. And it was well that it was decided to join the Socialist party. A small Socialist organization cannot accomplish much in any respect. Such organizations must first unite if the Socialist party expects to accomplish something worthwhile in the future. Without uniting with other Socialist organizations in this country that are active in politics, the Socialist party cannot grow strong and cannot gain great influence with the people. The stregth of the Socialist party can be shown by its unity and its activity. The results of voting are not very encouraging because the majority obtained by those who favored joining the Socialist party is too small. We are not satisfied with the results of voting in our organization. We must work harder to get more support from our members. Every member in the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance should support the decision of the majority. Especially <pb facs="5423970_1_0833.jpg" n="2"/>those members who opposed joining the Socialist party are asked to give a favorable support to the majority of the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance. We cannot afford to split our organization just because the majority of the members decided to join the Socialist party of America. In the first place there is no reason for opposing the majority of the members who made their decision. We cannot believe that some of the members of our organization would oppose joining the Socialist party from the viewpoint of principle. And to oppose joining that party from a practical viewpoint would be very irrational on the part of the members of this organization. From the analysis of this situation we can clearly see that there is no reason for opposing the majority of our members, if you are a Socialist. We want to repeat the statement which we made before in the same article that a small socialist organization cannot accomplish anything worthwhile if it is split into many groups. If we want to accomplish something worthwhile in the future we must unite into one group, and only then we will be able to do something for the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0834.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But not until we unite and demonstrate our strength in unity can we exert any power. Unity is our power and without it we cannot make any gains. Many nationalities have joined the Socialist Party of America. The Lithuanian Socialist Alliance is taking third place among other nationalities. The nationalities that have joined the Socialist Party of America are as follows: Finnish Socialist Federation, with 14,475 members; German Socialist Federation, 5,172; Lithuanian Socialist Alliance, 3,500; Jewish Socialist Federation, 2,175; Southern Slavs, 1,883; Polish Socialist Federation, 1,701; Bohemian Socialist Federation; Scandinavian Socialist Federation, 921; Hungarian Socialist Federation, 716; Italian Socialist Federation, 524; and Slovak Socialist Federation, 454. The federations having more than five hundred members will be permitted to have their own secretary who will receive a salary and will have an office at the headquarters of the National Socialist Party of America. Accordingly, the Lithuanian Socialist Alliance will have its own secretary at these headquarters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
