<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-26">June 26, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Appearances Are Sometimes Deceiving</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0296</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0296.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-26">June 26, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">APPEARANCES ARE SOMETIMES DECEIVING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we glance through our newspapers, we notice many news items about a large variety of Lithuanian social activities such as musical concerts, theatrical presentations, etc. On the surface, therefore, it appears that the Lithuanians of Chicago are in a happy state of contentment and have everything their hearts desire. However, a close examination of the conditions of their daily lives reveals a far different picture. They are beset with unemployment, misery, and even starvation. From day to day they are anxiously waiting for a favorable turn in events; they are asking each other, when will we go back to work and when will conditions improve? So far no one has been able to give a definite answer to these questions.</p>
   <p>The people are already starting to talk about the approaching election of the head, the "king," of our country. Some are upbraiding the Democrats; others are sending the Socialists directly into hell; and a third group is praising the Republicans. Many members of the latter group appear to forget that during the past few months they have been existing only on bread and coffee, and that sometimes they are unable to enjoy even that "luxury." In spite of that, they <pb facs="5423970_1_0297.jpg" n="2"/>say with great pride that under the present Republican administration very good times existed. Yes, it is true, good times did exist for a while. We must admit that we were employed and had an opportunity to exercise our limbs almost every day. However, look at our predicament now! Although the Republican administration is still in power, nevertheless, we are idle and walking the streets; the very same streets in which our masters ride in automobiles. We still have plenty of water to drink, but we have nothing to eat! The Republican boosters appear to believe that the matter of food is insignificant. They say, "We were employed during the past period of prosperity and received good wages."</p>
   <p>However, the important question is why have we nothing to eat today? Why are landlords throwing us and our little children into the streets? It is true, We were employed for a while; we traded our labor power and endangered, even sacrificed, our very lives for the crumbs of the capitalists; but why have we nothing to eat today? Is it because of the so-called masters' "love" for his loyal servants? When we beg our masters for some daily bread to alleviate the pangs of hunger, then, instead of giving us employment, they send bands of policemen to crush our heads with clubs. They are concerned only with their <pb facs="5423970_1_0298.jpg" n="3"/>own welfare. They do not feel any obligation to aid those unfortunates who helped to amass their fabulous wealth. Starving workers are forced to lie in the streets and appeal to all the saints for assistance, but even the saints are unable to help them.</p>
   <p>This period of unemployment plainly reveals our position in society; we have very much to learn from it. The voice of conscience is saying: "During the coming election, do not sell your vote for a glass of beer, but investigate and vote according to the dictates of your conscience. Then better times are sure to come, although not immediately."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
