<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 52,
<date when="1907-12-27">Dec. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of the "Zinycia"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0485</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0485.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 52,
<date when="1907-12-27">Dec. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE "ZINYCIA"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The administration of "Zinycia" announces that we have bought a tract of land, 560 acres in Wisconsin, County of Clark, near the town of Thorp. By comparing the price we have paid with the prices of the land that other companies are selling, we find that the price of our land at present would be $5 more per acre than we have paid. The price of the "Zinycia" stock is $10 per share. We have paid $10 per acre. As the price of the land at present is $5 higher, its present value is $15. Therefore, we have raised the price per share accordingly, and from now on it shall be $15 instead of $10.</p>
   <p>The "Zinycia" administration held its meeting on Dec. 22, 1907, and has decided that after Jan. 12, 1908 the price of the shares will be $12 per share for those who have joined this organization previously and have promised to buy shares. For those who shall join after the date mentioned, the price will be $15 per share.</p>
   <p>The "Zinycia" meeting will be held Jan. 12, 1908 at 2 P.M., at Northwestern University Settlement Hall, 122 Augusta St., corner of Noble St. All the members of this organization must be present at the meeting. The general <pb facs="5423970_1_0486.jpg" n="2"/>Lithuanian public is invited to this meeting. Come and join this organization and help us to build the Lithuanian colony. If we get more Lithuanians in our organization, we will buy more land there; then we can build our city, factories, stores, etc. At present, thousands of Lithuanians are out of work and they are starving. So we must buy more land there and give to our unemployed brothers jobs in our colony. It is time for our Lithuanians to consider the problem of unemployment at present. If we had bought land a long time ago and had established our colony, these thousands of unemployed Lithuanians would have gotten jobs in our colony. They would not starve as they are at present. The banks are closing their doors every day, the hard earned savings of the people are lost. The future of the people is dark, they have lost all they had, and now they must starve.</p>
   <p>Lo! Lithuanians, who have not lost their money yet, join our organization; help to buy more land on which to establish the Lithuanian colony, where we will have protection for ourselves and for our brothers. There will be no lack of jobs in this farm colony; everybody will work there, will be well paid, and the profits will be ours instead of being pocketed by the greedy trusts.</p>
   <p>The "Zinycia" administration:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0487.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>J. J. Hertmanovice, president, 3252 S. Halsted St. Nikeforas Zylevice, treasurer, 1418 W. 21st Pl. Mykolas Juska, secretary, 1098 S. Leavitt St.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
