<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 14, 4-5,1907.
<title level="a">The "Aurora" Society's Lecture</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Synopsis)</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LIETUVA</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 14, 4-5,1907.
<title level="a">THE "AURORA" SOCIETY'S LECTURE</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Synopsis)</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>March 24th, the fifth lecture was given by the "Aurora" Society. This lecture was delivered by a woman, K.A. G., "On Enslavement of Women". There was a larger audience than on previous ocassions, especially at this lecture, were twice as many women than have been before. The lady speaker stated that the women for ages have been enslaved, that the women are more sympathetic than men, and for this reason the women were much easier to enslave for the lack of aggressiveness. The men say that women have less thinking ability because they are physically weaker and for this reason are weaker mentally. This is not so. Physical weakness has nothing to do with mental power. When the man are enslaved, no matter how strong they are physically, their mental power is killed. So with the women, they have been slaves of the slave for centuries in the past.</p>
   <p>Then the lecturer stated that when the women have been permitted to attend higher institutions of education, we found out that the women are just as good in learning as the men are. For instance, the woman, P.M. Currie, by studying in laboratory, has discovered radium; at present she is a professor <pb facs="5423970_1_1453.jpg" n="2"/>in the University of Paris.</p>
   <p>The American women were unable to stand oppression any longer, began to organize societies to protect women's rights. The leader of this movement was Miss S. Anthony. She was laughed and sneered at by the men. Many times the clergy of various denominations organized the mob in order to obstruct Miss Anthony's lectures. But this brave and energetic woman went on with her fight for women's rights. As a result of this struggle propagated by Miss Anthony, the women in the state of Colorado won their right to vote. Previous to this, the Socialist Party used to get 4,000 votes, but when the women got right to vote, the Socialist Party in the last election, got 20,000 votes. This proves that the women have a much clearer conception on the labor conditions than the men.....</p>
   <p>A. Zimontas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
