<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 17, 
<date when="1907-04-26">4-26, 1907</date><title level="a">From the Women's Society "Enlightenment"</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1448</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1448.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LIETUVA</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 17, 
<date when="1907-04-26">4-26, 1907</date><title level="a">FROM THE WOMEN'S SOCIETY "ENLIGHTENMENT"</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Women, where is our salvation? Much has been written and spoken about the women of other nations, their societies, and organizations, clubs and circles, charitable organizations, enlightenment and culture. But about the Lithuanian women? We are lacking news about their activity. No doubt, some one will say that we few women can accomplish nothing. Every movement among the women has been started by one or a few women.</p>
   <p>We, the Lithuanian women, have less education, enlightenment and culture, must look very closely on what basis our organization should have. We must have our society without cockleweed, but on a sound cultural and scientific basis.</p>
   <p>The American women have many and various societies. Do such societies bring benefits to humanity? This is another problem. Let us take for instance the American Old Maid Association, which has introduced a bill in the Senate that all men who are not married and are over 45 years of age ought to be chloroformed! Secondly, the women societies have held their conventions after many foolish <pb facs="5423970_1_1449.jpg" n="2"/> questions had been brought forth and discussed: one question was raised about votes for women, that only those women can have rights to go to the ballot box whose husbands have a considerable amount of money. While others at their meetings discuss the new order of economics, that one should buy the cheapest food, etc., and if you have no money, don't try to buy anything, that in order to save money, but the cheapest food, clothing, and live in the cheapest house. Of course, when you have no money to buy shoes, go bare-footed; if you have no money to buy food, go hungry! That is the foundation of the new economics!</p>
   <p>One of the American milksop ladies' societies in Chicago once in a while arranges a meeting in the best hotel, and invites the city's big shots to to speak. The milksop ladies are interested in how to keep the city streets clean, and thanks to the American ladies' society's energy and effort, the streets of Chicago are clean, the people are living in mansions. The politicians also tell how the worker's wife ought to separate the coal from the ashes, how from used newspapers, to make paper baskets in order to keep the streets clean of paper, etc. This is not all. The politician tells how the streets are kept clean where the milksop ladies are living...</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1450.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I must not forget to mention, when at one such milksop ladies meeting, after the politician has finished his speech, one teacher stated: "Mr. Speaker and ladies of the meeting: you have talked about the education of the people, the upkeep of clean streets: I will suggest that if the milksop ladies and the politicians move out of the city, the city streets will be clean, and the immorality of the youth will disappear!" </p>
   <p>Instead of preaching economy to the poor, change the system, so that there would be no necessity to work 12 to 14 hours a day at starvation wages, and when the husband comes from work he should not see his children hungry, bare-footed...</p>
   <p>Instead of talking about the dirty streets and doing nothing, take the milksop ladies and the politicians to the stock yards, let them see how the workers are enslaved; take them to the streets where the workers live, let them see the dirty streets, and the streets are dirty because the politicians steal the public money. Instead of boys and girls of 12 and 14 years of age becoming slaves in the factories, send these children to school, educate them, instead of poisoning <pb facs="5423970_1_1451.jpg" n="4"/>their young bodies with the factory dirt, and poisoning their young brains with the daily yellow press' lies and the speeches of the city grafters. Give them proper education, see that they should live in proper houses, then economic injustice will adjust by itself.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the women must have such an organization, that they could discuss the problems of the system of today, find the causes why thousands are always in want while the few have too much.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Lithuanian women have organized a society under the name "Enlightenment". The purpose of this organization is to arrange lectures, spread the light, show to the people why they are exploited and oppressed. This society has arranged lectures on the 28th day of April, at Freiheit Turner Hall, 3417 So. Halsted Street. All the Lithuanians are invited, come and learn the truth.</p>
   <p>The "Enlightenment Society's Committee."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
