<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 21,
<date when="1908-05-22">May 22, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">From the "Zinycia" (The Temple) Society</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 21,
<date when="1908-05-22">May 22, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE "ZINYCIA" (THE TEMPLE) SOCIETY</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many Lithuanians have heard, that in 1905 in Chicago, there was organized a Lithuanian society under the name, "The Assembly of Lithuanian Zinycia", with the purpose of establishing a Lithuanian farm colony in America. This society was incorporated with a capital of four thousand dollars, and in 1907 it bought a tract of land, close to the town of Thorp, Wisconsin. But the capital of four thousand dollars was too small to start the colonization, so the action was postponed until the capital was increased.</p>
   <p>This year, the "Zinycia" Society increased its capital from $4000 to $25,000, and at the last meeting, on May 17, we decided to buy more land and to start the colonization at once. In order to make the colonization more successful, our society took as our organ the newspaper,Lietuva, in which from now on, all the official news of the "Zinycia" will be announced. And as the general manager of the colonization department was appointed Mr. A. Olszewski, publisher of Lietuva.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the "Zinycia" Society is this: To buy land in large tracts at a <pb facs="5423970_1_0483.jpg" n="2"/>fair price, and to sell it to the people in parcels of forty or eighty acres. The profit from such sales it to be divided equally among the shareholders proportionately to the number of shares owned by them.</p>
   <p>The price of one share is twelve dollars. Last year the price was ten dollars. Thus, during one year the price of a share went up two dollars. Last year, this society bought land at seven dollars per acre. Now, the same real estate company wants twelve dollars per acre if you buy a tract of land; but if you buy acres for individual farms, the price is sixteen dollars per acre. Thus, if the company sells the same kind of land, adjacent to the "Zinycia" land for sixteen dollars an acre, then our land is worth sixteen dollars an acre also. Consequently, the price we have paid last year has doubled this year.</p>
   <p>The "Zinycia" Society will hold its meeting on May 24, at 2 P.M., at the office of Lietuva. All the Lithuanians, who are interested the farm affairs, are invited to come to the meeting in order to learn the results. All will be admitted <pb facs="5423970_1_0484.jpg" n="3"/>to this meeting. For better acquaintance with the "Zinycia" Society, its bylaws will be given free.</p>
   <p>The "Zinycia" Administration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
