<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-04-16">Apr. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Refublican League of Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0927</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0927.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-04-16">Apr. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN REFUBLICAN LEAGUE OF ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Lithuanian Republican League of Illinois took place last Monday, April 12, at the Grand Pacific hotel, Chicago, Illinois. The meeting was called to discuss matters pertaining to the recent Chicago mayoralty election, from which the Republican candidate, William Hale Thompson, emerged the winner.</p>
   <p>It was pointed out at the meeting that the Irish, who control both political parties, pay very little attention to Lithuanian-Americans and that they do not sufficiently appreciate the work of Lithuanian-Americans in the field of politics. It was agreed that this state of affairs is abnormal and unfair, and that something must be done to correct it; ways and means to rectify this situation were discussed at the meeting. It was decided to appeal to those who control the Republican party in Chicago and demand that a reasonable number of deserving Lithuanian-American party workers be given municipal posts and positions in order that the Chicago Lithuanian-Americans may be adequately <pb facs="5423970_1_0928.jpg" n="2"/>represented in the city government.</p>
   <p>In this connection it was decided to give a banquet in which the Chicago Lithuanian-American political leaders will participate; the Mayor of Chicago and other important city officials will be invited to attend this banquet. An arrangements committee was elected at the meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
