<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-03-19">Mar. 19, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Women's Society Presents Drama and Musical Program</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1426</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1426.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-03-19">Mar. 19, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN'S SOCIETY PRESENTS DRAMA AND MUSICAL PROGRAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Lithuanian Women's Educational Society presented a three-act drama "Kaip Kas Ismano, Taip Save Gano" (Everyone Leads His Life According to His Understanding), on March 7, at the Hull House Theatre. The drama was interesting and educational. It pointed out the advantages of an education, and the disadvantages of ignorance. This was the first time the play was presented before a Chicago audience.</p>
   <p>The dramatic performance was satisfactory. Some of the actors did their parts unusually well. Mr. Vaitekunas, who played the role of "Pilvikis," the large landowner, did his part as well as a professional actor. Mrs. M. Damijonaitis, who played the role of "Mrs. Pilvikis," and Mrs. Sutkus, who played the role of "Mrs. Vizgiras," performed satisfactorily. Miss Katkus, who played the role of "Vanda," daughter of "Pilvikis," failed in her efforts to represent the bold character of a large landowner's daughter; she acted like a frightened servant girl. Mr. Ilgaudas, who played the part of 25 year old "Nepesa," lacked energy and gaiety during the matchmaking scene. "Sankunas", the servant, did not <pb facs="5423970_1_1427.jpg" n="2"/>know his part well. It appears that most of the actors did not know their parts, because even the people who were sitting in the gallery heard the prompter repeat lines over and over again.</p>
   <p>During the intermissions the audience was entertained with tableaux representing womanhood. These scenes were portrayed by Lithuanian women dressed in national costumes. This part of the program was directed by A. Zmuidinavicius (Zemaitis), world-famous Lithuanian sculptor and artist, who is here on a visit from Lithuania.</p>
   <p>The balance of the program consisted of musical numbers. One of the participants in the musical program was Mrs. Bradchulis, non-Lithuanian wife of attorney F. P. Bradchulis. This part of the program was as interesting and as entertaining as the drama. However, the intermission periods between the acts of the play were entirely too long.</p>
   <p>It is to be regretted, however, that only a small group of women attended. Why are women, especially girls, staying away from activities which are for <pb facs="5423970_1_1428.jpg" n="3"/>benefit of their sex? We all know that women, especially Lithuanian women, are far behind men in the field of intellectual development. Women should strive to at least catch up with the men. If women will equal themselves in deeds with men, then they will obtain equal rights with men; without equal deeds there can be no equal rights.</p>
   <p>Our girls, especially, are unwilling to make an effort to educate themselves. They refuse to attend any of our educational functions unless dancing is on the program. When they do attend a theatrical or lecture, with dancing on the program, they pay little attention to the educational part of the program.</p>
   <p>Our men should remember that a girl who is too lazy to make an effort to educate herself will likewise be too lazy to properly fulfill her duties as a wife or mother. These duties are not easy, and are much more difficult than dancing on a ballroom floor.</p>
   <p>By H. Mockus.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
