<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-03-02">Mar. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Another Victory for Wall Street</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0667</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0667.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-03-02">Mar. 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER VICTORY FOR WALL STREET</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday President Coolidge signed a new tax reduction bill. According to the provisions of this bill, taxes will be reduced to the extent of 385 million dollars per year. However, only the taxes of the rich have been reduced. That is the reason why this bill was called the "rich man's bill" when it was under consideration in Congress. Now it can very appropriately be called the "rich man's law."</p>
   <p>Wall Street, therefore, has scored another victory. Industrialists, bankers, and other capitalistic magnates will pay less taxes to the government, and will increase their exploitation of the workers of America. But in order to conceal the true nature of the bill, its sponsors have included a very slight reduction in the taxes on the incomes of the workers. For example, a married man with two children will now be obliged to pay an income tax only on earnings <pb facs="5423970_1_0668.jpg" n="2"/>above $3,500. A single person will be taxed only for earnings above $1,500. Formerly the tax percentage was 2%, but now it will be "only" 11/2%. Such a scant "reduction" in the tax on the workers, when compared to the large reductions in the tax on the rich, merely makes fools of the workers.</p>
   <p>The average annual income of a worker in this country runs from $1,000 to $1,500. It is true that some workers earn more than $1,500, but the greater majority earn less than $1,000. Under the old tax law the workers experienced great difficulty in paying the tax. Under the new tax law they will continue to experience great difficulty in paying the taxes. The kings of Wall Street, whom President Coolidge and Congress pitied and so reduced their taxes, are the very ones who are responsible for the miserable plight of the workers who cannot afford to pay an income tax. Instead of improving the lot of the workers, the Wall Street barons are planning to lower the wages of the workers still more and increase their misery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0669.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What does all this mean? It means that the capitalists are very strongly organized. They hold the governmental power in their hands and use it to suit their own purposes. Those who sit in Congress do only that which is beneficial to the capitalists, and it is very pitiful indeed to think that those servants of the capitalists are sent to Congress by the workers them-selves.</p>
   <p>The workers should organize. In order to defend our own rights in Congress and keep the paid agents of Wall Street out of Congress, we must have a strong labor party. The American Labor (Communist) Party stated a long time ago that the tactics of the greatest hypocritical labor leader in America, Samuel Gompers, served only to deceive the workers. Gompers' tactics were to "punish the enemies and reward the friends of labor." The communists have urged and still urge the workers of this country to organize independently of the capitalists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0670.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There is no other road for the workers of America. Until they are organized and fight for the rights of their class, the workers will continue to be exploited by their oppressors, the capitalists.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
