<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sandara</title>,
<date when="1930-03-14">March 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">American Lithuanians in Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0899</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0899.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sandara</title>,
<date when="1930-03-14">March 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN LITHUANIANS IN POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4............American Lithuanians in the field of politics are left too far behind by other nationalities. We understand that we cannot accomplish anything worth while, where there is a small number of Lithuanians. However, we can accomplish a great deal in other colonies where there is a large number of Lithuanian people. For example, at Bridgeport, we have the largest Lithuanian colony in Chicago. We only need to organize our people into one large voting group, as Lithuanian Political Organization of the Eleventh Ward. Then we will be able to accomplish something worth while in the political field. Above all things we must have an organization and unity, if we want to succeed in our aims. When we shall have our own organization and the unity of our people, then we can say that we have accomplished something that will bring benefit to our organization and our people. We must remember one thing:that we cannot place our own candidate on the ballot without any organization. Only through our organization can we place our candidate on the ballot. If we want to be recognized by the major parties, Republicans or Democrats, we must be well organized into one strong voting bloc. It <pb facs="5423970_1_0900.jpg" n="2"/>is a wise plan for us to stick together as much as possible if we want to succeed in American politics. Smart politicians know that we are not united and that we are lacking harmony within our organizations. We must, by all means, stick to the old proverb "united we stand and divided we fall." No doubt we will succeed in politics, if we stick together and maintain harmony among our own people.</p>
   <p>At the present time in Chicago, we have many large Lithuanian colonies or districts all over the city; but none of them is organized into voting blocs. For that reason, we haven't any of our own candidates and are compelled to vote for other nationality candidates who are not interested in the affairs of our people. Therefore we cannot blame anybody but ourselves for not having at least one of our people in the office of the city government.</p>
   <p>Our people are strange individuals. They would rather vote for candidates of other nationalities than their own. We are making a serious mistake by not putting our own candidate on the ballot at least for a small office in the city government. We must make every effort to remedy the present situation among our people. Our <pb facs="5423970_1_0901.jpg" n="3"/>people are not interested in American politics for some unknown reason. As a matter of fact, all of our people should be interested in politics; for it is a civic duty of every citizen to take part in politics and help to support and elect good men to the offices of the local government as well as state government.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to elect at least one of our countrymen to office of the city government. Having one of our people in the local government, we would benefit a great deal not only from a political point of view but also from a national point of view. Who could give us sympathy and brotherly advice if not our countryman? We cannot get any help from Irishmen. They only help their own countrymen, not other nationalities.</p>
   <p>In the near future we expect to have our own candidates for some city government office and also for some county government office. In the near future we will write about the Lithuanian candidates who are running for various offices of the local government. For the coming primary this year, we want every Lithuanian <pb facs="5423970_1_0902.jpg" n="4"/>citizen to vote for the Lithuanian candidate regardless of his political or religious affiliations. We must all vote for Lithuanian candidates. If we don't, we shall never have our own representation in the local government. This is the time for us to unite and work in harmony, in order to reach our aims.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
