<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-26">Feb. 26, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Apostles of Czarist Despotism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-26">Feb. 26, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">APOSTLES OF CZARIST DESPOTISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The servants of Wall Street who sit in the United States Congress, have decided to imitate the despotism of old Czarist Russia. As if they were suddenly seized by an evil spell, they appear to be competing with each other to please the dollar aristocracy. Under the pretext of "necessary requirements of the country," "national defense," and other similar phrases, our statesmen, in Congress, are making preparations to bury all the old democratic rights of the people, and instead, give the citizens a policeman with a club in his hand.</p>
   <p>A large number of bills, for curbing the rights of aliens, have been introduced in Congress. The real purpose of these measures is to make aliens obedient and helpless slaves of the capitalists. The terms of some of these bills are so harsh and cruel that they can make even the old Czarist despots blush with shame. According to the provisions of these bills, all aliens, noncitizens, <pb facs="5423970_1_1307.jpg" n="2"/>who reside in this country, would be compelled not only to register but also be photographed and fingerprinted!</p>
   <p>In other words, an attempt is being made to place about seven million people in the same category with criminals! Even Czarist Russia did not have such tyrannical regulations.</p>
   <p>Other provisions of the bills are not any better. They are all inimical to the best interests of aliens and the entire American labor movement. The most repugnant feature of these bills is that they are aimed at all the workers in the whole United States. While under the constant surveillance of federal agents and local police, the aliens would be employed as tools to obstruct political and economic reform movements. In other words, the main purpose of all these anti-alien bills is to make all aliens political and economic strikebreakers.</p>
   <p>There are over seven million aliens in this country. Nearly all of them are <pb facs="5423970_1_1308.jpg" n="3"/>employed in the basic American industries. The enslavement of these seven million workers means also the enslavement of all other workers in this country. It is, therefore, very clear that all workers are endangered--aliens, foreign-born Americans, and native Americans.</p>
   <p>Slowly, but surely, native American workers are beginning to realize the danger with which they are being threatened. In various industrial centers committees are being formed for the defense of the rights of aliens in this country. Many influential members of the large unions are beginning to take an active interest in this matter. In other words, the war against the reactionary measures of Wall Street is developing into a gigantic mass protest.</p>
   <p>Lithuanian workers also must take an active part in this campaign to protect our constitutional rights. There are over one million Lithuanians living in the United States. Nearly all of them are workers. Therefore, if even one of those anti-alien bills is enacted into law, it would be a severe blow to the Lithuanian population of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
