<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 15,
<date when="1898-04-15">April 15, 1898</date><title level="a">We Need the Light</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial-Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 15,
<date when="1898-04-15">April 15, 1898</date><title level="a">WE NEED THE LIGHT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial-Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We need the light, science, this word is understood by every one, and yet we find by our own experience that the people, as a rule are afraid of education, even some of our leaders are trying their best to keep out the light of education from the unenlightened people. Education is not dangerous, but is essential at every step in our life. We are receiving letters from our readers, that the priests are denouncing those people who are reading newspapers and books of science; that education is dangerous, etc.</p>
   <p>We hardly can believe that the priests would go against the enlightenment of the people, that the priests would try to stop the people from reading newspapers and scientific books. We cannot understand how the priests can say that enlightenment is dangerous for religious people. Even religious people need enlightenment. How, then, are we to uplift materially the life of Lithuanians? Even a common laborer requires education. Why - the Swedes, the Germans, the Frenchmen... are paid better because they are more educated, <pb facs="5423970_1_0108.jpg" n="2"/>enlightened people than the Lithuanians! The Lithuanians, the Poles, the Italians, are working for cheaper pay because they are uneducated and unenlightened people.</p>
   <p>We Lithuanians and other unenlightened people have no influence in America. Even on election day the politicians are taking crowds of unenlightened people to the polls, because the politicians get the benefit, while the voters get contempt and humiliation.</p>
   <p>In Chicago there are over ten thousand Lithuanians. We have a Lithuanian parish school, but only thirty pupils are attending it. In Illinois, education is compulsory, and yet, the majority of Lithuanians are not sending their children to school, where education is free.</p>
   <p>We could have in Chicago a Lithuanian school at the expense and under the control of the government, and yet, we have no such school because <pb facs="5423970_1_0109.jpg" n="3"/>we do not care for education and for the future of our children. Do not forbid your children from attending public schools. No matter what kind of a school it is, there is always enlightenment and education. Now, no matter what kind of education it is, it is always better than darkness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
