<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-05-13">May 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">L. S. S. Local 22's Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0835</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0835.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-05-13">May 13, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">L. S. S. LOCAL 22's MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian Socialist League held its meeting on May 10, at the Meldazis Hall, West Side, Chicago. At the meeting the members of the Lithuanian Socialist League discussed the possibility of joining the Socialist Party. They agreed to vote and settle the argument for good. The results of voting were as follow: the total number of votes cast, as estimated, was twenty-four, and from that number of votes cast, as estimated, was twenty-four, and from that number two-thirds were in favor of joining the Socialist party. One third, or eight votes, were against joining that party. At the same meeting the members decided to contribute $10 to the League Press Fund to buy a press for the newspaper Struggle, which is supported by the Lithuanian Socialist League. During the discussion the editor of Struggle and Dr. Stanckus mentioned a few incidents and it was decided to send a letter of sympathy to the paper and, if necessary, to support it financially as much as possible.</p>
   <p>At this meeting the organization acquired two new members, who joined the L. S. S. Local 22 and brought up our total membership to fifty-six, <pb facs="5423970_1_0836.jpg" n="2"/>which includes the old and the new members.</p>
   <p>It is a remarkable thing that the members in this local have maintained such an amicable relationship among themselves. They discuss all things throughly whenever they are confronted with difficult problems; they scrutinize every little detail and come to a logical conclusion without any disagreement or altercation among them.</p>
   <p>This organization has existed for a good many years and during its existence has maintained a spirit of brotherly love.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
