<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-09-05">Sept. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">How Ought We to Regard the Representatives of the National Museum</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-09-05">Sept. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">HOW OUGHT WE TO REGARD THE REPRESENTATIVES OF THE NATIONAL MUSEUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian nation, like every other nation, has its public divided into groups with different viewpoints or parties. Every national problem that came up was discussed and decided by these groups, according to their point of view. There are many problems which have been approved by one or another of these groups. There are problems which are supported not by all, but by several groups. Are there no problems that not several groups, but all the groups together would feel they could support? Speaking on this matter, I have in mind a question that concerns all of us; what attitude ought we to take towards the National Museum of Lithuania? Well at the beginning, all of our groups, together, regardless of their views, recognized the necessity of supporting the proposal <pb facs="5423970_1_0568.jpg" n="2"/>for our National Museum. But in a short time--it is very strange from our point of view--we witnessed a sudden change of attitude towards this matter. From the start, it was recognized by nearly everybody that this project should be supported. But now, certain groups are obstructing it in every way that they can.</p>
   <p>What is the reason for this curious manifestation? The main argument they have is that they do not agree with their (Dr. Basanavicius and M. Ycas) views. Upon serious consideration, this argument has no grounds; it ought to be set aside without any explanation. Our public life has become so degenerate, has reached such a point, that in discussing this matter, we must use earnest arguments in order to prove their mistakes.</p>
   <p>The weakest point of their argument is that they do not know what the Lithuanian Science Society is, nor the persons who are representing this</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0569.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>society. The Lithuanian Science Society is nonpartisan. It does not belong to any political party, nor to any partisan group of any kind. It is a cultural society, [whose aim is] to spread culture among Lithuanians. Every conscientious Lithuanian belongs to one or another group. There-fore, every Lithuanian can belong to the Lithuanian Science Society. In joining the Lithuanian Science Society, every Lithuanian leaves behind him all of his political aspirations. In this society every one feels that he is a Lithuanian only, his duty is to spread or support culture. In this society there is no clerical, no socialist, no nationalist, no anarchist. They are only Lithuanians--members of the society. Thus they are, and so we look at them. The society's officials are among the most illustrious Lithuanians. They do not belong to any party.... Those persons are elected who support and care for the society's benefit only.</p>
   <p>This is the point upon which some of the Lithuanian groups are making their mistake. They claim that a member of this society can be of any <pb facs="5423970_1_0570.jpg" n="4"/>color. When an elected official of this society wants to act as a partisan, it is against the principles of the society, and all the members of this society oppose him. This is a violation of one of the fundamental principles of the Lithuanian Science Society--it is nonpartisan.</p>
   <p>What, then, would become of this society if, as some people suggest, it became a partisan group? Suppose they would elect as officials, clericals, progressive nationalists, socialists--then the trouble would start at once, because each one of them would work for his group. Other officials of this society would object to the socialists' point of view, and vice versa. Then, we could not progress even a needle's point. As the Russian saying goes, "it is impossible to see the woods for the trees (sic)."</p>
   <p>If we want to co-operate, and if we are willing to be of service to our nation--we can accomplish this through the Lithuanian Science Society <pb facs="5423970_1_0571.jpg" n="5"/>of Vilnus. We must understand clearly the fundamental co-operative principle of this society; then we will reap the benefit. We talk about patience and broad-mindedness. This is the place where we can express our tolerance and show our conscientiousness to the public. I doubt whether another such opportunity would come in a lifetime. I am emphasizing these words [for the benefit] of those people who are guilty of destructive work, and who cannot foresee their own mistakes. Let them stop for a moment and think it over; we have no doubt but that tomorrow they will become the ardent supporters of this project which they have denounced, and yesterday trampled under their feet.</p>
   <p>For such malicious persons....and yet they have no reasoning faculty.....A long time ago, the public designated a suitable place and name for such people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
