<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Aspirations and Activities of the Lithunanian-American Chamber of Commerce</title>, <date when="1930">1930</date>, in possession of Secretary, 3251 S. Halsted Street, Chicago, Ill.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1589</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1589.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the Aspirations and Activities of the Lithunanian-American Chamber of Commerce</title>, <date when="1930">1930</date>, in possession of Secretary, 3251 S. Halsted Street, Chicago, Ill.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is my great privilege and a pleasant duty as president of the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce to pass in review from time to time, the aspirations and activities of that body of the Lithuanian-American business - and professional men, who form this organization.</p>
   <p>The need of a central organization of business - and professional men was felt by the Chicago Lithuanians for a long time and on November 8, 1922 a meeting was held at the Great Northern Hotel where a proposal was made that such an organization should be formed. The proposal was unanimously accepted by all and steps were immediately taken for the materialization of the idea. Soon after, namely November 23, 1922, the proponents, together with many other Lithuanian business and professional men met at the Hotel LaSalle, where the committees appointed at the previous meeting made their reports, which was unanimously approved. It was at this meeting that the Constitution and By-Laws of the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce were adopted, the Board of Directors <pb facs="5423970_1_1590.jpg" n="2"/>elected, Committees appointed and the organization has become a reality, fully equipped for carrying on its business.</p>
   <p>For the clearer understanding of the aspirations and activities of the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce it is necessary to visualize the whole question of the Lithuanian migration to America, and the problems that confronted the Lithuanian immigrants in this country. And in this connection I wish to observe that the Lithuanian migration is of comparatively recent date. The earliest Lithuanian immigrants came to this country in the seventies. In the eighties the emigration from Lithuania increased in volume, and in the nineties it has become general and from that time on Lithuanians were coming to this country in such large numbers that about one-fourth, it not more, of the whole Lithuanian nation has settled in the United States for permanent residence.</p>
   <p>The immediate cause of this mass emigration of the Lithuanian from their native land to the United States was the unbearable conditions to which they were subjected by the Russian rule following the uprising of 1863-1864, which was crushed. When the uprising <pb facs="5423970_1_1591.jpg" n="3"/>was crushed,in 1864,the Russian government, which abolished serfdom in 1862, to win the good will of the peasants and to set them against nobility has inaugurated the policy of Russi fication of Lithuania. For this purpose the Lithuanian press was prohibited, all public offices denied to the Lithuanians of the Roman Catholic faith, and the invitation was made to adopt the Russian language and religion, together with the whole Russian culture. Menaced by the design of denationalization, Lithuanians determined to resist this policy by all possible means, and the Russian government soon discovered that its policy does not work as smoothly as was expected. Then the government resorted to the harsh tactics of oppression and penalized the country with economic ruin. Life has become unbearable and when the people learned that across the Atlantic there is a country enjoying freedom, liberty and happiness, Lithuanians fixed their minds on that country and decided to seek better opportunities in that far - off land.</p>
   <p>It was not an easy task for the people of the soil to adapt themselves to a city life in a highly industrialized country far away from home, whose language, customs, <pb facs="5423970_1_1592.jpg" n="4"/>manners and the whole mode of life was so strange, unfamiliar and contrary to their whole tradition. But, endowed with sound bodies and minds, and accustomed to toil they soon made themselves at home in the strange surroundings, won appreciation from their employers for faithful performance of the task, honesty and general reliability, and keeping steady their jobs, began laying the foundation for their brighter future. Resisting forceful Russification by all means at their command, they eagerly sought to acquire the American language, customs, habits and the ways of life. Thrifty by natural disposition, they have laid aside part of their earnings and by and by, came to a possession of small capital, which raised the question of investments. The majority invested their savings in real estate, and those who were more enterprising, engaged in business.</p>
   <p>Such was the origin of the Lithuanian business men in America. And in a similar manner, part of these immigrants recognized the opportunities offered by following professions, and took up study. Lithuanian settlements offered great opportunities to professional <pb facs="5423970_1_1593.jpg" n="5"/>men of their own nationality, and by and by, along with growing numbers of the Lithuanian business men, developed a large number of professional men - physicians, dentists, druggists, lawyers, architects, accountants, teachers, artists, and the like. Business men themselves recognized the need of educational training, and a large number of them acquired quite an extensive knowledge in finance, management, office routine, and general business methods. As the time goes on, these recent immigrants and especially their children lost entirely their old rural traits and become thoroughly adapted to the conditions prevailing in their adopted country. The number of the Lithuanian students in high-school and colleges increases from year to year, and they are not satisfied with merely passing exams, but strive for the highest honors, and already there are Lithuanian students in the American universities whose names are inscribed on the bronze tablets for the superior scholarship. This younger Lithuanian-American generation takes equally to sports and in this field also trains for championships.</p>
   <p>This brief summary of the Lithuanian-American history will make it clear why, in such <pb facs="5423970_1_1594.jpg" n="6"/>a comparatively short time, Lithuanians in Chicago alone came to a possession of two prominent state banks, about twenty-five well doing Building and Loan Associations, over a thousand various business enterprises, three daily and several weekly papers, twelve churches, and parochial schools, one college, several music conservatories, several singing and dramatic societies of high merit, a well equipped hospital, and a number of other cultural and economic institutions, all growing and developing very nicely.</p>
   <p>To bring together all these various business and professional elements for the co-ordination of their activities and the integration of their interests is the aspiration of the Lithuanian -American Chamber of Commerce. And inasmuch as Lithuanian has regained its independent national existence, and has become a member in the family of sovereign states, it is the aspiration and desire of the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce to become a factor in promoting friendship and mutual good will between these two republics. And furthermore it endeavors to exert a beneficial <pb facs="5423970_1_1595.jpg" n="7"/>influence on the people of Lithuania, both in developing their institutions and economic conditions.</p>
   <p>In the field of activities the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce makes no claim to any great achievements. In the last few years its object was to increase its membership and to cultivate among its members most friendly relations, which is the basis of all collective activities, and to afford to its members an opportunity to meet frequently for lunch and to exchange views on various current topics. It has established a cozy club-room at 814 W. 33rd Street in the Universal State Bank Building, where members can meet daily and discuss all matters of interest.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as most of the Lithuanian business men are doing business individually, this organization felt that their interests may be best promoted by arranging meetings, where modern methods could be fully explained, and co-operation encouraged. Several attempts at organizing such educational meetings were made, and there is a hope that <pb facs="5423970_1_1596.jpg" n="8"/>in the near future they will become very popular and it is planned that services of eminent economists for such occasions be secured.</p>
   <p>Encouragement of trade relations between America and Lithuania has always been a desire of their organizations and some of the members are already engaged in the importation of Lithuanian goods, with a promise of success. Further development of this program shal receive due attention.</p>
   <p>In local affairs, this organization is taking an active part in the arrangements of the Chicago World's Fair - The Century of Progress - of 1933, and in this matter is aiming at organizing all the Lithuanian elements for the purpose.</p>
   <p>On the program of the future activities is the publishing of a Lithuanian Business Directory, for which purpose most of the material is already gathered. It is hoped that all the Lithuanian business and professional men shall co-operate in this great undertaking.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1597.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>To give members and other Lithuanian business and professional men an opportunity to combine education with pleasure, the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce arranged in the summer of 1929 a picnic at Lockport, Illinois, where the locks of the Mississippi River were inspected. This picnic was attended by about four-hundred people.</p>
   <p>Another excursion was arranged jointly with the Central District Business Men's Association to the three-mile tunnel under Lake Michigan, being built for the purpose of water supply for Chicago. This excursion took place on December 11, 1920, with the co-operation of the City Engineer, L. D. Gayton of the City of Chicago.</p>
   <p>During all these years of its corporate existence, the Lithuanian Chamber of Commerce has participated in all the public activities of the Chicago Lithuanians and has always lent assistance to every worthy cause. Among such causes were the taking care of Lithuanian orphans, commemoration of historic events, honoring distinguished Lithuanians, and helping Lithuanian institutions. Representatives of the Lithuanian government were <pb facs="5423970_1_1598.jpg" n="10"/>invariably appropriately received and entertained, and when the first Lithuanian Minister to the United States, Mr. B.K.Balutis, came to Chicago in February of last year, a banquet in his honor, as well as a commemoration of the 11th anniversary of Lithuanism independence was given in the "Golden Room," Congress Hotel, and subsequent to that he was introduced to Mayor Thompson and the City Council of Chicago, where he was given a warm reception. He laid a wreath at Lincoln's monument in Lincoln Park, and also visited the University of Chicago and other institutions, escorted by the members of this organization.</p>
   <p>In the program of commemoration of historic events, the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce has arranged an excursion to Lithuania, headed by its secretary, Mr. J. P. Varkals, who will sail from New York, O.S.S. Paris, June 12, 1930 to participate in the commemoration of the 500th anniversary of the death of Lithuanians national hero, Vytautas the Great, the Grand Duke of Lithuania.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1599.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>There are some of the activities of the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce briefly stated. And as it is a first venture to bring Lithuanian business and professional men together, their response to every good cause is most encouraging and holds a promise that in the future they shall act collectively in all important matters and thereby promote the best interests of the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
