<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 37,
<date when="1907-09-13">9-13-1907</date>.
<title level="a">The New Charter of Chicago</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Synopsis)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0998</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0998.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LIETUVA</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 37,
<date when="1907-09-13">9-13-1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW CHARTER OF CHICAGO</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Synopsis)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Previously. "Lietuva" reported on the new charter for the city of Chicago. This time we will discuss more broadly what this new charter will give the citizens of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The new charter will make the mayor the dictator of Chicago; the mayor will have such power, that he can do as he pleases with the citizens of this city. The mayor can remove all the officials under him and in their place can appoint whom be wishes.</p>
   <p>The new charter gives power to the mayor to raise taxes on the people for the sum of $6,000,000,00. The taxes, as we know, always are paid by the workers, the rich capitalists are always freed from taxes. The new taxes will be a burden on the common people. This is not all: The new charter permits the city administration to make a new loan on the city for the sum of $40,000,000.00. This loan also will be a burden on the workers.</p>
   <p>This new chart will give power to be mayor to assist with special taxes <pb facs="5423970_1_0999.jpg" n="2"/>every tradesman and businessman.</p>
   <p>If the city administration dislikes any tradesman and businessman, it can revoke his license. Then such a worker cannot get a job anymore in Chicago. It will be the same with the businessman; he could not open a business in Chicago if the city administration or the mayor will not like him.</p>
   <p>According to the new charter, the mayor will have absolute power to control the schools. That the mayor dictates, the pupils must be taught. The mayor will stop the enlightenment of students; we know that the American politicians do not want to have an enlightened public.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time, if the street car company wanted to place street cars on the street, it had to get the signatures of the people of the street. Under the new charter, the street company will ask the mayor for permission, but not of the people. Therefore, as citizens, if you don't want to be under the absolute control of the financial masters of this city, vote against the new charter on the 17th day of September. Under the new charter, the citizens will be forced to take passports. The new charter will close all the theaters, <pb facs="5423970_1_1000.jpg" n="3"/>dancing halls, banquets and other amusements on Sunday. The workers have only one day, Sunday, to have their pleasure day, now all this will be closed.</p>
   <p>Citizens of Chicago! On the 17th day of September be sure to vote against the new charter! Mark a cross in the rubric where it says, "Against an Act entitled", and everybody go to vote against this new scheme that the politicians want to put on the people's shoulders. Vote against the new charter!</p>
   <p>J. Ilgaudas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
