<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-10-19">Oct. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Anna Doris--First Lithuanian Aviatrix</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-10-19">Oct. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ANNA DORIS--FIRST LITHUANIAN AVIATRIX</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We do not know whether there is a Lithuanian aviator in America or the rest of the world, but we have learned a few days ago that in Chicago there is a Lithuanian aviatrix. Her name is Anna Doris. She has completed an aviation course in the Moler Aviation School, Chicago, and has already made several long trips in the air. Miss Doris is American born, but she can speak very good Lithuanian. In an interview with B. K. Balutis, editor of Lietuva (Lithuania), she stated that her greatest ambition is to become a famous aviatrix. She plans to go to South America, and for that reason she is now studying the Spanish language. She said she is making fast progress with her Spanish lessons, because she has already mastered the Italian language.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1403.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss Doris is also an inventor. She has invented an airplane safety belt for which she has secured a patent. The belt makes it possible for a pilot to release himself instantly when something goes wrong with the plane. When Mr. Balutis reminded her that she is engaged in a very dangerous occupation, she answered:</p>
   <p>"It only appears to be so, but it is not. Believe it or not, I feel safer in an airplane than in an automobile. There are no telephone poles, store windows, or sidewalks to bump into in the air. I float in the air as though I were sitting on a soft pillow. It is a wonderful experience."</p>
   <p>Miss Doris is probably the first Lithuanian aviatrix in the world. As far as we know, Vytautas Gray [Graiciunas], eldest son of Dr. A. L. Graiciunas, will probably be the first Lithuanian aviator. He has enlisted in the aviation corps of the United States Army and is now taking a special course in the United States war aviation branch school at the University <pb facs="5423970_1_1404.jpg" n="3"/>of Illinois. He is nineteen years of age.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
