<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1892-12-10">Dec. 10, 1892</date><title level="a">How Lithuanians of Today Ought to Look Toward Poles and Their Language</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0656</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0656.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 1,
<date when="1892-12-10">Dec. 10, 1892</date><title level="a">HOW LITHUANIANS OF TODAY OUGHT TO LOOK TOWARD POLES AND THEIR LANGUAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On this question I will give a short answer.</p>
   <p>Lithuanians of today should not fancy about Polish language, because that language will not help us in Lithuania, nor in America. In America, it is understood by all, that the English language is a necessity to everyone, that without the English language a man cannot exist. In Lithuania under the Russian government, was a Russian language, under Germany, was German language. Lithuanians must turn to that side which is most beneficial to them. Although we cannot hold Poles as our enemies, we are obliged to give them as much rights, just as much as to Germans, French and other nations. Today all the enlightened in the world, except the rich and the rulers, are anxious to have freedom for humanity in material and spiritual needs and for this reason we cannot be intolerant towards other nations. Of course, we cannot forget our own language, which must be first to Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>Patriotism is necessary, but it must not be extreme fanaticism. It would be beneficial if every nation would once in a while raise the question of cosmopolitanism.</p>
   <p>Memersys</p>
   <p>The skylark.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
