<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-08-10">Aug. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Are the Military Execption Boards Unfair?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-08-10">Aug. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ARE THE MILITARY EXECPTION BOARDS UNFAIR?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reports are pouring in that in several districts the local military exemption boards are unfair to some men. It is reported that some of the boards try to force men into the army who have legal grounds for exemption from army service. Some reports state that these boards or their members refuse to issue blanks for making exemption claims; still other reports state that members of the boards snow partiality to certain nationalities, that they assist men of some nationalities to claim exemption but deny the service to men of other nationalities. We have also received complaints that in some districts aliens are forced to take out first citizenship papers under threats of deportation.</p>
   <p>We must not allow any of these threats to scare us. We must insist and demand everywhere that the exemption boards do their full duty--no more and no less. All irregularities of the exemption boards and their members should be immediately reported to higher authorities who will punish them for their unlawful conduct.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1176.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In some districts the government is already investigating alleged irregularities by local exemption boards.</p>
   <p>Every man has a right to claim exemption from army service if he has not declared his intention to become a citizen, or if he has a wife, children, old parents, or small brothers and sisters to support. Everyone has a right to take advantage of this privilege. When a law is enacted to draft into the army those who do not have first citizenship papers, then the Lithuanian aliens will do their army duty. However, in the absence of such a law, every Lithuanian without first papers has a right to claim exemption. Lithuanian aliens do not intend to serve in the army while aliens of other nationalities are exempted from military service.</p>
   <p>In time of war all must be equal; all must have equal rights, responsibilities, and obligations. When the government will want aliens to do military duty, it will enact a law to that effect, and, in respect to Lithuanian aliens, it will make some agreement with Russia. Then everyone will be treated equally. In the absence of such a law and such agreements with foreign countries, no member of <pb facs="5423970_1_1177.jpg" n="3"/>any exemption board has the right to force any alien into the army. They also do not have the right to exempt men of one nationality and deny exemption to men of another nationality. Higher authorities of the government should be immediately informed whenever or wherever such irregularities occur in any exemption board district.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
