<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>, Vol. I, No. 21,
<date when="1899-05-25">May 25, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Correspondence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>, Vol. I, No. 21,
<date when="1899-05-25">May 25, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">CORRESPONDENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>May 20, 1898</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>Hereby I have acknowledged the receipt of two dollars for the subscription of Lietuva. I will send to you the next issue as soon as possible. As for your request in your letter to write in our paper Lietuva about your villainous wife, I regret to say, my dear countryman, that such publicity will not do any good. These evils cannot be corrected. Such publicity may even make it worse; instead of correcting such people it may encourage them to be more obdurate. I know that you will not benefit at all by doing such a thing. Moreover, it is against journalistic ethics, and degrading to the paper and the nation to publish such an advertisement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0284.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We should have national pride besides being good Catholics, especially among our Lithuanians; we should bear our national dignity among other nations. I wish to repeat that again, that I am very sorry that I cannot fulfill your request, and I hope you will understand my reasons. My best advice for you is to go to the Domestic Relations Court, where you could settle your domestic troubles. If you cannot get along with your wife, you have a right to divorce her. Then you will be able to find another lady that will love you. But first, you must divorce your wife before you can marry another lady. Of course, some crazy Catholic priest may object to your marriage again in the Catholic Church. But a broad-minded, intelligent and cultured priest will not consider your second marriage in the Catholic Church as a sin. We know that God would never force any one to live with a murderer or a dissolute person, and for divorcing bad wives or husbands God will not punish those people after death. Don't be afraid and don't pay any attention to the old ladies' gossip that you will be punished by God.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>A. Olszewskis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
