<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-22">Jan. 22, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Abolish Private Ownership of Industry</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-22">Jan. 22, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ABOLISH PRIVATE OWNERSHIP OF INDUSTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2. The domination of the capitalists is becoming increasingly repugnant to the people. Looking only after their own selfish interests, the capitalists conduct business and industrial affairs in a manner that causes wide-spread suffering to the entire public.</p>
   <p>The workers, on whose backs the greatest burden of such a system falls, were the first to recognize its evil character. Through the lips of their defenders, the Socialists, the workers have been declaring for a long time that the people must abolish private ownership of the means of production and take them over into their own hands as public property.</p>
   <p>The more intelligent members of the bourgeoisie are beginning to realize the necessity of public ownership of the means of production. This class, naturally, <pb facs="5423970_1_1355.jpg" n="2"/>cannot advocate the abolition of all private property, because then they would be renouncing the foundation of their means of livelihood. But in certain instances they sometimes take a firm stand against the present system of private ownership.</p>
   <p>The above fact has been demonstrated during the past three days in the United States Congress. D. J. Lewis, chairman of the committee on labor, made the suggestion before the House of Representatives that the government should take over into its own hands all coal and iron mines. Mr. Lewis, of course, is not the entire Congress, and it is even doubtful if he possesses the necessary courage to carry on a campaign until his suggestion by a leading congressman can be construed as a definite trend of the modern era.</p>
   <p>If the bourgeoisie themselves are beginning to realize that the social order which they uphold is no good, then how can anyone honestly defend that system?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
