<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-12">May 12, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Business and Patriotism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-12">May 12, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">BUSINESS AND PATRIOTISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The slogan of the American patriots is to "melt in the pot of Americanism" all immigrants of all nationalities and thus make them pure Americans in accordance with the motto "America first, last and forever". If that slogan receives support from anyone, then it is probably in the middle and small business circles. That slogan is altogether foreign and even inimical to the giant capitalists. A good example of this is the famous farm machinery manufacturing company in Chicago [McCormick's]. The company's employees are now conducting a bitter struggle for a bigger bite of bread. The policy of that company has always been to hire workers from as many nationalities as possible so as to prevent the employees from becoming organized. The more nationalities there are among the employees, and the more different languages they speak, so much harder it is for them to understand each other and organize. It is very difficult for such a group of employees to learn how to speak a common language, the English language; in their homes they meet only people who speak their own language <pb facs="5423970_1_0684.jpg" n="2"/>and do not use English. In the factory they meet only people who speak languages other than English. They have no opportunity to learn to speak English. Thus they are badly exploited, but being unable to talk to each other properly and understand one another, they continue to quietly submit themselves to long suffering.</p>
   <p>This is a rather clever policy of the capitalists for, to certain extent, they can and do achieve their purpose. So far, in such giant industries as the above-mentioned farm machinery manufacturing company where thousands of workers of a great variety of nationalities are employed, there has been no workers' organizations or ties among them of any kind! The very same thing is true in regard to the stockyards, and all other giant capitalistic institutions. The capitalists are doing everything within their means to keep their employees divided and away from each other; in order to do so they hire workers from as many nationalities as possible, keep their employees in darkness and ignorance by denying them an opportunity to become enlightened, and by preventing them from becoming "Americanized".</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0685.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The capitalists know very well that lofty ideals and patriotism cannot be expected of ignorant people. But the capitalists are not at all concerned with that. They are, first of all, interested in business. And for the sake of business they let patriotism go to the devil!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
