<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce Reports</title>, in Possession of Secretary, Lithuanian American Chamber of Commerce, Chicago,Ill.
<title level="a">Constitution and By-Laws of the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce of Illinois:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1557</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1557.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce Reports</title>, in Possession of Secretary, Lithuanian American Chamber of Commerce, Chicago,Ill.
<title level="a">CONSTITUTION AND BY-LAWS OF THE LITHUANIAN-AMERICAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE OF ILLINOIS:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Article 1. - Name:</p>
   <p>The name of this organization shall be the Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce.</p>
   <p>Article II. - Objects:</p>
   <p>Section 1. Objects. The Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce is organized for the purpose of establishing closer commercial, economic, industrial and political relations between the United States and the Republic of Lithuania; to defend, promote and advance political integrity; to organize an exchange of industrial and commercial statistics, and of information of value between Lithuania and the United States, and to present the Lithuanian situation in its proper light to the American people.</p>
   <p>Section Z. Limitation of Methods. This Chamber of Co erce and its activities shall be non-partisan, non-sectional and non-sectarian.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1558.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Article III. - Membership:</p>
   <p>Section 1. Classes of Membership. The Lithuanian-American Chamber of Commerce shall be composed of active members, Associate members and honorary members Men of good standing, interested in the commercial, industrial and political program of Lithuania, shall be eligible for active and associate membership. Distinction in affairs shall confer eligibility to honorary membership. Honorary membership shall include all the privileges of active members except that of holding office, with exemption from the payment of all fees and dues.</p>
   <p>Section 2. Active. Canditates for active membership shall make written application to the board of Directors, and this application shall be regarded as a guarantee on the part of the applicant of his interest and sympathy with the purpose of the organization, and of his adherence, if elected, to its by-laws, rules and regulations. Election to active membership shall require the recommendation of the Membership Committee and shall be posted on the bulletin board. Objection to any applicant recommended for election by the Membership <pb facs="5423970_1_1559.jpg" n="3"/>Committee shall be communicated to the Board of Directors before the meeting of the Board at which the eligibility of the candidate is to be considered. At each regular meeting of the Chamber of Commerce the names of members elected since the preceding meeting shall be announced.</p>
   <p>Section 3. Associate. Associate membership shall be comfined to those members who cannot take part in the activities of this Chamber of Commerce. Associate membership shall include all the privileges of active membership, except that of holding office.</p>
   <p>Section 4. Honorary. Honorary members may be nominated by the Membership Committee and elected by the Board of Directors. A proposal to confer honorary membership may be made in writing to the Membership Committee by any member of the Chamber of Commerce. If the Membership Committee approve such a proposal, the name shall be presented in nomination to the Directors, with a brief statement of the reasons thereof. If such nomination shall be approved by the Board of Director's announcement of such approval shall be posted on the bulletin <pb facs="5423970_1_1560.jpg" n="4"/>board for a period of ten days. Objection thereto may be communicated to the Board of Directors in writhing within this period. If a nominee shall receive an affirmative vote of the Board of Directors he shall be declared elected. Two negative votes shall defeat a proval by the Membership Committee of a proposal for honorary membership, and three negative votes shall defeat election by the Board of Directors. Every election to honorary membership shall be announced to the Chamber of Commerce at its first meeting thereafter. An honorary membership may be revoked by the Board of Directors at any time.</p>
   <p>Section 5. Dues. Each active member shall pay ten dollars annually as dues toward the maintenance of the Chamber of Commerce, two dollars of which shall be for annual subscription to the official organ of this Chamber of Commerce. These dues shall be payable on the first day of December. Members elected during the fiscal year shall pay prorate for the months intervening between the date of election and the first day of December. Associate members dues shall be five dollars per year, two dollars of which shall be for annual subscription to the official organ of this Chamber of Congress.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1561.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Section 6. Dolinquincy. If any member shall fail to pay his dues within three months after date of maturity, ten days written notice of delinquency shall be given to him by the Treasurer. If at the end of ten days he still remains delinquent his membership may be forfeited by action of the Board of Directors.</p>
   <p>Section 7. Rebatement. The Directors shall have the power to rebate the dues of any delinquent member, and continue his membership in good standing. The Directors may also rebate the dues of any member unable to avail himself of the privileges of the organization by reason of lillness, absence from the city or any other cause while such cause is existent.</p>
   <p>Section 8. Resignations. All resignations shall be tendered to the Board of Dirextors in writing. A resignation received after a payment is due shall not relieve the member presenting such resignation from liability for the dues of the year entered upon.</p>
   <p>Section 9. Expulsion. Any member may be expelled for cause by resolution passed by two-thirds of the entire Board of Directors at any meeting. Such members <pb facs="5423970_1_1562.jpg" n="6"/>shall be notified of the intention of the Board to consider his expulsion and shall be given the opportunity of a hearing before the Board, but shall not be represented by professional counsel. Passage of such resolution shall, without other act on the part of the Board of Directors, annul such membership.</p>
   <p>Article IV - Board of Directors.</p>
   <p>The government of the Chamber of Commerce, the direction of its work and the control of its property shall be vested in a Board of Directors consisting of fifteen members, who shall be elected annually as hereafter provided. Their duties shall begin within the three days following their election, when they shall meet, qualify and elect from their own nimber a president, four vicepresidents, a treasurer and secretary. The directors shall have power to fill all vacancies in the Board. They may adopt rules and regulations for conducting the business of the Chamber of Commerce. They shall meet not less than once a month. At the annual meeting they shall submit in writing a full report of the work and finances of the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1563.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Article VII - Meeting.</p>
   <p>Section 1. Annual. The annual meeting of the Chamber of Commerce shall be held on the first Tuesday in December of each year. Regular meetings of the Chamber of Commerce shall take place upon the dates determinable by the Board of Directors, not less than once in three months. Special meetings of the Chamber of Commerce may be held when the Board of Directors deems it desirable. Twenty members shall constitute a quorum at any regular or special meeting of the Chamber of Commerce.</p>
   <p>Article VIII - Elections.</p>
   <p>Section 1. Elections. The election of Directors shall be held on the first Thursday in December of each year.</p>
   <p>Section 2. Nominating. At the last regular meeting of the Chamber of Commerce prior to the annual election a vote shall be taken by ballot on open nomination for the selection of a Nominating Committee. Due notice of such meeting shall be previously given to each member by the secretary. The five members receiving <pb facs="5423970_1_1564.jpg" n="8"/>the highest number of votes cast shall constiute the Nominating Committee.</p>
   <p>Section 3. Official. The Nominating Committee shall prepare a list of twenty-eight candidates to be known as the "official ticket", from which members select fifteen for directors.</p>
   <p>Article IX - Disbursements.</p>
   <p>No disbursements of the funds of the Chamber of Commerce shall be made unless the same shall have been approved and ordered by the Executive Committee or Board of Directors. All disbursements shall be made by check. Checks shall be signed by the secretary and countersigned by the president, or one of the vice-presidents, or the treasurer.</p>
   <p>No appropriations of money or other property of the Chamber of Commerce shall be made for any purpose other than to defray the legitimate expenses, except by the unanimous vote of the members present at a meeting of the Board of Directors, or a four-fifths vote of those present at a meeting of the Chamber of Commerce.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1565.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Article XII - Amendments.</p>
   <p>Section 1. By-Laws. These by-laws may be amended or altered by a two-thirds vote of those present at any regular or special meeting, provided notice of the proposed change shall have been posted on the bulletin board and mailed by the secretary to each member not less than ten days prior to such meeting.</p>
   <p>Section 2. Approval. All proposed amendments shall first receive the approval of the Board of Directors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
