<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">At the Beginning of the Scholastic Year</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">AT THE BEGINNING OF THE SCHOLASTIC YEAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The European War has created much confusion even on this side of the sea. The attention of the entire American public is directed eastward, where the greatest slaughter in the history of mankind is taking place. The immigrants who, in many instances, have left behind their parents, brothers, sisters, and others close to themselves are especially worried about the conflict which has arisen.</p>
   <p>Lithuania, along with many other nations, has been drawn into the war. Therefore, the heart of every Lithuanian in America aches, and grief and worry have taken hold of us, even though we are far removed from the thunder of the cannons and the rivulets of blood. The attention of the Lithuanians in America is directed overseas and private, daily, and local affairs are forgotten.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0057.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the most important and most neglected matters is school attendance. Over here, perhaps more so than in any other land, great pleasure is derived from speaking about enlightenment and education, but such speeches have little practical value. Our youth coming here is not very much inclined to education. We cannot say whether the lack of inclination is innate or whether our youth does not know how to gain admittance to the schools, but the fact remains a fact: there could be many more Lithuanians in the schools than we see there now.</p>
   <p>Since the value and importance of education has been spoken of so often, we do not see any need for repeating the facts again. In their appeals in behalf of education and study, the Lithuanian newspapers have covered the matter in such great detail that it would be almost impossible to find a new argument which has not been mentioned already, which has not been hammered into the readers many times, and which has not been known by newspaper readers for a long time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0058.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The one thing we can do here is to remind the readers that this month is the beginning of the scholastic year in the United States. By now most of the schools have begun their scholastic terms. But even those who are late still have the opportunity to enroll and thus avoid wasting the school season. There are schools in every town of the United States which can be attended by Lithuanians during the day or in the evening. Those Lithuanians who live in larger colonies are especially fortunate in this respect. Our young men and women should take advantage of even the smallest opportunity for educating themselves. They will later receive a hundredfold reward for the work they begin now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
