<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-06">Jan. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">What Our Professionals Teach</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Voice of the People Column)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-06">Jan. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT OUR PROFESSIONALS TEACH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Voice of the People Column)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.... Some of our Professionals say that people who do not have the honor of wearing a toga and the right to smoke cigars wrapped in tin foil, should be prohibited from writing newspaper articles. However, they do not practice what they preach. Are any examples necessary? There are so many so very many of them.</p>
   <p>For instance take a priest: He goes into his pulpit on Sundays and urges all his parishioners to say their prayers at least twice each day, that is, when going to bed and upon rising in the morning. But as far as I know the priests themselves go to bed without saying their prayers, and then certain botanical or chemical scientists pop up with their teachings. In their talks and writings they passionately urge people not to be afraid to keep windows open so that their homes will always have fresh air; saying impure air breeds all <pb facs="5423970_1_0176.jpg" n="2"/>kinds of disease, etc. etc! But readers, just look at the windows in the homes of these savants, especially during the winter months. Their windows are so tightly closed that even smoke from the above mentioned cigars is unable to leak out.</p>
   <p>We are also confronted with agitators against smoking and drinking. Those who wear the toga paint ghastly pictures of warning to smokers. They point out how it affects our health, and how good money is needlessly wasted away into smoke and into thin air.</p>
   <p>A Lithuanian proverb says: "When a farmer in Lithuania puts on a new pair of rubber overshoes over his old patched boots, then he must be sure to have a thoroughbred horse, a brightly painted sleigh, and a beautiful horse-whip otherwise those overshoes will look out of place." (What a long proverb? Editor.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0177.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The very same thing is true with our professional people? When they don the toga they must necessarily find a ten cent cigar and make so much smoke that even without the addition of salt their flesh would not become wormy.</p>
   <p>Well, what do you readers say about that? In my opinion our professional people should first of all practice what they preach.</p>
   <p>For instance, if a professor in a class room would spit towards the ceiling, would not his students stand on chairs and do likewise?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
