<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-23">Feb. 23, 1926</date><title level="a">Notice to Coal Strike Contributors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0394</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0394.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-02-23">Feb. 23, 1926</date><title level="a">NOTICE TO COAL STRIKE CONTRIBUTORS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The long strike of anthracite coal miners ended Feb. 7. The Central Committee for the Relief of Strikers has informed the Lithuanian public, through the Chicago district of the Lithuanian-American Workers Literary Society, that the coal strikers' relief fund was liquidated on the day the strike ended. Those who have made collections, and still have funds on hand are advised to donate the money to some other worthy, working class cause.</p>
   <p>The Central Strike Committee has sent the following letter of thanks to the Lithuanian public.</p>
   <p>"We are very grateful to all those who have donated for the relief of hungry, coal mine strikers and their families.</p>
   <p>"Whenever, you, fellow workers of other industries, find it necessary to go out on strike against your exploiters as we have done, then we will always be with you, and will gladly assist you as much as possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0395.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"We appealed to you for aid, and you did not fail to answer with generous donations to assist us in the hour of our greatest need. We were engaged in a very hard struggle. We shall never forget your generosity and sympathy. In the history of coal mining, it will be written in large letters that workers of all industries have common interests and needs. No matter in what industry we are employed, we are all lashed brutally by the whip of the present rotten social order."</p>
   <p>A detailed statement of the strike fund will be made, shortly, in the Lithuanian newspapers. Contributors to the fund will be told what has been done with their money.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
