<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-11-21">Nov. 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanians Become Acquainted with the Farm-Land of Wisconsin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-11-21">Nov. 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIANS BECOME ACQUAINTED WITH THE FARM-LAND OF WISCONSIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday evening, at Davis Square Park Hall, Town of Lake, B. G. Packer, Immigration Commissioner of the State of Wisconsin, delivered a lecture on farming in Wisconsin. This same lecture, in a Lithuanian version, was delivered by Dr. A. L. Graicunas. The lecture was illustrated by lantern slides of land suitable for farming, and the methods of cultivating land. About two hundred people were present.</p>
   <p>The State of Wisconsin takes great interest in farming and spends large sums of money to help the farmers. Wisconsin, for taking an interest in farms, stands as a model to other States. Recently the government of Wisconsin began taking a great interest in immigrants, who are crowded in cities, and wants to bring them back to the farms. The State of Wisconsin does not sell the lands, but gives information to those who want to buy farm-land. The State also informs the buyer what crops can be produced on such a farm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1481.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Packer is sent to Chicago by the State of Wisconsin. Here he delivers illustrated lectures before Lithuanians, Poles, and other nationalities about the land in Wisconsin. During the lecture, he shows several hundred lantern slides, which illustrate the conditions and the mode of farming in various parts of the State.</p>
   <p>This coming Saturday, November 22, at 8 P. M., in Davis Square Park Hall, a lecture will be delivered before Lithuanians only. Admission is free. We would advise anyone interested in farming to attend this lecture, because you will get reliable information, which you cannot get from private farm agencies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
