<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1911-12-29">Dec. 29, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Have Our Banquets Without Liquor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1911-12-29">Dec. 29, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">LET US HAVE OUR BANQUETS WITHOUT LIQUOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Chicago, not matter what the Lithuanian organizations present, [be it] theater, concert or other forms of entertainment, liquor is always sold. It seems as though we cannot have a program without selling liquor.</p>
   <p>For example, compare the Lithuanian activity in other cities. The Lithuanians there have their halls and libraries--we in Chicago have nothing. True, we have the Aurora school and library, but considering the number of Lithuanians in Chicago, this means very little.</p>
   <p>Here are the facts: The Dr. V. Kudirka Society has proposed that a library be established on the West Side. [Trans. note: "west side" means 22nd and Leavitt streets district.] The following societies have considered and approved the project: The Farmers of Lithuania Society, The Lovers of the Fatherland Society (branch), and The Lithuanian Socialists Alliance of America, branch 22. The delegates of these societies held their meeting, and decided, that every <pb facs="5423970_1_0257.jpg" n="2"/>member of each society shall pay five cents now, and one cent per month for the upkeep of the library. They also decided that every society shall contribute five per cent of its yearly income. So far so good. One saloon keeper has promised to give his hall free for the use of the library. The delegates then decided to have a banquet for the benefit of the library. Here is where the "hitch" came--to sell or not to sell liquor at the banquet. Disagreement arose on this point. The delegates of the Dr. V. Kudirka Society and the delegates of the Socialists, branch 22, voted against the sale of liquor at the banquet. And they also gave warning that if their delegates, or the members of their societies should attend a banquet [where liquor was sold], they would be fined by their societies. The farmers of Lithuania Society, and the Lovers of the Fatherland delegates voted to sell liquor at the banquet. What irony!</p>
   <p>They decided to have a big program--to have the finest speakers, for example, Messrs. Balevicius, Biezis and Bucinskas, and to ask the Birutes Choir to sing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0258.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And then, when this splendid program is over, all will rush to the keg of beer for enlightenment and cultural enrichment.</p>
   <p>Those societies that voted for the sale of liquor already have moved into the saloon keeper's hall, and are begging the other two societies, that voted against the sale of liquor, to move in--into the saloon hall.</p>
   <p>Then, during a conversation with the saloon-keeper, he said that for permission to keep the library in his hall, he would charge a small rental--only two hundred dollars a year!</p>
   <p>Isn't this splendid? Of course it is....The banquet will take place around New Year's.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
