<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1926-12-10">Dec. 10, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Judge John T. Zuris Installed</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0924</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0924.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1926-12-10">Dec. 10, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE JOHN T. ZURIS INSTALLED</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1....John T. Zuris, the first Lithuanian to win a place on the Chicago judicial bench, was installed as Associate Judge of the Municipal Court last Monday, December 7th. The new judge will occupy room 1106, City Hall. The installation ceremonies were attended by several hundred people, who crowded the courtroom to capacity.</p>
   <p>Chicago's Mayor, E.J.Kelly, did the first honors; in his speech he clearly outlined the active part that young Lithuanians took in Chicago's political affairs. Among the Lithuanian speakers were the newspaper men, Leonard Simutis and Vaidyla; Clergy, Reverend A. Baltutis; business men, J. Mackiewich, who was also the president of the late John T. Zuris Boosters' organization. The lawyers were represented by their president, Rudy A. Vasalle. Radio hour representative was Anthony Olis. Chicago Lithuanian Democratic organization representative was Doctor J.Poska of the 13th ward club. A total of about twenty speakers showered <pb facs="5423970_1_0925.jpg" n="2"/>congratulations upon our young judge during the morning's proceedings.</p>
   <p>Mackiewich, Poska, and Mr. Vasalle presented the new judge with practical gifts, while the courtroom was crowded with baskets of flowers from business and political friends and fraternal organizations. After the proceedings, many of the Honorable Judge's friends gathered for lunch at the Hotel Brevoort Gold Room where more speeches were heard, and everyone had an unusually fine time celebrating, eating, drinking, and even singing, far into the afternoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
