<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-02-09">Feb. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">America and the War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1213</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1213.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-02-09">Feb. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICA AND THE WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past two and a half years, America did everything within her power to keep out of the European war. Today, however, the United States has been forced to sever diplomatic relations with Germany, and may become involved in the war against her will.</p>
   <p>A severance of diplomatic relations does not mean war, but it can easily lead to war. Examples taken from history show that whenever two major powers sever diplomatic relations they usually become engaged in war, This was true of [the powers that fought] the Russo-Japanese War, and it may become true of the United States and Germany.</p>
   <p>If war comes--and war can come only if the Germans really start sinking American ships with citizens on board--it will not be the fault of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1214.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>By its present attitude, the United States takes its stand not only for its own rights, but also for the rights of all mankind; the United States takes its stand for the defense of liberty and human righteousness, for which principles this country has shed its blood more than once.</p>
   <p>One hundred and thirty years ago, when the American colonists rose up against England and waged a war for independence, they fought against English tyranny, which was unjustly restricting the liberty of the freedom-loving colonists. By that war the United States became an independent nation.</p>
   <p>In the latter part of the nineteenth century, the Americans spilled oceans of blood during a great civil war. That war was likewise fought for the principles of liberty and human rights--for the freedom of millions of Negroes from the bonds of slavery.</p>
   <p>The present difficulty which the United States is having with Germany is also based on a principle--the great principle of liberty. The United States is <pb facs="5423970_1_1215.jpg" n="3"/>determined today, as in 1776 and 1864 (sic), to defend the rights of its citizens, those rights which belong equally to all mankind.</p>
   <p>Everyone can readily understand the necessity of going to war when our country is attacked, and when our homes and lives are threatened with destruction. But only those who know the true meaning of principles, civilization, and humani-tarianism can understand a war waged for principles, civilization, and humani-tarianism. We do not know whether or not the United States and Germany will go to war; that is something no one can tell at this time. But we who have witnessed the unlimited patience of President Wilson during the past two and a half years are convinced that it will not be the fault of the United States if it is forced into war to protect the rights of its citizens. America has never permitted--and probably will not now permit--any nation to dictate to United States citizens, telling them what they must do, and how and where they must go.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
