<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Kaiser Must Be Removed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1181</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1181.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE KAISER MUST BE REMOVED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is understood that the kaiserists and worshippers of kaiserism do not see any reason whatsoever why the kaiser should be removed. Even many sound-thinking and conscientious people are of the opinion that all attacks against the kaiser are merely unfounded shouts of foreign chauvinists, jingoists, and so-called "patriots". However, all that is not true. Besides many other reasons, there is one reason which everyone can and should clearly understand. Let us not forget the year 1914. Let us remember that during the latter part of July in that year 1914. Let us remember that during the latter part of July in that year, when France, England, Russia, and Italy proposed a conference to settle the dispute between Austria and Serbia, when even Austria herself expressed a desire to deliberate with Russia, then the entire ghastly question of war or peace depended solely upon the word of the kaiser and not upon the word of the German people. The kaiser uttered the word. As a result, seven million human beings have already died on the battlefields, all on account of one word uttered by one man.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1182.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today, there is no other man among civilized nations who has so much power as the kaiser. The world has already progressed too far to be able to further tolerate such a Middle-Age autocrat. For that reason, all friends of peace and liberty demand not only the removal of the kaiser but also the destruction of such an autocracy under which the word of one man could cause the slaughter of an entire nation. For three long years (or more) his word has caused unheard of misery, tears, and seas of blood to be imposed upon humanity; these three years have cost the people a very dear price, and for that reason they cannot forget them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
