<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-05-11">May 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Democracy Versus Kaiserism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1189</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1189.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-05-11">May 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DEMOCRACY VERSUS KAISERISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The slogan of the entire world today is everywhere the same--Kaiserism must be banished from the face of the earth. Now that Russia has freed herself from the bands of monarchism, Germany, together with her satellites, remains the last stronghold of militarism and monarchism. The peace of the entire world requires that this stronghold of modern feudal lords be destroyed, in order that the bloodthirsty militarists who have been soaking the world in blood for the past three years will no longer be able to breed.</p>
   <p>The German nation can get along and live in peace with the rest of the world without the Kaiser and the Junkers. Although grumblings among the people in Germany are beginning to be heard, nevertheless, it appears that the German nation is not yet completely convinced that it can get <pb facs="5423970_1_1190.jpg" n="2"/>along without Kaiserism. However, since Kaiserism is now a grave menace to the democracy of the entire world, it is the duty of the Allies to take all necessary steps to convince the German people on this point.</p>
   <p>Today, with America's entry into the war and with radical changes in Russia, the war has acquired a new significance. The war has now become a life-or-death struggle between a life-or-death struggle between monarchism and democracy; one of the two must survive, and one of the two must parish. The world will either enter into a new, hitherto unheard-of quasi-federation of free and democratic nations, which will destroy the roots of and abolish all future wars; or the world will revert back to the shackles of militarism and monarchism, with the accompanying policies of plunder, secret diplomacy, intrigue, and the oppression of nations.</p>
   <p>The fate and future order of the entire world hang in the balance, and everything will either be lost or won. Mr. Viviani, head of the French mission to America, spoke the truth when he stated that when America entered <pb facs="5423970_1_1191.jpg" n="3"/>the war "all the forces of liberty became released" to fight against Kaiserism.</p>
   <p>Yes, after this war is over, either the liberty of all nations and peoples will prevail, or the budding liberty of the nations of the entire world will be crushed under the heavy boot of Kaiserism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
