<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. V. No. 36,
<date when="1897-09-03">Sept. 3, 1897</date><title level="a">The Most Important Affair of Ours</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. V. No. 36,
<date when="1897-09-03">Sept. 3, 1897</date><title level="a">THE MOST IMPORTANT AFFAIR OF OURS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nobody will dispute that the most important thing to the Lithuanians in America is the Lithuanian schools. It is the only institution that can uplift the intellect of our brothers and inspire our children with the Lithuanian spirit.</p>
   <p>In other countries we are prohibited our own Lithuanian schools. Do we have in this broad territory of America, a school that would answer our purpose? We do not know of such a school. This shows that we do not care to fulfill our most important duty. We do not know how to use the liberty which we have in this country.</p>
   <p>Until there is a school for Lithuanians in this country, we do not need to prophesy what future there is for us. By the way we have the parish schools but the benefit is very small, because they have no suitable teachers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0111.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The pupils after being in school two years can hardly read Lithuanian, when a good teacher could teach them in one year to read and write perfect Lithuanian. How can we expect our children to learn Lithuanian when the teachers themselves do not know enough of the Lithuanian language?</p>
   <p>If we cannot improve the parish schools, let the Lithuanian Alliance of America establish Lithuanian schools independent of church. This is a very important problem. We think if we could have at least one such a school in America we could get support from the Lithuanian intellectuals of Europe, because such a school would benefit not only the Lithuanians in this country but the Lithuanian nation as a whole. Do you think we cannot accomplish this important object? We would like to hear from other Lithuanian newspapers what they have to say on this important proposition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
