<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-09-27">Sept. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">What Place Will the Lithuanians Take This Time?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-09-27">Sept. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT PLACE WILL THE LITHUANIANS TAKE THIS TIME?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Harmonized, planned,and organized activity means something. The Liberty Loans prove this.</p>
   <p>When the First and Second Liberty Loans were made, not a word was heard about the Lithuanians, although they probably bought as many bonds then as they did during the Third Loan.</p>
   <p>It is officially recorded that during the Third Liberty Loan the Lithuanians bought more than four million dollars worth of bonds. According to the figures, the Lithuanians stand tenth among other nationalities in this respect. That certainly is not the worst.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1085.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Lithuanians have been given credit for activities of which they can not be ashamed, considering their numbers in America. This was made possible by merely a little organization among the Lithuanians during the Third Liberty Loan.</p>
   <p>But that is not all. Organization among the Lithuanians was not perfected during the Third Loan. And, it can be stated without any doubt, at least several million dollars spent by the Lithuanians were credited, not to the Lithuanians, but to other nationalities. This happened because many Lithuanians did not understand the matter, and either failed to purchase their bonds through Lithuanian divisions, or did not insist that the bonds they purchased be credited to the Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>This Saturday, September 28, the Fourth Liberty Loan campaign will be started. What place will the Lithuanians take this time? Tenth? No, they should rise closer to the top in their rating.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1086.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Every Lithuanian should purchase as many bonds as he can during this campaign. He must do so for many reasons, a few of which we give here:</p>
   <p>Every cent invested in these bonds is a real saving--just as if it were put into a safe bank for a dark day.</p>
   <p>Every cent invested in these bonds helps Uncle Sam to win the war. That means a quicker victory and a smaller loss of men, the lessening of hardships and sorrows, and the more immediate realization of peace and quiet for America and the whole world.</p>
   <p>Every cent invested in these bonds is a brick in the reconstruction of a free and independent Lithuania.</p>
   <p>There should not be one Lithuanian who is unwilling to do his bit in this work. The Lithuanians should be in first place in zeal, self-sacrifice</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1087.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>and understanding, for we Lithuanians are on trial before the world. We must show whether we are able to understand our duties, whether we are grown and matured enough to rule ourselves in the free and independent Lithuania which we demand.</p>
   <p>The Fourth Liberty Loan compaign will continue through three weeks, starting September 28. During that period not only every individual Lithuanian, but every Lithuanian society, lodge, club, and organization should have one, two, three, or as many Liberty Bonds as possible under the glass on their charters.</p>
   <p>Let us make a better record this time, fellow Lithuanians! And let us watch to see that all bonds purchased by Lithuanians are credited to the Lithuanians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
