<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-06-22">June 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The People Are Doing Their Duty; the Government Should Also Do its Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-06-22">June 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEOPLE ARE DOING THEIR DUTY; THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD ALSO DO ITS DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of loud-mouthed oppositionists, kaiserists, and cheap politicians of this country, the people of the United States are performing beautifully their war duties. The first Liberty Loan of two million dollars--larger than all the German war loans of the first war year--has been oversubscribed by about one million dollars. The war registration has been successful and very peaceful (it will be remembered that during the Revolutionary and Civil Wars it was necessary to search for young men at night, and to use the bayonet to force them into the army). Except for a few very minor incidents, the United States is preparing for war in a very peaceful and successful manner.</p>
   <p>It cannot be said that anyone desires war, because it is a well-known fact <pb facs="5423970_1_1187.jpg" n="2"/>that everybody abhors war. No, no one wants it, however, it appears that the American people, with teeth tightly clinched, are determined to fulfill their duties--though they be very hard and unpleasant--in order to safeguard themselves and their children from the woes which threaten, not only America but also the entire world, if German militarism conquers the world. Therefore, the American people are doing their duty by supplying money and men with which to wage war. But, the Government should also perform properly its duty toward the people, by taking necessary steps to protect them from the exploiters hiding behind the mask of war, for they are striving to skin the people several ways at one time. The prices of food, clothing and other living necessities have risen to an unspeakably high level. A war can precipitate the rise of prices to a certain extent, but it is very clear that the present high prices are due not to the war alone but largely to speculators and profiteers, the greatest bandits in the country, of whom there is no shortage anywhere. They should be bridled by the Government, because as Mr. [Herbert] Hoover, the proposed food dictator, honestly said, "every person who takes advantage of the war to raise food prices should be <pb facs="5423970_1_1188.jpg" n="3"/>hanged on a dry limb".</p>
   <p>It is not enough to overthrow kaiserism; it must be replaced with something better. If, in our democratic country, a person must pay more for a bushel of potatoes in Chicago or New York during peacetime than in Berlin under kaiserism in time of war, then it will be very hard for such a person to understand how a democracy can be better than kaiserism.</p>
   <p>The congress at Washington, D. C. is now considering a "food bill". We will wait and see what will be the outcome.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
