<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-11-05">Nov. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Rupert Brooke's Play Is Gross Slander against Lithuania</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0547</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0547.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-11-05">Nov. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">RUPERT BROOKE'S PLAY IS GROSS SLANDER AGAINST LITHUANIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A play entitled "Lithuania" and written by one Rupert Brooke (an Englishman who is said to have been killed in the war in the Dardanelles) was recently staged in the so-called "Little Theater" in the Chicago Fine Arts Building. An announcement about the play appeared in the October 15 issue of the Lietuva. However, we have learned that the play is nothing else but a gross slander against Lithuania. The play depicts the characters of the most highly depraved degenerates, who are completely sunken in a life of drunkenness and immorality. It is very apparent that the author of that play never was in Lithuania and is not acquainted in any way whatsoever with real life in Lithuania. With the same degree of honesty or dishonesty the author could have entitled his play "Russia," "Germany," "England," "America," "Hell," or any other name. Only the author himself knows why he named his play "Lithuania."</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0548.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Everyone who is well acquainted with the Lithuanians can easily see that the play is the greatest nonsense that anyone can invent to blacken the reputation of the Lithuanian people. However, dramatic critics, whose comments on the play appeared in the local English-language press, appear to believe that the drama is an accurate portrayal of life in Lithuania. Chicago Lithuanians should have made a vigorous protest against such a defamation of Lithuania immediately after the initial performance of the play.</p>
   <p>The editors of the Lietuva have been informed that a letter of protest against the play was sent to the Chicago Daily Tribune. However, like all other articles that have been submitted about Lithuania and Lithuanians to the Tribune, that letter was never published.</p>
   <p>A letter entitled "In Lithuania" protesting against Mr. Brooke's play appeared in the October 28 issue of the Chicago Daily News. It was written and submitted by Miss St. Ciurlionis, a member of the recently organized <pb facs="5423970_1_0549.jpg" n="3"/>Gabia Sorosis (Gabia Sorority). The letter is intelligently written and is a good refutation of Mr. Brooke's play.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
