<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-04-05">Apr. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Third Liberty Loan</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-04-05">Apr. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE THIRD LIBERTY LOAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The campaign for the Third Liberty Loan has begun. This Loan is needed by the government of this country in order to wage a successful war against Germany.</p>
   <p>Hitherto,America could not help very much with its army to overthrow German militarism and autocracy, which are preparing to destroy the freedom of peoples and to swallow the whole world. On the fields of France the Allies are saving civilization with their money and their blood. America must therefore help them with that aid which she can supply fastest -- money. That is why the government of this country is launching the Third Loan for war purposes.</p>
   <p>A part of this Loan will be used for the preparation of America's army; for <pb facs="5423970_1_1144.jpg" n="2"/>maintenance of the soldiers, for adequate arms, clothing, food, and ships. This is necessary in order that American soldiers, among them many Lithuanians, will not have to face the German cannons empty-handed and bare-chested, as did the Russian forces, with whom many thousands of Lithuanians perished unnecessarily, because they lacked arms and provisions. Another part of the money raised will be used to aid our allies, who also are fighting against Kaiserism.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of all the citizens and inhabitants of America to join in this fight to save the independence of the whole world. Not everybody can fight with sword and gun, but everybody can give a blow to Kaiserism--with a dollar. The more Liberty bonds you purchase, the greater the blow you will deliver to German militarism and the more help you will give to effect an early and successful termination of this war. The more dollars you invest in Liberty bonds, the more soldiers' lives you will save. Therefore buy these Liberty bonds!</p>
   <p>Just a few more words. During the first two loans, Lithuanians bought many <pb facs="5423970_1_1145.jpg" n="3"/>Liberty bonds. They did a good deed for themselves and for this country--for themselves, because they invested their money in a good, safe place; for this country, because they helped Uncle Sam wage a successful war against the aggressors of the world.</p>
   <p>In this Third Liberty Loan, you can all do a good deed for your mother country, Lithuania,also. During the other loans, Lithuanians purchased Liberty bonds any place and, therefore, it is not known how many of these bonds were purchased by the Lithuanians of America. This means that the Lithuanians did not receive the credit they deserved.</p>
   <p>A Lithuanian division, approved by the government, has been created in Chicago for the Third Liberty Loan. It will sell these bonds and will register the number bought by Lithuanians. This will help the Lithuanians very much in their demands for Lithuania's freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1146.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Therefore, instead of purchasing Liberty bonds somewhere else, Lithuanians should buy them through the Lithuanian division, the address of which is as follows: Lithuanian Division, Liberty Loan Campaign Committee, Universal State Bank, 3252 South Halsted Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Here you can get complete information, either in person or by mail. Here you can purchase your Liberty bonds (also by mail, and even on easy payments).</p>
   <p>Lithuanians, go to this one place. Purchase Liberty bonds. By doing so you will benefit yourselves, this country, and Lithuania.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
