<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>,
<date when="1901-06-20">June 20, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">[Meeting Held at St. George's Parish]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Katalikas</title>,
<date when="1901-06-20">June 20, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">[MEETING HELD AT ST. GEORGE'S PARISH]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our honorable fellow countryman, Rector Anthony Milukas, came to Chicago on Thursday, June 11, 1901, and gave a short talk at St. George's parish hall the same evening. The crowd was unusually large and the hall was completely filled so that many people had to stand up because there were no more seats left in the hall. The people were curious to see and hear the visitor speak because they had read and heard so much about him.</p>
   <p>Our local rector, Rev. Krawczunas, opened the meeting and introduced the honorable speaker, Rev. Milukas, as the keynote of the evening. Rev. Milukas spoke about the Lithuanians in Chicago, their attitude toward education, and the Lithuanian schools. He mentioned two incidents among Chicago Lithuanians, one of which he considered a good example, the other a bad one. The first example he considered very important and practical, it being about the interest of the Lithuanians about having Lithuanian schools in Chicago. He approved their plans very highly and encouraged them to carry them out. He stressed the point about the building of parish schools, emphasizing their importance to Lithuanian children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0151.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Their parents should see that the children know their own language in addition to the English language. He explained that our present school was too small to accommodate all Lithuanian children. Moreover there were no Lithuanian teachers who knew their own language well enough to teach Lithuanian children. The Catholic sisters who are teaching your children now cannot teach them the Lithuanian language. It is very important for every child to know their parents' language well. At the present time I realize there is a shortage of Lithuanian nuns in the teach your children, but there will be some Lithuanian nuns in the near future. Your school problems will than be solved with no difficulty. Most practical teachers in elementary school are nuns. When we have Lithuanian sisters, all Lithuanian Catholic parishes will be able to teach children the Lithuanian Catholic parishes will be able to teach children the Lithuanian language. At the present time we will have to be content with what we have. I hope that Lithuanian standards in the future schools will come up higher, and we will all be proud of the work and the <pb facs="5423970_1_0152.jpg" n="3"/>energy expanded for the cause of our nation and a brighter future for your children. I am very proud that Chicago Lithuanians were the first colony who became interested in their children's education and at the same time Chicago Lithuanians are pioneers of education, and opened the way for other parishes in America. The second example which Chicago Lithuanians set up is bad and degrading to our nation, especially to have such a paper as Lietuva, which makes attacks on Lithuanian Catholic priests. Not long ago there was an article published in Lietuva, which abused Rev. Burba personally for no good reason. In addition, it harshly criticized fellow countrymen, calling them ignorant and uneducated, just because they don't take sides with them to degrade Catholic priests. It is a pitiful thing to see our people quarrel and accuse one another over trivial things that have no meaning or value in our lives. If we consider ourselves educated and cultured people, we should understand better than to quarrel over trifling things for nothing. Moreover, we are grown-up people and not children any more; our senses are supposed to be fully developed and we must <pb facs="5423970_1_0153.jpg" n="4"/>be old enough to understand about life. Let us end all our quarrels and let peace reign upon this earth."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
