<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-06-28">June 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Support Our Government as Much as We Can</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-06-28">June 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LET US SUPPORT OUR GOVERNMENT AS MUCH AS WE CAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Very few people in this country fully realize with what kind of an enemy we are now at war. Few realize that we are fighting with the most brutal, un-merciful enemy. The Germans, who are the present-day Huns, have revealed, during this war, a bestiality which is appropriate to wild, but not civilized, nations.</p>
   <p>One American correspondent had an interview with a wounded English officer who, after long imprisonment in Germany, was finally exchanged and free to go home.</p>
   <p>This officer stated that the prisoners in Germany were so weakened by starvation that they could hardly stand up. Nevertheless, they were forced, at bayonet-point, to work until they fell to the ground in a faint. He related that the broken arms and legs of prisoners were purposely set badly; that the German soldiers laughed and derided the prisoners when they were burying <pb facs="5423970_1_1102.jpg" n="2"/>their dead; that severely injured prisoners were transported great distances without medical aid and without food and water; that wounded prisoners were forced to go great distances on foot and were shot like dogs in the road when they could not go any farther; and that newly captured prisoners were sent to camps infested with typhoid fever.</p>
   <p>This is the kind of enemy against whom we are now at war. This is why we must hunch our shoulders and help the government.</p>
   <p>Most of all, we must buy only those things that are absolutely necessary. This will save work for other people and will provide more money for the government to use in conducting the war. With our savings we should buy war-savings stamps. They cost only twenty-five cents each. Use every spare quarter to buy these stamps. The large sum which will grow out of these quarters will be used by our Government to effect a successful conclusion to this war. The Government will repay you all that you invest in these stamps, and you will even receive a larger per cent of interest than the banks pay.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1103.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>President Wilson urges all to buy war-savings stamps and Liberty bonds.</p>
   <p>Then, even those of us who sit at home, will have done our duty, to the benefit of our country and ourselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
