<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-02-21">Feb. 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Two American Giants</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0704</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0704.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-02-21">Feb. 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">TWO AMERICAN GIANTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the exception of the month of July, when Americans celebrate their Independence Day, the month of February is the most notable month for Americans. In this month they celebrate the birthdays of the two greatest men in American history--the real American giants.</p>
   <p>This coming Saturday, February 22, is the birthday of George Washington, the first President of the United States, and the real Father of this country. He, with his devotion, energy, and labor, brought liberty to the United States. He rendered services so great to this commonwealth that his name will long be remembered not only in American History but in the history of the world as well. Beside him, and equally meritorious, stands Abraham Lincoln, the martyr president, whose birthday is February 12. The first one gave his <pb facs="5423970_1_0705.jpg" n="2"/>country political independence by freeing it from the yoke of England The second washed away a disgraceful stain from the honor of the United States by abolishing slavery, by giving liberty and civil rights to millions of negroes. The work for the cause of freedom originated by Washington was promoted by Abraham Lincoln more than by any other man, and for that cause he paid dearly--with his life.</p>
   <p>The wheels of history move very rapidly. The Constitution today has the same significance which it had in the days of Washington; it is the pearl of liberty and happiness.</p>
   <p>The constitution guarantees that this country's government shall be "of the people, for the people, and by the people", but greedy hands can get around the best statutes and nullify the high ideals for which men haves shed their blood and laid down their lives.</p>
   <p>Today the Constitution of the United States is the same as it was in the <pb facs="5423970_1_0706.jpg" n="3"/>days of Washington and Lincoln. But the interpretation of the Constitution by the greedy rulers of today, with regard to life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness is not the same as it was in the time of Washington. Washington broke the chains of England's yoke. But now, after a hundred years, gigantic trusts weight upon the country's neck. This yoke of the trusts on the American people is no lighter than was the earlier yoke of England. Lincoln abolished negro slavery, and paid with his lifeblood. But today in the southern States the former negro slaves' places are occupied by children--slaves in the cotton factories. That the foundations of liberty are crumbling is evident in the constantly increasing restrictions against immigrants and upon the rights of aliens; thanks to the unbridled power of the trusts, living and economic conditions are growing worse instead of getting better.</p>
   <p>The Constitution--the foundation of this country's government--is still here, as it was before, and we need no better one. What we do need is another giant like Washington or Lincoln, with enough determination and energy to <pb facs="5423970_1_0707.jpg" n="4"/>protect the Constitution and the life of this country.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The photos of both Lincoln and Washington appear in connection with this article.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
