<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-11-26">Nov. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Long Our Travelers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-11-26">Nov. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LONG OUR TRAVELERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not one observer of our activities has noticed that there are many individuals among the Lithuanians who are interested in various inventions.</p>
   <p>This fact has been reported in our newspaper several times. It is a reliable indication of the talents of the Lithuanians. It reveals their lively imagination, their richness of mind and their seriousness of thought.</p>
   <p>So far, nobody knows exactly how many Lithuanian inventors there are, but the number is quite large. If someone had time to examine the records in the United States Patents Office, they would uncover a long list of Lithuanian inventors. Many Lithuanians would gain fame as inventors but are not successful because they lack a good fundamental education. They are unable to overcome various and mathematical barriers.</p>
   <p>In view of their mechanical inclinations, it would seem that if more Lithuanians had a fundamental education there would be many more Lithuanian inventors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1608.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This increase will be noticed when elementary schools are made compulsory for every Lithuanian and when the schools of higher education are available to every youth.</p>
   <p>Now we will mention a few Lithuanian inventors who have had their inventions patented and are applying them to practical use.</p>
   <p>Lithuanian Inventors In Chicago alone, there are several such Lithuanian inventors.</p>
   <p>Some time ago we published a detailed report concerning the invention of Miss Anna Doras, a young Lithuanian aviatrix, who invented an automatic appliance for airplane seats. In case of emergency, this invention enables an aviator to free himself from his seat by one movement.</p>
   <p>In the last issue of Lietuva, we mentioned another Chicagoan, Mr. Najauskas. He invented a machine which digs and cleans onions, and makes them ready for <pb facs="5423970_1_1609.jpg" n="3"/>crating as they come out of the machine.</p>
   <p>In the Bridgeport district of Chicago, at 3321 Mosspratt Street, there lives a young Lithuanian, Mr. Sylvester Zolpis. Mis contributions are represented by a variety of smaller inventions. For instance, he has designed a special kind of small chair which could be very handily used by farmers. Mr. Zolpis is well acquainted with farming and is a carpenter also. He hit upon the idea that the farmer who must milk cows, pick cotton or berries, and weed patches, could do so much more easily if he could sit comfortably while engaged in these duties.</p>
   <p>True, the farmer of today does not stand when doing these chores. However, the necessity of moving a chair from place to place is more trouble than benefit to him. Mr. Zolpis' invention makes it possible for the worker to sit down and move from place to place without having to carry the chair in his hands. He designed a small stool which makes this possible. The illustration published here clearly shows the form of the chair and its conveniences. It is a small chair constructed of light wood, and has one leg in <pb facs="5423970_1_1610.jpg" n="4"/>the center of the seat. This leg has a spike or a removable wide ring at its base. The use of the ring or spike is dependent upon the hardness or softness of the ground. When work is being done on hard ground (in the yard) the spike is used because it will not allow the chair to slip. The wide ring does not permit the leg to sink too deep when the chair is in use on soft ground. Belts stretch from the sides and back of the chair. The worker fastens these belts on himself. From the illustration, it is easy to understand that having strapped the chair to himself, the worker can move about and sit down wherever his work requires it. Both his hands are free, and having once strapped on the chair, he does not have to use his hands to carry it from place to place.</p>
   <p>Mr. n has had this chair patented; the patent number is 1,267,953. He reports that he has received thousands of orders for it already. Mr. Zolpis says that several companies have offered to buy his patent, but he is considering forming a Lithuanian corporation to manufacture his product.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zolpis has several other improvements besides this one. One of them is <pb facs="5423970_1_1611.jpg" n="5"/>a special kind of envelope which, according to the inventor, opens automatically.</p>
   <p>The Zolpis chair has received mention in the English press, for instance, in World Progress.</p>
   <p>Mr. Matthew Spirikavicius, also a Chicagoan, is another inventor of several practical devices. For example, he has patented a new type of trap for catching mice, rabbits and other small creatures. This trap differs from others in that the old type closes after catching one mouse or other animal, and must be set again to catch another animal. Spirikavicius' trap can catch as many animals as the trap can hold. This invention was patented on July 9, 1912, as No. 1,032,089.</p>
   <p>Spirikavicius and John Masiliunas, also of Chicago, have patented a special kind of wrench for turning nuts.</p>
   <p>From its outward appearance the wrench is somewhat similar to the so-called <pb facs="5423970_1_1612.jpg" n="6"/>"French Key", or as it is called in America, a "monkey wrench". But there is a great difference between them in practical application. The "French Key", or wrench, will tighten or loosen any sized nut. However, it must be set by hand according to the size of the but. Spirikavicius' wrench is automatic. That is, it will tighten or loosen any sized nut without any adjustment. It is only necessary to turn the wrench after placing it on the nut. The wrench adjusts itself to the size of the nut. The patent on this device was issued on April 11, 1916, and is recorded as No. 1,179,341.</p>
   <p>Copies of these patents, with complete explanations, can be had for five cents apiece. Write to the following address: Commissioner of Patents, Washington, D. C. Mention the number of the patent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
