<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-21">Jan. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">War Proves That Darwin Was Wrong</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-21">Jan. 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WAR PROVES THAT DARWIN WAS WRONG</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.... Our readers, undoubtedly, have heard of Darwin, who is the author of the famous theory of "natural selection" or "survival of the fittest." According to his theory all living organisms (species) in nature - animal and plant life - are continuously engaged in a struggle for existence. In this struggle, those living organisms (species) that are weak, unfit, and unable to become accustomed to the conditions of life, perish and become extinct; while those organisms that are more fit and are more powerful survive and flourish. That battle of "survival of the fittest" goes on from day to day, from year to year, and in that manner the quality of all living organisms (species) is being continuously improved. In the same manner in which an expert cattle breeder or plant expert improves the breed and plant, so the living creatures of nature are being improved by means of that never ending struggle for existence, in which only the fit survive.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1264.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, we see that the direct opposite of that theory is now happening in connection with the present war in Europe. In ten countries the most fit and able-bodied men are being selected and sent to the battlefields of war, where they are being slaughtered already For over six months. Hundreds of thousands of men have been killed, and many more were wounded; cold and disease are also taking a heavy toll among the soldiers. If the war will last two more months, then the number of killed and wounded will reach into the millions.</p>
   <p>In the belligerent countries, only those men who are old, weaklings, and in poor health are left at home with the women and children. These men will remain alive, and their number after the war will even be greater than the number of fit and able-bodied men. What, then, will be the nature of the following generation?</p>
   <p>War is also a struggle - a struggle for existence. It is a struggle in which large masses of men meet and kill each other. These struggles do not improve <pb facs="5423970_1_1265.jpg" n="3"/>but lower the quality of the human race. The best element of the race is selected and destroyed, and the weaker individuals are allowed to remain and propagate. Therefore, war brings about the "survival of weaklings."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
