<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-11">Jan. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Reader Advocates Prohibition</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Voice of the People column)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 3</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-11">Jan. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A READER ADVOCATES PROHIBITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Voice of the People column)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2...I must admit that it becomes very monotonous to read articles in the newspapers about the hygienic and scientific effects of the excessive use of intoxicating liquors. To combat intemperance merely by pointing out its ill effects upon an individual's health by displaying pictures of a drunkard's kidneys, liver and heart, is a backward way of fighting that evil; because a close study of the matter reveals a doubt whether those bad effects were caused by liquor or by some other causes.</p>
   <p>The most appropriate way to combat intemperance is to point out the vulgar deeds of a drunkard and the bad material effects upon the individual and his family. These facts are so clear and convincing that even without an education they can be seen. With such vivid facts we can destroy the very roots of intemperance by passing a law prohibiting the sale and use of intoxicating liquors. Unless the roots are destroyed the evil cannot be eradicated.</p>
   <p>The argument that if legal prohibition is enacted people will secretly make and <pb facs="5423970_1_0234.jpg" n="2"/>sell intoxicating liquors is without foundation. Even at the present time it is comparatively easy to illegally make and sell liquor at a fairly good profit. But, as we can see, very few people dare to do that for fear of legal punishment. With the coming of legal prohibition thus illicit liquor traffic would be curbed still more.</p>
   <p>Our police would always be able to locate illicit stills and saloons. If our police can smell a revolver in ones pocket, and if they can find a piece of paper secretly hidden behind wall plaster in a home and thus uncover a secret conspiracy against the government, then it should be a trifling matter for them to detect any illegal traffic in liquor.</p>
   <p>Speaking about the hygienic aspect of intoxicating liquors, can we find anything more unsanitary anywhere than a five cent mug of beer? (C.J.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
