<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1927-01-04">Jan. 4, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">They Speak for Everybody</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1927-01-04">Jan. 4, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THEY SPEAK FOR EVERYBODY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Secretary of Labor James J. Davis and Secretary of Agriculture Jardine, after fully satisfying their appetites with food and drinks, started the new year by delivering addresses in the name of all the workers and farmers of America. The former stated that the workers are enjoying wonderful "prosperity" Secretary Jardine said that the farmers are enjoying wonderful "prosperity" also. Neither of these two gentlemen know anything at all about the life of the workers and poor farmers. Evidently they figure that if the steel trust and other corporations <pb facs="5423970_1_0665.jpg" n="2"/>are making gigantic profits then the workers and farmers are also enjoying "good times." However, such reasoning is all wrong. That is admitted even by some members of the bourgeoisie. A Congressman from Georgia recently made the following statement about those corporation profits:</p>
   <p>"These fabulous corporation profits mean that a small army of corporation magnates, who are heartless, inhuman, dishonest, unpatriotic, soulless and without conscience, are taking advantage of certain laws to exploit millions of wearisome and suffering men, women and children."</p>
   <p>After explaining that wealth, gained by means of exploitation <pb facs="5423970_1_0666.jpg" n="3"/>of the workers, brings about misery and want to millions of people, the Congressman from Georgia concluded with the following remark:</p>
   <p>"And that is called prosperity, good times. It is good times only for a lion who has captured a young eagle."</p>
   <p>Those who have plenty to eat and drink do not know what it means to be in misery and want. Industrial magnates and their servants in Washington will probably say that the Congressman from Georgia made the above remarks during "an uncontrollable bit of frenzy." The capitalistic newspapers are even trying to make a joke out of his remarks. However, steel and mine workers, whose sweat produced those gigantic corporation profits, know that the Congressman from Georgia spoke the truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
