<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
            <date when="1916-05-19">May 19, 1916</date>.
            <title level="a">A Favorable Hour (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0725</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0725.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
            <date when="1916-05-19">May 19, 1916</date>.
            <title level="a">A Favorable Hour (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Working people now have greater opportunities than ever before and should take full advantage of them. America is now enjoying the greatest prosperity in her history, and never before were there so many workers in America demanding higher wages, shorter working hours, and better working conditions. In all parts of the United States the workers are also demanding the right to organize and the right to belong to labor unions. And they must win all these demands.</p>
   <p>The workers are determined to fight for conditions, and they are fighting full of hope, a hope that is not without foundation. Emigration to the United States has almost completely stopped because of the European war. For that
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0726.jpg" n="2"/> reason the number of workers in this country has greatly decreased, doing away with practically all employment. There is a big demand for workers in factories and business establishments. Employers have become unsually lenient and considerate. They hurriedly adjust every grievance of the workers, and they do so without grumbling. The reason is that the employers are receiving profitable orders.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the voice of the workers is now louder and bolder than it ever was before. That voice now rings with demands and authority and not with prayers or humbleness! However, the workers must make secure their present and future gains in order that they will not lose them later on. The present high level of prosperity cannot last very long. It will end with the close of the European war.</p>
   <p>When the war ends--and it must end soon--large hordes of people will flock to <pb facs="5423970_1_0727.jpg" n="3"/>America from war-torn Europe; they will come here to find employment and make a living. The labor market will overflow with people seeking employment, people who will offer their services for the least possible compensation. When the war ends, the industries that are producing war materials and ammunition will experience a serious depression. Hundreds of thousands of workers will be layed off and a giant army of unemployed will result. When the war in Europe ends, millions of men who are today are serving in the various armies and slaughtering each other will return from the battlefields to their homes and become engaged in useful work. The demand in Europe for American products will constantly decrease. American exports will fall and as a result American industry will suffer and decline.</p>
   <p>Workers must not forget this. Everything that the workers in America have won today is due to the bloody slaughter in Europe which started two years
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0728.jpg" n="4"/> ago. Immediately after the war in Europe started the munitions factories in America experienced a great business revival. They needed more and more qualified workers. When these workers demanded more money for their work, their demands were immediately satisfied. When they demanded an eight-hour working day even that demand was immediately granted (especially to the machinists), because the employers has no alternative. The war industries drew workers from other branches of industry. That offered an opportunity for the workers to make demands and win them. The workers took advantage of that opportunity. As a result, the struggle of the workers has greatly increased: Everywhere there are strikes, strikes, strikes!</p>
   <p>There are no more unemployed; new workers are not coming from Europe to take the places of those who are out on strike. The solidarity of the workers in this struggle is unusual. They have attained mreo courage and power to fight<pb facs="5423970_1_0729.jpg" n="5"/> on to victory. It is hoped that their courage and power will not decrease, but grow to such a degree that it will enable them to put an end to the present social order which exploits the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
