<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-03-09">Mar. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">President Wilson and the War Danger</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1203</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1203.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-03-09">Mar. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT WILSON AND THE WAR DANGER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After taking the oath of office last Monday, President Wilson started a new four-year presidential term. During the inauguration he delivered the traditional address to the people of the United States. While speaking of present conditions in this country, he was unable to refrain from mentioning the war danger which is now threatening the United States. He expressed his views on this danger, and among other things he made the following statements:</p>
   <p>"We have been deeply outraged on the seas, but we have had no desire to repay evil with evil; during all this time we have adhered to our determination to remain neutral. When the abuses which have been heaped upon us have become intolerable, we have still pointed out clearly that we have not desired anything for ourselves that we are not prepared to demand for all mankind--neutrality, honesty, and the right to live and prosper in an atmosphere that is free from the danger of injury by any organized group.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1204.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"We have been forced to arm in order to defend our rights. We are now in a strong state of armed neutrality, because it has become evident that there is no other way to express our wishes or to preserve that which we cannot renounce.</p>
   <p>"We may be forced by circumstances, but not by our own desire, into a more active defense of our rights. However, nothing will change our thoughts or purpose. They are too well known to become beclouded. They have sunk their roots too deeply into our principles of national life to be altered.</p>
   <p>"We desire neither to gain territory nor to obtain privileges. We do not desire anything that must be secured through injury to others."</p>
   <p>By these words the President once more shows clearly that deep within his heart he is a man of peace. He has demonstrated that not only with words. Since the very beginning of the European war he has proved by word and by deed that he is really a man of peace.</p>
   <p>The fact that he has severed diplomatic relations with Germany, and has asked <pb facs="5423970_1_1205.jpg" n="3"/>Congress to grant him more powers, should make it evident to everyone that this situation could not have been tolerated by even the greatest advocate of peace.</p>
   <p>Everything soon came out into the open. It became known that Germany was actively plotting against this country by urging Mexico and Japan to attack the United States; it became known that German agents were preparing the ground right here for a revolution against the United States Government; it became known that German agents were responsible for the sabotage of America factories; and it also became known that German agents even planned to assassinate President Wilson. No country, even with an angel for President, could permit such things.</p>
   <p>Therefore, if in this critical hour even such a person as our chief executive warns the nation of the danger of war, it is time for us to do some sound thinking, and to stop making foolish protests against the President in order to tie his hands. At this time every citizen should stand behind the President and support him. Otherwise the enemy will see that the people of the United States are divided, and that they do not support their President. This would give the enemy still greater courage and, instead of abolishing the danger of war, such behavior <pb facs="5423970_1_1206.jpg" n="4"/>would tend to bring it about much sooner. "Even a goat will climb a tree that is bent," says an old proverb. When you come up against the Kaiser you are dealing, not with a goat, but with a mad bull.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
