<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-04-19">Apr. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Thousands of Chicago Lithuanians Buying Third Liberty Loan Bonds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1129</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1129.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-04-19">Apr. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THOUSANDS OF CHICAGO LITHUANIANS BUYING THIRD LIBERTY LOAN BONDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Universal State Bank, in which the Lithuanian Branch of the Third Liberty Loan is located, is being swamped by Lithuanians who are hurrying to Uncle Sam's aid to help him defeat the Germans. The officers of the bank were hard at work during the last week, receiving thousands and thousands of dollars from Lithuanians who were purchasing Liberty bonds. This flood of purchases is constantly growing larger. Most of the Lithuanians are buying the smaller fifty-dollar bonds, but there were many calls for bonds of larger denominations.</p>
   <p>Societies Buying Bonds</p>
   <p>The Bridgeport societies are leading all other societies in the purchase of Liberty bonds. Besides the Simanas Daukantas Society, which we mentioned <pb facs="5423970_1_1130.jpg" n="2"/>last week, the Sons of Lithuania Society has purchased a thousand dollars' worth of bonds and the Keistutis Building and Loan Association, also in Bridgeport, has bought two thousand dollars' worth. It is apparent that these men know a good thing when they see it. Instead of keeping their funds somewhere else, societies should invest them in Liberty bonds. You could not find a better and safer investment.</p>
   <p>Below we are publishing a partial list of those Lithuanians who have purchased Liberty bonds in Chicago. We shall publish as many names as our limited space permits.</p>
   <p>Last Monday, April 15, the Sacred Heart Society called a special meeting to discuss the Liberty Loan bonds. The meeting was held at the Woodman Hall, 3251 Lime Street.</p>
   <p>Among the members of this Society there is a large number of people who are concerned with the problems of Lithuania and Lithuanians. Therefore, having <pb facs="5423970_1_1131.jpg" n="3"/>the opportunity to better the reputation of Lithuanians, the Society decided, at this meeting, to buy a thousand dollars' worth of Liberty bonds.</p>
   <p>At this same meeting B. M. Butkus, John Martinkus and John Gaubas sold to individual members more than a thousand dollars' worth of bonds. Ben M. Butkus is the president and John Martinkus the secretary of the Society.</p>
   <p>In this manner the societies of Bridgeport led the societies of other colonies in the purchase of Liberty bonds.</p>
   <p>We have heard that other societies in this colony are planning to call special meetings, which will put this colony even farther ahead of the others in the sale of bonds.</p>
   <p>The following purchased Liberty Loan bonds in Chicago: [Translator's note: Here follows a long list of names of the Lithuanians who purchased Liberty bonds, with designations of the amounts purchased.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
