<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 31,
<date when="1893-08-12">Aug. 12, 1893</date><title level="a">A Second Reminder about the Lithuanian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1501</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1501.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 31,
<date when="1893-08-12">Aug. 12, 1893</date><title level="a">A SECOND REMINDER ABOUT THE LITHUANIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In number 29 of Lietuva we wrote about the necessity of a Lithuanian colony in this country. We are writing again because we received many letters asking information about such a plan, how to establish a Lithuanian colony.</p>
   <p>We have a great opportunity to establish a Lithuanian colony because this country is free, we have liberty, no policemen or any other official can interfere or forbid us to buy land or a farm.</p>
   <p>Look at the workingmen's condition in the city of Chicago, thousands of workers are going from factory to factory seeking jobs, and they get the same answer, "No help wanted." These strong and healthy men are starving. How look at the farmers' life; his barn is full of all kinds of animals, his storehouse is full of grains; the farmer has everything he needs - bread and meat; the farmer eats wholesome food and laughs At the city people and says how crazy the city people are.</p>
   <p>The best place for a Lithuanian colony is Nebraska, the land there is very fertile and cheap. Few Lithuanians farmers already living there are glad and proud that they bought farms. Now those Lithuanians do not know what <pb facs="5423970_1_1502.jpg" n="2"/>starvation is.</p>
   <p>Seven Lithuanian families declared already their readiness to buy land in the Lithuanian colony. As soon as there is enough Lithuanian families to go on with the establishment of a colony, we will find proper place to buy the land.</p>
   <p>Editor</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
