<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sandara</title>,
<date when="1930-09-26">Sept. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Educational Facilities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sandara</title>,
<date when="1930-09-26">Sept. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATIONAL FACILITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Looking at the problem of education from the point of educational facilities there seems to be no immediate reason for worry about the situation. These facilities are abundant and available for every one. Public schools, high schools and state universities are the problems of general tax distributing agencies. If they are inadequate to meet the public needs, the task of making improvements and extensions lies with our respective governmental subdivisions. Public libraries are also the problem of our tax-spending bodies, and we have a right to look to them for gratification of our wants. Besides these institutions, created and maintained by taxation, which makes them public property to be enjoyed by the people without extra fees, there are many private educational institutions, of the highest standing, accessible to all who can afford to pay the tuition. In large cities, like Chicago, one can secure good school training of all types from ordinary trade and business college courses to a university <pb facs="5423970_1_0044.jpg" n="2"/>of the highest order. And these educational institutions aim at meeting the needs of every individual desiring to acquire a formal education. One compelled to earn his living by working days, may attend evening schools and slowly but surely get a fair training in a chosen vocation. If that is inconvenient, one may take up university extension courses and study at home under the direction of a competent educators. Sandara need not worry, and may happily pursue its own course in providing facilities for social gatherings. But what we need now is more cultural Lithuanian people. At present we do not have a sufficient number of college graduates. Lithuanian parents should make every possible effort to send their boys and girls to a college or some university.</p>
   <p>It is a duty of every parent to send his or her child to an institution of higher learning. It is not enough to be a Lithuanian and a good citizen, but one should strive to be a cultured Lithuanian.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
