<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-03-29">Mar. 29, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Women, Let Us Not Forget Our Alliance!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ada Vilmanius</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-03-29">Mar. 29, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN, LET US NOT FORGET OUR ALLIANCE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Ada Vilmanius</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Naujienos and other progressive newspapers have already published several articles about the Lithuanian Women's Progressive Alliance of America. It is known to many that this Alliance has made notable progress in a short period of time. It is apparent that Lithuanian women are awakening, and are beginning to become interested in civic problems as well as household problems. They are no longer satisfied with merely a prayer book and the Stations [of the Cross]. Although their work is as hard and responsible as that of their men, they are often shunted to the rear. Almost everywhere their work is considered of less value than that of their male companions. Though they see, feel, and understand all this, the women are not able to make an adequate protest because they are not yet organized.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1406.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Some of our women realized long ago that they lacked an understanding of their own affairs and that there was no organization which could enlighten them in these matters. They tried, as much as they could and as well as they knew how, to enlighten themselves and their lagging sisters. True, their work was not easy. It demanded much effort, sacrifice, and determination.</p>
   <p>I remember when the Lithuanian Women's Progressive Alliance was created. How much joy and celebration there was! But nothing more has been done. Having expressed their joy and having celebrated a while, many of our sisters again closed themselves up in their steaming kitchens--and they have not returned. Only those who had a broader point of view with respect to life and matters which concerned them as working women remained, but there were not many of them. It has even been feared that this work which had been begun so successfully would have to be abandoned. But no! The few women were determined to work and work more, and work they did. They worked during every hour they were free from their domestic duties. In the newspapers, <pb facs="5423970_1_1407.jpg" n="3"/>at meetings, and in private conversations they urged their sisters to enlighten themselves, to organize and to fight for their rights!</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, their intentions and devotion were often misinterpreted or even maliciously interpreted. Clericalism, one of the most vicious enemies of progress and freedom, barred their path. Our rectories, sensing an imminent danger in the greater enlightenment of the women, did everything to vilify the work of these idealists and to lower them in the estimations of their parishioners. The rectory realized that if it lost the support of women, its days of overlording were numbered.</p>
   <p>However, one curse is not sufficient. Even the least enlightened person--one who can understand very little--will ultimately realize the reason for the curse. Something had to be done to conceal the real purpose of the rectory. The spiritual politician who sits in the rectory decided to use the floors of the meeting halls and the newspapers for his shady work. In this way he <pb facs="5423970_1_1408.jpg" n="4"/>swayed hosts of our unthinking sisters to his side. In their name he created a branch of the "Roman Consulate" and told them that this was their organization--an organization of Catholic women. In view of this, we, the liberal women, have not only failed to become discouraged, but have become determinded to work even more. This work of ours will not go for naught. We have already organized branches of the Lithuanian Women's Progressive Alliance in the larger Lithuanian colonies in America. The same is being done in the smaller colonies. In a word, our Alliance is growing and expanding. In order that it grow in depth as well as breadth, however, it is necessary that we do not put down our hands. Let us work, work, work! Let us not be content with the mere fact that we do have an alliance and think that there is nothing more to be done, for much is still left undone. First of all, we must explain to our less enlightened sisters the real purpose of the Roman agent. We can accomplish this with the aid of good books, newspapers, lectures, and public meetings. In other words, by enlightening ourselves and others, this can be accomplished.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1409.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Sisters, let us all get to work, now!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
