<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-02-23">Feb. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Several Opinions about War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1207</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1207.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-02-23">Feb. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SEVERAL OPINIONS ABOUT WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the danger of war between the United States and Germany has become evident, many different opinions on the subject have been expressed by various individuals and groups. Some persons demand that the United States keep out of the war at any cost, while others declare that war is inevitable if Germany continues to sink American passenger and merchant ships. The antiwar proponents charge that the war advocates want war because they are servants of the capitalists and that the President is their tool.</p>
   <p>It is to be expected that many people become enraged and that they make rash statements during such a feverish political period. However, it is best for us to keep cool heads and to weigh carefully both sides of the question. By this deliberation and restraint we can avoid many unpleasant situations, and thus reduce the harmful effect of the war on this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1208.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the first place nobody wants war. It is hardly possible to find a person who would hope for such a horrible affair. But that does not mean that there will be no war. Although no one likes to fight, it sometimes happens that even the most peace-loving person is forced to defend himself. In order to avoid conflict, to preserve peace, it is necessary--absolutely necessary--that both interests remain strongly averse to war. Even though one interest maintains a strong desire for peace, war will result if the opposite interest continues to commit acts of aggression. In this case there are but two alternatives: either stand and fight for your life and rights, or lay down and let your adversary break your backbone with his boots. To preserve peace both sides must shout with sincerity, "We want peace--down with war!" But if one side is pleading for peace while their opponents are busily preparing to rain blows then of course peace cannot prevail.</p>
   <p>The Socialists have issued a proclamation against war which states that American workers have no quarrel with the workers of Germany. That is true. It is also true that the United States Government has no quarrel with the <pb facs="5423970_1_1209.jpg" n="3"/>workers of Germany. But it does have a quarrel with the German Government: with German militarism which by means of submarines has violated all human rights. Furthermore, the Socialists of Germany, through their representatives in the Reichstag, have supported the German Government from the very beginning of the war. Their party is still supporting the Government (although lately some of the members have resigned). If the United States ever becomes involved in a war with Germany this country will be waging war not against the workers of Germany, but against German militarism, to whom no law is sacred.</p>
   <p>One newspaper which has debated the issue with us has attempted to prove that we are mistaken in our assertion that Germany is the aggressor nation. That paper reasons in the following manner: England violated international laws when she declared a blockade against Germany, forbidding her to send ships to the rest of the world. Germany [retaliated by violating laws] with her submarines. Therefore both sides are guilty. Since the United States refrained from declaring war on England she should likewise refrain from <pb facs="5423970_1_1210.jpg" n="4"/>declaring war on Germany.</p>
   <p>It is true that both England and Germany have violated laws but our opponents [newspaper] have forgotten one thing: When England seizes a ship in forbidden waters she takes it to a port and carries the matter before a special court, which decides whether or not the ship is carrying contraband; neither lives nor cargo are lost. But Germany is determined to act differently: She threatens to sink every ship--passenger or merchant--without regard for cargo or lives. President Wilson very logically pointed out that in the matter of cargo we can wait until the end of the war and then take the matter before a third [neutral] court for settlement. After all money can compensate for the loss of cargo, but neither money nor a third court can restore the lives of people. Although England is violating international laws no lives have been lost on account of that violation, but the Germans are violating laws in such a manner that several thousand innocent people already have been sent to the bottom of the sea, as in the sinking of the Lusitania. There is a vast difference between the naval war policies of these two nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1211.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Another newspaper asserts that the workers of the United States do not share in the profits or the justice of this country but that these qualities only embrace the interests of the capitalists, who have no business endangering our ships by sending commodities abroad during a war. The trouble between the United States and Germany is not due to the loss of cargo but to a great and important principle which we have explained in a previous issue of the Lietuva. That principle involves not only the capitalists but also the workers of the United States. Nearly two thousand people perished when a submarine sank the "Lusitania" without warning. Among those who perished on that ship were several hundred women, innocent children and infants, one identified Lithuanian (there were probably others), and several hundred workers. Can it be possible that such matters do not concern the workers? Such a catastrophe should concern every person. On every ship there are workers who have a right to earn their bread by means of their occupation. Are not their lives of importance to all workers? Only that country and that nation can and should exist which stands up for and defends even its most worthless citizen. Any other kind of nation does not deserve to exist.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1212.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>All for one and one for all should be the principle of every nation. A nation should stand up for even one citizen if he or she is unjustly injured.</p>
   <p>Therefore, as we have seen, every medal has two sides and we must scrutinize both sides before an honest opinion can be formed. Let us first ascertain the truth. It does not pay to go to war nor to waste a single thought on anything that is dishonest. But it is the duty of every honorable person to fight to the end for a just cause.</p>
   <p>The United States is fortunate that it has such a President as Woodrow Wilson. He may have numerous weaknesses, but there is one weakness that he does not have: He will not involve the United States in the war if he can find any honorable way to avoid it. We may place implicit faith in the President because he is a born enemy of war. If war does come to America it will not be the fault of our country or our President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
