<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-12-04">Dec. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Make Reforms</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-12-04">Dec. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S MAKE REFORMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We all know that never before in the annals of history has this world been in the unfortunate state in which it is today.</p>
   <p>Thousands of our youngest people are falling daily on the battlefields. Woe and hardship have become widespread.</p>
   <p>Who can describe the tortures of those thousands who lie wounded on the battlefields, in the bitter cold; who have nothing to eat for days and failing to receive assistance, die in the greatest of agonies? Who can measure the streaming tears of the mothers and sisters who are parted from their beloved sons and brothers forever?</p>
   <p>Who can imagine the faltering hearts of the mother and father, probably forsaken old people, who find themselves bereft of their beloved sons, and without support in their old age? More than one mother and father have lost their minds. Their hearts are breaking as they think about their sons <pb facs="5423970_1_0242.jpg" n="2"/>and the unfortunate fate in store for the latter.</p>
   <p>Let us visualize thousands of innocent children dying of starvation. These unfortunates find no comfort; they die of starvation and undergo the agonies of all sorts of diseases. The mind and imagination cannot conceive of such an awful calamity. They cannot fully picture that spectre which is called "war".</p>
   <p>Our motherland, Lithuania, has been drawn into that awful whirlpool of war. The foreign-born here in America, the land of liberty and blessings, are aiding their brothers who are innocent sufferers of the war. The newspapers tell us how the people of the nationalities which are inundated by the waves of war are sharing their hard-earned pennies with their brothers overseas, trying to provide them with some sort of relief. For example, the Chicago Serbs, of whom there are far fewer than Lithuanians, have already sent thousands of "relief" dollars to their brothers who are fighting for Serbia's existence.</p>
   <p>In connection with the war and war relief there are certain manifestations <pb facs="5423970_1_0243.jpg" n="3"/>which reveal the reactions of the people of different nations to the war. Among them is the saloon question. Saloon licenses were renewed in Chicago beginning November 1. The number of saloons owned by people of other nationalities has been reduced fifty per cent.</p>
   <p>It is apparent that those who formerly frequented the saloons have now pledged to give their pennies to fellow nationals who, far away on the other side, are suffering hardship and starvation in that terrible war.</p>
   <p>Yes, they are prepared to lessen the hardship and woe of their fellow nationals. They are prepared to wipe away the tears of these unfortunates; prepared to defend their brothers from cold and starvation.</p>
   <p>And we Lithuanians, whose motherland is probably leveled to the ground, whose sisters, brothers, and parents are suffering the most terrible hardships, in whose motherland perhaps hundreds are starving today--what are we doing at least to lessen their terrible tortures?</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0244.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Lacking will power, we frequent the saloons and spend those pennies which, if sent to Lithuania, might save many from death.</p>
   <p>Since November 1, the number of Lithuanian-owned saloons in Chicago has not only failed to decrease, but actually has increased.</p>
   <p>Visit a Lithuanian neighborhood. The first thing one notices is the large number of saloons. Go past them on a Saturday night or a Sunday. You will hear a terrible, animal-like howling: those are our brothers "singing" and perhaps even fighting. In those dens they often leave behind their last cent and all human feeling. More than once we hear of cases among Americans, where a husband, having come home drunk, strangles his wife or murders his child. There are many such incidents.</p>
   <p>At this time we should cease entertainments with dancing and drinking. We need to replace them with mass meetings at which we could obtain firsthand information on the fate of our brothers and could make donations to aid <pb facs="5423970_1_0245.jpg" n="5"/>Lithuania during her times of hardship. Our brothers overseas await our assistance. They are waiting for that moment when they will hear that the Lithuanians of America, their brothers living in the far-distant country, are prepared to offer that assistance which a brother has the right to demand of a brother. How are we fulfilling the expectations of our brothers overseas? How are we fulfilling our brotherly duties? Comes Saturday and Sunday and we stream into the saloons, leaving there the money with which we could provide relief. In these foul-smelling dens we are destroying the ideals of humanity and brotherly love. In them we are killing our consciences and are hiding from the task of silencing the moans overseas.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian temperance organization and those of us who recognize the awful misfortune and the shame to all of us must get to work and erase that foul mark which concerns every Lithuanian. Let us organize and start the fight, a most energetic fight, against those dens.</p>
   <p>There are laws in Chicago forbidding the making of noise and playing of <pb facs="5423970_1_0246.jpg" n="6"/>music in saloons after ten o'clock at night.</p>
   <p>Singing and music is banned on Sundays. On Sundays the doors and windows of the saloons must be curtained so their lights are not visible from the outside. I believe the same laws apply in many other states.</p>
   <p>Members of temperance groups, it is your duty to see to it that the saloonkeepers at least comply with these laws. We need not tolerate saloonkeepers, for we derive very little, if any, benefit from them. There were certain incidents when donations were being collected for the Saule School of Lithuania. More than once, donation-seekers were chased out of the saloons. The same happened when donations were being collected for the National Buildings of Vilnius[Vilna]. I remember one saloonkeeper saying to Dr. Basanavicius: "What do you want, greenhorn? Go stretch bellies in the stockyards; you'll soon learn the value of money. I fed many lice well, after I came here, until I was able to buy this saloon." I know that on that same night that same saloonkeeper spent a large sum of money entertaining a few customers at "a house of gaiety".</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0247.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Workers of the Lithuanian nation, do not let my words go past your ears, unheeded. Let us uproot that terrible spectre from our midst. Those dens of darkness, those places of misfortune, must leave our midst. Let us do away with drunkenness among the Lithuanians. Let us use the money being spent for drunkenness to provide relief for our brothers and to create a bright tomorrow!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
