<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1930-01-25">Jan. 25, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Judge J. T. Zuris Honored by the Lithuanian Chamber of Commerce</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1018</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1018.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jaunimas</title>,
<date when="1930-01-25">Jan. 25, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE J. T. ZURIS HONORED BY THE LITHUANIAN CHAMBER OF COMMERCE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6 - Last Sunday about 300 prominent Lithuanian business and professional men gathered once more to honor our young Lithuanian-American, John T. Zuris.</p>
   <p>The dinner itself was enjoyed by all those present, but the speeches, as usual, were less appealing, since a number of our distinguished orators made the usual mistake of becoming over zealous in their efforts to do justice to the occasion. For good measure, as master of ceremonies, Dr. Drangelis gave a long speech between each speaker. Our prominent business men, who were never bothered with politeness or good taste, acted as usual, completely ignoring the speeches. The guest speakers themselves attracted more interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1019.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Honorable Chief Justice Sonsteby and County Clerk Michael J. Flynn, were both very popular as speakers. The former presented the judicial robe to our judge while the audience sang the Lithuanian and American National Anthems.</p>
   <p>Among the evening's speakers were: Leonard Simutis, Editor of Draugas (Friend); R. A. Vassale, president and council of the Lithuanian Bar Association; Albin Peters, president of Lithuanians Lawyers' Association; Justin Mackevich; Rev. A. Baltutis; Chief Justice John J. Sonsteby, Dr. Strikol; Mr. Vincas Uzdavinis: Honorable Michael J. Flynn, Clerk of Cook County and Honorable John T. Zuris.</p>
   <p>The musical program was given by two soloists: Ann Juozaitis and John Romanas. Both sang well and were complimented by the speakers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
