<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-09-05">Sept. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Our Young Students</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Zigmas Vitkauskas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-09-05">Sept. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">OUR YOUNG STUDENTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Zigmas Vitkauskas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lithuanians who emigrate to this country find it necessary to adjust themselves to a new situation, to the American way of life. Some of the customs of the cities and towns of this country are distasteful to former Lithuanian farmers. However, nothing can be done--the American customs must be endured. It is always hard to establish oneself, but it is especially difficult when it must be done among foreigners in a strange country. If it is difficult for an adult to adjust himself to foreigners in a strange country, then it is still harder for the immature youth to do so. Our young people, especially those who attend schools in this country, are almost entirely dependent upon the "providence of God". No one appears to be interested in them, and no one does anything to help them. Our students are abandoned like the birds in a forest.</p>
   <p>I will make an effort to describe here the plight of our students in at least one school, Valparaiso University, Valparaiso, Indiana. An average of sixty or <pb facs="5423970_1_0063.jpg" n="2"/>seventy Lithuanians are usually members of the student body. They represent an exemplary group of our youth. The University is a beautiful and pleasant center for the flower of our youth. No other school in America has as large a number of Lithuanian students. However, one must admit that hardly anyone but God is concerned about their welfare. I do not mean to say that bad habits or questionable elements exist among the students--not at all. There may be one or two "agitators" [radical propagandists] of the working class; that is an undeniable fact. But that is a trifling matter. These elements sometimes show themselves openly. When one party makes a statement that is disagreeable to another party, then, naturally, there is a strong inclination to denounce the statement; whenever the nationalist press publishes true facts that are disagreeable to the Socialists, then the Socialist organs answer with sensational statements. The editors of the newspaper Kova (The Struggle) dug deep into philosophy in an effort to support their arguments. We must admit that what appeared in Kova had nothing to do with the Lithuanian Students Literary Society of Valparaiso University; their comment was nothing but an outsider's view of a street-corner debate. The <pb facs="5423970_1_0064.jpg" n="3"/>majority of the students are mentally sound and responsible individuals. The Literary Society of the students is likewise organized on a sound and lofty basis. Therefore, the Lithuanian public should look upon our students more favorably.</p>
   <p>However, it appears that our people are not at all concerned with the welfare of our students. Our people seem to look upon our students as a foreign element. It should be the duty of our clergy to visit the students now and then. They should show more concern for our young, growing intelligentsia. I don't think I would be mistaken if I said that thus far, no Lithuanian priest has visited the Lithuanian students at Valparaiso University. Such behavior shows that our priests are not interested in the moral and religious training of our students.</p>
   <p>Priests of other nationalities often visit Valparaiso University; they hold missions in local churches and do whatever they can to build a [sound] foundation of morality and religion among the students. Our priests do not do that. The fare from Chicago is only ninety cents, but for some unknown reason, our priests <pb facs="5423970_1_0065.jpg" n="4"/>do not make the trip. Some of our priests offer the excuse that if the parents failed to inculcate morality and religion in their children, then the priests cannot do so; whether or not such reasoning is sound, is a debatable question.</p>
   <p>Our intelligentsia is even more to blame than our priests. Members of our intelligentsia do not care to visit Valparaiso, and do not do so. The intelligentsia of other nationalities act differently; they keep in close touch with their students in order to prevent them from becoming denationalized.</p>
   <p>There are about fifteen or twenty Polish students at the school; someone visits them every year. Last year, Dr. Zurawski went there, addressed all the Polish students, encouraged them, and then left. This year the Polish visitor was Frank Danisch, clerk of the Municipal Court of Chicago. There are only a handful of Polish students at the University--they have no library nor anything else of importance--and yet Polish leaders do whatever they can to keep them from becoming denationalized, because they know that these students will be the future leaders of the Poles in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0066.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Valparaiso University ought to be of greater interest to the Lithuanians than to the Poles, because not only is the Lithuanian language taught there,but also Lithuanian literature. Our intelligentsia should at least take an interest in the way the Lithuanian classes are conducted. There are many members of the Lithuanian intelligentsia in Chicago, but they are as unwilling to leave the city for a while as a wolf would be unwilling to leave the forest. If no one else is interested, then at least the editors of our press should take an active interest in our students, but so far, none of them has been seen in Valparaiso.</p>
   <p>Thus, our young students are growing up among foreigners, like birds in a forest. When they are raised in this way, they sometimes make mistakes. God forbid that our intelligentsia should notice any student behaving contrary to their wishes, for then the poor student would have to block his ears in order to deafen himself to the long flow of ridicule and scorn that is certain to be heaped upon him.</p>
   <p>It ought to be clear now to everyone that our intelligentsia should be more concerned with our students. It is their sacred duty to raise our students in the <pb facs="5423970_1_0067.jpg" n="6"/>spirit of Lithuanianism, because the intelligentsia of other nationalities has been doing so for a long time. Why doesn't our intelligentsia follow the example of other nationalities? But it appears that we do more talking and shouting than work. Let us strive to work more, then there will be less time for talk. If our intelligentsia pays more attention to our students, then our intelligentsia will not have to listen to unpleasant criticism from time to time. Therefore, honorable members of our intelligentsia, set a good example, a moral and lofty one, and we will follow you.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The newspaper Kova (The Struggle) was the weekly organ of the Lithuanian Socialist League and was published in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. When Mr. Vitkauskas wrote this article he was the instructor in Lithuanian at Valparaiso University. During 1914 and 1915 he was publisher and editor of the monthly Laisvoji Mintis (Freedom of Thought), organ of the Lithuanian Freethinkers Society, published in Chicago, Illinois. As he was a poor man he studied hard under unfavorable conditions, contracted tuberculosis, and died in 1915 at the age of twenty-eight].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
