<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-04-06">Apr. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Why Lietuva Did Not Support Candidates Gugis and Galskis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0906</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0906.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1917-04-06">Apr. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WHY LIETUVA DID NOT SUPPORT CANDIDATES GUGIS AND GALSKIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Tuesday the aldermanic election took place in Chicago. Among the candidates were two Lithuanians, Casimir Gugis and Peter Galskis. These men ran on the Socialist ticket, and were strongly supported by the newspaper Naujienos. The newspaper Lietuva did not support any of the Lithuanian candidates, and because of this the editors of Naujienos became enraged.</p>
   <p>In a long editorial Naujienos denounced Lietuva and its editors, and accused them of not practicing what they preach. The editorial stated that although Lietuva constantly preaches "unity and love for the Lithuanian nation," it failed to live up to these principles when it was necessary to support candidates Gugis and Galskis. The editors of Lietuva are referred to as liars, humbugs, hypocrites, etc.</p>
   <p>Our answer to that editorial is short and simple. Lietuva supports Lithuanianism, but not those who do not recognize Lithuanianism, and who disgrace their <pb facs="5423970_1_0907.jpg" n="2"/>nationality. Our Socialists do not recognize Lithuanianism; for that reason they cannot demand in its name support for their personal ambitions. While in Washington, D. C., Mr. Gugis made vile remarks concerning Lithuanian organizations, and disgraced Lithuanianism in the eyes of foreigners. By these remarks he aided neither the Lithuanian cause nor the war-stricken people of Lithuania. Why, then, should Lithuanians support his candidacy for public office?</p>
   <p>According to Naujienos, Mr. Gugis was a candidate of the "working class". However, he showed by his actions that he regards himself as an aristocrat. Although he lives almost directly across the street from the office of Lietuva he sent flunkys to the newspaper to request its support. Apparently the steps of the Lietuva offices are too far beneath his aristocratic legs.</p>
   <p>In regards to Mr. Galskis, we believe that he was not qualified in all respects for the office for which he ran. We never support candidates merely because they happen to be Lithuanians; they must also be fully qualified for office.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0908.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As far as Lithuanianism is concerned, we believe that we have acted fairly well by refraining from telling our readers what we think of the candidates before the election. We knew that these candidates had no chance of being elected; therefore, we kept quiet and allowed them to have a little fun.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
