<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 35,
<date when="1898-09-02">Sept. 2, 1898</date><title level="a">The Chicago Parish School Affairs</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. VI, No. 35,
<date when="1898-09-02">Sept. 2, 1898</date><title level="a">THE CHICAGO PARISH SCHOOL AFFAIRS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When Lietuva brought up the question of the Chicago parish school, I believed that the matter soon would be closed. But as the struggle is going on, it might be permissible for me to stick in my own dvileki (a coin with the value of 11/2 kopecks).</p>
   <p>Some of our people may not like what I will say, but I love the truth and will say what I believe.</p>
   <p>I like to offend neither the committee nor others. A man, consisting of soul and body, requires double propagation for his soul and body. The people of Chicago understand that nobody will take such good care of their children, soul and body, as the sisters or the nuns.</p>
   <p>When Lietuva mentioned the improper conduct in the school, all started to cry that there were no truth in it, and they say that the nuns are teaching <pb facs="5423970_1_0157.jpg" n="2"/>our children very well; they teach to say their prayers, good conduct in the church, to worship the Lord God, in other words, they rear the children for the good of their souls. For this I am honoring the committee of the Chicago school. When we sow into their young hearts the good seed, we will reap a good crop. But ... unfortunately, the Chicago school committee was mindful only of the souls, and forgot to rear the bodies and the minds of our children. Therefore, Lietuva had the right to talk about such a teaching. In the Lithuanian school, supported with Lithuanian money, the Lithuanian children are instructed by teachers who do not know Lithuanian! This is a real scandal. I would try to justify the committee on this point; I will say that when a chicken is looking for a night's sleep and flies up to the top of a tree, then the chicken believes that it sits so high that even the eagle would not be able of fly up that high. It is the same way with the Chicago school committee, it believes that when the children can read and write, then they can climb up to the top of the cherry tree. Now then, when the chickens are looking for the highest tree, and when we have seen the protest against the Chicago school committee, and proving the benefit of knowing the Lithuanian language, we must <pb facs="5423970_1_0158.jpg" n="3"/>say, "Dear members of the committee, you like to sit on the top of the tree, but you do not wish to see your children lift themselves higher."</p>
   <p>The Chicago school committee itself does not know much about the Lithuanian language. The Lithuanian school is supported with Lithuanian money. I wish that in the Lithuanian school Lithuanian would be taught besides English. But the teachers - nuns - do not know Lithuanian.</p>
   <p>For such conduct of the committee I blame Rev. Krawczunas. The priest as a spiritual leader paid no attention to teaching our children the Lithuanian language.</p>
   <p>I am acquainted with schools in several countries where the nuns are teaching as in Italy, Austria and France. The nuns there not only are teaching in elementary schools, but in high schools, too. The nun-teachers there are qualified by the government, educated in higher schools. In England and Scotland the nuns have no high education, so they are not allowed to teach civil education.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0159.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Of the nuns in the Chicago Lithuanian school who have diplomas or not I do not ask. Even if they are highly educated, if they do not know the Lithuanian language, they cannot teach in a Lithuanian school.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Chicago school committee should see that your children would get not only spiritual education, but civil education as well.</p>
   <p>(The school committee can do nothing in the school affairs, because the priest controls the school. Editor.)</p>
   <p>A Priest from Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
