<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-04">Jan. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Year Is New--Our Hardships Are Old</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1356</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1356.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-04">Jan. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE YEAR IS NEW--OUR HARDSHIPS ARE OLD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Again we are on the threshold of another year. Factories have been shut down temporarily so that the capitalists can take inventory in order to determine how much profit they have derived from the brawn of the workers. We cannot censure then for that because it is their business to profit from their employees. They must calculate and plan ways to make still greater profits from their employees during the coming year.</p>
   <p>But how do the workers look at the new year? Very few are making plans to better their standard of living. Usually they content themselves with a little celebration, and with extending the season's greetings to each other.</p>
   <p>Workers! Why not take an example from the capitalists? You also should take an inventory of the past year and plan for the coming year. What benefits have we derived from our past activities? What steps must we take so that in the future the exploiters of the working class will "chisel" at least one dollar less from us and our children?</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1357.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We all remember the grief with which last New Year's eve was ushered in. A large group of children of striking workers were enjoying a banquet in the Calumet district on Christmas Eve. Through the nefarious work of some unknown scoundrels, seventy-two innocent children perished in agony. We, therefore, greeted 1914 with bitterness in our hearts.</p>
   <p>However, our misfortunes did not decrease at all throughout the whole year. An industrial depression was steadily creeping upon us. The army of unemployed increased from day to day. The coal miners in Colorado suffered unusually severe hardships. Unable to endure any longer their economic misery, the miners went out on strike. As a result they and their families were evicted from the company-owned shacks in which they were living. But when the strikers set up living quarters in tents in the open fields a band of murderers who were hired by the capitalists, attacked the colony. They set fire to the tents, shot and slaughtered the men, women and children. And why? Merely because the workers dared to ask for a larger piece of bread, for a better standard of living.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1358.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Furthermore, the above incident is not the only example of the hardships which the workers are forced to endure. Let us look at the conditions of our brother workers in Chicago. How many have been forced to greet the New Year on the street, without shelter? How many did not have a bite to eat? How many of our sisters and daughters, in order to have some food on New Year's day, were forced to sell themselves on the streets as prostitutes? How many healthy young men, in the prime of their lives, were forced to commit suicide because they were unable to find employment? We must take an inventory of these conditions. Let the New Year be a day of inventory for us just as it is for the capitalists.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
