<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-01-05">Jan. 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Communist Party Reorganized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0761</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0761.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-01-05">Jan. 5, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">COMMUNIST PARTY REORGANIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reorganization of the Communist party in Chicago has been completed. All sections, including the foreign language groups, have been divided into geographical districts, without regard to nationality. The latest mass-meetings show that members of the party have met the new reorganization plan with great enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The main difficulty encountered in the reorganizational plan has been the large number of different foreign language sections. However, this difficulty will soon be overcome, because there are no more workers in this country who are entirely unable to speak English. The difficulty is that members of the various language groups are accustomed to speaking in their native tongue at meetings. In district meetings the English language will prove inconvenient at first, but the members will gradually become accustomed to it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0762.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Chicago the larger and more active districts have started their own little mimeographed newspapers. It has been found that factory workers, among whom these newspapers are distributed, become interested in them immediately, because they deal intimately with their problems in the factories.</p>
   <p>The language obstacle is also the only problem encountered in the reorganization of our Lithuanian section. Especially those members who have been active only in the Lithuanian section and have been attending only Lithuanian meetings "feel strange" at these meetings, where only the English language is spoken. Those members who have been attending all the gatherings and activities of the party, or those who have been active in the various labor unions, have entered the activities without any changed feelings.</p>
   <p>It is true that those districts where there is a large number of members with the language handicap will be less effective. However, those members <pb facs="5423970_1_0763.jpg" n="3"/>who offer the language handicap as an excuse for lessening their activities, cannot be called Communists. The language handicap will not deter a real Communist, especially when he knows that the purpose of the reorganizational plan is to create a more effective Communist party.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
