<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-06">Jan. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Classes in Sewing Cooking and English</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-06">Jan. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CLASSES IN SEWING COOKING AND ENGLISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.3.... The Lithuanian Ladies' Educational Society plans to resume its popular educational activities this winter on Jan.5th. Every winter season this society organizes and conducts evening classes for the study of English, sewing, cooking and other interesting subjects.</p>
   <p>The society has gained a large number of new members during the past year. Many of these are well qualified to take an active part in the leadership of the organization and are expected to render valuable service. A record enrollment for the evening classes is forecast.</p>
   <p>The following evening courses will be offered this winter at Mark White Square, 29th and Halsted Sts:</p>
   <p>Sewing: Beginning Jan.5th, every Tuesday evening. Bring your own material for any garment you wish to sew; such as a dress, blouse,skirt, or various clothing for children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0179.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The English Language: Beginning Jan. 6th, every Wednesday evening. It is absolutely essential for everyone to know how to speak English. Without a knowledge of the language one experiences many inconvenient and embarrassing moments. When you apply for work you are at a great disadvantage because you are unable to speak to the employer,on certain important occasions one is compelled to waste as much as a half day looking for an interpreter. It will pay anyone to devote at least one evening every week for the study of the English language.</p>
   <p>Cooking: Beginning Jan.7th, every Thursday evening. This is a very important and essential course, because ones health, life, and happiness depend upon properly prepared food.</p>
   <p>The courses in English and sewing are free to members and outsiders. The course in cooking is free only to members of the Lithuanian Ladies' Educational Society. A charge of fifteen cents is made to non-members to help defray expenses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
