<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-01">May 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">May Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0793</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0793.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-01">May 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MAY DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today is May Day, the holiday of all the working people throughout the entire world. The holiday was established more than a quarter of a century ago, when the American Federation of Labor, assembled in a convention in 1888, in St. Louis, Missouri, decided to make May I a holiday for all workers. A short time later, the International Socialist Congress, in Paris, France, discussed the question of a workers' holiday and decided to dedicate May 1 for that purpose. Beginning with the year 1890, this holiday has been observed every year.</p>
   <p>May Day is the mark of unity of all the workers of the world. It shows that the workers, although they are of different nationalities, different religions, different races, etc., they are virtually members of one big family. They are all equally exploited by the capitalists, oppressed by their governments, <pb facs="5423970_1_0794.jpg" n="2"/>and they all are forced to unite in order to fight against exploitation and oppression. May Day urges all members of the oppressed class all over the world to fight for better conditions. Workers can improve their lives and better their working conditions only by fighting for them; they can maintain all gains, can reach liberty and free themselves from the bondage of capitalism only by fighting.</p>
   <p>On May Day the workers of the world declare their determination to fight for that liberty. They let the world know that they do not wish to remain slaves of the rich. They declare their right to all the products of the world that they produce and make with their own hands; they announce their determination to rule the world in order that they, the working people, can benefit from the fruits of their own labor.</p>
   <p>On May Day the workers of the world stand up against the capitalists of the entire world, the power of the oppressed against the power of the oppressors, as two uncompromising enemies. These two forces are enemies of each other because of the nature of the existing social order; a social order that has separated the workers from the means of production; one that has placed the <pb facs="5423970_1_0795.jpg" n="3"/>control of the tools of production in the hands of a small minority, and forced the majority to be servants and slaves of those who control the means of production. In order for the working people to obtain liberty they must wrest the control of the means of production from the small mindrty and make them the property of all the people. The workers of the whole world are now engaged in a determined struggle to effect such a change in the social order of the world.</p>
   <p>On May Day the workers raise a protest against the capitalistic system and all of its terrible evils--long working hours, meager wages, exploitation of women and children in factories, restriction of the liberty of the workers, etc. This year the greatest protest must be directed against war and militarism.</p>
   <p>For almost two years a ghastly slaughter of human beings has been in progress in Europe, Asia, Africa, and on the high seas. This slaughter was started and is being continued by the capitalistic governments, that are servants of greedy business interests. Millions of lives have already been destroyed, an inestimable amount of wealth has been destroyed, and there is still no visible <pb facs="5423970_1_0796.jpg" n="4"/>end to the war. American workers cannot look upon that barbarous orgy without raising a voice of protest. They stand for the immediate return of peace and for their comrades in Europe to again be given an opportunity to establish relations with the workers of America, to strengthen their organizations and continue the struggle for the achievement of their aims that was retarded by the war.</p>
   <p>American workers desire an end to the war all the more because the European war is adversely affecting America. It is true that the sale of munitions to Europe has remedied business and lessened unemployment in the United States, but at the same time, it has strengthened the influence of American capitalists who profit from the enlargement of the United States Army and Navy, from all wars, and from the spoils of all wars.</p>
   <p>For twenty months the American capitalists have been making all kinds of efforts to place the yoke of militarism on the shoulders of this country; lately they have become so audacious that they began to agitate openly for the establishment of compulsory military service in the United States. Thanks to their intrigues, the United States became involved in an insane adventure in Mexico, <pb facs="5423970_1_0797.jpg" n="5"/>and there is great danger that in a short time these two countries will become engaged in a real war. It is the duty of American workers to defend American from those misfortunes. Today, while observing the May Day holiday, it is their duty to impressively express their disgust against the nefarious deeds and efforts of the capitalists.</p>
   <p>The working class thirsts for peace and liberty. It denounces war and preparations for war.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
