<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 36,
<date when="1901-09-06">Sept. 6, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">We Should Help the Students</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 36,
<date when="1901-09-06">Sept. 6, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">WE SHOULD HELP THE STUDENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We lack educated people who could regain for us our nation and her honor. The clergy, for the education of its own class, has organized a society under the name of Motinele (Little Mother), the purpose of which is to help clerical students. They do not care and will not help the liberal students. Dr. Szliupas agreed to send one student every year to Columbus University, at his own expense. Such an effort on the part of Dr. Szliupas is a blessing to the Lithuanians. One of our good nationalists. Mr. V. Ambrozevicia from Newark, N. J., announced in Vienybe that a fund should be organized to help the Lithuanian students. The sponsor of this fund promised to pay $5 yearly for five years. The graduates may repay the loan as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>I support the project and will donate $5 as soon as the fund committee becomes organized. I think that such a committee should be separated from the influence or the control of any society, since an independent committee could work better and bring better results. In this committee, <pb facs="5423970_1_0135.jpg" n="2"/>besides the treasurer there should be other people, in order to make the students fund committee stronger and more stable. We must be careful not to get the lower class of people for these scholarships.</p>
   <p>J. Naujokas</p>
   <p>Editor's note: We think there should be organized a reliable organization with branches in the various Lithuanian colonies. The branches should have agents to agitate and collect the money for the students' fund. One central committee could not accomplish much, but through the branches it would be possible to make a great progressive movement among the Lithuanians in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
