<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-17">Oct. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Profusion of Our Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-10-17">Oct. 17, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROFUSION OF OUR SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If we look at the life of Lithuanians of America we see at once a very pleasant characteristic. When we examine a larger Lithuanian colony, our eyes will be attracted first to the large number of societies. Indeed, this is a striking and important characteristic. This large number of our societies should mean growth and strength to our public life, but if we look closer into this matter, our attitude toward this problem will change abruptly. We will find that the profusion of our societies adds no importance to our public life.</p>
   <p>Let us see! In every Lithuanian colony every time that we are confronted with Lithuanian societies, their aims and purposes are the same. The only difference between them is that they have the names of different saints, or that they hold their meetings at different saloon halls. What benefit are we getting from such multiplicity?</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0565.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Another thing, we are weak in intellectual leadership. We have very few good leaders. If it is difficult for us to accomplish something good by acting together, what can we accomplish when we are disunited? Why is this division into many branches necessary amongst us? Well, we might find some arguments to justify the existence of the various societies. We can say that every society has its own customs and practices, and thus every person may choose one to his own taste and inclination. But such an argument does not outweigh the disaster brought on by intellectual disunity.</p>
   <p>Finally, even if such a separationist idea exists among us as an innate trait, if we cannot individually exist without it, should it not be possible for the majority of our societies whose aims and principles are identical to develop centralization among them? If this is impossible among all the Lithuanian colonies in America, should it not be possible to develop centralization in the larger Lithuanian colonies? Let us consider the Chicago Lithuanian colonies. It is said that there are from 150 to 200 <pb facs="5423970_1_0566.jpg" n="3"/>Lithuanian societies, clubs, etc., here. Yet, where they are, what they are doing, no one knows. If you ever want to do something of importance, you will be able to find the addresses of only a few societies. If it could be possible to locate all such societies through some centralized office, we could accomplish much.</p>
   <p>Incidentally, there has been organized in Chicago the Lithuanian Societies Association, but for the lack of activity or some other cause, this organization is far from successful. If it were active, it would produce huge benefits. The same situation exists in other Lithuanian colonies, in Brooklyn, New York City and its vicinity, Pittsburgh and its suburbs; the Pennsylvania hard coal district, where many Lithuanians are living; the New England Lithuanian colonies, etc. Every district could organize its own center.</p>
   <p>Of course, it would be much better if the number of our societies could be decreased. A smaller group of societies could grow in strength, not only in membership, but financially, too. Such societies would be much stronger and could accomplish a lot of good for our own benefit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
