<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-09">May 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Strikes</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-09">May 9, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR STRIKES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Throughout the United States labor strikes are spreading, affecting all branches of industry. Strikes are nothing new, but it is significant that the increased activity of the workers is taking place in the dawn of spring. But there is nothing surprising in this. As Nature awakens from her long winter sleep and all life begins anew, there is born in the heart of the oppressed and exploited worker the strong desire to rid himself of the shackles that bind his body and spirit: it is a rebirth of that strong desire for freedom that has been dormant deep in his soul. As the refreshing winds of spring blow, the worker is imbued with new power, a new energy with which to fight against those who oppress and exploit him. (There is a good reason, therefore, why May first was selected as the holiday of all the proletarians of the world.)</p>
   <p>There are other reasons, besides those stated above, why the workers of America <pb facs="5423970_1_0407.jpg" n="2"/>have become more active now than they ever were before. This activity has been stimulated by the capitalistic "prosperity". Our capitalists have received many war orders. Almost everywhere our industries are now working at full capacity. Workers are in demand everywhere because immigration has been greatly decreased during the war. However, wages are still very low in spite of an unusual increase in the cost of living. The workers realize all this very well. They know that the present is a suitable moment for an economic struggle, and for that reason they have become unusually active. A struggle with the capitalists is in progress everywhere. One victory is following another. The workers are winning higher wages, shorter working hours, etc.</p>
   <p>However, the workers should make sure that their present victories and gains will not be merely temporary; they must see to it that they will not lose tomorrow what they have gained today. They can preserve their gains, and hold out against the strongly organized capitalists, only by remaining united in strong labor organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
