<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-18">May 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-18">May 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In yesterday's issue of the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> (News) we wrote of how the capitalists became seriously <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>; we pointed out out that they bee me so concerned that, in order to <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> influence of <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Rockefeller proposed at the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> convention of the Young Men's Christian Association the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of a <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. It is a known fact that these <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> are not concerned with Christian ideals, and they are not interested in <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, but they seek to reform that element which say it represents Christianity--<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> accurately, the Christian church--or the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>The <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> have become <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. They have not been <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> with sufficient energy their duty to instill the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> with the spirit <pb facs="5423970_1_0679.jpg" n="2"/><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[blank]"/> <pb facs="5423970_1_0680.jpg" n="3"/>particularly in the state of Colorado. That is also the reason why the capitalists are so <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> supporting the Young Men's Christian Association. Thus very extensive and highly developed organization is fully, with soul and body, in the service of the capitalists (Mr. Rockfeller himself is one of its most active members).</p>
   <p>Many people, especially working people, who are not closely acquainted with the Young Men's Christian Association believe that it is an innocent young peoples' cultural institution. But that is a gross error. The Association is carrying on the same kind of <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> work for the benefit of the capitalists as do all priests and ministers. The active clergymen of that organization go into factories and during the noon hour they conduct services, read passages from the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, sing holy hymns, and employ other tricks to cloud the minds of the workers. During the past year alone (1915) the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of the Young Men's Christian Association conducted services in factories <pb facs="5423970_1_0681.jpg" n="4"/>in various towns and cities in which nearly two million workers participated.</p>
   <p>Today in America there is a widely known revivalist of Christianity, known as Billy Sunday, a former athlete. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> has a very good throat and has become famous for his efforts to bring back into the Christian fold those who have gone astray. Tens of thousands of people assemble to hear him talk, mostly poor people. And Billy Sunday does not hesitate to threaten those people with devils, flames of hell, and boiling tar. Incessantly he hammers into their <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> and pray, work and pray! <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Sunday religious revival meetings are arranged for him by capitalists in various towns and cities and they pay him hundreds of thousands of dollars for his services.</p>
   <p>That, then, is the kind of Christianity that is desired by the capitalists: Christianity that will fool the workers. That is the kind of Christianity that is being advocated by our own Lithuanian priests. They not only advocate <pb facs="5423970_1_0682.jpg" n="5"/>it, but are busily engaged in organizing unsuspecting and ignorant people so that they will sacrifice their bodies and souls upon the altar of the capitalists. They have established and control the St. Joseph's Workers Association, the slogan of which is: "Workers of all lands unite for one purpose! And that purpose is very great: Pray and work, pray and work!" The only trouble is that not many people want to pray and work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
