<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-08-07">Aug. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Even the Fight against Business Is a Business</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Svirplys</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0822</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0822.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-08-07">Aug. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">EVEN THE FIGHT AGAINST BUSINESS IS A BUSINESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Svirplys</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is no end to the cunningness of people in these times. If one would believe that there are no cunning people among the Lithuanians, one would err. Thanks to the gods, we also have some of them. Perhaps we even have more of them than is necessary. We even have many clever men who are totally unnecessary to us, for, instead of bringing one or another kind of benefit to the people, they do them harm--and, of course, profit by it themselves.</p>
   <p>Let us take, for instance, so-called business. At the time that a large number of Lithuanians began coming to America, the majority were common, uneducated people, and all the energies of our leaders and newspapers were turned to the idea that our brothers must enlighten themselves, enlighten themselves above all else.</p>
   <p>Later, when the number of immigrants had increased, when more intelligent <pb facs="5423970_1_0823.jpg" n="2"/>and more enlightened men were evident among them, those same leaders and newspapers began urging that our people, having opened their eyes more or less, should undertake businesses and trades.....</p>
   <p>The people understood and obeyed. For, they thought, it is unworthy for our brothers always to remain with scum; for we Lithuanians will never gain anything by working at the most common and heaviest jobs and then putting the profits of our industry into the hands of Jews and other foreign nationalities; if we continue doing this we will always remain on the bottom rung of the ladder of nationalities and we will be looked down upon by others as oxen which are only good for plowing.</p>
   <p>Therefore, led by our more intelligent leaders, we Lithuanians began to better our position among nationalities. The more ingenious persons took to businesses or trades and, at this time, though commerce and industry are far from the development and growth that they can attain through us, we are already able to take care of many things for our own people. We have a good number of tradesmen and a large group of our own businessmen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0824.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>No harm has been done any Lithuanian because we do have these men; everybody understands that. The money (or at least a part of it), with which the Lithuanians formerly fed Jews and other foreigners (and they did not even thank us for that) now remains in the midst of our own fellow-nationals. In this manner we have witnessed the development of wealthier Lithuanians, especially in the larger colonies. Their example is drawing more ingenious Lithuanians to the easier and better-paying work. And all of this has even forced the members of other nationalities to change their opinions somewhat about the Lithuanians: today the Lithuanians are rapidly rising from the classification of "cattle", as the Americans formerly regarded them, to the ranks of the more honored citizens.</p>
   <p>That is not all. When more or less large Lithuanian industries came into existence, they attracted more intelligent men for whom there was no work in America previously. When the number of more enlightened men increased, our cultural life also began to develop. And if one would compare the present day Lithuanian-Americans to those of fifteen to twenty years <pb facs="5423970_1_0825.jpg" n="4"/>ago, even a blind man would see the great difference and would admit that the welfare of the Lithuanian immigrants has been bettered and augmented several times.</p>
   <p>It could have been no other way. The more or less widespread businesses and trades among our people developed more talented people, gave birth to more intelligentsia. The larger number of enlightened people worked more energetically to raise our lowly, unenlightened masses to a better life by showing them the paths by which other enlightened nations had bettered themselves.</p>
   <p>In that manner, as you see, a healthy and intelligent movement began among the Lithuanians. Go into business and trades, and do not envy those of other people, for there are so many businesses and trades in this country.</p>
   <p>However, recently something began to go wrong someplace. An altogether contrary movement has come into being, the imp knows from where. Entirely opposed voices are audible.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0826.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It was formerly pointed out that the undertaking of a business is a good and beneficial thing. Now all at once entire mountains are being rolled down on the businessmen; they are the targets for mudslinging and are called, without any cause, robbers and cheaters. There is a general attempt to instill in our people the idea that business is a deceitful, dirty occupation, unworthy of a good name. Even now a voice occasionally buzzes in our ears: "A businessman is a cheat; a businessman is the exploiter of the common worker. You are a common, ignorant laborer, therefore, you cannot see that. But I am your friend and I am showing it to you. Of course, you must be grateful to me, for I alone am concerned with your welfare while the businessmen are leeches...."</p>
   <p>Such agitation has been going on for several years. For some not understandable reasons no one among us was able, or wanted to, or was brave enough to raise his voice against that destructive agitation.</p>
   <p>A few bawlers dominated the stage and, apparently, others did not wish to engage in an argument with them for fear of having themselves called <pb facs="5423970_1_0827.jpg" n="6"/>"capitalistic exploiters of the workingmen".</p>
   <p>Finally, however, the ice was broken. Our older and more sedate newspapers, which have survived all the worries and failures together with all of our immigrants, raised their voices.</p>
   <p>As much as I can recall, it seems that last year the Lietuva was the first to comment on the matter when, in an editorial, it turned attention to that agitation and pointed out that such attacks on the Lithuanian businessmen and the rousing of the people against them was neither just nor beneficial. It emphasized the benefits derived by the Lithuanians from prospering industries in their midst and pointed out what makes a good business good and a bad business bad.</p>
   <p>I remember that the socialistic newspapers, especially the Pirmyn, then edited by Pius Grigaitis, disagreed. You see, it was these newspapers that gave birth to that perverse agitation among the Lithuanians and, to this day, they are striving to continue it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0828.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>They did that, apparently, for two reasons. The first reason was that, according to their theory, they consider business a "capitalistic" and "bourgeois" thing, with which a worker must not concern himself; rather he must remain a proletarian beggar and wait for the advent of socialism; then everybody will be equal--like in Heaven: it will not be necessary to work and the only thing that will have to be done will be to distribute the wealth of the bourgeois. The second and most important reason which urged on some of our men to such a destructive, to Lithuanians, agitation against business was their observation that they themselves could make a good business, a good profit, and much wealth out of such agitation, without even waiting for the advent of socialism. If you yell about the businessmen, preach that they are injurers and exploiters of the workers, naturally, you will become the guardian angel of the workers and they will bring you a huge pile of pennies.</p>
   <p>Experience has shown that such a business is an excellent one. In other words, a business (and at that an easy one) can be made out of a fight against business.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0829.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>This sort of a speech is now often repeated: "You ignorant workers, ignore business; we will teach you how to curse business. We will moan, day and night, about your hardships and the orgies and debauchery of the bourgeoisie. In other words, we will show you the road to an earthly paradise--but you, with your purses, hold on to our coattails."</p>
   <p>The same can be said of our priests who also sing the same antiphons to us: "You listen to us and have no ties to earthly wealth and you shall have Paradise. In the meantime, give us your pennies." The similarity is complete; both forbid the people to do that which they themselves do.</p>
   <p>It is a good thing that, as I have mentioned, our newspapers have finally lifted their voices against such befooling of the people.</p>
   <p>A silence was kept while there was hope that they (the socialists) would become ashamed of themselves and would cease their ugly work. The silence was finally broken and the curtain was raised to show the people a bit of the naked truth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0830.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Because of this, the newspapers which have broken the silence will undoubtedly become the targets of attacks from the socialists, both in their newspapers and from their platforms. However, it is desirable that our newspapers should not put aside this question which is so important in our lives. This agitation against business in order to make themselves a business out of it is a most stupid thing and must be stopped.</p>
   <p>Business is not injurious, to either the worker or the Lithuanian. The whole world knows that today, and each nation strives to expand business. If it is necessary to the whole world, it is also necessary to us Lithuanians.</p>
   <p>To conduct a business ethically is no deceit; it is a service for which the remuneration remains in the hands of Lithuanians....</p>
   <p>Our socialists, however, befoul and slander individuals and institutions which do not please them and fan the discontent of the people against them.....</p>
   <p>Business is a good thing, but it must be conducted conscientiously. Let <pb facs="5423970_1_0831.jpg" n="10"/>the Lithuanians take to it and ignore all kinds of cutthroats.</p>
   <p>Let the Lithuanians remember that the chimney sweep soils the whitest of clothes. Let them remember that a clever cheat always calls others cheats. Because he cheats he thinks that everybody else must necessarily cheat.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
