<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1896-09-26">Sept. 26, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">About the Lithuanian Evening School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1896-09-26">Sept. 26, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE LITHUANIAN EVENING SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last year there were two evening schools in Chicago for Lithuanians who wished to learn the English language. Even though the instruction, books and paper were free, not many Lithuanians attended those schools. It shows that our brothers do not understand the value of English in this country. The English language is most essential to every one in this country. For not knowing English, the Lithuanians are living on a low standard of living; it is hard for them to get a good job. If Lithuanians only knew English they could even get city jobs; it would be much easier to get jobs in the factories. And yet our brothers do not want to learn the English language, they do not understand what benefits they can derive from a knowledge of the English language.</p>
   <p>A few of our brothers did understand the necessity of English language. They had a meeting last Sunday at Juszka Hall, 22nd and Wood street, where they recognized the necessity of having the evening school for <pb facs="5423970_1_0198.jpg" n="2"/>this coming winter. This matter was discussed by Messrs. Jaksztis, J. Zacharewiczius, Braczulis, Pocewiczius and Palionis. Mr. Braczulis gave up the teaching for this coming winter, because he had no time to devote to it. For his place was unanimously elected Mr. Jed. Zacharewiczius, who accepted the position on condition that there would be forty Lithuanians who were willing to attend the evening school. At present there are twenty-nine Lithuanians waiting for the opening of the evening school.</p>
   <p>Those who want to attend the Lithuanian evening school, go to see Mr. Zacharewiczius at Pulaski Hall, 800 S. Ashland avenue. Because Mr. Zacharewiczius must notify the Board of Education, to show them, that such a number of Lithuanians want to have the evening school.</p>
   <p>Therefore, brothers. I would like to see a great number of Lithuanians in the evening school. If you will not come on time to register, then the evening school will not be opened.</p>
   <p>J. Ed. Zacharewiczius</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
