<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-06-03">June 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Expanding His Nation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1914-06-03">June 3, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">EXPANDING HIS NATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A census-taker came to a Lithuanian saloon keeper, P. Katkeviciu, who has a business at 3310 Mospratt St., in Bridgeport, and asked him what his nationality was. Mr. P. Katkeviciu told the census-taker that he is Lithuanian. The census-taker told him that there is no such nationality. Mr. P. Katkeviciu argued with this census-taker for an hour and failed to convince him that he is Lithuanian. In spite of Mr. Katkeviciu's protest, the census-taker, who was a Pole, entered him in the census records as a Pole and not as a Lithuanian.</p>
   <p>The Poles are Polanizing Lithuanians not only in Europe, but in the United States as well. The Poles are making every effort to increase their population by Polanizing Lithuanians and other nationalities. This census-taker was a Polish patriot and politician who wanted to make a name for himself in Chicago politics. Poles, even in Chicago, want to show their strength by misinforming the American people about their voting power. The Poles are always bluffing the American people by spreading false propaganda, writing in their newspapers that there is no such nations as Lithuania, that Lithuanian is the name of a Polish province.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0560.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We cannot expect much from the Poles, because they have no honor and no character.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
