<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-12-16">Dec. 16, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning Lithuanian Phonograph Records</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. Olszewskis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0581</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0581.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-12-16">Dec. 16, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING LITHUANIAN PHONOGRAPH RECORDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A. Olszewskis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We often receive letters inquiring about Lithuanian phonograph records. Unfortunately, no one has made any Lithuanian records up to now.</p>
   <p>Last summer I saw representatives of the Victor Company in Camden, N. J., and the Edison Company in Orange, N. J., and urged them to manufacture Lithuanian records. Both companies stated that they would not make Lithuanian records because the Lithuanians are too few, the sales of such records would be too small, and would not cover the manufacturing costs. The Victor Company stated that during its existence it had received only five letters requesting Lithuanian records and the Edison Company has received only three such letters. They said that the manufacture of Lithuanian records would cost several thousand dollars and, probably, not even a thousand dollars <pb facs="5423970_1_0582.jpg" n="2"/>worth would be sold. "Convince us", they said, "that we can sell at least $10,000 worth of such records and we will then make them."</p>
   <p>Therefore, if we want Lithuanian records we must, as you see, convince the phonograph companies that many people will want such records. Then the companies will make them.</p>
   <p>But how can we convince them? The companies will not hear the arguments of one individual and will not believe them. In order to interest the phonograph companies, it is necessary that they receive several letters with requests for Lithuanian records. They will judge from the number of letters received whether it will pay them to manufacture Lithuanian records or not. We advise all those who want Lithuanian records to write in Lithuanian to the phonograph companies, inquiring whether they have or can make Lithuanian records. Write to both companies, whose addresses we give here:</p>
   <p>(1) Victor Talking Machine Co., Camden, N. J.</p>
   <p>(2) National Phonograph Co., Orange, N. J.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0583.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Write to both these companies in Lithuanian. They will get translators who will translate your letters into the English language for them.</p>
   <p>If there are enough requests the companies will undoubtedly make Lithuanian records and then they will be available in all stores. If the companies receive few requests they will not make them. Therefore, let everybody who wants Lithuanian records write to them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
