<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-11">May 11, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Childeen in Institutions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0315</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0315.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-11">May 11, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN CHILDEEN IN INSTITUTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large number of Chicago Lithuanian children are being placed in institutions by the Cook County Juvenile Court. These children are placed in institutions for several reasons: they are either orphans, abandoned children, children who have been neglected and mistreated by their parents, and those whose parents are unable to support them. Many Lithuanian children are placed in Catholic institutions that are controlled by nuns and priests. Money for the support of all children placed in institutions through the Juvenile Court is supplied by the County treasury, although the County cannot and does not attempt to control or supervise those institutions to see that the children receive proper care and that they are reared properly. The Catholic institutions into which Lithuanian children are being placed have many shortcomings: the method of rearing the children is bad and is permeated with the spirit of the middle ages; the children experience much suffering.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0316.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is a wide difference between the Catholic and Protestant benevolent institutions (orphanages). The educational methods in Protestant institutions are modern, the treatment of the children is humane, and the children are reared in the proper manner. Children who are unfortunately born of Catholic parents are condemned to all kinds of tortures under the whip of nuns and monks in Catholic orphanages. The people of Cook County have not progressed sufficiently to establish governmental orphanages into which children would be admitted without regard to religious affiliations, and where they would be reared and educated by experienced and humanitarian teachers and pedagogues of the modern age. Lithuanian children are among those unfortunates who must suffer in institutions controlled and operated by nuns and monks. Furthermore, they are forced to go into non-Lithuanian institutions.</p>
   <p>During the past month sixty Lithuanian children have been placed into institutions through the Juvenile Court as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0317.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Fifteen Lithuanian girls were placed in the Chicago Industrial School for Girls (St. Mary's Orphanage, Desplaines, Illinois). Thirty-one Lithuanian boys were placed in the St. Mary's School for Boys (St. Mary's Orphanage, Desplaines, Illinois). Eleven Lithuanian girls were placed in the Katherine Kasper Industrial School for Girls (a German Guardian Angel orphanage). Six Lithuanian boys were placed in the Kettler School for Boys (a German Guardian Angel orphanage). Two Lithuanian boys were placed in the Lisle School for Boys (a Czech orphanage). Six Lithuanian girls were placed in the House of Good Shepherd (a Catholic house of correction for girls).</p>
   <p>All these orphanages and institutions are Catholic and are controlled and conducted by Catholic nuns and monks. For the sixty Lithuanian children these institutions will receive $5,360 from the County treasury. In Chicago there is the St. Vincent's Orphanage in which about 250 children are confined every day. Many Lithuanian babies are placed into that institution; most <pb facs="5423970_1_0318.jpg" n="4"/>of these are abandoned babies and babies of unwed mothers. This institution is famous as a place where the babies that are confined there often part with this world of tears and go hurriedly to God. Really, the death death rate of babies in St. Vincent's Orphanage is ghastly large. In no other institution do the children die so fast as in this Orphanage which is in the hands of the "Sisters of Mercy".</p>
   <p>Much more fortunate, however, are those innocent and neglected children of Catholic parents who are placed by the Juvenile Court in the governmental houses of correction or schools, such as the St. Charles School for Boys and the Cook County School for Boys. These institutions are well equipped, well conducted, and the children enjoy good life, compared to the Catholic institutions. Last month there were about thirty Lithuanian boys (all accused of some crime) in these two schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
