<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-26">June 26, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Results of a High Tariff</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0871</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0871.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-06-26">June 26, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">RESULTS OF A HIGH TARIFF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is a presidential election year and for that reason the citizens of the United States are taking an increased interest in the political affairs of the country. Lithuanian citizens are also vitally interested in the affairs of their adopted country. The election will take place, as usual, in the fall.</p>
   <p>At the national convention of the Republican party, which was held last week in Chicago, the Republican candidate for president of the United States was nominated. William Howard Taft, who is now the Secretary of War in President Roosevelt's Cabinet, was the one who was selected. The Democratic party did not nominate its candidate yet, but it is generally understood that William Jennings Bryan will be selected to run for the third time.</p>
   <p>Mr. Taft has already resigned from his post in the President's Cabinet and is now making preparations to launch his campaign.</p>
   <p>It is very difficult at this time to guess which candidate will be elected. Both parties, especially the Republican, have been engaged more or less in <pb facs="5423970_1_0872.jpg" n="2"/>propaganda work. The Republicans have been boasting very loudly that they have returned prosperity to the United States with their shameless high tariff policy. However, the evidence does not substantiate the claims of the Republicans. We all know that under the present Republican administration of President Roosevelt, there has been a marked increase in unemployment. Many people believe that the present wave of unemployment was brought about purposely by the capitalists to furnish them with a pretext for lowering wages, and wages are really going down. That may be true, but it is also true that it is impossible to sustain any kind of national prosperity very long with high tariff rates. Whenever we increase our tariff rates, other countries always retaliate by increasing their rates. This tariff war inevitably decreases our export trade, and sometimes it chokes it entirely. Then our national prosperity vanishes, wages are lowered, and there is a marked curtailment in our economic and industrial activities all over the country. Therefore, it is evident that the Republican idea of high tariff rates is a short-sighted policy. The practice of increasing our tariff rates cannot serve any other purpose except to breed economic and industrial depressions in our country.</p>
   <p>Because of the above reasons it is impossible at this time to make an accurate <pb facs="5423970_1_0873.jpg" n="3"/>prediction as to which candidate will receive a majority of the votes of the citizens of the United States. Lithuanians, undoubtedly, will study and analyze the various campaign issues and vote according to their convictions. Being members of the working class, naturally, we will favor that candidate who will make the most promises to benefit the working class.</p>
   <p>The Socialist party will also nominate a candidate for the presidency. However, there is no hope that he will be elected. Even if he would be elected, he would be unable to accomplish much good for the benefit of the working class, because the Senate and House of Representatives will be composed of Republicans and Democrats. Before attempting to elect a Socialist for president, it is necessary first to elect Socialists to the Senate and House of Representatives. At the present time there is not a single Socialist in our government at Washington, D. C.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
