<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-09-10">Sept. 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Improvement Club of Cicero</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Stankevicius</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1508</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1508.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-09-10">Sept. 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN IMPROVEMENT CLUB OF CICERO</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Stankevicius</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Cicero, Illinois, there is an association of Lithuanian home owners, known as the Lithuanian Improvement Club. It was organized in July of 1911, and now has over a hundred members.</p>
   <p>This large membership indicates that there are many Lithuanian home owners in Cicero. The purpose of this Club, as its name suggests, is to sponsor various improvements in the town of Cicero. Now and then the Club comes in conflict with the Irish and other "foreigners" of Cicero.</p>
   <p>About two years ago a group of Irish, joined by some Germans and Jews, sponsored a movement to prohibit the building of frame (wooden) homes. A resolution to that effect was submitted to the town government. If this resolution had been passed by the town government, it would have painfully affected a large number of Lithuanians. However, the Club protested against <pb facs="5423970_1_1509.jpg" n="2"/>that resolution, and demanded that a mass meeting of the citizens of Cicero be called to decide such an important issue. The demand of the Club was accepted and a mass meeting called. At the meeting, the resolution was defeated by a vote of seventy to thirty-two.</p>
   <p>This year, during the month of March, the Club held a meeting to which T. Brennan, an official of the town government, was invited to explain certain very important governmental matters. In his talk Mr. Brennan suggested that all alleys should be paved. The suggestion created discussions, but voting on the matter was indefinitely postponed.</p>
   <p>Some time later, it was learned that the Irish were about to collect signatures for a petition to the town government, requesting that a law be passed forcing all home owners to pay for paying work close to their homes. Such a law, if passed, would have greatly affected the Lithuanian home owners of Cicero. The Club, together with another similar organization, was instrumental in the calling of a public town meeting in regard to this matter. The <pb facs="5423970_1_1510.jpg" n="3"/>measure was defeated by a vote of one hundred and fifty to four.</p>
   <p>It was explained at the above meeting that, according to estimates of engineers, the poorest paving job would cost thirty dollars for a twenty-five-foot lot, and that a better paving job would cost no less than fifty dollars for the same amount of space. Therefore, a lot of money was saved in this manner for the home owners of Cicero.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian Improvement Club is still guarding and protecting the interests of its members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
