<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 12,
<date when="1914-02-19">Feb. 19, 1914</date><title level="a">Congressman Sabath a Dirty Politician</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 12,
<date when="1914-02-19">Feb. 19, 1914</date><title level="a">CONGRESSMAN SABATH A DIRTY POLITICIAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sabath, Lipsky and others made fat profits in selling lands to the Board of Education.</p>
   <p>Two newspapers, Lietuva and Katalikas, praised Congressman A. J. Sabath as a man of fine character, but later it appeared that he was not so honest as they thought him. As a politician he was a clever man for making big profits with public money. A few people who received large lumps of money are as follows: Alderman Abraham and his brother; Lipsky, trustee of the Board of Education; one gambler; one real estate man who was selling lots and homes; and A. J. Sabath and his brother. This company consisted of members picked by Congressman Sabath. The only man who was not accepted in the organization was Samuel Goldman who, being one of the outcasts and feeling hurt, exposed A. J. Sabath and his company.</p>
   <p>The plan under which they worked was not very complicated. Lipsky <pb facs="5423970_1_1047.jpg" n="2"/>was a member and trustee of the Board of Education which made considerations and gave its decision where to buy lands for building schools. Lipsky, knowing where the committee decided to buy, notified Sabath and his friends. Then Sabath bought the land. When the committee of the Board of Education came to buy this land, Sabath charged $60,000 for land for which he and his friend paid only one sixth of this amount, $50,000 going into their pockets. In order to make this appear more real, it was arranged with the party who sold the lots and homes to put on the records three times its original value. When sold to the Board of Education the price was increased four times that amount. For example, they bought the land for $5,000, put on the records its value for $15,000, then sold it to the Board of Education for $60,000. This shows that they were selling the land to the Board of Education for twelve times its original value. Mr. Goldman exposed Sabath to the investigating committee of the Board of Education, requesting the committee to make an investigation <pb facs="5423970_1_1048.jpg" n="3"/>of Sabath's graft. Mr. Goldman explained to them that Sabath had defrauded the city not once but many times.</p>
   <p>A. J. Sabath replied to Goldman's charges against him by stating that Goldman was the biggest liar he ever heard of. Further investigations proved the charges to be true.</p>
   <p>The trouble started when the Board of Education made arrangements for buying playgrounds for the Goethe School. One member of the school board indicated in his letter to the secretary that the Board of Education had decided to buy additional playgrounds two hundred feet wide for the Goethe School. Immediately after this piece of ground was bought by Feldstein, a gambler, who was a member of Sabath's company. This piece of land originally cost $5,000, but Feldstein raised its price to $15,000 in his records.</p>
   <p>In 1912 Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, in a letter to the school board, made the suggestion of buying land for the schools on the West Side. She <pb facs="5423970_1_1049.jpg" n="4"/>explained in the letter which schools needed more grounds and even mentioned the names of the schools, and sent her plans to the committee in charge of buying land for the Board of Education. Nobody had any right to know about the plans suggested by Mrs. Young. But as soon as this plan was considered by the school board committee, the lots near the schools began to pass from one party to another, and finally Sabath, his relatives and friends became the owners of the lots near the schools. The school board committee and the people were surprised when they found that Congressman Sabath and his friends were the owners of the lots near the schools.</p>
   <p>These were the aims of our honorable Congressman Sabath, who was so highly praised by our two newspapers, Lietuva and Katalikas. He claims to be a friend of foreign groups. He claims also that he has a bill which sponsors unrestricted immigration for foreign people. It does not matter what he says about himself and the bills <pb facs="5423970_1_1050.jpg" n="5"/>which he proposes to Congress. We judge the man's character by his deeds and not by his words. Regardless of what he said we know that he is not honest and that he is a dirty politician in the eyes of the public. We only mention a few of his bad deeds as congressman of the United States. Later we will have more about him in the Naujienos. Then you will be able to see how honest is Congressman Sabath.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
