<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-12-12">Dec. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">W. S. S</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-12-12">Dec. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">W. S. S</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What do those letters, W. S. S., mean? They mean War-Savings Stamps.</p>
   <p>The Government has issued two kinds of War-Savings Stamps: separate stamps which sell for twenty-five cents each, and certificates which sell for five dollars each. When you have accumulated five dollars' worth of the twenty-five cent stamps they should be exchanged for a five-dollar certificate. This certificate bears four per cent interest--more than the banks usually pay.</p>
   <p>The rest of this month is being devoted to a drive to sell more of these stamps. We advise all Lithuanians to purchase them.</p>
   <p>The sale of War-Savings Stamps was one of the best undertakings initiated by the Government of this country during the war. This is attested to by the fact that <pb facs="5423970_1_1066.jpg" n="2"/>millions of dollars' worth of these stamps have been purchased by the people up to now.</p>
   <p>First of all, War-Savings Stamps are a good financial investment, for they pay you four per cent interest. In the second place, they are accessible to all--the poor and rich, the old and young. Anybody can afford to pay a quarter for a stamp.</p>
   <p>In the third place, War-Savings Stamps encourage thrift, a virtue which should be cultivated by all--the young as well as the old.</p>
   <p>Finally, those quarters add up to the millions of dollars needed by the Government to wind up all war business: the transportation of the troops back to America, the completion of various projects, etc.</p>
   <p>This newspaper has often urged its readers to purchase these stamps. It can <pb facs="5423970_1_1067.jpg" n="3"/>give you no better advice at this time. Buy as many War-Savings Stamps as possible!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
