<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 40,
<date when="1903-10-02">Oct. 2, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Would it Be Profitable?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0937</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0937.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 40,
<date when="1903-10-02">Oct. 2, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">WOULD IT BE PROFITABLE?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are a large number of Lithuanians in America. In almost every large city the number is increasing rapidly. No matter how numerous we are, we do not know how to exploit politics, we mean nothing in politics, and we have a very low standing. Some of us are selling our votes for a scoop of beer, while others are selling their votes for a few cents.</p>
   <p>Our Lithuanian politicians are working for the benefit of the American politicians in order to get some minor political job, although there is nothing good for our nation. It would be essential for ourselves to organize and to show the power we have. It would be better for our organizers, who are organizing societies under the various holy names, to organize beneficial political clubs. Such clubs should take interest not only in sick benefits, but in political affairs as well. We have many religious and national societies, but they are taking care of sick benefit only. They have nothing to do and have never done anything for national affairs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0938.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The political clubs can give the same sick benefit like all the other societies. Whereas the trouble arose in the religious societies about the religion problem, the liberals began to organize the national societies, although even the national societies show no activity. If we would have as many political clubs, our influence would be much greater; the Americans would take us into consideration; many Lithuanians could get political jobs (If the clubs organize for the sake of getting political jobs, it would be of no benefit for the nation. Editor). In the courts and in other official places, they would look to us with a different attitude. Look at the Jews: there are not more of them in America than (there are) Lithuanians, yet many of them have government positions. (Many of them get government positions by examination, not all through the politicians favor. Editor). Always we must go to the strangers in case of some event and must pay dearly for service. By not understanding English, we cannot answer properly the questions stated to us in the court, and many a time we are found <pb facs="5423970_1_0939.jpg" n="3"/>guilty just for not knowing the language. The political and benefit clubs would bring benefit, because they would have nothing to do with religion. The members can pay the same monthly dues as in other societies and would get the same sick benefit. It is necessary to discuss this problem more broadly.</p>
   <p>The Businessman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
