<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sandara</title>,
<date when="1930-10-01">Oct. 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Spare Time Study</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sandara</title>,
<date when="1930-10-01">Oct. 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">SPARE TIME STUDY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The principal reason so many children do not seek a higher education after graduation from the public schools, is that their parents cannot afford to support them for the four years required to complete a general high school course, and the additional four years in college. Formal education requires great resources, and only a comparatively small percentage of wage earners possess them. This is especially true of large families, where the earnings of the father are barely sufficient to provide the prime necessities of life for his family.</p>
   <p>This is the only reason that excuses parents who send their children to work immediately after completing the elementary school course.</p>
   <p>Discontinuance of a formal education, however, is one thing, and discontinuance of study is another. When economic reasons make it impossible <pb facs="5423970_1_0040.jpg" n="2"/>to attend schools during the working hours, evening schools should not be forgotten for they offer valuable and systematic courses of study. And when even the evening schools, for one reason or another, become inaccessible, then the correspondence school should not be ignored. But, if the expense of both the evening school and correspondence school, especially university extension courses, are beyond one's means, one should not throw up his hands in despair and give up studying, for books can be borrowed from the libraries, and in the books one will find the wealth of contemporary scientific knowledge.</p>
   <p>Thus, while there may be valid reasons for discontinuance of a formal education, there is no reason in this world for discontinuing study entirely.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0041.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is possible to acquire a liberal education by spare time study. Spare time study is both a pleasant and profitable pastime. Knowledge is the most important and fascinating thing in this world, and after one has finished his day's task, has taken the necessary rest and diversion in some amusement, he or she will find a moment where there is nothing to do. Some people are bored by such moments and seek a way to kill time, but there is no way of bringing it back to life. Killing of time is a crime as great as taking a life. Life filled with idleness is empty, and the idler is a dead burden upon society, and an extorter of other people's efforts.</p>
   <p>By recognizing idleness as a crime, and recreation and rest as the storing up of energy, we at once come to the point of evaluation of the business of living and the proper use of our time. A day has only <pb facs="5423970_1_0042.jpg" n="4"/>twenty four hours. Granting that rest takes about eight hours, gainful occupation another eight hours, we find that of each day of the working week we still have eight hours which is our surplus for investment. In what way should these eight hours be invested? The answer to this question determines the value of our lives. Should we invest these eight hours in study and deprive ourselves of many pleasures in life perhaps making ourselves miserable? This should not be done. It will suffice if we divide the spare time among several interests in life, setting aside for study only two hours a day, another two hours for light reading such as fiction, and the remaining four hours we should devote to our social needs. The program for each and every day should be varied. Sundays and holidays may be exempted from our time budget and used for pleasure and social functions. And as circumstances vary with each individual, so each individual should make his</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
