<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IV, No. 12,
<date when="1896-03-21">March 21, 1896</date><title level="a">Lithuanians, Be Lithuanians!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IV, No. 12,
<date when="1896-03-21">March 21, 1896</date><title level="a">LITHUANIANS, BE LITHUANIANS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reading the statistics of the registered people in Chicago, we found people of various nationalities, but we failed to find Lithuanians. Why so? Because our Lithuanians did not register as Lithuanians, they registered as Poles or Russians.</p>
   <p>One English newspaper in Chicago stated that there are about one thousand Lithuanians in Chicago. We protested against such a false statement. We have told in the Chicago news papers, that there are over 10,000 Lithuanians. Now the Americans know that we represent a nation which they ought to take into consideration.</p>
   <p>In order that our protest would not be in vain, every Lithuanian should not be ashamed of his nationality. Always and everywhere, must you admit that you are a Lithuanian. Do the Russians, the Poles stand higher than we? We know that everybody hates the Poles, and yet they do not deny that they are Poles <pb facs="5423970_1_0646.jpg" n="2"/>Every man wins honor or disgrace by his own conduct. By concealing your nationality you will not gain higher honor, you will be known by your conduct. Let us live decently, then everybody will respect us even though we were descendants of cannibals; we must conduct ourselves morally, educate ourselves; then everybody will respect us, but, above all, do not conceal your nationality. You cannot make a chicken from an eagle, likewise Lithuanians cannot become Irishmen nor Poles, no matter how hard you try to conceal your Lithuanianism.</p>
   <p>He who denies his own nationality and tries to assimilate himself with other nationality will not be respected by the people of that nationality.</p>
   <p>Lithuanians do not conceal your Lithuanianism, because Lithuania in her past was one of the most honorable nations among the European nations. Now it is our duty, by our own good conduct, to regain the lost honor of our nation. Let us honor ourselves; then others will respect us.</p>
   <p>This year the city of Chicago will take a census of the people. Let us not stoop behind others, but bravely admit that we are Lithuanians; otherwise we will be a laughing stock of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Since the last meeting the Chicago city officials were convinced that <pb facs="5423970_1_0647.jpg" n="3"/>we were not Russians, Poles nor Germans. And now they placed on the blank a rubric, marked Lithuanians. We must admit who we are; others are smaller than we are and yet they are recognized and honored. We also will be honored as others. Let us follow the road which other nations have pointed to us.</p>
   <p>Editor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
