<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-03">May 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Demand an Eight-Hour Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">by P. P. Nunchikas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1336</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1336.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-03">May 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">LET US DEMAND AN EIGHT-HOUR DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by P. P. Nunchikas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear brother worker, are you not tired from long working hours? Do you work only eight hours per day? Do you receive adequate compensation for your work, so you and your family can live like human beings should live? If not, why? A worker who works from ten to twelve hours per day is unable to find time for peaceful rest; he has no time to read newspapers in order to learn what goes on in the world; and he has no time for wholesome and moral recreation. All his energy is expended in his work, and when he comes home he must hurry to bed in order to rest and be able to return to slavery in the morning to earn his meager wages and feed himself and his family in a half-starving manner. And in order to preserve his life he must work for the wages that are offered to him by the capitalists. A capitalist never pays enough to provide the worker with a decent living.</p>
   <p>Therefore, what remains for the workers to do in order to better their lives, <pb facs="5423970_1_1337.jpg" n="2"/>to guarantee their future, and to have something to depend upon in case of unemployment or other misfortunes? Demand higher wages from the capitalists? It is true, such a demand should be made; but will the capitalists heed the demand for higher wages and shorter working hours? Not only will the capitalists never willingly heed such a demand, but they will actually discharge the workers who make such demands. In such cases there is no alternative but to oppose the employer by going out on strike, and strikes can be successful if they are operated correctly. Before a demand is made of the capitalists for shorter working hours and higher wages, all workers must organize into a strong union. When the workers are well organized and go out on strike they can win a better living for them-selves and for others.</p>
   <p>Every day we hear that workers have won a strike in one place and lost in another. Those workers who lost were not organized, and no strike can be won without proper organization. Only in this way will a demand for an eight-hour <pb facs="5423970_1_1338.jpg" n="3"/>day and higher wages be granted. In every. case where the workers remained well organized the capitalists were defeated and the workers are enjoying a much better life than those who are still being forced to work twelve hours a day.</p>
   <p>For example, let us take the small town of Bridgeport, Connecticut. There, in nearly all the factories, the workers work eight hours a day. If in any factory in that city the workers put in more than eight hours a day, they are making preparations to strike. The workers in that city are organizing rapidly and strongly. They have already won many strikes and some are still in progress; they expect to win all these strikes. This shows that workers must become organized, that every worker must belong to a union in order to help themselves and others to win shorter working hours and higher wages!</p>
   <p>When the capitalists feel the danger of a strike of their employees, they first of all investigate to find out how well the employees are organized. If they see that the workers are sufficiently well organized to win a strike, then the <pb facs="5423970_1_1339.jpg" n="4"/>capitalists give in to the demands of the employees because they know that it is very expensive to fight a group of well-organized workers. Therefore, brother Lithuanian workers, let us not lag behind the workers of other nationalities! Let us also join the unions, forget our racial and religious differences, and extend a brotherly hand to each other--"unity is power". We can obtain a better life only by remaining united. Let us join a union that is energetically and strongly fighting for the good of the workers--such a union is the International association of Machinists. The union accepts all kinds (?) of workers as members. [Translator's note: Interrogation point made by editor of Naujienos.] This union recently started a strong campaign againist the capitalists because they have been oppressing workers too long. Therefore, let us Lithuanians not lag behind the workers of other nationalities; let us join this international union and through struggles and unity we will attain a better life. Let us all demand an eight-hour working day and more pay for our work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
