<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-02-03">Feb. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Deterioration of Youth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1346</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1346.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-02-03">Feb. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE DETERIORATION OF YOUTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Youth is the maturing generation. In a few years the youths will be grown men and women. The mature men and women of today were young boys and girls not so many years ago. These are very plain truths, but from them we may draw important conclusions.</p>
   <p>If the youths of today, who will become mature citizens in a few years, are to be good citizens, we must concern ourselves with them. If the mature citizens of today are inferior, we must seek the reason for their inferiority first of all in the imperfect training they received in their youth.</p>
   <p>The youth of the poor has been and is still being badly reared. That is why so many transgressors have come from the ranks of the poor. But this is not the <pb facs="5423970_1_1347.jpg" n="2"/>fault of the poor people, as the moralists claim. This wretched situation is inevitable under the circumstances.</p>
   <p>Poor people rear their children badly not from choice but from necessity. They can do no better because their living conditions--due to their poverty--will not let them.</p>
   <p>Oscar F. Nelson, factory inspector for Illinois, seeking the reason for the great number of crimes in Chicago, has come to the conclusion that the source of most crimes may be found in the small wages received by the workers. If the wages of the workers were higher, they would be able to make better homes for their families, and it would not be necessary for their children to seek enjoyment and room to play in the streets. If the workers were paid more, their children would not be forced to go into the factories; they would be able to finish school.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1348.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The majority of young criminals today, "declares Mr. Nelson," come from starving families whose heads are forced to put their children to work in order that they may have enough to live on."</p>
   <p>Child labor deprives youths of the opportunity to receive an education. Child labor deprives youths of the opportunity to play, and makes them unhappy and sullen. Child labor weakens the bodies of the youths and exposes them to the dangers of occupational diseases. This labor does not allow youths time to learn a trade, and, as a result, they remain common laborers all their lives. But worst of all is the fact that child labor makes the youths prey to all kinds of bad influences.</p>
   <p>"Child labor is almost always mechanical," says the factory inspector. "It requires no mental exercise. The children go home tired in body, but their minds are hungry for activity and amusement. The boys go to a stuffy poolroom, <pb facs="5423970_1_1349.jpg" n="4"/>the girls to a stuffy dance hall."</p>
   <p>It is in these and similar places that they encounter the pernicious influences which destroy their innocence.</p>
   <p>Clean, healthy places of amusement for boys and girls would noticeably lessen the number of youthful criminal and moral offenders. But their number would be reduced even more by the betterment of working conditions for adult workers. Then the adult workers would have no trouble in taking care of their families, and they would be able to rear their children properly.</p>
   <p>It has become apparent that the fight for the betterment of workers' living conditions is a fight to promote morality among men.</p>
   <p>Our priests condemn this fight and call it "destruction of morality" and "godlessness". On the contrary, the truth is that nothing destroys the morality of the <pb facs="5423970_1_1350.jpg" n="5"/>people as much as the conditions of worry and poverty under which poor people are living today. A priest who strives to retain these conditions is not only a hindrance to the well-being of the workers, but an enemy of morality as well.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
