<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-12-02">Dec. 2, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Some Do Not Understand Our News Items on the Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0339</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0339.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1910-12-02">Dec. 2, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">SOME DO NOT UNDERSTAND OUR NEWS ITEMS ON THE STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has become apparent that some of our readers have an erroneous conception of the news items given on the strike. We write one thing and the readers understand another.</p>
   <p>Here, for instance, in the last issue of Lietuva we announced, in our news items about the Chicago garment workers strike, what M.A. Strauss, a representative of Hart, Schaffner and Marx, had stated at a conference with the representatives of the Citizens Committee on the matter of the strike. Strauss said that his employers "cannot in any manner agree on a closed shop or a preferential shop," and he ended his statement with these words: "Many of those who had been striking are beginning to realize that they were demanding the impossible and are beginning to return to work. Another week will go by and only a small group of <pb facs="5423970_1_0340.jpg" n="2"/>strikers will remain."</p>
   <p>Those are the words of M.A. Strauss, a Hart, Schaffner and Marx representative. That was very clearly pointed out in the last number of the Lietuva. However, some of the strikers, reading that item, understood it to be the words of the Lietuva and became very angry with the Lietuva, saying that the Lietuva is on the side of Hart, Schaffner and Marx and not with the strikers.</p>
   <p>We are very sorry that the strikers so erroneously understood the news items given by us. We advise them to read the mentioned item once more; then they will understand that those words were not original and that they are not ours but M.A. Strauss'.</p>
   <p>The Lietuva has not and never did have anything in common with Hart, Schaffner and Marx or any other firm. The Lietuva fully sympathizes <pb facs="5423970_1_0341.jpg" n="3"/>with the strikers and desires that the workers win their fight. Our sympathies are especially inclined toward the strikers because many Lithuanian garment workers are participating in this strike. Why, then, would we have sympathy for the exploiting Jewish employers instead of for our own people, the wronged Lithuanians?</p>
   <p>Wishing to serve the strikers, we are publishing more news items about the strike. In those items we also mention what the employers or other people are planning, for it is obvious that the more the strikers know about the plans of the other side, so much the better will they be able to hold their own and win. We are only turning the strikers' attention to the fact that they should read better and should not mistake the opinions of some people for the opinions of others.</p>
   <p>The editors of the Lietuva are in full assent with the strikers and hope that their fight for improved conditions will be won as soon as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
