<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 46, 11-15, 1907.
<title level="a">The Special Meeting of "Zinycia"</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0488</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0488.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LIETUVA</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 46, 11-15, 1907.
<title level="a">THE SPECIAL MEETING OF "ZINYCIA"</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Zinycia",- The Temple by-laws gives power to its president to call the meeting of stockholders and directors every time when there will be an essential cause for the benefit of the organization. Therefore, I hereby announce to all the stockholders and directors, that the special meeting of the "Zinycia" organization will be held on Sunday, November 27, 1907, at 2:00 P.M. North-Western University Settlement Hall, corner Augusta and Noble Streets. All the stockholders and the directors are urged to come, if they care for the future success of "Zinycia".</p>
   <p>At this meeting to all the stockholders, the by-laws of the "Zinycia" will be distributed, printed in English and Lithuanian languages. In the same by-laws, the charter of the "Zinycia" is printed.</p>
   <p>I have learned from the lawyer of "Zinycia", that the attorney of the company, from whom we have bought the land, have agreed to make all the documents as our attorney requested. And I have hoped that at this special meeting the matter of buying the land will be completely finished. Many members have appealed to me with questions, will we sell the land, and on what basis?</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0489.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Therefore, at this meeting, we will decide and make a complete plan for the further activity.</p>
   <p>The third important affair, which the meeting must take into consideration, we ought to find out which members of this organization want to become full pledged stockholders, and on what stipulations the shares will be sold. As we joined to the "Zinycia" organization, and promised to buy shares for the amount of $100.00 but there were few who have fulfilled their pledges. Minority of the members have fulfilled their promise, while the majority are active with their tongues, but not by their deeds. Therefore, it is time to make a complete statement in our books, and to strike out those who did not fulfill their pledge. Therefore, those who are the supporters of the "Zinycia" project come to this meeting and convince yourself what great results the "Zinycia" organization has brought forth. Only two years have passed since the inception of this organization of"Zinycia", - the organization is completely established, has its own tract of land to start the Lithuanian colony.</p>
   <p>Who loves land, wants to have his own roof, who have tired of working in factories, mines and stock-yards, railroads and other dangerous places and have been slaves of the industrial masters, come to "Zinycia" and be free.</p>
   <p>J.J. Hertmanovicia, President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
