<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 5,
<date when="1907-02-01">Feb. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Two Projects</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 5,
<date when="1907-02-01">Feb. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">TWO PROJECTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last issue of Lietuva we published an article from Vienybe about two projects concerning the best way to enlighten and to uplift scientifically our Lithuanians in America.</p>
   <p>The author of the projects suggests the establishment of a Lithuanian university in America. This is possible by selling shares, by donations, etc.</p>
   <p>Building a university for Lithuanians in America sounds very good, but to raise the money necessary for such an undertaking is hardly possible. Suppose we could erect a building for our university. What about its upkeep, what about the teachers, the laboratory equipment?</p>
   <p>At the start Lithuanians will donate, but later they will stop doing so. We know that from our own experience. For anything new Lithuanians donate <pb facs="5423970_1_0091.jpg" n="2"/>freely, but when it gets old the donations are stopped and our countrymen look for some new projects.</p>
   <p>We are planning to build a university when we have no primary schools. True, we have primary schools in the parishes, but these schools are worthless, because the teachers do not know the Lithuanian language themselves.</p>
   <p>We ought to take into consideration the universities in Russia, Germany, or in any other country. These universities could not exist if they were not subsidized by the government. It is known that the fees of the students cover only one fourth of the expenses of the universities.</p>
   <p>It is not bad when the Lithuanian students attend the universities in foreign countries. American students attend the universities in France and Germany, yet they do not become Frenchmen or Germans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now in order to give education to Lithuanians it is much easier and cheaper to establish primary schools. We are denouncing the parish schools, yet we do not try to build better schools. If we, the liberals, would have better primary schools, the clergy, too, would improve the parish schools.</p>
   <p>Take for example the Aurora society. This society was organized with the purpose of helping the poor Lithuanian students. How many branches of this society have we in America? Only three. At first, here and there the Lithuanians collected a few dollars for the Lithuanian students' fund; now no more donations are coming. The money is raised from the members' monthly dues. How can we establish a university when such an important organization as the Aurora society barely exists?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
