<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-03-22">Mar. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanians to Participate in Selling Liberty Bonds</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1147</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1147.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-03-22">Mar. 22, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIANS TO PARTICIPATE IN SELLING LIBERTY BONDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Advertisement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sale of the third issue of Liberty bonds will begin on April 6, 1918. Lithuanians will also participate officially in the selling of these bonds. The government has appointed Joseph J. Elias, president of the Universal State Bank, and John I. Bagdziunas, treasurer of the same bank, to represent the Lithuanians in the Seventh Federal Reserve District, which is composed of five states: Illinois, Wisconsin, Iowa, Indiana, and Michigan. These two representatives are fully authorized to appoint commissions and committees to sell Liberty bonds in the counties and cities of each of these states.</p>
   <p>Though the Lithuanians have already purchased many Liberty bonds, people of other nationalities received the credit because the bonds were purchased through the committees and organizations of other nationalities. Now the Lithuanians have the opportunity to show their patriotism by helping <pb facs="5423970_1_1148.jpg" n="2"/>this country when help is needed most. Therefore, Lithuanians, become active! Organize Lithuanian Liberty bond committees in every town of the above-mentioned states and make arrangements to buy Liberty bonds! Our own welfare here and the freedom of Lithuania, our motherland, depend on the outcome of the war this country is waging. Therefore, honored Lithuanians, let us buy as many Liberty bonds as we can and let us urge others to do so. By buying Liberty bonds you will not only protect your welfare and your property and the freedom of this country; you will also help to create an independent Lithuania, since Uncle Sam will be the best intercessor for the Lithuanians. Other nationalities are using all their energies in this matter; therefore we Lithuanians must not lag behind, but must be outstanding in our activity and patriotism. Since subscriptions to the third issue of Liberty bonds will be accepted during two weeks only, the organizational work must be begun immediately.</p>
   <p>Lithuanians who are interested in participating in this work are requested to seek more detailed information from the government-appointed Lithuanian agents at the following address: Lithuanian Liberty Loan Campaign Committee: Joseph <pb facs="5423970_1_1149.jpg" n="3"/>J. Elias, Chairman; John I. Bagdziunas, Executive Secretary, 3252 South Halsted Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
