<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 15,
<date when="1906-04-13">April 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Little Rain from a Big Cloud</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XV, No. 15,
<date when="1906-04-13">April 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">LITTLE RAIN FROM A BIG CLOUD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This saying can be applied to the Zinycia (The Temple) convention that was held on April 8, 1906. J. J. Hertmanowich proudly stated in No. 3 of Lietuva that the new Zinycia organization in Chicago, in the three months of its existence got more members than any other society. He said that they have three branches with 400 members, while branch 36 of the Lithuanian Alliance of America has only 151 members, even though this branch has existed for many years.</p>
   <p>The convention was called at 1 P. M. I arrived at 1:15 P. M. and was surprised to find not one member of Zinycia at the so-called convention. The session was opened at 2:30 P. M. At the session there were 20-22 people including the administration.</p>
   <p>The chairman, J. J. Hertmanowich stated that they had 40 members in their organization. Previous to this "grand convention" he boasted that their organization had over 400 members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0493.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I will not repeat here what worthless discussions they had at the convention, but I will mention their "scientific" plan of colonization.</p>
   <p>Every member must pay $1.50 for initiation. When they get 1000 members every member must buy a share for $100. They will buy a tract of land at one dollar per acre. On it they will build a city, factories, houses, etc. They will ask the railroad company to extend the railroad to the city. Then the price of the land, from one dollar, will rise up to $100 per acre. This is how the Lithuanians will become rich. The question was asked, "what about the educational part that you have boasted so much about? The answer was, "if some one cares he can read books, etc."</p>
   <p>The question was brought up, can they sell land to strangers? The answer was yes, because selling land to stranger will bring profit to Lithuanians, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0494.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Geschaeft ist Geschaeft!</p>
   <p>So the convention was a failure. The "scientific" organization of Zinycia is a common, ordinary scheme to exploit Lithuanians, etc.</p>
   <p>John Ilgandas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
