<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-13">Jan. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Unemployment Insurance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1359</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1359.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-13">Jan. 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Insurance serves a very useful purpose in the life of the people. It assists individuals to bear various misfortunes of life.</p>
   <p>Fire can destroy a farmer's home or barn; a storm at sea can sink a trader's ship with all its cargo; a misfortune can take away the health or life of the head of a family and make orphans out of his children. In that manner a farmer or a merchant can instantaneously become a pauper; orphaned children can be left without a bite of bread.</p>
   <p>These and similar circumstances illustrate the great need for insurance. when a heavy burden suddenly falls upon the back of one man it is lessened considerably by the collective assistance of other members of the insurance company. It is much easier to combat misfortune with united forces.</p>
   <p>That very same principle of insurance should be applied to unemployed workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1360.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Unemployment is also a misfortune. It is one of those misfortunes which torture the masses frequently and with great severity. Honest and intelligent people no longer believe that the army of unemployed consists only of lazy and degenerate workers. We notice everywhere that the whip of unemployment lashes also the most eager and most industrious workers. Employment does not depend on a worker's ability any more than does fire, sickness or death. No worker is free from the danger of unemployment. Therefore, all workers should be interested in a movement to secure them against unemployment.</p>
   <p>We cannot abolish unemployment under the present social order, because this social order itself is the direct cause of unemployment. However, the dire consequences of unemployment can be lessened considerably by various means, but especially by unemployment insurance.</p>
   <p>Unemployment insurance can be set up practically on the same basis as other forms of insurance: 1) co-operative basis--where full control of unemployment insurance is in the hands of the insured; 2) capitalistic basis--where unemployment insurance is conducted on a basis of profit; 3) Governmental <pb facs="5423970_1_1361.jpg" n="3"/>basis--where unemployment insurance is conducted and controlled by the Government.</p>
   <p>This last system of insurance is the most convenient under present conditions. The Government has more capital than can be raised by workers' co-operative societies; the Government can organize and conduct such matters more practically and more honestly than a capitalistic company. It is even doubtful if capitalists could be interested in such a humanitarian project! They would be more interested in the profit angle than in the welfare of the workers.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, it is a duty of the state to protect the workers from the ravages of unemployment. Today the state represents the public, and the public is indebted to the workers for all the riches it possesses and controls. Therefore, the public is under obligations to protect the producers of wealth from the misery of unemployment, over which the workers have no control.</p>
   <p>Thus far the United States Government has done nothing at all in this field. Even the Wilson Administration, in spite of the fact that it is endorsed by <pb facs="5423970_1_1362.jpg" n="4"/>the largest American labor unions, is not contemplating any action on the matter. With dreadful unemployment raging all over the American continent, the Administration is "fighting" it with prophecies of "better times" and still greater prosperity in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
