<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-12-18">Dec. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Progress of Temperance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0237</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0237.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-12-18">Dec. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROGRESS OF TEMPERANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In last week's Draugas the executive committee of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Total Temperance Society directed a special appeal to the pastors of Lithuanian parishes, requesting that at future parish entertainments, which usually draw large crowds of parishioners, the serving of intoxicating beverages be eliminated. In its appeal the committee pointed out that parish entertainments which also include the sale of intoxicants not only give another opportunity to confirmed drunkards to get drunk, but also encourage moderate drinkers to drink more and "even those who do not drink at all learn to tipple at such parties."</p>
   <p>This appeal, if those to whom it is directed will heed it, will immediately push the temperance cause forward. This step by the Lithuanian-American Catholic abstainers must be regarded as one of the most practical weapons in the fight against drunkenness which is so widespread among the Lithuanians <pb facs="5423970_1_0238.jpg" n="2"/>in America. It is hoped the appeal will prove successful.</p>
   <p>A second step toward temperance among the Lithuanians of America is the removal of the societies from the saloons.</p>
   <p>At present the majority of Lithuanian societies, regardless of their tendencies, hold meetings in saloon halls. The saloonkeepers willingly permit the societies to hold their meetings in these halls, making no rental charge for them. Of course, the rent for the hall is paid, with interest, by the members of the societies who congregate in the saloon itself. The meeting hall and the bar so beautifully divide up the members of the society that it is, at times, really difficult to guess where the real meeting of the society is being held: in the hall or at the bar. A committee member is called for in the meeting. He is not there. "Go get him. He's at the bar." This is a common occurence among our societies. The initiation of a new member or the completion of an important task by the society can seldom get along without a "sprinkling" at the bar.</p>
   <p>Therefore, if the parish entertainments are propagators of drunkenness, the <pb facs="5423970_1_0239.jpg" n="3"/>meetings of societies in saloons are no less guilty of hampering temperance. Here also those who drink little or not at all are becoming accustomed to drinking.</p>
   <p>But how can we find an escape from this? In the majority of localities the saloon halls are the sole places available for society meetings. The majority of societies are so situated financially that they cannot afford to hire a special hall.</p>
   <p>One solution to this situation is the union of several societies, which could then afford to hire a suitable hall. Such a hall, kept up by several societies, could serve as a meeting place for the societies and as headquarters for other Lithuanian public matters of the locality. It would not be difficult to set up a public library and reading room in such a place. We are speaking here of "peoples' buildings" which we commonly call "national buildings". There are several of them in existence among the Lithuanian-Americans today.</p>
   <p>In certain localities in our larger towns, there are small public parks <pb facs="5423970_1_0240.jpg" n="4"/>which societies can usually use without charge (Chicago, for example). Lithuanian societies could use the halls of these parks.</p>
   <p>In the smaller colonies, where only one or two small societies exist, the meetings could be held in private homes. One can always find a Lithuanian willing to offer a room for this purpose from time to time.</p>
   <p>The removal of societies from saloons is one of the truly necessary and important tasks confronting the Lithuanian public. An effort made for this purpose is an effort made toward real progress, toward the cultural development of the Lithuanians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
