<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1906-03-23">Mar. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Is it Not Time to Awaken?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1906-03-23">Mar. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">IS IT NOT TIME TO AWAKEN?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When we observe only superficially the life of the Lithuanian colony in America, we overlook the most essential things. Many of the manifestations of this life of ours are very bad, as, for instance, the altercations arising in our Lithuanian parishes. Have we no more important work to do than the establishing of parishes and the building of churches which only help make our life more miserable? Civilized nations care but little about the building [of churches, which] give no benefit but misery to us. Civilized nations don't care about the building of churches; they care about economic improvements. We Lithuanians should do likewise in order to improve our living conditions.</p>
   <p>Look at our compatriots in Chicago, for instance. We are over 30,000 Lithuanians here but have nothing we could be proud of. We have over fifty national and religious societies, some of which arrange celebrations, anniversaries and banquets. From such activities, however, we derive but little <pb facs="5423970_1_0619.jpg" n="2"/>benefit. Most of the benefit goes to non-Lithuanian breweries and hall owners--complete strangers to us.</p>
   <p>We have built a great multitude of churches and are preparing to build new ones. What benefit do we derive from all this? We are giving thousands of dollars for the churches, but of what benefit is it to our nation and to the Lithuanian public? Yes, the benefit goes to the clergy and the bishops. Look at the massacre committed by the priest at the Lithuanian church, Providence of God, 18th Street and Union Avenue. And this is not an isolated case either. A similar occurrence was reported not long ago from a Lithuanian Church in Philadelphia, Pa. Do you think that the money and the bloodshed go to the glory of God? No. It was of benefit to the priests, bishops, police captains, lawyers, and judges. In spite of this we cry at cur meetings for unity--but where is our unity?</p>
   <p>It is high time for us to become conscious and lay a firm foundation to our unity. The time is ripe when we should lock lack to our fruitless accomplishments.</p>
   <p>What is it that is most essential to us? The schools, of course, because we see that the Lithuanian youth is denationalizing rapidly. The parish school teaches <pb facs="5423970_1_0620.jpg" n="3"/>nothing good. We need asylums. We have many old people who cannot work anymore. We need halls where we can hold meetings to discuss various problems of importance. We need cooperative stores or else keep on making the Jews rich, as we have done up to now. In short, we have many important affairs to be taken care of. In Chicago there are many Lithuanians and we must take a different mode of action from the one we took before.</p>
   <p>As a common man, I am appealing to all the national and church societies, as well as to the Lithuanians individually, to start action for the benefit of our national cause.</p>
   <p>At present a project has been proposed to establish a cooperative store on the corner of 33rd and Halsted Streets. No doubt this will be a great benefit, as a few of our compatriots will get positions.</p>
   <p>I am calling our brothers to action!</p>
   <p>Frank Eismontas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
