<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-11-07">Nov. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">"Miraculous" Advertisements</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-11-07">Nov. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">"MIRACULOUS" ADVERTISEMENTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The so-called "miraculous" advertisements by some doctors in our newspapers, are not a new problem of our press. They have been discussed many times in our newspapers. Several weeks ago, we discussed this same matter at the convention of newspaper men in Shenandoah, Pennsylvania. Up to the present time though, we have not found a way to abolish this sore from our newspapers. The Lithuanian press has been too weak to fight against this evil, which is widely spread not only throughout the press of other national groups, but throughout the powerful American press too.</p>
   <p>Today, when one of the greatest American newspapers, the Chicago Daily Tribune, has started to fight against "miraculous" advertisements, and has brought to light many merciless exploitations, we believe the time has come when the Lithuanian newspapers must join the powerful American press to fight this evil.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1517.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Therefore, the first decision of the corporation of this newspaper, Lietuva, was to abolish all "miraculous doctors'" advertisements, and with this issue we have ceased publishing the fraudulent advertisements.</p>
   <p>Even though the editor of this newspaper, according to the ethics of newspapermen, never assumed responsibility for such advertisements published in this newspaper; even though many times we published articles and cartoons, criticizing various advertisements for the benefit of our readers; we think the time has come to clean up the garden of our newspaper, to root out the monkshood from the flowers--of course, within the power of the newspaper. We believe other Lithuanian newspapers will take this problem under consideration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
