<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 36,
<date when="1903-09-04">Sept. 4, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">The Americans about Lithuanians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0622</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0622.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XI, No. 36,
<date when="1903-09-04">Sept. 4, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICANS ABOUT LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the largest daily newspapers, the Chicago Record-Herald, for some time, in its Sunday issues, has been writing about the different nationalities in Chicago. Every Sunday issue contains one article about one nation. In last Sunday's issue it published about the Lithuanians, their pictures, etc. It seems that the American writers do not care much about the truth of their writings. They are making no effort to get acquainted with the subject they are writing about. Such writing is sometimes absurd.</p>
   <p>The same author, not long ago, wrote that the Lithuanians were the most ignorant people; that they still are worshipers of the holy oaks. But now the same writer states that the Lithuanians are not idol worshipers, but are highly cultured, civilized, with high ideals, with their soul and body devoted to their Fatherland, which is under the severe oppression and persecution of the Russian government. Now he wrote about the Lithuanians from the best point of view. We are sorry that the writer has gone too far. From the author's article we found out that every Lithuanian in <pb facs="5423970_1_0623.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago pays $1.50 to the National Lithuanian Society, which keeps the orphans and poor Lithuanian children.</p>
   <p>Even the least enlightened Lithuanian knows the writings of John Stuart Mills, Jeremy Bentham, Sir Henry Maine, etc. During their leisure time, the Lithuanians are reading scientific books, attending museums, the public libraries, the art institute, etc.</p>
   <p>We are not astonished that when the author praised the Lithuanians so highly he did not want to go to the other side, where the Lithuanians are spending their money and health in the saloons; where they spend their time for learning cards, playing pool, etc., because this would be too big a contrast. This is the crossroad where the Lithuanians are stopped from the cultural and the intellectual way. We do not ask undeserved praise, but we do ask the truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
