<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1892-12-31">Dec. 31, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A Few Words to Lithuanian Brothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1892-12-31">Dec. 31, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A FEW WORDS TO LITHUANIAN BROTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, the Lithuanians of Chicago are awakening from slumber, are looking into the bright future. Brothers, let us go forward in this free land of America.</p>
   <p>A man, through education, by reading good books and newspapers, enlightens himself, acknowledges the real God, upholds the orders of church and the duties of his class. A man who does not read good books and newspapers is like a black night without light. A man without any enlightenment is dangerous to himself and to others. What does such a man do when he does not read books nor papers, when he comes home from work? He goes to a saloon! Then, when you ask him to buy a book or subscribe to a paper, he says that he has no money. Brother Lithuanians, let us consider how much money we are spending on Saturday night in saloons! If we ant to show to others that we are people of one nation, we must show to other nations that we are an enlightened people, and not half wild. We can obtain education by reading good books and papers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0268.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Therefore, brothers, I appeal to you once more, let us awaken from darkness, we must love education and co-operate among ourselves. Let us begin this coming New Year with new hope; let us drop the old costumes of drinking and card playing; let us begin the New Year by reading good books; let us begin a new life after New Year. A lover of the mother country makes this appeal.</p>
   <p>Dychawicze.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
