<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-08-06">Aug. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Temperance Is Increasing Among Our People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0221</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0221.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-08-06">Aug. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TEMPERANCE IS INCREASING AMONG OUR PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is hardly another nationality in which drinking is so prevalent as it is among the Lithuanians. But we must recognize that during the past few years temperance has been steadily increasing among our people. A marked increase in temperance has been noted especially among our younger generation. Decreasing crowds in salcons, large number of deficits that result at socials and picnics where intoxicating drinks are sold, and an increasing number of saloon bankruptcies testify to the fact that the days of the reign of Bacchus among our people are numbered.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanian press is responsible to a large extent for the decrease in drinking among our people. Although to date the Lithuanians did not have even a single publication devoted to the temperance cause, nevertheless, our newspapers did not fail to attack the drink evil.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0222.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now it is planned to place before the Lithuanian-American public a permanent soldier, whose duty will be to fight unceasingly against intemperance, that greatest enemy of human welfare. A periodical devoted entirely to the promotion of temperance among our people has been established. The first number of that periodical has already appeared.</p>
   <p>The name of the publication is Tautos Rytas (The Future of Our Nationality). In its message to the readers the Tautos Rytas says, in part:</p>
   <p>"Our great patriots have devoted and are devoting their health, much effort, and personal wealth to prepare a better future for Lithuania and to place their fatherland on a level with the free and highly cultured nations of the world. However, during the pursuit of their lofty labors, our honorable leaders have been confronted and are still confronted with a great domestic enemy. That enemy is the inclination of Lithuanians to drink. Many lofty projects have perished merely because our people, being under the influence of alcohol, were <pb facs="5423970_1_0223.jpg" n="3"/>unable to understand the great value of the projects."</p>
   <p>The initial number of the Tautos Rytas has a variety of features. Besides a number of general articles, it contains an interesting historical article entitled "The Temperance Movement". The editor is Reverend J. J. Jakaitis, of Worcester, Massachusetts.</p>
   <p>The periodical will only be continued provided its necessity is recognized and funds for its publication are appropriated by the coming convention of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Total-Abstinence Alliance, which has many branches in Chicago and other parts of the United States. The convention is scheduled to take place on September 10, at Minersville, Pennsylvania. This convention will mark the fifth anniversary of the Alliance.</p>
   <p>There is an interesting news item in the Tautos Rytas, stating that the late Reverend J. Zebris, former pastor of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Church in <pb facs="5423970_1_0224.jpg" n="4"/>New Britain, Connecticut, was the organizer of the first Lithuanian anti-alcohol society in America fifteen years ago. Readers will recall that Reverend Zebris met his death a few weeks ago at the hands of two Lithuanian murderers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
