<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-19">May 19, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Socials in Saloon Halls</title><title level="a" type="sub">by the Son of Agatha</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0213</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0213.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-19">May 19, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIALS IN SALOON HALLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by The Son of Agatha</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is no shortage of news in our community, the Brighton Park district of Chicago. On Saturdays, about 7 P. M.. musicians may be seen on their way to one of the saloon halls where some Lithuanian church society or saloonkeeper is sponsoring a dance or other form of social entertainment. As soon as the Lenten season is over, all the church societies go into the saloon halls for entertainment like flies go for honey.</p>
   <p>Even the St. Casimir Guardsmen who, like angels, guard the body of Christ in church during Easter, go into the saloon halls and sponsor dances etc. Their entertainment affairs differ in many respects from the socials that are sponsored by other societies. The Guardsmen come dressed in their society uniforms and bring along all their cannon and ammunition. They rent the bar in the saloon and wait for people to arrive. Business at the bar is good, there is no <pb facs="5423970_1_0214.jpg" n="2"/>shortage of ammunition. In the dance hall, the girls are unwilling to dance with anyone except the Guardsmen who are dressed in brilliant military uniforms and have swords dangling at their sides. Furthermore, the parish priest placed his stamp of approval upon the Guardsmen and praised them for their work of guarding Christ in the church during Easter.</p>
   <p>Another church society, known as the Immaculate Conception Society, also sponsors dances and socials in saloon halls. Besides the local church societies, some societies from other districts occassionally come to this district to sponsor entertainments in saloon halls.</p>
   <p>Although these entertainments are sponsored by church groups the behavior of the people in these halls is shocking, nothing but a demoralization of our youth, when these affairs are held, about fifty young men stand at the door and wait to be admitted free of charge. It is embarrasing to admit that our young people are interested in nothing but saloon socials.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0215.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us drop all saloon hall entertainments and gambling. Let us devote our time to more lofty pursuits. Let us learn to sing, go to lectures, mass meetings, etc. By doing so we will improve ourselves and aid others to do so. There are some moral young people in this district, but very few.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
