<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanians Have Two Days at Tuberculosis Exnibit</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1511</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1511.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIANS HAVE TWO DAYS AT TUBERCULOSIS EXNIBIT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A committee of twenty prominent Chicago Lithuanians, headed by Dr. A. Zimontas, successfully took charge of the two Lithuanian days, January 21 and 22, at the anti-tuberculosis exhibit, which was sponsored by the Chicago Tuberculosis Institute from January 15 to 29, at the Mark White Square field house, 29th and South Halsted Streets.</p>
   <p>During the afternoon of the first Lithuanian day, about 1,200 children from the Armour Public School attended. The principal of the school was in charge of the program for the children. The children sang three songs. Dr. Jonikaitis and Dr. Zimontas delivered lectures. Since the children who attended were composed of many different nationalities, and in order to avoid misunderstandings and bad feeling, the speakers spoke in the American language.</p>
   <p>The program during the evening of the first Lithuanian day was for adults. About one thousand people attended. The speakers were Dr. Juska and Dr. K. Drangelis. The audience was entertained with music by the St. George's (Lithuanian) <pb facs="5423970_1_1512.jpg" n="2"/>parish choir. Mr. F. Jakutis (a well-known Chicago Lithuanian tenor), and Mr. Sarnaliust, violinist, also entertained. Mr. Petraitis was in charge of the program.</p>
   <p>About three hundred pupils from St. George's (Lithuanian) parochial school attended the exhibit during the afternoon of the second Lithuanian day. The children sang two songs, one Lithuanian and the other American, and also "Lietuva Tevyne Musu" (Lithuanan Our Fatherland)--the Lithuanian national anthem. Lectures were delivered by Dr. Drangelis and Mr. A. L. Graiciunas. The nuns, who came to the exhibit with their pupils, were very active in showing and explaining the various features of the exhibit. Dr. Zimontas was in charge of the program.</p>
   <p>The program during the evening of the second Lithuanian day was for adult Lithuanians. About one thousand Lithuanians attended. Dr. Kulis, Dr. Zimontas, and Dr. Drangelis delivered lectures. Entertainment for the evening was furnished by the Diruta chorus, Aathony Pocius, and One Pocius. Attorney F. P. Bradchulis was in charge of the program.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1513.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Both Lithuanian days were in all respects very successful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
