<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 20,
<date when="1905-05-19">May 19, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Buy Farms at the Lithuanian Colony Valynius, Ripley County, Missouri</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 20,
<date when="1905-05-19">May 19, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">BUY FARMS AT THE LITHUANIAN COLONY VALYNIUS, RIPLEY COUNTY, MISSOURI</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Do not put your hard-earned dollars in the banks. The banks are unsafe, are closing, or dishonest bank officials will steal your money.</p>
   <p>Land is the best investment for your money. Thieves will not rob you of it. Fire will not burn it. Water will not wash it away. Land always will supply you food and give you safety for the future.</p>
   <p>If you wish to avoid strikes and unemployment, which are common this year, settle on a farm where you will have enough food and your future well-being is guaranteed.</p>
   <p>We have thousands of acres of good and productive soil for industrious Lithuanian farmers, workers and tradesmen. If you wish to live on farms where the climate is healthy and agreeable, where the winters <pb facs="5423970_1_0517.jpg" n="2"/>are short and mild, while summer is long and the climate medium; where the dark gray clay land has a sufficient supply of water to raise crops and hay; where vegetables grow fast and bring good prices; where the water is clean and healthy; where there is lumber in abundance, there fore cheap for building houses; where the railroads are going through, assuring the transportation for farm products; where the farmers, on account of light winters, can work on the farms through the winter months; if you want all these advantages go to the Lithuanian colony Valynius. In the northern or eastern part of this country the farmers cannot make such profitable living as they can make here. Quit the dangerous factories and the deceitful mines and establish yourself and your family on a farm. Own your roof and farm.</p>
   <p>Do not wait too long. Buy now that the land is cheap and you can choose better land. Our land is just 6-hour ride from a large city, St. Louis, No. Four miles from the town of Doniphan and eight miles from Poplar Bluff.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0518.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are selling choice land from eight to twelve dollars an acre, on easy payments. All the documents for the buyer are made free. We refund the railroad expenses to the buyers of farms.</p>
   <p>We have excursions to our farms every first and third Tuesday of each month. The railroad tickets are cheap. Convince yourself by seeing the farms as others have done before they bought. For further information and for maps, write to the Lithuanian Colonization Company, Charles Peters, General Agent, or K. Zychinski, Manager, 217-220 Manhattan Bldg., 315 Dearborn St., Chicago. Mr. Vaicaitis is the Lithuanian representative.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
