<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Association of Lithuanian Doctors of America</title>, <date when="1937">1937</date>, in possession of Secretary, Association of Lithuanian Doctors of America, Chicago, Ill.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the Association of Lithuanian Doctors of America</title>, <date when="1937">1937</date>, in possession of Secretary, Association of Lithuanian Doctors of America, Chicago, Ill.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To this organization belong the doctors of medicine and dentistry. This society was organized in June 9, 1912.</p>
   <p>Twenty-five years ago some of the Lithuanian doctors of Chicago saw that the people who were forced to flee from their despotic countries in Europe, and seek refuge in free America were unable to speak the English language and became victims of medical quacks. There existed among the foreigners many medical quack institutions under the names of various specialists. They said that they could miraculously cure any disease, thus they exploited the foreign workers.</p>
   <p>Individually the Lithuanian doctors were unable to fight against the charalatans; so they decided to organize the Association of Lithuanian Doctors of America. This was done in order to protect the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1521.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the Association of Lithuanian Doctors of America was established the members of this society started to write articles to the Lithuanian newspapers on medical and dental science. At the same time they devoted their efforts to explaining and to bring "to light the fraudulent practices of medical charlatans."</p>
   <p>Later on, the Association of Lithuanian Doctors of America published a monthly magazine "Gydytojas" (The Physician) from 1921 to 1925. The magazine was devoted to the popularization of medical and dental science and the various disease. Twice the organization has arranged a "Week of Health." During these two weeks the physicians and the dentists read essays on the question of health.</p>
   <p>During the World's Fair in Chicago the healthiest Lithuanian children were selected. For a few days the Lithuanian doctors of this organization examined without any charge many Lithuanian children, and instructed their parents in the methods of rearing healthy children.</p>
   <p>When the publication of the journal "Gydytojas" (The Physician) was stopped, the <pb facs="5423970_1_1522.jpg" n="3"/>Society's doctors started to write regularly to the Lithuanian newspapers. The health section in the newspaper is taken care of by the doctors' committee. The committee sees to it that the articles on health be scientific and ethical. The members of this association delivered hundreds of lectures and read hundreds of essays on health problems at the meetings of various organizations of Chicago and other cities. This organization gave financial aid to such a progressive movement as to Darius-Girenes and Vaitkus transatlantic flight. At the beginning of the organization of the government in Lithuania the doctors' association donated $450.00 for the establishment of higher educational courses. Now it is known that these higher courses gave the start to the university of Lithuania. For many years the doctors' association supported the Birutes Choir and other artistic enterprises.</p>
   <p>This Association of Doctors in 1919 organized a society to help Lithuania. It has raised over $100,000.00 for the people in Lithuania who have suffered during the World's War.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1523.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In 1935 a few Catholic doctors left this society and founded a Catholic organization of their own. Only a few of them left the former organization, so their newly organized society soon dispersed and some of these doctors came back to the old organization.</p>
   <p>Officials:</p>
   <p>Dr. M. Strikolis, president, 3645 S. Ashland Ave.</p>
   <p>Dr. K. Dranselis, vice-president, 2403 W. 63rd St.</p>
   <p>Dr. J. Simkus, secretary, 1821 S. Halsted St.</p>
   <p>Dr. J. Kowar, treasurer, 2359 S. Leavitt St.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
