<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-03-09">Mar. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Lithuanian Garment Workers 'Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0350</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0350.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-03-09">Mar. 9, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">LITHUANIAN GARMENT WORKERS 'UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian local, No. 269, of the Amalgamated Garment Workers of America, will hold a meeting, March 12, at the Amalgamated hall, on Robey Street and North Avenue. All Lithuanians who are members of this union are requested to attend the meeting because many important questions will be discussed. A delegate to the coning National convention of the union will be elected at the meeting. The new contract of the union with employers will be considered.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0351.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All Lithuanian garment workers must bear in mind that we can make progress and win our demands only by taking an active part in the affairs of our union. We have learned from bitter experience that we cannot make progress not win demands when we leave all the affairs of the union in the hands of our leaders. It is very essential for the rank and file to control the reins of our union. That can be realized only when all members attend union meetings regularly and take an active part in all the activities.</p>
   <p>Employers always take full advantage of every opportunity to exploit the workers. Very often our union leaders either do not notice the exploitation or they pretend <pb facs="5423970_1_0352.jpg" n="3"/>not to notice it. This great evil can be abolished if all members of the union attend meetings regularly. In so doing, they will know exactly what is going on in the union. They will then be in a good position to present all their grievances and demands, and force their leaders to carry out the will of the rank and file.</p>
   <p>Under the capitalistic social order, a labor union is the most effective means for gaining a higher standard of living, better working conditions, and for combating persecution of workers by employers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
