<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 13,
<date when="1907-03-29">3-29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Before the Election!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LIETUVA</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 13,
<date when="1907-03-29">3-29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">BEFORE THE ELECTION!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The time is very close when the workers of America, especially the Lithuanian citizens of Chicago, will give their votes for election of officials. For this reason I want to have a little talk with the citizens about selling their votes. The sellers of their votes, I call scabs. I name such people scabs, because not knowing the situation, they say: "Citizens, vote for the republican candidate! Just look at him, what a prudent man he is. Have mercy, vote!... Then he will do much good, or he may arrange for you to get a city job, now go over there and you will get a glass of free beer!"....</p>
   <p>This unfortunate patient, the narrow-minded citizen, begs to vote for such a candidate and after the election the elected candidate will sit on his neck. He is a capitalistic government servant, he always will do what the government tells him to do. In the event of a strike, the police will be placed around the factory. Then you will denounce the scab and you will call yourself a scab. Why?</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let us look! I will prove to you that by voting for a republican or democratic candidate you make yourself a scab. As a rule you call the man a scab who, when you go on strike takes your place in the factory. The scabs are protected by the police. The policemen are scabs, the captain who gives orders to the police he is a scab, the mayor gives orders to the captain he is a scab, the mayor gets the orders from higher officials they are also scabs, they get the order from the president he also is a scab. And when you sell your ballot for the above mentioned masters you are a scab yourself.</p>
   <p>Worker citizen, remember the word "scab"! Do not become a scab yourself, on this problem make decision with your own mind and say that you will never be a scab!</p>
   <p>There is a party the worker's party, it is the socialist party. For this party you as a worker must vote. This party gives you liberty. In this party are people who are devoting their lives to win liberty for the oppressed and exploited people. Worker! you have a weapon, the ballot is in your hands, yet you do not <pb facs="5423970_1_1060.jpg" n="3"/>know how to use it you are selling your vote and then you suffer. Be conscious! Vote for the socialist party candidate. Do not be degenerate, do not sell yourself.</p>
   <p>By A. Zimontas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
