<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-03-13">Mar. 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Pullman Car Washers on Strike</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-03-13">Mar. 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">PULLMAN CAR WASHERS ON STRIKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About 850 employees of the Pullman Company are on strike. They are men and women of various nationalities, and include Poles, Lithuanians, Jews, Slovaks, Germans, Czechs, and others.</p>
   <p>Last Tuesday the workers presented to the Company a demand that wages be raised to twenty-one cents an hour; that every second Sunday be a paid holiday for the workers; and that full wages be paid for overtime. The bosses informed the workers that they would not agree to these demands. The workers left their jobs on Friday, March 10.</p>
   <p>On Saturday, March 11, the workers sent their representatives to the office of the Company. One of the bosses, Volter, told the representatives that the Company's board of directors would not meet before Monday, March 13, and that the workers would receive the Company's answer on that date.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0423.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the causes of the strike was the unscrupulous behavior of some of the superiors, the so-called foremen. They would accept bribes of twenty-five or thirty dollars, or even more, from new workers. If occasionally a person received a job without paying a foreman, this person did not remain happy long, for the foremen put such people to work at the worst kind of jobs. Not only the foremen, but the forewomen and supervisors in charge of the girls acted in this manner.</p>
   <p>There were other dirty practices by the bosses. For example, two people are usually assigned to one machine, but if you did not tip the foreman, you would be assigned alone to a machine. The unscrupulousness [of the foremen] reached such a height that some of the bosses used the workers to perform their household duties. In other words, workers were forced to wash floors in the foremen's homes, and even paid tailors to press their foremen's clothes.</p>
   <p>The foremen exploited the workers in still another way. They forced the car washers to help the electricians, and at this work the car washers suffered losses through damage to their clothing. Because of this, the workers added one more <pb facs="5423970_1_0424.jpg" n="3"/>demand to those mentioned above--that each worker work only at the job to which he is assigned.</p>
   <p>The strikers' committee is composed of representatives from each of the Company's yards, and includes men and women. The leader of the strike is Joseph Zajonc (a Pole). [Names of members of strikers' committee omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>It is apparent that the unity among the strikers is strong. If they will persevere in the future as they have persevered in the past, victory will be theirs. Long live the unity of the workers! In unity lies their strength!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
