<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-01-12">Jan. 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Women and Enlightenment</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1912-01-12">Jan. 12, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN AND ENLIGHTENMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The enlightenment of women is looked upon among us as some special kind of understanding. Men especially like to write that only those women are enlightened who attend lectures or are interested in political problems. When one newspaper printed items about domestic things, many complained that the home was too lowly a subject for women to bother about, that ideals should be written about instead. What a misunderstanding of ideals!</p>
   <p>Political rights for women will come in their own way, for that is being forced by women's participation in industry. And the more they are pushed into factories, the more necessary it is for them to acquire rights which they will undoubtedly receive.</p>
   <p>But the question of enlightenment is more important than political truths. With Lithuanian women the fundamental concern for enlightenment should be the improvement of character and spirit. That is more important than all kinds of "consciousness," for it composes life itself. Just as man, so <pb facs="5423970_1_1419.jpg" n="2"/>will woman--virtuous, energetic, intelligent, guided by a sound mind--learn to understand things. Having that understanding, she will receive all the rights of life. Our women need that understanding first of all. It is necessary to nurture character and courage in them, for in them lies the enlightenment of women.</p>
   <p>Just as one grain added to another eventually makes a pile of grain, so the study and improvement of each small incident of life makes for the understanding of life and controls the manner of making life. Articles which urge women to wake out of lethargic sleep and have consciousness will help very little. It is necessary first of all to improve the personal concern of life, starting with cooking, sewing, washing, conduct, rearing children; then to go to the more important things: family life, virtue, and other concerns of life. Those are the things that create a woman's life and each one of them should be very clearly understood by every woman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1420.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The recognition of these facts, followed by perfecting them; the understanding of other women, and the recognition of women's duties will be their real enlightenment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
