<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 22, 5-31, <date when="1907">1907</date>.
<title level="a">To the Honorable Lithuanian Sisters</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LIETUVA</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 22, 5-31, <date when="1907">1907</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE HONORABLE LITHUANIAN SISTERS</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One feels uneasy when remembering the hardship of our sisters. Our sisters do not know why they are carrying the hardship on their shoulders. The misery, the misfortune, the hardship, our sisters say its God's will, it is God's way. Let us do away with this idea that hardship is God's will. God has nothing to do with our misfortunes. Let us leave God for a while for the clergy and nuns, and start to think why we are ignorant and poor. Our sisters say that education is a detriment to the people, that education brings immorality and infidelity. Such a statement is wrong. Among the ignorant and uneducated people, are more drunkenness, fights and immorality than among the educated. And yet all this misfortune, misery the people say is the will of God, so we cannot help it. Such a baseless and wrong thought has been propagated among us by the spiritual leaders for years in the past.</p>
   <p>Now the question arises, how to get rid of this illusion, that the miserable life of the poor is God's will? We, Lithuanian sisters must read progressive newspapers <pb facs="5423970_1_1447.jpg" n="2"/>and scientific books. In order to get enlightenment, we Chicago Lithuanian women, as you know by now, have organized a society under the name "Enlightenment". This young society already has given several lectures on various scientific and social problems. We ask our sisters to join our society, attend our meetings and lectures and learn why you are so poor, while your spiritual leaders control a fortune.</p>
   <p>The "Enlightenment" Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
