<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-02-06">Feb. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Forgotten Opportunities</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Pajauskas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-02-06">Feb. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">FORGOTTEN OPPORTUNITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Pajauskas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The majority of youths, having arrived in America, drift into factories. They must suffer many hardships and work hard before, in one way or another, they blaze a better path for themselves. One year, two years, three years go by. The youths have already learned some of the English language, so necessary in this country. Finally they get some kind of an easier job. That job, though it is easy, is often not very well paid. What is more important, the youths, not being thoroughly acquainted with some kind of a trade, have no guaranteed future, and are not certain that the job will not end within another week or two. And having lost their jobs, where will they go, not having any trade? The only solution is;once more hard work in a factory.</p>
   <p>Is it not possible to do away with that sword of Damocles which continually <pb facs="5423970_1_0060.jpg" n="2"/>hangs over a person's head? Is it not possible to arrange it so that a person could always feel secure in his future? Undoubtedly, it is possible and, if one is willing, it is even easily attained. One of the best weapons in this country's battle of life is the knowledge of some sort of trade.</p>
   <p>Today the United States is flooded with "dirty work" hands, ordinary laborers. At the same time there is a shortage of various trained tradesmen. People with trades are in demand and, if there are none, they can be trained. Local governments realize this and therefore provide special evening trade schools. In such schools the training is given free of charge. The government only urges the people to attend them.</p>
   <p>There are many such schools. Let us take, for instance, even Chicago. Here there are, it seems, about ten government trade schools (technical high schools). In all the general organization is about the same.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0061.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The evenings of our youths are usually free. We let that free time pass, unused.... Now is our chance. If we do not benefit by it, we must blame ourselves and not others later. It is my sincere wish that the Lithuanian youths hear this plea and turn their attention to it. It is always possible for those who do not understand all that is written here to approach the nearest school, where they will be given detailed information. I believe that our newspapers will not decline to give more information to interested persons. (We, as much as we are able, will gladly serve. - Editor, Lietuva).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
