<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 30,
<date when="1904-07-22">July 22, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">A Protest of the Chicago Young Lithuanians Pleasure Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0881</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0881.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XII, No. 30,
<date when="1904-07-22">July 22, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">A PROTEST OF THE CHICAGO YOUNG LITHUANIANS PLEASURE CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are protesting against sending a delegate to Holland to the International Labor Congress under the name of the Lithuanian freethinkers when the Lithuanian public contributed the money. We hold that the delegate should be sent from the Lithuanian public, but not from a certain organization, and that Dr. J. Szliupas be elected by the Lithuanian Freethinkers Alliance as their delegate. The members of the Young American Lithuanian Pleasure Club have donated money for the said delegate. We are protesting against the decision of the Lithuanian Freethinkers' Alliance for sending the delegate to represent the Freethinkers' organization, but not the Lithuanian public of America.</p>
   <p>John Bagdziunas, Secretary.</p>
   <p>Editor's note: The Young Lithuanians Pleasure Club knew when they donated the money for the delegate that he would be a delegate from <pb facs="5423970_1_0882.jpg" n="2"/>the organization mentioned. A delegate cannot represent the Lithuanian public of America, even though the public has contributed the money. The Socialist congress will not accept a delegate from the general public, but will accept only such a delegate as representing a labor organization.</p>
   <p>As the Lithuanian Freethinkers' Alliance upholds Socialist principles, that organization is sending a delegate in its name.</p>
   <p>Now we would like to know against whom the Young Lithuanians Pleasure Club is protesting, when they knew what they were doing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
