<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 42,
<date when="1907-10-18">Oct. 18, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">What Good News in Chicago?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0260</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0260.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 42,
<date when="1907-10-18">Oct. 18, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT GOOD NEWS IN CHICAGO?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The summer has passed, the boisterous picnic season has gone. But our people know how to amuse themselves, it makes no difference to them what season it is: summer, autumn or winter. Now our newspaper are full of ads about banquets, balls, dances, etc. We have fifty or more Lithuanian societies in Chicago; everyone of these societies has one or two banquets during the winter season. The aim of such banquets is how much profit the society will make, and the profit comes from selling beer and whiskey! What benefit does such a banquet bring to the people? Does it uplift them morally and culturally? And who gets the profit from such banquets? The distilleries and the hall proprietors; the Lithuanian empty their pocketbooks and get a headache.</p>
   <p>Here is one example: In Chicago we have a very small society, the Aurora. Instead of dances and banquets, this society arranges scientific lectures on various subjects. Those who have attended <pb facs="5423970_1_0261.jpg" n="2"/>these lectures have learned something, but those who have attended banquets frequently remained ignorant.</p>
   <p>In recent days there arrived in Chicago one of the musicians and composers best known among Lithuanians, Mr. Mikas Petrauskas. He is the first Lithuanian musician and singer. We Lithuanians will have an opportunity to hear our own singer. But how many of us will appreciate him? He is the creator of our music and song. How many of us will respect this musician? We say that the Lithuanians were no good when our writer and historian, Simonas Daukantas lived, that he was neglected and even thrown out of his room when he was sick and poor, because he had no money to pay for his room. What about our poet, composer and writer, Dr. V. Kudirka? We neglected him when he was sick, if he had not been neglected by us, he would be alive today. Now we are praising him when he is dead. Therefore, we should not neglect our present musician, Mikas Petrauskas, who has devoted his life for Lithuanian music. Let us support him, let us show that we understand beauty and culture, music and song.</p>
   <p>Dzukas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
