<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1918-05-08">May 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The United States and Germany</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1226</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1226.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1918-05-08">May 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED STATES AND GERMANY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Germany's answer to the ultimatum of the United States did not satisfy President Wilson, but it appears that a break of diplomatic relations between these two countries has been averted for the time being. The most important point in the answer is the statement that Germany has issued a new order to her submarine commanders. The commanders have been ordered not to sink any merchant ships without a warning and a chance for the passengers to save their lives. This order would mean the complete surrender of Germany to the demands of the United States if it were not for a certain specified condition which greatly weakens the significance of the order. It is stated in the answer that Germany will put into effect the order to her submarine commanders only when the United States will force England to stop trying to starve Germany by means of a blockade. President Wilson was very much displeased with that specified condition. Furthermore, the tone of Germany's answer is very sharp, but that, of course, is not <pb facs="5423970_1_1227.jpg" n="2"/>important.</p>
   <p>The most important thing is the answer itself, and the answer is such that it would be very difficult for the United States Government to reject it and deal with Germany as an enemy. Germany really did make a rather big compromise. The compromise has satisfied most of the people of this country, and now they would never advocate or support a war with Germany on account of the submarine Question. Most of the members of both houses of Congress are especially opposed to a war with Germany at the present moment.</p>
   <p>Out of respect for the wishes of the people and their elected representatives, President Wilson and his cabinet have decided not to take any drastic steps against Germany at present, but to wait and see if Germany will adhere to the promise she has made in her note. If, however, the submarine incidents, against which the United States has been protesting, are repeated, the government of this country will probably fulfill its threat to break off diplomatic relations with Germany. President Wilson does not care whether Germany renews her old <pb facs="5423970_1_1228.jpg" n="3"/>submarine tactics on account of England's violation of international laws or for any other reason. He states that the action of England is a "different matter" and has nothing to do with the United States, and that Germany has no right to punish the United States for the acts of England.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is plainly evident that the crisis has been averted only temporarily. Only one careless step of a German submarine commander, which can happen any hour, will be sufficient to start a war between these two big nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
