<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,Vol. II, No. 21,
<date when="1894-05-06">May 6, 1894</date><title level="a">To the Chicago Lithuanians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0976</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0976.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,Vol. II, No. 21,
<date when="1894-05-06">May 6, 1894</date><title level="a">TO THE CHICAGO LITHUANIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wants to Organize a league of the Lithuanian Political Clubs</p>
   <p>Brother Lithuanians!</p>
   <p>At present we have great unemployment, hundreds of Lithuanians are on the edge of starvation, there is no way to help our starving brothers, we cannot help them, because we are disorganized.</p>
   <p>No matter where we go we are always behind others. We are behind others in politics and everywhere. When we need some help for our starving Lithuanians, we must go to the politicians of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>In order to accomplish something in politics or in any other field of activity we must have a strong political organization.</p>
   <p>We Lithuanians in Chicago have seven political clubs. We are sorry to say that our clubs as individuals can accomplish nothing, have very little influence in comparison with the political parties of others nationalities. In order to gain a name and position in politics, those seven Lithuanian political clubs must be organized into the Lithuanian political league. Let all the clubs elect their delegates, come to a meeting, discuss and make plans of our future activity in politics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0977.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have political clubs in the 6th, 7th, 9th, 10th, 16th and 29th wards and an independent political club.</p>
   <p>On the 10th of May we had a meeting of the 9th and 16th ward on this question.</p>
   <p>The officials of those wards were present on this meeting. We decided to call another meeting on the 3rd day of June of all the Lithuanian political clubs in order to organize the league.</p>
   <p>Now the Lithuanian political club members take into consideration this important question.</p>
   <p>We had enough of bowing to the politicians of other nationalities. We can be just as good and our name will be just as important if we are strongly organized.</p>
   <p>Officers of the 6th Ward.</p>
   <p>President, A. Olszewski</p>
   <p>Secretary, W. Zacharewiczia</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
