<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 12,
<date when="1901-03-22">March 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">In Recard to the Election of the New City Officials</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1061</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1061.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 12,
<date when="1901-03-22">March 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">IN RECARD TO THE ELECTION OF THE NEW CITY OFFICIALS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the coming election of Chicago's mayor and other officials on April 2nd, every citizen should take into consideration very carefully the platform of the candidates, and decide which of the candidates are best suited for the affairs of the city of Chicago. During the past four years, from 1897 to 1901, the city of Chicago had as its mayor, C. H. Harrison, of the Democratic Party. Thanks to his management he has made the city into an impassable cesspool. The cesspool is filled with hoodlums and various classes of thieves. The people of this city even in daylight cannot go on the streets without being robbed and assaulted. To keep order, to protect citizens' life and property, we have the police. But do the police fulfill their duty? No! There are many proofs that the police are arresting innocent people while the thieves and the murderers are at leisure, assaulting and robbing the people in all parts of the city. We have all this because the mayor of the city, Harrison, does not care to protect the people, nor does he care to have any order in the city.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1062.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>How, then, the question arises why was Harrison elected two times as mayor of the city? The answer to the question is this: Harrison was first elected mayor in 1897 on account of his father's name; his father was known for his honesty, and the city affairs were conducted honestly and properly. The present mayor, C. H. Harrison, when he had the fortune to take over the reins of the city of Chicago, in the two years of his administration he filled the city with thieves and all kinds of criminals. The saloons are refuge for criminals and hoodlums. A great number of houses of prostitution were opened and every house of evil was the fortress for the campaign of mayor Harrison in 1899 and Carter H. Harrison again was elected mayor, as the protector of the good name of the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>But the judge of the Circuit Court, Eldridge Hennessy, seeing that the city of Chicago was falling to the lowest degree of disgrace, decided to take action to pull the city out of this cesspool. For this reason the Republican Party put him on the Republican Party ticket as the most honest and efficient man to be the future mayor of the city of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1063.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is the duty of every citizen, Democrat or Republican, to give his vote to Judge E. Hennessy. When he is elected mayor of Chicago he will clean up the city of thieves, hoodlums, and criminals. Then the citizens of Chicago will be safe. Their rights will be protected and they will be able to live a peaceful life as all citizens should in a civilized community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
