<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-06-25">June 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Chicagoans Contribute $204.97 to Lithuanian War Relief</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-06-25">June 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGOANS CONTRIBUTE $204.97 TO LITHUANIAN WAR RELIEF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>So far four mass meetings have been held in Chicago for Stasys Simkus, who recently arrived in America as the representative of the Lithuanian War Relief Society [in Lithuania] for the purpose of soliciting funds for the Society.</p>
   <p>The first mass meeting was arranged by the second [Chicago] district of the Lithuanian Alliance of America at Milda Hall, 3140 South Halsted Street. At this meeting Mr. Simkus collected a total of $71.35.</p>
   <p>The second meeting, also arranged by the second district of the Lithuanian Alliance of America, took place in Meldazis Hall, 23rd Place and Oakley Avenue. A total of $41.27 was collected at the meeting.</p>
   <p>The Roseland, Illinois, lodge of the Lithuanian Alliance of America called a mass meeting for Mr. Simkus in Roseland. Donations at this meeting totaled <pb facs="5423970_1_1257.jpg" n="2"/>$19.35</p>
   <p>The fourth mass meeting was arranged by the National Fund [a war relief fund set up by the Lithuanian-American Catholic faction] in St. George's [Lithuanian]parish hall, 32nd Place and Auburn [now Lituanica] Avenue. A total of $73 was realized.</p>
   <p>A mass meeting for Mr. Simkus was scheduled to take place last Tuesday in Divine Providence (Lithuanian) parish hall, 18th Street and South Union Avenue. However, for some unknown reason the Reverend M. L. Krusas, the pastor, refused to grant permission for the meeting. Besides that, the Reverend Mr. Krusas opposed Mr. Simkus in other ways. It is said that he unfavorably criticized Mr. Simkus in a sermon at mass. It appears that the Reverend Mr. Krusas is incensed at Mr. Simkus because Dr. Jonas Sliupas, the foremost leader of Lithuanian-American freethinkers, was invited to speak at his mass meetings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1258.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Naujienos(News) is arranging a mass meeting for Mr. Simkus on Thursday evening, June 24, in the Colony Center at 18th and Halsted Streets. Besides Mr. Simkus, other speakers will be Pius Grigaitis, editor of the Naujienos, and Kleofas Jurgelonis.</p>
   <p>The National Fund is arranging two mass meetings for Mr. Simkus; one is to take place on Friday evening, June 25, in the Town of Lake colony; the other is scheduled to take place on Saturday evening, June 26, in the Melrose Park colony. Dr. Anthony K. Rutkauskas, president of the National Fund, will be one of the principal speakers at these two meetings.</p>
   <p>The Committee of the Englewood Lithuanian Societies is planning a mass meeting for Mr. Simkus on Sunday, June 27. Among others Mr. Bruno K. Balutis, member of the editorial staff of Lietuva (Lithuanian) will speak at the meeting.</p>
   <p>More mass meetings in Chicago for Mr. Simkus will be arranged by the National Fund. Although it is already two weeks since Mr. Simkus arrived in Chicago, <pb facs="5423970_1_1259.jpg" n="4"/>his itinerary is still unorganized. He plans to stay in Chicago until July 16 and then to leave for the Lithuanian colonies in Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>It would be a good thing for other Lithuanian-American colonies to arrange itineraries for him in advance. Mr. Simkus can be reached by mail at the following address: Mr. Stasys Simkus, 3261 South Halsted Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
