<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-16">Jan. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Unemployment Day Declared on Lincoln's Birthday</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0750</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0750.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-16">Jan. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">UNEMPLOYMENT DAY DECLARED ON LINCOLN'S BIRTHDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.... Today there are about five million unemployed men and women in the United States. Although they are undergoing severe hardships, nevertheless, no one is coming to their aid - neither the capitalists whose wealth has been created and piled up by these unemployed workers, nor the government whose duty it is to look after the welfare of the people of the nation.</p>
   <p>The unemployed, therefore, must seek help themselves,</p>
   <p>Their class-brothers, the workers, must come to their aid in this crisis.</p>
   <p>The problem of unemployment is the problem of all workers. The burden of unemployment is a burden to the entire working class. Today there are a great many workers suffering unemployment; tomorrow many more workers will fall into its <pb facs="5423970_1_0751.jpg" n="2"/>wretched claws. You workers, who still hold jobs in the factories, are not secure against unemployment. You, too, are constantly confronted with the probability of losing your jobs and being thrown into the army of unemployed.</p>
   <p>Not a single worker is guaranteed against unemploymend.</p>
   <p>That means that it is the duty of all workers to combat unemployment collectively.</p>
   <p>It is a fact that unemployment brings misery to other workers besides those who are forced to walk from factory to factory, travel from town to town, and to freeze on the street and watch their families suffer from hunger. Unemployment also tortures those workers who are still employed, because it adversely affects their working conditions.</p>
   <p>When unemployment rages, even those workers who are still employed are placed in a bad predicament. Large numbers of unemployed workers assemble at the factory gates seeking work. Such conditions encourage the employers to speed up and abuse their employees. The capitalists become bold and no longer fear the workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0752.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They know very well that if they lose one worker,there are hundreds of others anxiously waiting at the gates of the factory ready to take his place, and who will gladly sell their labor at lower wages. The capitalists take full advantage of such situations by lowering wages and by imposing various restrictions upon the employees.</p>
   <p>During a span of unemployment the workers usually lose all the gains which they had won in hard struggles during the previous ten years. Periods of unemployment are destructive times to the workers, but they are golden times to the capitalists.</p>
   <p>It is true that when unemployment prevails in the nation it means that business has decreased. In fact that is how unemployment is brought about; when unable to sell the products of the factories fast enough, the capitalists begin to lay off employees. But the remaining employees are forced by the capitalists to work harder and produce more at lower wages. Therefore, every dollar invested in business yields a larger profit to the capitalists during mass unemployment periods than it does during normal times.</p>
   <p>There is one more thing which the capitalists do when unemployment prevails. Since <pb facs="5423970_1_0753.jpg" n="4"/>there are fewer commodities produced, there is less competition between the capitalists. When their rivalry is lessened, it becomes easier for them to raise commodity prices. On the other hand, the higher cost of living adds greatly to the misery and suffering of the unemployed workers.</p>
   <p>Today both of these evils are tormenting the proletariat of the United States mass unemployment and the high coast of living. But of these two the worst and more painful is the evil of unemployment.</p>
   <p>Unemployment must be fought. It must be fought by all workers, by the entire working class, - men and women, old and young unemployed and employed.</p>
   <p>The capitalists who have waxed fat by the sweat of the workers refuse to assist victims of unemployment; the capitalist government is not concerned with the fate of unemployed workers. Therefore, the workers themselves must get busy.</p>
   <p>On February 12th the Socialist Party is making preparations for a gigantic working class movement. All workers are invited to conduct big mass demonstrations all over the country; organize large mass meetings; and raise a voice of protest against <pb facs="5423970_1_0754.jpg" n="5"/>people and institutions refusing to do their duty at least by lessening the agony of unemployment.</p>
   <p>There are many simple and effective means by which to dininish the dire consequences of unemployment. There are real and understandable methods by which the evil of unemployment can be banished entirely and forever. These methods will be duly explained to the working people at the mass meetings on Feb.12th. Appropriate demands of the workers will also be formulated and made to proper authorities. Therefore, each and every workingman and workingwoman should attend these meetings.</p>
   <p>February 12th is a legal holiday, Lincoln's birthday. The Socialist Party proposes to convert the day this year into "Unemployment Day."</p>
   <p>Workers, do your share to make this plan a big success!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
