<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[Lithuanian War Problnms Discussed]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1272</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1272.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[LITHUANIAN WAR PROBLNMS DISCUSSED]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About twenty-five Lithuanians met at the Grand Pacific Hotel last Monday evening to discuss the problems which have arisen in connection with the present war. Three Chicago Latvians also attended the meeting.</p>
   <p>With F. P. Bradchulis acting as chairman, the following problems were presented for discussion: 1. What should the Lithuanians and Latvians demand at the end of this war? 2. On what shall those demands be based and in what manner can they be realized? 3. What attitude should be taken toward the convention called for September 21-22, in connection with the Lithuanian Catholic Federation's Congress? 4. How should the matter of handling donations for Lithuania be organized?</p>
   <p>Many arguments resulted over the convention question. [Translator's note: The convention referred to was the proposed general convention of all Lithuanians <pb facs="5423970_1_1273.jpg" n="2"/>in America. The purpose of the proposed convention was to discuss ways and means of giving Lithuania needed help during and after the war.] The point on which there was the greatest disagreement was the request that the convention being called in connection with the Federation's Congress be designated a general convention and that it be recognized as such by all factions. P. Grigaitis, Dr. A. J. Zimontas, and Mr. Sarka pointed out that this convention would not be a general one and could not be called such since it was dominated by the right wing. A majority vote finally accepted the following definition of this convention:</p>
   <p>"A Political convention of the Lithuanian Roman Catholic Alliance, to which other factions are also invited." Many of those who had signed their names to an appeal entitled "Fellow-Nationals," which was sent to Lithuanian newspapers, were present and they voted for this definition. As we see it, this definition eliminates the element of universality from the convention sponsored by the Catholic Federation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1274.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, Mr. Gabrys and Reverend F. B. Serafinas expressed the opinion that the final definition is up to the convention itself.</p>
   <p>There was little time left to discuss the matter of donations, but it was hurriedly agreed that each faction collect donations as it sees fit. Later, it was agreed, donations could be turned over to a central donation acceptance unit, if such a committee were later organized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
