<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-09">Jan. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Worse it Gets, the Better it Is</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0994</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0994.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-09">Jan. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORSE IT GETS, THE BETTER IT IS</title>.
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.... An article on Socialism by Tautietis in the latest edition of Lietuva (Lithuania) shows what kind of critics we have among us. He writes as follows:</p>
   <p>"Socialists look upon their daily life only in terms of their ultimate good. They try to wreck everything in the present social order that does not appeal to them. More often that wrecking consists of pounding their heads against a wall. They completely ignore the realities of daily life."</p>
   <p>Usually the Nationalists and Catholics accuse Socialists of the direct opposite; that is, that they conform too much to the realities of daily life. They even point that out as the reason for an ever increasing popularity of Socialism among Lithuanian people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0995.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Tautietis continues as follows:</p>
   <p>"In order for the Socialists to attain their ultimate goal it is necessary for the masses to be highly dissatisfied with the conditions of their daily life. The more dissatisfied they are the more members the Socialists can recruit. Bad economic conditions are absolutely indispensable for the spread of Socialism. The worse it gets, the better it is," reads a Socialist slogan. The aims of Socialism are undeniably beautiful and lofty, but they can be attained in an entirely different manner.</p>
   <p>"Socialists are not interested in the prosperity and welfare of the working class under the present social order. On the contrary, they crave for a sharp increase of poverty and misery among the workers in order to stimulate the growth of the Socialist movement.</p>
   <p>According to the Socialist slogan, the present daily welfare of the masses is sacrificed for the benefit of the Socialist idea. A worker who is starving and suffering can more easily be attracted to the Socialist movement. Such is the <pb facs="5423970_1_0996.jpg" n="3"/>spirit of Socialism."</p>
   <p>But, if Socialism requires the present day impoverishment of the masses, as Mr. Tautietis charges, then how does he account for the world famous fact that Socialists are continuously fighting to better the standard of living of the masses? Mr. Tautietis himself sees that there is a hole in his criticism However, he attempts to plug it with the following phrases:</p>
   <p>"And when Socialists do sometimes you see, not always! "N" Editor) fight to better the conditions of the masses under the present social order, it is only because they are compelled to do so by the masses, in violation of their slogan: "The worse it gets, the better it is!"</p>
   <p>But such accusations against the Socialists can be made only by a fool or deliberate liar, because no intelligent person doubts that Socialists always fight for the welfare of the masses.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0997.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Tautietis appears to be familiar with a Socialist statement that mass misery, caused by the capitalistic system, compels the masses to seek for a better social order. Therefore, according to his logic, if mass misery aids the Socialist movement it must be a good thing for Socialist, something to desire for and promote. In that manner Mr. Tautietis formulates his so-called Socialist slogan: "The worse it gets, the better it is "</p>
   <p>Mr. Tautietis' error lies in the fact that he is unable to distinguish between the objective causes of Socialism and the subjective aims of Socialism.</p>
   <p>Mr. Tautietis unwittingly transforms a cause of Socialism into an aim of Socialism thus creating the false impression that Socialists desire and promote mass misery. He fails to realize that Socialism is a reaction against mass misery.</p>
   <p>In conclusion we express our astonishment at the fact that in the twentieth century such Socialist critics as Mr. Tautietis still dares to come forward before the public, and that they can still find space in the newspapers. Apparently the Nationalists are satisfied to employ any kind of methods, as long as they are directed against Socialism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
