<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-12-13">Dec. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Government Concerns Itself with the Protection of Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1322</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1322.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-12-13">Dec. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE GOVERNMENT CONCERNS ITSELF WITH THE PROTECTION OF CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There was real turmoil in Europe at the very beginning of the great war. While much noise was being made about mobilizations of armies and production of armaments, the children were completely forgotten. Most of the schools became army encampments, and many teachers left their posts to go to war. There was so much work to be done that children were taken out of school and placed in factories. Child-labor laws were broken and the children's welfare was neglected. The children, so to speak, were left to take care of themselves.</p>
   <p>As time passed, the European states realized their error in neglecting and failing to take care of the children. They realized that the children were not able to take care of themselves. Those children who were uncared-for committed twice as many offenses [as those who were given care].</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1323.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The European governments also came to realize that young children cannot take the places [in factories] of the men who go to war, since the small amount of work they are able to do does not compensate for their lack of education. Therefore, England, France, and Italy are now engaged in devising better laws to assure the attendance of children at school. They also plan to spend more money for the support of government schools than they spent before the war.</p>
   <p>The problem just discussed likewise affects the children of the United States. We must strive to avoid the mistakes the Europeans made in regard to the training and education of their children.</p>
   <p>Upon our entrance into the war, many states attempted to violate the child-labor laws so that children could be employed in jobs vacated by soldiers. However, the United States government did not lend its support to such attempts. Not very long ago, President Wilson said: "With <pb facs="5423970_1_1324.jpg" n="3"/>working conditions changing during the war, I am now more than ever concerned with protecting women and children from too great and injurious hardships at work".</p>
   <p>The President is of the opinion that in order to protect the children adequately, it is necessary to have national child-labor laws. He has pledged his support to the passage of such laws by Congress.</p>
   <p>There are many societies in the United States which concern themselves with the protection and welfare of children. The Children's Bureau is interested in the welfare of every young child, and the War Labor Policies Bureau looks after older children who attend school and who are looking for jobs.</p>
   <p>However, the government is not able to perform the task of satisfactorily protecting the children with its agencies alone. Mothers and fathers should help the government to provide protection for the children in the same spirit <pb facs="5423970_1_1325.jpg" n="4"/>of co-operation they have shown in other matters--the saving of food, for instance.</p>
   <p>If, in these times, we consider it a terrible thing to waste food, is it not even more terrible to waste our children?</p>
   <p>Even if children were to earn two dollars a day at the present time, what would be the ultimate outcome? These big earnings will decrease at the end of the demobilization period, and the youth who did not attend school, but went to work instead, will be unable to find a good job in the future because of lack of training. Uncle Sam says a child earns ten dollars a day when he is in school!</p>
   <p>If the European countries have decided to spend more money on schools, especially now when they have very little money because of the large war costs, it must be that they consider education a very important matter.</p>
   <p>Help the United States government to develop your children by keeping them <pb facs="5423970_1_1326.jpg" n="5"/>in school!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
