<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-08-07">Aug. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Secluded Nooks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0248</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0248.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1914-08-07">Aug. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">SECLUDED NOOKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is one matter on which all of our newspapers, of all tendencies, agree and co-operate. That is the question of temperance. Some have taken a stern and clear position against drinking. Others, because of some outside circumstances, fight less vigorously against the spread of the epidemic among our people. But, in principle, all have proclaimed themselves to be the foes of drunkenness.</p>
   <p>Thanks to the continual agitation by our newspapers, drunkenness, at least in some places, is beginning to surrender its place to temperate living. One can read, more and more often, of the sponsorship of temperate affairs, picnics, excursions, etc. The ideal of temperance, apparently, is taking deep root among our masses. This can be seen in their private lives, at weddings, christenings, etc., which our people used to find difficult to <pb facs="5423970_1_0249.jpg" n="2"/>imagine without intoxicating liquors.</p>
   <p>Drunkenness is decreasing today and the totally temperate private parties are not the white crows which they used to be in our lives, let us say ten years ago. In public life, however, temperance manifests itself much more for a very understandable reason: all kinds of assemblies find it easy and handy to receive mention in the press, and a correspondent seldom misses an opportunity to attack tippling when such an opportunity presents itself. In part, the public nature of such assemblies is a sort of bridle which checks drunkenness. In part, a sensible reaction to the ideal of temperance is being noticed,and it is not only fear of public censure that is behind the effort to banish intoxicants from our assemblies. Of course, we do not intend to state here that the matter of temperance is making perfect progress among us, and that only the remnants of drunkenness remain with us. No, we are fully aware of the sea of drinking which has deluged our people, and we realize that much work will yet have to be put in the fight against it. In speaking of the propagation of temperance, we have in mind only that which <pb facs="5423970_1_0250.jpg" n="3"/>we had several years ago and which we still have today.</p>
   <p>In order to block the path to drunkenness, however, it is necessary to give the people a foundation on which they can brace themselves. It is necessary to give them what is called an equivalent; that is, something to replace the drunkenness which is being ejected. It cannot be said of the majority of people that they drink because they are very addicted to intoxicants, and have learned to like them very much. The majority of our people drink because that is the custom, because others do so, and because there are no other ways to pass leisure time, or they cannot see or understand any other ways. Very often a secluded nook--in some saloon is the only place where people can meet to visit and converse with each other. At home, also, the bottle is recognized as the best stimulus to a gay conversation.</p>
   <p>This fact might make one unhappy, but the situation does not change because of that. And no matter how strong the fight against this situation might be,</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0251.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>the results will not be felt. It seems that we understand this thing: We wish to fill that void which the extermination of the mentioned practice leaves in the life of the average Lithuanian, by organizing societies and by public activity. But organizational activity takes up comparatively so little time of the average member that, at least up to now, there have been many instances where there is room for that equivalent. However, it is a step--and a large step--forward. In this respect our people, compared to the Americans, are a full step in advance.</p>
   <p>The prohibition movement is more widespread among the Americans than among the Lithuanians. That movement is growing, as evidenced by the ever-increasing number of "dry" towns and counties where the sale of all intoxicants is prohibited.</p>
   <p>However, does the propagation of temperance benefit by this? Are intoxicants altogether removed from the people? Undoubtedly, the use of intoxicants in <pb facs="5423970_1_0252.jpg" n="5"/>"dry" places is decreased, but, as experience proves, their universal abolition is not possible. Drinking begins in secluded nooks. Clandestine saloonkeeping, which, in many respects, is less desirable than the public sale of intoxicants, is born and flourishes.</p>
   <p>Working in this manner from the top instead of beginning at the bad roots, the supporters of prohibition can hardly bring any benefits to the movement of which they would be the apostles. The people are not infused with the realization of the injurious nature of intoxicants; they are not shown how they could fill voids in their lives; they are not being trained for temperate living. Instead of doing that work which, though it would be long and difficult, carries the full guarantee of success in the future, they choose the easier path of prohibition. They are laying no positive foundation on which the prohibition battle could take root so that, when it ceases to be a battle, the idea of prohibition would remain a permanent and firm control in the lives of the people. That is why, when some certain place becomes "dry", clandestine saloonkeeping, with all its vices, flourishes. That is why, <pb facs="5423970_1_0253.jpg" n="6"/>when the public saloons are banned, almost every private home, in some districts, becomes a secret saloon, or "a case" or more is kept on hand in almost every home to entertain a welcome visitor or for "family needs."</p>
   <p>The prohibition movement of the Americans also concerns the Lithuanians. As we know, there are many Lithuanian colonies in many of the "dry" places. We can see from the frequent news items in our newspapers how widespread clandestine saloonkeeping is in such places. On adding up many of such items, it seems that prohibition has not decreased drunkenness even a little bit, but has only chased it into secluded nooks. And herein lies the task for our newspapers and the leaders of the people. It is our duty, as far as our own people are concerned, to fill that void left by American prohibition. We must turn attention to this matter so that prohibition will bring the greatest possible positive benefits. Experience proves, as we stated above, that this can be attained by the organizing of temperance societies and clubs, by the founding of libraries and reading rooms and by propagandizing various <pb facs="5423970_1_0254.jpg" n="7"/>temperate entertainments, games, and excursions. This is a part of the cultural work now being done. And it must be directed where it will do the most good: in the secluded nooks of clandestine saloonkeeping.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
