<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-26">Dec. 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to Lithuanian Garment Workers of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-26">Dec. 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO LITHUANIAN GARMENT WORKERS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago we sent an appeal to every Lithuanian organization of garment workers in America in regard to the selection of one of the Lithuanian newspapers as their official organ. Very few have paid any attention to our appeal. Some have refused to give any consideration to this matter because they belong to an entirely different organization,--the I. W. W.</p>
   <p>Regardless of the fact that we belong to different organizations, the interests of all workers are the same. For this reason, closer co-operation among us is very essential. As long as we have no unity, our organizations will be too weak to secure better working conditions. It very often happens that in one city or another there is a garment workers' strike. Often it also happens that the news of such a strike comes to <pb facs="5423970_1_0358.jpg" n="2"/>us very late. Meanwhile, the employment agencies, with their tricks, send garment workers to work in that city, but they arrive only to find that the garment workers there are on strike. In order to secure closer co-operation among Lithuanian garment workers, we must have one of the Lithuanian newspapers as our organ so that we can discuss our common affairs. In such an organ,we could announce the latest events in the activities of the United Garment Workers of America.</p>
   <p>The purpose of this appeal is to renew the project described above. Lithuanian garment workers, do not pass this appeal by without discussion. Make your decision at once, and let us know it. Also, make suggestions as to which of the Lithuanian newspapers would be the best one for our organ. Later we can communicate with the newspapers to find a basis for its acting as our organ, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0359.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the name of Local 269 of the United Garment Workers of America.</p>
   <p>Julius Mickevicius</p>
   <p>P. Galskis</p>
   <p>P. S. Mail replies to this address:</p>
   <p>P. Galskis</p>
   <p>1652 North California Avenue</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
