<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-01-19">Jan. 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Repulse Attacks on Aliens</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-01-19">Jan. 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">REPULSE ATTACKS ON ALIENS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of narrowing the rights of aliens in this country appears to be the most important issue in Washington. A bill on that question has been introduced in Congress.</p>
   <p>The proponent of this bill is Congressman Oswald from Louisiana. It is said that the public declaration of president Coolidge concerning the restriction of the rights of aliens, and the unceasing agitation of the Secretary of Labor Davis against aliens, has inspired and encouraged Congressman Oswald to introduce such a bill. According to it all aliens will be compelled to register and be photographed. They will be required to carry a passport at all times. At any time and at any place they may be required to show their passports on demand.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0531.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Anyone found without his passport will be punished.</p>
   <p>The purpose of this proposed passport system, as it was in Czarist Russia, is to afford a means for persecuting and terrorizing our foreign-born workers, to make them powerless to resist exploitation, and to make it impossible for them to get organized. Most of the workers in the basic American industries and railroads are foreign-born. For that reason if all their rights are taken away then it will be possible to persecute them severely during a strike, and even force them to become strikebreakers. Under such conditions it will be very difficult or even impossible to win a strike. The reason why the capitalists are threatening to divide the foreign-born and American-born workers is to disrupt their unity, destroy their unions and organizations, and make them their slaves, because then the workers will be unable to resist even the most brutal exploitation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0532.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We must protest strongly against this brazen attempt to shackle the foreign-born workers and cripple the entire working class movement. Every organization of naturalized Americans and aliens must call all factions to conferences and arrange to hold big protest mass meetings. In a crisis such as this, it is possible to marshal the forces of all factions into a united front, because it is very evident that all are equally endangered.</p>
   <p>Lithuanians should also get busy and do their part in this crisis. We have hundreds of organizations. They must not be silent. In every city and town they must call a conference of all factions for a united front, and arrange to hold protest mass meetings. If no one raises a voice against such brazen measures of the reactionaries, then the latter will succeed in carrying out their Czarist plans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
