<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-22">Oct. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">American Imperialism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1909-10-22">Oct. 22, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN IMPERIALISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Taft is still touring the country. He is imitating the monarchs of Europe, and until the middle of the last century, the will of a monarch was believed to be the will of God. In Russia, this theory prevailed until the war with Japan in 1905. The people in European countries are winning liberty more now than ever, and many privileges of the rulers are being abolished. In America, civil liberties are constantly being reduced. In some matters, the President of the United States already has greater power than some rulers in Europe.</p>
   <p>During his journey, President Taft will have a conference on the border with President Diaz of Mexico, which is the second most powerful country in North America. Thus far, the Presidents of these two neighboring republics have not met. If they are planning to meet now, then it is not merely for the purpose of saying hello to each other; most likely they <pb facs="5423970_1_1384.jpg" n="2"/>will meet to discuss some important matters.</p>
   <p>Although the North American republic of Anglo-Saxon descent has advertised itself as the "protector" of the weaker American republics, nevertheless, it is a fact that the United States has greatly extended its borders to the lands of weaker American republics which are populated by people of Spanish descent. The United States grabbed a large expanse of land from Mexico; the entire republic of Texas was annexed by the United States. Therefore, it is not at all surprising if the small Spanish-American republics fear their so-called "protector" (the United States) more than they do the European countries; and the United States is constantly attempting to convince others that the nations of Europe are imperialistic and aggressive.</p>
   <p>Therefore, a distrust for the largest republic of North America is growing. This fact has been noticed by the politicians of the United States, and <pb facs="5423970_1_1385.jpg" n="3"/>as a result, they are employing various means in an effort to mitigate this lack of confidence of the Spanish-American republics. That is unquestionably the real purpose of the coming meeting between President Taft and President Diaz; the latter is more than seventy years of age, but like a Russian czar, he knows how to put his wishes into effect with the aid of the army.</p>
   <p>The two Presidents will undoubtedly discuss important problems pertaining to the western hemisphere. There are quite a large number of such problems. For example, the steadily recurring revolutions in Central America must be stopped. The United States, fearing the loss of its influence over other republics, is urging Mexico to"take the potatoes out of the hot ashes" for the United States by occupying the revolution-infested area--the Central American republics. President Diaz will probably do that. He has demonstrated that he knows how to subdue revolutions; and he does not lack courage. There were plenty of revolutions in Mexico, too, but President Diaz suppressed them with an iron hand.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1386.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Although President Diaz, like the Russian czar, deprived the masses of liberty, nevertheless, he did do some good for his country. During his long term in office, the prosperity of the country has increased; the intellectual level of the masses also increased. The constantly recurring revolutions, which formerly interfered with the normal life of the country, now have entirely disappeared. For these reasons, while President Diaz was on his way to meet the President of the United States, he was greeted by most of the people with enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The presidential election in Mexico is approaching. Judging from the enthusiasm with which the people of Mexico are greeting President Diaz on his journeys, it is very probable that he will be reelected. Although the Mexican President is allegedly elected by the people, nevertheless, the presidency will most likely remain in the hands of Diaz for the rest of his life. He is powerful enough to retain the presidency even without elections. In that manner, Mexico can become a monarchy. Such an ambition <pb facs="5423970_1_1387.jpg" n="5"/>is being nurtured by President Taft, several American millionaires, and Republican politicians. These corresponding ambitions and aims are uniting the Presidents of both republics, but not the people. Therefore, the meeting and friendship of the two Presidents will not mitigate the distrust of the United States held by the Mexican people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
