<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the Amalgamated Clothing Worker's of America, Lithuanian Local 269</title>, in possession of the Secretary, Local 269, Chicago, Illinois.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the Amalgamated Clothing Worker's of America, Lithuanian Local 269</title>, in possession of the Secretary, Local 269, Chicago, Illinois.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(This material was taken from the Executive Board records and from the Local 269 minutes book.)</p>
   <p>The first year's books are lost, so I took the records since Jan. 15, 1915 to April 1937.</p>
   <p>Jan. 12, 1915. It was decided to pay 12 cents per member to the Chicago Society League.</p>
   <p>Jan. 12, 1915. A union man complained that the shop chairman of tht Local 39 would not allow them to organize Lithuanians in the Lithuanian Local 269, saying, that only members of Local 39 could work in that shop.</p>
   <p>May 11, 1915. The shop chairman made a complaint, that two Lithuanians refused <pb facs="5423970_1_0362.jpg" n="2"/>to participate in the May first parade; so the organizing committee decided to send the two members a letter asking them to come to the local meeting to expla their attitude in this matter.</p>
   <p>July 2, 1915. Delegate P. Galskis reported that the May 1st parade expenses would have to be paid by the Local proportionately.</p>
   <p>Aug. 21, 1915. $5 was donated for the help of the two workers -leaders of Los Angeles.</p>
   <p>Sept. 18, 1915. In preparing for the organizing of a non-union general strike it was voted to put an assessment of $1 on each member.</p>
   <p>Oct. 1, 1915. $15 was donated to the women strikers.</p>
   <p>Oct. 16, 1915. It was decided to send a letter to the Baltimore tailors belonging to the I.W.W., to the Garment Workers' Union, so they would not do the work of the <pb facs="5423970_1_0363.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago strikers' firm.</p>
   <p>Oct. 25, 1915. $200 was donated to the Chicago Tailors strikers' Fund.</p>
   <p>May 5, 1916. It was decided to join in preparing welcome speeches in honor of the newly arrived guests from Lithuania, A. Bulota and Zemaite.</p>
   <p>Aug. 4, 1916. $25 was donated to the New York Women's Clothing strikers.</p>
   <p>Aug. 4, 1916. $25 was donated to the St. Louis Tailor Strikers.</p>
   <p>Aug. 8, 1916. It was decided to give several lectures, to explain more extensively the union's principles.</p>
   <p>Aug. 23, 1916. A letter received by the board from the General office was read, asking for information regarding the number of members of the Local who bought American Liberty Bonds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0364.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Sept. 16, 1916. It was decided to take part in the Chicago Society League meeting called for Sept. 16, which was given in order to collect donations for Lithuanian Day to help Lithuanian war veterans in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>Oct. 29, 1916. It was decided to join the North Side United Organization Public Library. Delegates were selected to participate at the meeting.</p>
   <p>Oct. 29, 1916. $25 was donated for the Lithuanian war veterans in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>June 15, 1918 a letter asking that three speakers be selected, was read from the U.S.Government,who were to talk four minutes for this country. The letter was accepted and three speakers were elected: P. Galskis, A. Cepaitis and J. Kaslikauskas.</p>
   <p>Feb. 7, 1919. $10 donated for the cigar makers strike.</p>
   <p>Feb. 22, 1919. It was decided to assess each member 50c in order to help the workers' leader, Mooney.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0365.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>March 15, 1919. A delegate reported that the Chicago Joint Board would hold a mass-meeting on March 20 at the Garments' Hall, to push the organization work more quickly, and also to stir up the people advising them to elect candidates from the Workers' Party to high offices in Chicago.</p>
   <p>April 8, 1919. The organizer, P. Galskis said, that this (sic) strike was not called by the organization, but that the people themselves went on strike out of sympathy with their fellow workers, who were laid off from work because they we active unionists. Con Richman got an injunction,and many were arrested. There are many shops which are thoroughly organized and pay monthly dues. Also, there are such non-union shops where for sixty hours work they make about $70; and in such shops workers are very much against short hours. During this organization period, about 5,000 new members joined the union.</p>
   <p>April 8, 1919.$50, a proportional payment, was paid to the strikers' fund from the local treasury.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0366.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>April 11, 1919. Each union member was assessed one dollar a week, while the srike lasted in the non-union shops.</p>
   <p>Aug. 8, 1919. $10 donated to the Lithuanian Socialist Protection League Fund.</p>
   <p>Aug. 8, 1919. A letter was received from the Lithuanian Liberty Bell Committee inviting to participate in the parade and farewell banquet of the Bell. After a short and lively discussion the invitation was rejected.</p>
   <p>Aug. 8, 1919. The Mooney Protection League's invitation to the conference for working out a plan of how to release Mooney, and other political prisoners from prison was accepted, and delegates were elected.</p>
   <p>Oct. 3, 1919. $10 donated to the Lithuanian Aid Society.</p>
   <p>Oct. 18, 1919. The North Side United Organization Public Library delegate reported that an evening school had been organized by the Public Library.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0367.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Nov. 7, 1919. It was decided to join the American Freedom League, each member paying one cent.</p>
   <p>June 10, 1920. A union member was fined $2, because he had pressed more coats than the union's regulation allowed, and if he did it again he would be suspended from the shop.</p>
   <p>June 10, 1920. The Lithuanian News Pub. Co. Naujienos paid 30% dividends. They sent three shares as dividends.</p>
   <p>July 2, 1920. $100 donated to the Waterbury strikers, and the members collected $55.</p>
   <p>Dec. 14, 1920. $15 was donated to a member, M. Prunis, a poor man.</p>
   <p>Jan. 7, 1921. It was decided to withdraw from the North Side United Organization <pb facs="5423970_1_0368.jpg" n="8"/>Public Library.</p>
   <p>Jan. 7, 1921 $250 donated from the treasury for the New York strikers.</p>
   <p>April 1, 1921 $200 worth of Lithuanian books were bought for the union library</p>
   <p>April 1, 1921. $15 donated to Sernas and $15 to John Perkunas.</p>
   <p>Aug. 8, 1921 A resolution of sympathy was passed regarding the Lithuanian News Pub. Co. Naujienos striking workers, promising them help in every way. Also, P. Grigaitis, K. Jurgelioniz and Co. were censured for their treatment of their workers. It was decided to publish this resolution on the pages of Vilnis and Draugas. After passing the resolution the members turned to P. Galskis, asking why he, the president of the Naujionos Publ. Co., had voted for a wage cut for the workers. Mr. Galskis explained that such a question was never discussed <pb facs="5423970_1_0369.jpg" n="9"/>at a meeting and that the workers had gone on strike because they wanted to oust K. Jurgelionis from the manager's place.</p>
   <p>Sept. 2, 1921 $150 donated to the Russian people. The money was sent to "The Friends of Soviet Russia."</p>
   <p>Oct. 7, 1921. It was decided to pay $5 a month to the Friends of Soviet Russia Aid Fund, while it was necessary.</p>
   <p>Oct. 7, 1921. It was decided to send a delegate to the starving Russians Aid Conference.</p>
   <p>Nov. 4, 1921. It was decided to open a school teaching Lithuanian grammar.</p>
   <p>March 31, 1922. $50 was donated to the Amalgamated Textile Workers strikers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0370.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>April 7, 1922. The $40.70 collected for A. Janusius, who was ill, was donated to The Friends of Soviet Russia when he died.</p>
   <p>May 5, 1922. $10 donated to the Amalgamated Textile Workers of America strikers.</p>
   <p>June 23, 1922. A letter was received from the Russian American Industrial Corp., soliciting to buy shares. It was decided to acquire shares. The members took right then twenty-nine shares.</p>
   <p>Aug. 11, 1922. $10 donated to the Socialist Labor Party for the Protectors Fund.</p>
   <p>Aug. 11, 1922. Fifteen shares were bought for $150 from the Russian-American Industrial Corp.</p>
   <p>Sept. 29, 1922. A letter was received from the Darbas (Work) editor, Mr. V. <pb facs="5423970_1_0371.jpg" n="11"/>Poska, to the effect that he would not publish in the tailor's organization The Work the resolution adopted against the Lithuanian news Naujienos. After talking this over, it was decided to translate this resolution into English and send it to the General Secretary, Schlosenberg.</p>
   <p>Sept. 29, 1922. A letter was read from the workers of Naujienos, whereby the workers demanded that the resolution against Naujienos, and their directors be removed. The executive committee intended to write a letter in answer to this demand, but ultimately they decided to leave this question open and bring it up at the local meeting for further discussion.</p>
   <p>Oct. 6, 1922. Donated $10 to buy books in America and send them to Lithuania.</p>
   <p>Nov. 3, 1922. The Friends of Soviet Russia reported that the Lithuanian group during the year has collected $5,679 for the starving people of Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0372.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Nov. 3, 1922. Decided to call a protest meeting against the government of Lithuania.</p>
   <p>Dec. 8, 1922. The delegates reported that in Chicago a union of the seventeen Lithuanian societies had been organized.</p>
   <p>Jan. 17, 1923. Resolved,that the administration members of Local 269 must buy shares of the Russian American Industrial Corporation.</p>
   <p>April 6, 1923. A delegate was sent to the Farmer Labor Party convention which was held on April 8, 1923, Chicago.</p>
   <p>July 13, 1923. A resolution was brought in against Dr. A.L.Graiciunas for organizing scabs in the Shaine Co.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0373.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>Jan. 11, 1924. Donated $50 for the political prisoners in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>Mar. 14, 1924. The delegate reported that the Friends of Soviet Russia, had began to help the starving workers in Germany and the orphans in Russia.</p>
   <p>Mar. 14, 1924. Resolved to advertise the local union meeting in the Daily Worker, for a whole year for $3. Also donated $10 for the political prisoners' fund.</p>
   <p>July 11, 1924. The local approved W.Z.Foster, as candidate for president of the U.S.</p>
   <p>Aug. 8, 1924. The delegates announced that the Board decided to support La Follette for president.of the United States and donated $50 for the campaign. The delegate of the Local voted against this and the decision was rejected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0374.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>Aug. 22, 1924. The Local 269 officers brought in a resolution against the General Board for supporting the Republican candidate for the United States presidency, and congratulated brother Schosberg for voting against it.</p>
   <p>Sept. 12, 1924. The delegate announced that the Joint Board donated for the La Follette campaign fund $1,000. The members of the Local voted against it. Also, the delegate reported, that the Political Prisoners' Defense Fund had bee reorganized, and that from now on it was decided to help, not only political prisoners, but the strikers, too.</p>
   <p>Nov. 28, 1924. Donated $5 for the Young Workers' League.</p>
   <p>Jan. 9, 1925. The General Auditors' report showed that the Joint Board had as assets in Aug. 31, 1924 the sum of $2,059,692.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0375.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>Jan. 9, 1925. Resolved,that the Local should withdraw from the Friends of Soviet Russia, The Political Prisoners' Fund, and from the Chicago Societies Association.</p>
   <p>After a long discussion, it was decided to remove the "censure" from the daily newspaper Naujienos. The Local before had forbidden to publish in this newspaper notices about meetings and other advertisements. Also, it was decided not to pay henceforth any money to the Daily Worker for announcements of the Local meetings.</p>
   <p>March 13, 1925. Donated $10 for the Sacco-Vanzetti Fund. The members collected another $10. Decided to forgive Mr. A. Kemezis for writing for Naujienos.</p>
   <p>April 9, 1926. A resolution adopted and recommended to the A.C.W. of America.</p>
   <p>1. In favor of organizing all workers of the clothing industry.</p>
   <p>2. Against the bill introduced in the U.S. Congress to deport all those that <pb facs="5423970_1_0376.jpg" n="16"/>not citizens.</p>
   <p>3. To establish a Labor Party in America.</p>
   <p>4. For forty hours work per week.</p>
   <p>5. Against the bill for registration of foreigners.</p>
   <p>May 21, 1926. Donated $10 for the strikers of Textile Workers, Passaic, N.J.</p>
   <p>April 5, 1927. Resolved to have a lecture; the speaker should be P. Grigaitis, the editor of Naujienos.</p>
   <p>May 13, 1927. A resolution was brought against the execution of Sacco-Vanzetti. Decided to sell the shares of the Russian American Industrial Corp.</p>
   <p>June 10, 1927. The delegate from the Joint Board announced, that the Chicago tailors had donated for the sufferers of the Mississippi flood $8,000 which was sent to the Red Cross Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0377.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>Aug. 12, 1927. The delegate from the Joint Board announced that one garmet firm, where the workers had been working overtime, had not paid for time and a half. The firm was fined $400, and the money was donated to a charitable institution.</p>
   <p>The business agent, Mr. Kairis, announced that, as a protest against the execution of Sacco-Vanzetti, work was stopped for half an hour. This demonstration succeeded 100%.</p>
   <p>Dec. 9, 1927. Donated $10 for the striking miners of Colorado.</p>
   <p>Oct. 12, 1928. An assessment of $25 was made on every member.</p>
   <p>Dec. 14, 1928. A letter was received from the Holy Cross Hospital Fund asking for contributions. The demand was rejected.</p>
   <p>May 10, 1929. The delegate from the Joint Board announced that they have <pb facs="5423970_1_0378.jpg" n="18"/>donated $500 for the Labor Party of England.</p>
   <p>The business agent, Kairis, announced that for the A.C.W. of America to build their building would cost $1,059,700.</p>
   <p>Sept. 13, 1929. Donated $50 to the garment strikers in Philadelphia.</p>
   <p>Nov. 14, 1930 Made assessments of $8 on each member for the unemployed tailors. The assessments should be paid in sixteen weeks.</p>
   <p>Aug. 5, 1930. Resolved to hold the 20th year anniversary of the killing of brothers K. Lazinskas and P. Nagrecki.</p>
   <p>Jan. 2, 1931. Resolved to have speeches at every meeting on certain questions.</p>
   <p>March 6, 1931. A letter was read from the Socialist Party, inviting Local to take part in the convention on March 8 at the Douglas Auditorium. Resolved to <pb facs="5423970_1_0379.jpg" n="19"/>elected two delegates, and donated $10.</p>
   <p>May 8, 1931. Donated $5 for the state conference concerning the Unemployment Insurance.</p>
   <p>June 12, 1921. Resolved, to participate in organizing the Illinois Farmer-Labor Party. Elected two delegates.</p>
   <p>June 10, 1932. A protest resolution was brought forth against the Melrose Park authorities for shooting innocent citizens.</p>
   <p>Oct. 14, 1932. Resolved to have an agitation lecture for the Farmer-Labor party and the Socialist Party to unite the parties in Cook County.</p>
   <p>Dec. 8, 1933. The A.C.W. of America joined the union of the American Federation <pb facs="5423970_1_0380.jpg" n="20"/>of Labor.</p>
   <p>April 13, 1934. Donated $10 for the A.L.T. A. for the flight to Lithuania.</p>
   <p>July 13, 1934. Joined the Lithuanian committee of the World's Fair for the Lithuanian Day on Aug. 5, 1934. Elected two delegates.</p>
   <p>Sept. 14, 1934. Joined the Chicago convention which was called against war and fascism. Elected two delegates.</p>
   <p>Oct. 11, 1935. Donated $5 for the defense of Tom Mooney.</p>
   <p>April 10, 1936. Resolved to participate in the Chicago Lithuanian Societies convention. Elected five delegates.</p>
   <p>May 6, 1936. Donated $10 for the strikers at the Kohler Co., Sheboygan, Wis.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0381.jpg" n="21"/>
   <p>June 12, 1936. Sent delegates to the Lithuanians' of America convention, Cleveland, Ohio.</p>
   <p>Jan. 7, 1937. Donated $5 for the miners' defense fund.</p>
   <p>Feb. 5, 1937. Donated $5 for the political prisoners in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>Mar. 5, 1937. Resolved to join the Labor Party of Chicago and Cook County, with initiation fees of $5.</p>
   <p>This local every year has one or more banquets, lectures, and picnics.</p>
   <p>The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, Lithuanian Local 269, has about seven hundred members. Formerly had about 1,600 members.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0382.jpg" n="22"/>
   <p>John Bachiunas, Pres., 5547 N. Austin Ave.,</p>
   <p>V. Prusis, Sec., 3247 Beach Ave.,</p>
   <p>C. Kairis, Business Agents, 333 So. Ashland Blvd.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
