<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record Books of the United Lithuanian American Political Club</title>, in possession of Secretary, 9th. Ward, Chicago, Ill.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0916</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.2"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0916.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record Books of the United Lithuanian American Political Club</title>, in possession of Secretary, 9th. Ward, Chicago, Ill.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This political club was organized in 1933. Before this there were two political clubs: The Democratic and the Republican, both of which barely existed. The officers of those two clubs discussed the problem among themselves, and after consideration and mutual understanding, they organized the new club, by uniting these two clubs into one and this new club was given the name shown above. After the amalgamation of these clubs the leadership of the new club remained in the hands of the Republicans.</p>
   <p>During the presidential election of 1936 for the presidential campaign, the Republican officers of this club invited American-English speakers to give talks about the Republican candidate for president. As the people listened to the speakers in a very friendly way the Republicans were thinking that the people were supporting the Republican presidential nominee; so they asked the people to have a straw vote for the president. After counting the vote they found the following results: For the Democrats there were 153 votes, for the Communists eight votes and for the Republicans seven votes. After such a blow to the republicans, at the next meeting, all the Republican officers were voted out and the Roosevelt Democrats were elected officers of this club.</p>
   <p>A. Draugelis, president, 24 W. 104th St.</p>
   <p>J. Pivorunas, secretary, 22 E. 101th St.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
