<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 2, 2;3,
<date when="1914-03-04">March 4, 1914</date><title level="a">How Tax Payers' Money Is Spent Political Jobs - Reward for Stealing Votes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 2, 2;3,
<date when="1914-03-04">March 4, 1914</date><title level="a">HOW TAX PAYERS' MONEY IS SPENT POLITICAL JOBS - REWARD FOR STEALING VOTES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Most of the political jobs in Chicago are for milking out the tax funds from the city treasury, and not for beautifying our city or improving sanitary conditions.</p>
   <p>The Bureau of Public Efficiency made the investigation of the patronage department sponsored by the City Attorney, Peotrowski, and found people placed on the city payroll with good salaries who were not working for the city at all, but for themselves.</p>
   <p>For example, one saloon keeper who has a patronage job as an investigator, gets $125.00 per month for making a few social calls to the city hall, and visits to his friends. Some days he goes to the city hall, gossips for twenty minutes with his political friends, goes back to his saloon to get a couple of drinks and then goes back to the city, - gossips again and his <pb facs="5423970_1_1042.jpg" n="2"/>day's work is done. The second party is an alcohol agent who is also an investigator and gets $83.33 per month for doing nothing. The only thing he does is to go to the city hall, spend about half an hour there, go back to sell whiskey to saloon-keepers, and his day's work is done. The third party is a cigar maker, also on the city payroll, getting $100.00 per month for walking the streets looking for new customers to whom to sell his cigars.</p>
   <p>From the foregoing examples we see clearly where taxpayers' money goes and for what purpose it is spent. These things are going on not only in Chicago, but all over the United States. There are six people on the payroll, not working, to one who is working for the city. They were on the payroll getting big salaries for their assistance during the campaign before the last election. They were well rewarded for stealing votes and helping to elect their friends to various offices. These politicians are wasting taxpayers' money. Not only thousands of dollars, but millions, are wasted throughout the country yearly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1043.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now we may ask the question, what is wrong with our system? The answer to this question is, we are negligent in our civic duties and in not taking an interest in remedying this terrible situation in this sytem. We cannot have economy and efficiency in our government as long as we have this dangerous patronage system, which may destroy our democracy in the future. The patronage system in our form of government is just as dangerous to our government as any subversive element in this country. What brings about bad conditions, heavy taxation and demoralization of our government, if not the patronage system in this country? If we substitute a civil service system for the patronage system then we will save our country from downfall. We know that many citizens don't understand that the patronage system is dangerous to our government and its people. The patronage sytem is the media by which political parasites are thriving today and destroying the principles of democracy. They are not interested in civic problems, but they are interested only in their own pocket-books. Their main mission and objective is to build up a strong patronage system, through which they are enabled to maintain a strong political machine for reelection again and again. Their real interest is not in the government itself, but in <pb facs="5423970_1_1044.jpg" n="4"/>creating stronger patronage for putting on the payroll their supporters who helped elect or re-elect them to office.</p>
   <p>After every election each politician brings in his own gang and puts each one on the pay-roll according to the number of votes he delivered during the election. They are placed in positions, not according to their qualifications and education, but according to the numbers of votes they delivered, no matter whether these votes were legal or illegal. Then comes another politician, who represents an opposing party. He runs for the same office and beats the opponent who has already been in for one term. As the result of his election he fires his opponents' supporters from the patronage payroll and puts his own gang in its place. This system goes on in cycles indefinitely. This is the reason why we cannot have efficiency in our government. It is because of these changes during each administration.</p>
   <p>The Chicago politicians and their immediate associates are very ignorant people. This group is composed of the people who are failures in civil life and are <pb facs="5423970_1_1045.jpg" n="5"/>without proper education. They are the ones who control the Chicago government and make the laws for Chicago intelligentsia. They make many complicated laws to suit themselves and to protect themselves from going to prison in case they embezzle money from the city treasury. Those who do embezzle are protected from serving terms in prison.</p>
   <p>The patronage system has two great evils. First, it levies heavy taxation upon citizens for the support of political parasites who are placed on the city payroll. Second, it reduces efficiency in our government. The citizens of Chicago should unite and kick out these political parasites who exploit taxpayers and over-burden them with heavy taxes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
