<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-08-30">Aug. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Are Lithuanians "Undesirables"?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-08-30">Aug. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ARE LITHUANIANS "UNDESIRABLES"?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. V. Gaizauskas sends us the following letter:</p>
   <p>"It would be very desirable to know how the Lithuanians and other Russian subjects are looked upon in this country. I have had experiences which other Lithuanians also may have had, and I feel they should be revealed publicly so that the Lithuanians can take steps to protect their good name.</p>
   <p>"On the twenty-third of this month I went to the Employment Office at 116 North Dearborn Street and asked for a carpentering job at one of the soldiers' camps. I was asked if I was a carpenter. I answered that I was. I was asked where I was born. I answered that I was born in Lithuania.</p>
   <p>"Then they told me that they did not give jobs to those who were subjects of <pb facs="5423970_1_1098.jpg" n="2"/>Russia.</p>
   <p>"Why?" I inquired. "The Lithuanians are loyal to this country: they join the army--many of them volunteer--they buy many Liberty bonds, and in many other ways show their unswerving loyalty to this country. They replied that they have had unpleasant experiences in the past.</p>
   <p>"That was not my only experience. At the beginning of May I went to ask for work in an ammunition factory in East Chicago. They told me that they had open only jobs for carpenters. I replied that I was a carpenter. They asked If I was a citizen. I said I was not. They asked me where I was born? It seemed that, if I was born in Lithuania and was a subject of Russia, there was no job for me even if I had my full citizenship papers. They said they would rather hire Germans, Austrians, or Turks than Lithuanians or anybody else who was a subject of Russia.</p>
   <p>"Such insults hurt the heart of a true and loyal Lithuanian. Why are we so <pb facs="5423970_1_1099.jpg" n="3"/>mistreated?"</p>
   <p>From the editor: Some time ago we turned attention to the fact that "the Lithuanians and the Koreans" are regarded as undesirables. The Lithuanians are put in this class because, thanks to the work of several half-witted agitators, there has sprung up among them a crop of crybabies who attempted to mislead the Lithuanians at the very beginning of the war, inciting them against joining the army, against the government and against the Liberty bonds. These agitators, hiding under various names--most often as "the friends of the workers"--have made more than one slacker and have misled some people.</p>
   <p>The government, the factories, and the American public notice all of these things. Therefore, all of the Lithuanians must suffer for the actions of a few crazy fanatics.</p>
   <p>We warned our readers, long ago, that things might come to such a state of affairs that none of the better jobs in the factories would be open to Lithuanians. At that time those who call themselves "the friends of the workers" <pb facs="5423970_1_1100.jpg" n="4"/>laughed at and derided our warning. Now, more and more cases are coming up to prove that our warning was and is a good one.</p>
   <p>Mr. Gaizauskas did well to inform us of his experiences. We beg all of you who have had such experiences to let us know about them. Then steps will be taken to wash that blot from the reputation of the Lithuanians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
