<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-01-08">Jan. 8, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Alien Registration Proposal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1318</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1318.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Vilnis</title>,
<date when="1926-01-08">Jan. 8, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE ALIEN REGISTRATION PROPOSAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4..........A recent report by the executive committee of the American Federation of Labor contained the following statement:</p>
   <p>"With every new session of Congress attacks against alien workers in the Unites States are renewed. The danger of being enacted, requiring the registration, finger printing and photographing of all alien workers is continuously increasing. Now even the United States secretary of labor, Davis, is openly advocating such a law. Agreement with such a measure has also been noted in a recent talk by the United States president.</p>
   <p>The executive committee of the American Federation of Labor urges all workers to declare a war against this reactionary attempt to completely narrow the rights of alien workers. The Labor Party also urges all workers, especially the foreign-born workers and their organizations to fight for the rights of alien workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1319.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The narrowing of the rights of alien workers is a threat against the entire labor movement. A very large number of alien workers are employed in the basic industries. If a Czarist passport system is put into effect and if all the rights of alien workers are taken away from them, as the reactionaries plan to do, then that would seriously cripple the labor unions in the basic industries. The unions then would become powerless and it would be an easy task to abolish them altogether. We must fight against these reactionary measures as a serious threat against the entire labor movement. The alien workers, of course, will be more affected than other workers. For that reason all the organizations of the foreign-born should enter the fight against those reactionary proposals of the servants of industrial and business barons, who sit in the United States Congress in Washington, D.C. Furthermore, every intelligent and class-conscious worker should join the Labor Party, which is everywhere in the vanguard in defense of the rights and interests of the working class. As the Party becomes larger and stronger, it increases its activities for the benefit of the masses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
