<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 26,
<date when="1914-08-06">Aug. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Is it Possible to Fight against War?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>, Vol. I, No. 26,
<date when="1914-08-06">Aug. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IS IT POSSIBLE TO FIGHT AGAINST WAR?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialists, as we know, are the enemies of all wars. Their echo rings loud, "War against war." We also know that war makes the capitalists, and the war is the medium in which the capitalistic germ is thriving under the capitalistic system. We the Socialists have worked hard; we have put in all our efforts and exerted our energies; yet we failed to bring about peace in this world under the capitalistic order. Notwithstanding how hard we work for the peace of the world, wars still remain inevitable under the present system.</p>
   <p>The Socialist fight against the capitalists for the injustice done to humanity will not be in vain in the future. The Socialist Party cannot accomplish its task in a short period of time. As long as the capitalists exist, the working man will always be exploited. The capitalists must exploit the workers by all means; if they didn't exploit them, there wouldn't be large profits and there wouldn't be such an easy life for the capitalists. In other words, we understand <pb facs="5423970_1_1290.jpg" n="2"/>that the exploitation of labor under the capitalistic system is inevitable. It is possible to fight against labor in time of peace, but in time of national emergency, the labor is used to fight the enemy and defend the country in which he lives. Labor is a patriotic organization that defends its country with its life, and its reward for defending the country is exploitation by the capitalists. A working man has to fight for his mere existence if he wants to live. His working conditions are not improved without a fight and sometimes not without bloodshed; and sometimes he sacrifices his life to improve the condition of his fellow workers.</p>
   <p>Working people never got anything for nothing; they paid high prices for whatever they got. Many of them died fighting against the capitalistic exploitation and injustice. Labor exploitation still exists, but not to such a great extent as before. The very same is true of war.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1291.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>War will be inevitable as long as the capitalistic system exists. Maybe we cannot abolish war completely, but we can make them fewer and shorter. Under Socialism we have a better chance of decreasing wars and the destruction of humanity. The capitalists have no use for human lives, because they have no sympathy for humanity. They look upon fellow workers disparagingly, as the Romans looked upon their slaves who were chained to the galleys. People are human and they must be treated as such. We must save human lives by abolishing wars or by decreasing them in number, if we cannot abolish it completely.</p>
   <p>It is possible to prevent war if we make an effort to stop the war before it starts, and also it is possible to stop the war after it has started. This depends upon the people of various nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
