<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-09-13">Sept. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">On Organizing Lithuanian Legions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1088</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1088.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-09-13">Sept. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ON ORGANIZING LITHUANIAN LEGIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In this issue there appears an announcement, signed by the Lithuanian National Council (the Nationalists) and the Lithuanian-American Council (the rightists), battalions, here in America.</p>
   <p>That is probably the biggest and most important step to be made by the Lithuanians of America. It was not unexpected and is not surprising, for it is the natural and logical result of that toward which the Lithuanians have been aiming for a long time.</p>
   <p>The supreme and final goal of the Lithuanian nationalistic movement--like that of any other nation--is to fight successfully for the freedom of its nation <pb facs="5423970_1_1089.jpg" n="2"/>and the full independence of its country.</p>
   <p>Notice that we do not say "plead successfully for, beg for or demand," that independence, but "fight for" it. People who have freedom and do not want to protect it are not worthy of that freedom. Equally true is the statement that people who do not know how to fight for freedom, or do not want to fight for it, are not worthy enough to receive it.</p>
   <p>That is as plain as the sun in the sky and is very well understood by every Lithuanian who desires freedom for his nation.</p>
   <p>What some of the Lithuanians are asking is this: Will the Lithuanians, having organized their legions and having entered the war to make the world safe for democracy, be given the assurance that they are really fighting for Lithuania's independence? In other words, will the Allies guarantee independence to Lithuania?</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1090.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The behavior of the Allies toward the Czechoslovaks and the Poles, who have such legions and whose independence the Allies have already acknowledged, does not leave any doubt that, when the Lithuanians have organized their legions, they, also, will receive an acknowledgement of independence.</p>
   <p>While we do not have such legions, various pro-German sympathizers, the enemies of the Lithuanian nationalistic movement, and, finally, the "doubting Thomases," will undoubtedly strive to instill a poisonous doubt in our people's minds concerning the Allies' sincerity. We must protect ourselves from such poisons with our utmost effort.</p>
   <p>The sooner America and the Allies make an official statement regarding the fate of Lithuania, the smaller will be the field for such poisonous propaganda.</p>
   <p>We do not doubt that the creation of these Lithuanian legions is in accordance <pb facs="5423970_1_1091.jpg" n="4"/>with the wishes of the American Government. The Lithuanians of America themselves do not have the means to support such legions, but undoubtedly they will be supported by America. America, who provided us refugees with a haven from despotism, who was the first to extend a helping, motherly hand to the Lithuanian nation by proclaiming "Lithuanian Day," again comes to our aid by giving us the opportunity to create Lithuanian legions. She could draft the Lithuanians without regard for their nationality, but instead she is the first of all nations to offer arms to the Lithuanians, saying: "Here, stand beside me and let us fight together for your liberty and mine!"</p>
   <p>Lithuanians! Lithuania's day of independence is dawning! Be prepared to meet it appropriately!</p>
   <p>In the meantime, the Lithuanians of America are anxiously waiting for more detailed information from our councils.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
