<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1906-04-27">Apr. 27, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Celebrate the First of May</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0876</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0876.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1906-04-27">Apr. 27, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">LET US CELEBRATE THE FIRST OF MAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Socialist party, the party of American labor, [this year]for the first time will officially celebrate, together with all the workers of the world, the international holiday, the First of May. The party is appealing to all workers of the United States, regardless of their nationality, not to work on that day, but to join in the celebration.</p>
   <p>In Chicago the parade will start at 2 P.M. from the following places:</p>
   <p>Section I, Wosta Hall, 122 Lake Street</p>
   <p>Section II, 55 North Clark Street</p>
   <p>Section III, Appolo Hall, Twelfth Street and Blue Island Avenue</p>
   <p>Section IV, the office of the Czech newspaper Spravedlnost (The Truth),</p>
   <p>18th and Loomis Streets.</p>
   <p>[The line of march will end in] Douglas Park.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0877.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Comrades, workers of Chicago! Remember that on the First of May, the world over, not one worker will work! Remember that the workers in Russia, and our brethren in our native land, under the bullets and the whips of the Cossacks, will march through the streets singing the "Marseillaise"! Let us quit work on that day and forget the differences of nationalism. The world over, let workers unite and march under the red banner, dyed with our brothers' blood, and let us cry out with the voice of the oppressed:</p>
   <p>"Down with despotism! Long life to equality and brotherhood! Long life to socialism! Down with rotten tyrants!"</p>
   <p>Every one will be cordially accepted in the ranks of the marchers during the parade. At Douglas Park, along with speakers of other nationalities, there will be Lithuanian speakers, too.</p>
   <p>On the same day, at 7 P. M., the Lithuanian Socialists will have their meeting <pb facs="5423970_1_0878.jpg" n="3"/>at K. Liaudanska's Hall, 3119 South Morgan Street; at this meeting the importance of the First of May will be explained.</p>
   <p>A. Zagaras, representative of the</p>
   <p>Lithuanian Social-Democratic party</p>
   <p>A. Petrailis, of the Chicago Central</p>
   <p>Committee of the Lithuanian Socialist</p>
   <p>Party</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
