<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-16">Jan. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Opponent of Political Action by Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0989</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0989.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1915-01-16">Jan. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">OPPONENT OF POLITICAL ACTION BY LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.... There are elements among the workers who are opposed to political action by the working class. They maintain that meddling into politics is not only a waste of time but also harmful to the interests of the working people.</p>
   <p>Those opponents claim that when people vote and select representatives for congress they are at the same time supporting the state and expressing their confidence in the existing social order of the state. And what is a state? They say the state is merely a tool of the capitalists to keep the workers in slavery and darkness. Therefore, away with the state, away with congress, voting, political parties and all politics.</p>
   <p>But if we do away with congress, voting, political parties, political agitation, then how can the present social order be improved? They agree that the present social order is in need of radical reform.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0990.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Instead of political action they advocate "direct action." They say that workers should act not through congress or the government but "directly"against the capitalists who exploit them; and fight particularly in those places where the exploitation actually takes place. And they recommend that the workers employ the strike as the only real and effective weapon of warfare against the capitalists; also adding "sabotage" and a variety of other helpful tactics.</p>
   <p>People who painstakingly expound these theories are known as Anarchists, who, it appears, express the inclinations of small business men and not of the workers. However, they have followers even in the labor unions; for example, in the I.W.W. union.</p>
   <p>During normal times these opponents of political action do not enjoy much success among the masses of workers. The more intelligent workers even refuse to listen to their theories. For that reason Anarchists become unusually active whenever something abnormal occurs in the world.</p>
   <p>One of those abnormal events today is the European war. It was caused by states.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0991.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Parliaments, political agitation and political parties were unable to prevent it. To opponents of political action such an incident is a precious weapon of propaganda.</p>
   <p>"Did we not tell you", they shout, "that a state, parliament, voting,political parties, and all politics, are no good?"</p>
   <p>It is true, they did say that. But they also said that "direct action" is a good thing; they continuously praised the strike as the only real and most effective weapon with which to combat the evils of the world. And how effective was their "direct action" and their glorified strike in preventing the European War?</p>
   <p>These apostles showed no "direct action", none whatsoever, to prevent the European countries from entering into a war; they did not even show as much effort as did those who advocate political action. As a united force they failed completely to show any action.</p>
   <p>That is one thing. Another thing, it is apparent from various angles that their proposed weapons of struggle would not have had any success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0992.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Opponents of political action very often declared that if the workers would unite on some beautiful day and make a general railroad strike, then the capitalists and their government would be forced into immediate surrender: because such a nation-wide strike would bring all trade and commerce to a complete standstill and in a few days' time the population of the nation would become short of the most essential things of life. According to their reasoning, that would compel the public to rise against the exploiters of the workers and put an end to their power and existence.</p>
   <p>The facts of the present war prove the above theory to be inaccurate. At the outset of the war, in many localities of the belligerent countries, all railroads were for a certain length of time devoted solely to the transportation of soldiers and ammunition; although the shipment of commodities had ceased, nevertheless, neither the populations of those localities nor the "capitalistic system" experienced any real danger. That condition continued in Germany not for days, but for weeks, and did not even bring about a marked increase in commodity prices.</p>
   <p>It is plainly evident that the capitalists are much more stronger than opponents of political action. Capitalists cannot be exterminated with mere strikes or any other <pb facs="5423970_1_0993.jpg" n="5"/>forms of "direct action".</p>
   <p>Therefore, the present war not only failed to confirm the accuracy of the anarchistic theory against political action, but also served to again prove its impracticability.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
