<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-03-21">Mar. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Inciters of the Workingmen</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-03-21">Mar. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">INCITERS OF THE WORKINGMEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The wave of strikes which accompanied the improvement of business conditions in the United States has encountered much criticism in the capitalist press. They could not openly condemn the workers for fighting for better working conditions because such a condemnation would mean the loss of a host of readers. But the capitalist press is trying to smear the workers and to discredit them before the eyes of the public by "revealing" them to be the tools of Teutonic agents. Wherever a strike occurred, the capitalist newspapers uncovered a German or Austrian "plot".</p>
   <p>Innumerable facts reveal that the strikes were caused, not by the intrigues of foreign agents, but by the miserable plight of the workers of the country. Here is one of these facts: In its annual report the United States Steel Corporation announced that in 1915 the average wage paid to its workers was <pb facs="5423970_1_0421.jpg" n="2"/>$3.01 a day, while in the previous year the average daily wage was "only" $2.97. During a whole year the workers' wages were raised--by all of four cents! Could the workers' in the steel industry be content with their share (four cents) of this "prosperity" when, at the same time, the cost of living had been greatly increased and the profits of the steel trust had reached a figure unheard of in history--$726,683,589?</p>
   <p>During the "prosperous" year of 1915 the plight of the workers had become much worse, despite the few cents that were added to their wages. Real prosperity was experienced only by the capitalists. That is why the workers revolted against their employers. The greatest inciters of the workers to strikes always were and still are our own capitalists, and not the agents of foreign countries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
