<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-05-03">May 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Lithuanians Hold Gigantic Mass Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1918-05-03">May 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO LITHUANIANS HOLD GIGANTIC MASS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A heavy rain early Sunday morning threatened to ruin the mass meeting sponsored by the Lithuanians that day to publicize the Third Liberty Loan. But at noon the rain stopped and the sky cleared. The societies--about a hundred of them--gathered at the locations designated for their divisions and marched, with martial music, to the Seventh Regiment Armory, at Wentworth Avenue and 34th Street.</p>
   <p>The largest divisions were from the Bridgeport and Town of Lake neighborhoods. These divisions, when they were lined up for the parade, seemed to be endless. The monotony of the long lines was broken by Lithuanian military societies and women's societies. The girls and women joined the parade with no less enthusiasm than the men.</p>
   <p>The starry flags of the United States, waving with the new tricolors of the Lithuanians (red, white and green), the thousands of smaller flags, the various signs urging readers to buy Third Liberty Loan bonds, the numerous bands, the <pb facs="5423970_1_1119.jpg" n="2"/>crowds of people, and the hosts of automobiles coming from all sides of the city, made an unusually impressive sight at the Armory. It can be said truly that the Lithuanians of Chicago had never before had such a gigantic meeting.</p>
   <p>In The Hall</p>
   <p>When I entered the gigantic hall, it was almost full. I went up to the gallery from which the speakers were to deliver their speeches. A truly unusual sight was before me: society after society was entering the hall, each accompanied by waving American and Lithuanian flags. In a few minutes the hall became so crowded that, from above, it seemed as if one could walk on the heads of the people below. The flags of the societies lined the middle aisle, from the very front to the doors. A uniformed guard of honor stood at the head of the line of flags.</p>
   <p>The place was crowded to the roof. The parish choirs of Chicago, united under the direction of A. Pocius, occupied at least a half of the left gallery. In front of them stood a girl who wore armor and a shining helmet and represented Lithuania.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1120.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Soon the scheduled speakers appeared on the flag-decorated gallery. There were about eight thousand people in the hall. Many could not get in.</p>
   <p>The Program</p>
   <p>The master of ceremonies was J. Elijosius, president of the Universal State Bank who, with J. I. Bagdziunas, did most of the work of preparation for this mass meeting.</p>
   <p>The program began with the singing of the American and Lithuanian national anthems. Then followed the speeches. Among those who spoke in English were Judge Carter, Congressman-At-Large McCormick, Mr. Streyckmans, a Belgian, Captain J. W. Gorby, president of the Seventh District of the Liberty Loan Campaign, and Attorney Height.</p>
   <p>We do not have the space to write about all the speeches. Noteworthy are the speeches of the last three, who spoke very complimentarily about the Lithuanians. The Belgian likened the fate of Lithuania to that of Belgium. The most important aim of all the speeches was to emphasize the need for faithfulness to America and the necessity of helping her in all possible ways at this time--especially by purchasing Liberty bonds.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1121.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Every reference to Lithuania's liberty and to the crushing of Kaiserism was met by applause which, as the saying goes, shook the walls. If anybody doubted the loyalty of the Lithuanians, if anybody doubted the stand Lithuanians were taking, he had only to take one look at this crowd of thousands and his doubts would immediately have been dispersed.</p>
   <p>The Lithuanians stand body and soul for America, for the liberty of all nations, for the liberty of Lithuania, and for the crushing of Kaiserism and German military power in such a manner that it will never again be enabled to create a similar slaughter in the world.</p>
   <p>Of the Lithuanian speakers on the program, two are noteworthy: Attorney B. K. Balutis, editor of the Lietuva and J. I. Bagdziunas, treasurer of the Universal State Bank, who spoke in English. Besides these, a short speech was delivered by Reverend A. Skripka.</p>
   <p>Attorney B. K. Balutis, speaking in Lithuanian, and, as usual, very beautifully, about Lithuania, compared its pre-war state to the present. Tears rolled down <pb facs="5423970_1_1122.jpg" n="5"/>the cheeks of many people. After that he reminded the audience that, if we wanted liberty for Lithuania, every Lithuanian would have to buy Liberty bonds. In short, Mr. Balutis reminded us of those things which many had forgotten.</p>
   <p>J. Bagdziunas delivered a short but excellent speech in English and, what is more important, presented it in good, clear, beautiful English. Among other things, he mentioned that the Lithuanians would not accept such an independence as is offered by the Kaiser, for it is offered by hands stained by the blood of our brothers; that the Lithuanians expected to attain liberty together with other nations from the hands of the allies of liberty--and, most likely of all, from the hands of Uncle Sam (deafening applause); and that the Lithuanians would devote all their energies to this purpose; that the Lithuanians of America, having gone to France with the American army, having crushed Kaiserism, having crossed Germany, would reach Lithuania and, standing on its earth, would say to their brothers: "Here, we bring you freedom--not the Kaiser's kind, but real freedom." Long and loud applause followed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1123.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Reverend Skripka explained the principles for which the war is now being fought and reminded the audience that America has always been the champion of liberty; Washington fought for the freedom of the American Colonies, Lincoln for the freedom of Negroes, and now President Wilson fights for the freedom not only of small nations, but of the whole world.</p>
   <p>Mr. Elijosius ended the speeches with a word of thanks. The program was varied by occasional songs sung beautifully by the large chorus under the direction of the talented Mr. A. Pocius.</p>
   <p>This mass meeting will long be remembered in the lives of the Lithuanians of Chicago. Much credit is due to its organizers, Mr. J. Elijosius and J. I. Bagdziunas.</p>
   <p>The next morning, all the English newspapers published long articles about this meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
