<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1905-05-19">May 19, 1905</date><title level="a">To Lithuanians Who Are Interested in Learning</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I B 3</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1905-05-19">May 19, 1905</date><title level="a">TO LITHUANIANS WHO ARE INTERESTED IN LEARNING</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2-4.... Through newspaper correspondents, we have learned that many Lithuanians are spending their valuable time in playing cards, drinking, fighting and going to civil courts to settle their arguments. Moreover, they are spending their hard earned cents foolishly, ruining themselves physically as well as morally. They have money to spend for drinking, but they have no money to spend for education, which is the most important item of all. We have no words adequate enough to describe the value of education in life. An education is an asset and a necessity to all individuals today, more than ever before.</p>
   <p>Educated Lithuanians should strongly and consistently urge our people to take advantage of educational opportunities. However, most of our people fail to understand the great good which they can derive from an education. Instead, they would rather travel on the hard road of life, for getting that which education brought about on this earth. We are sorry to see that our people <pb facs="5423970_1_0098.jpg" n="2"/>do not seek learning since it is so valuable to them and humanity.</p>
   <p>Incidently, we will say a few words concerning our daughters. They think that they must wear silk dresses and hats with expensive plumes, but they do not worry about beautifying their brains. Therefore, it is not a bit surprising that those young Lithuanians who have become somewhat educated marry non-Lithuanian girls. It happens that our ladies fail to understand that the shiny case of a watch is not the time-piece itself, and that any watch with a good mechanism can keep good time regardless of the beauty of its case.</p>
   <p>Even silks fail to decorate when the brain is not developed. Usually, we say that it is too late to think of learning when we reach old age. But why is it never too late for English and other nationalities to strive for improvement? They continue their educational pursuits even after they are married and have children. Therefore, it is not at all surprising that they have large factories and become wealthy. Through education they know how to seek riches. Now many of our young men and women could by a little educational effort, hold better positions in the factory, office and store. Therefore, we most heartily hope that our young people will get interested in education.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0099.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Learning is not as hard as it appears to be; nor the cost as great as popularily believed. For instance, at Valparaiso University, a student can find work to defray expenses. All subjects are taught at this university and it is the cheapest place in the United States to gain an education. That is why very poor people seek an education here. Those who are interested are advised to send addresses to the university and ask for a catalogue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
