<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-18">May 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Capitalistic Christianity (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-05-18">May 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Capitalistic Christianity (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In yesterday's issue of the Naujienos (News) we wrote of how the capitalists became seriously concerned with Christianity; we pointed out out that they become so concerned that, in order to increase the influence of Christianity, Mr. John D. Rockefeller proposed at the Cleveland convention of the Young Men's Christian Association the creation of a "Christianity trust". It is a known fact that those capitalists are not concerned with Christian ideals, and they are not interested in reforming Christianity, but they seek to reform that element which says it represents Christianity--more accurately, the Christian church--or the priesthood.</p>
   <p>The priests have become neglectful. They have not been carrying out  with sufficient energy their duty to instill the working people with the spirit <pb facs="5423970_1_0679.jpg" n="2"/>of humbleness and patience, and keep them from grumbling about their material status in life. They have not been fulfilling their main duty which is to incessantly hammer into the heads of the working people the following precept: "Work and pray, work and pray! And do not desire anything on earth so as to lose your opportunity of getting into Heaven." That precept is very precious to the capitalists. The priests must not forget this for it is intended solely for the working people. If a worker follows that precept and prays, then he will not demand from his employer an increase in wages or shorter working hours. If he continues to pray, no matter how bad his economic status in life may be, he will not go against his employer; he will not join any workers' organization, and if he desires an improvement in his economic condition he will not go to his employer but will pray to God and ask Him to have pity on him.</p>
   <p>That is the reason why the capitalists have never opposed the church. That is the reason why Mr. Rockefeller established churches wherever possible, <pb facs="5423970_1_0680.jpg" n="3"/> particularly in the state of Colorado. That is also the reason why the capitalists are so generously supporting the Young Men's Christian Association. Thus very extensive and highly developed organization is fully, with soul and body, in the service of the capitalists (Mr. Rockfeller himself is one of its most active members).</p>
   <p>Many people, especially working people, who are not closely acquainted with the Young Men's Christian Association believe that it is an innocent young peoples' cultural institution. But that is a gross error. The Association is carrying on the same kind of "Christian" work for the benefit of the capitalists as do all priests and ministers. The active clergymen of that organization go into factories and during the noon hour they conduct services, read passages from the Bible, sing holy hymns, and employ other tricks to cloud the minds of the workers. During the past year alone (1915) the clergymen  of the Young Men's Christian Association conducted services in factories <pb facs="5423970_1_0681.jpg" n="4"/>in various towns and cities in which nearly two million workers participated.</p>
   <p>Today in America there is a widely known revivalist of Christianity, known as Billy Sunday, a former athlete. He has a very good throat and has become famous for his efforts to bring back into the Christian fold those who have gone astray. Tens of thousands of people assemble to hear him talk, mostly poor people. And Billy Sunday does not hesitate to threaten those people with devils, flames of hell, and boiling tar. Incessantly he hammers into their heads: work and pray, work and pray! Those Billy Sunday religious revival meetings are arranged for him by capitalists in various towns and cities and they pay him hundreds of thousands of dollars for his services.</p>
   <p>That, then, is the kind of Christianity that is desired by the capitalists: Christianity that will fool the workers. That is the kind of Christianity that is being advocated by our own Lithuanian priests. They not only advocate <pb facs="5423970_1_0682.jpg" n="5"/>it, but are busily engaged in organizing unsuspecting and ignorant people so that they will sacrifice their bodies and souls upon the altar of the capitalists. They have established and control the St. Joseph's Workers Association, the slogan of which is: "Workers of all lands unite for one purpose! And that purpose is very great: Pray and work, pray and work!" The only trouble is that not many people want to pray and work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
