<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-12-18">Dec. 18, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Zinycia Society to Sell Three Hundred New Land Shares</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1908-12-18">Dec. 18, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ZINYCIA SOCIETY TO SELL THREE HUNDRED NEW LAND SHARES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting held last Sunday the directors of the Zinycia Lithuanian - American Colonization Society decided to sell three hundred new shares of the society to raise funds to pay the balance of the cost of the farm lands which had been purchased by the society. The directors have already purchased 138 shares, leaving 162 shares still to be sold. A mass meeting, at which shares will be sold, will be held by the society in Lietuva's building, 3252 So. Halsted Street, on January 3, 1909, at 2:00 P.M. Old shareholders will be given the preference in purchasing more shares. However, everyone who desires to buy shares will be accommodated even if it becomes necessary to issue more shares. The price of each share is $12; the limit to one person is 50 shares.</p>
   <p>It is desirable that new shareholders purchase at least ten shares with <pb facs="5423970_1_1483.jpg" n="2"/>the intention of settling on the land.</p>
   <p>The society has purchased three strips of farm land in the state of Wisconsin, near the city of Thorp, with the purpose of forming a nucleus for a Lithuanian - American agricultural colony. Enough land has been purchased so far to create fourteen good - sized farms. It is planned to erect buildings on the land, and to clear and improve the land this winter for farming and grazing purposes.</p>
   <p>This is an excellent opportunity for Chicago Lithuanians who have a small capital and who are unable to secure decent employment in the city, and for those who would like to settle down on a farm. The land is for sale at $15 and up per acre, for either cash or on time payments.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1484.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The farm land of the society is level, is easy to cultivate, and, judging from other farms in the vicinity, is very fertile. Therefore, those who wish to secure a strip of farm land, work in healthy air, and be their own bosses, should not fail to come to this meeting. For further information apply to the president J. J. Hertmanavicius, 3252 So. Halsted Street, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
