<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 20,
<date when="1893-07-29">July 29, 1893</date><title level="a">We Ought to Have a Lithuanian Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_1503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_1503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. I, No. 20,
<date when="1893-07-29">July 29, 1893</date><title level="a">WE OUGHT TO HAVE A LITHUANIAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most beneficial propositions to our Lithuanians is the establishment of a Lithuanian farm colony.</p>
   <p>There are many Lithuanians in Chicago out of employment, and they cannot get a job. Many Lithuanians are on the edge of starvation and many of them are already starving.</p>
   <p>If there were a Lithuanian farming colony, many unemployed Lithuanians could get help at such a colony.</p>
   <p>It would be beat to organize such a colony of forty Lithuanisan families. Some Lithuanians have a few thousand dollars, but when they have no jobs, their money is going down very fast.</p>
   <p>There is a very good land in Nebraska, the climate is almost like in Lithuania. The land there is cheap.</p>
   <p>If we could organize a colony of forty Lithuanian families, in such a colony they could have churches, schools, and even factories where they could make <pb facs="5423970_1_1504.jpg" n="2"/>necessary things for themselves.</p>
   <p>This is the best solution of unemployment. About one hundred Lithuanians are coming every day to this country to their friends and relatives. Neither the friends nor relatives can help those who come to them because they are unemployed themselves. It would be best for those new friends who come to this country to be sent to such a Lithuanian Where they could get help until the conditions improve.</p>
   <p>Editor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
