<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Naujienos </title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0554</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0554.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE NAUJIENOS <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lithuanian daily Naujienos (News) writes about the fact that the Lithuanian nationalist press has ceased to publish articles dealing with the various disputes among our people, especially about Socialism, in order to devote more space to articles dealing with the raising of money for the relief of Lithuanian ware refugees and for the Lithuanian autonomy fund. For that reason the Naujienos is restless; now the Naujienos will not have anybody to quarrel with. The Naujienos interprets this step by the nationalist press as a sign that the nationalists have recognized that their arguments with the Socialists were erroneous. With this point in mind, the Naujienos invites the nationalists to form a united front with the Socialists.</p>
   <p>The article on this subject in the Naujienos appears to be purposely written in such a manner as to irritate the nationalists, with the aim to revive the disputes and quarrels between the two factions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0555.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Naujienos loves to call others wreckers and quarrel inciters. However, the Naujienos is really the greatest trouble-maker. When others put aside disputes and quarrels in order to devote their time and energy to a useful purpose, then the Naujienos makes another challenge to quarrel by throwing a "glove."</p>
   <p>The nationalists did not come to any realization that their arguments with the Socialists are erroneous. They merely came to the conclusion that it is a waste of valuable time and energy to quarrel with other factions through our newspapers.</p>
   <p>The nationalists believe now more than ever that they did not make a mistake by refusing to form a common front with the Socialists. It is now very clear that if a united front had been made between these factions, it would have led to unpleasant misunderstandings. That this would really happen is proven by Mr. Kapsukas, popular Lithuanian Socialist. The Vienybe Lietuvninku (Unity of Lithuanians) makes the following comment <pb facs="5423970_1_0556.jpg" n="3"/>about Mr. Kapsukas' proposal to secretly send war relief funds to "known and unattached individuals":</p>
   <p>"The proposal by the Socialists to send war relief funds to 'unattached individuals' who are known to them is sheer nonsense. Let us not send any money to persons who are 'known' to the Socialists but unknown to the Lithuanian public! We demand that Lithuania be assisted openly through committees, and not through unattached individuals. Who knows those unattached individuals? They are known only to one or two members of our Socialist faction. And who can vouch for the honesty of an individual who is so little known? Only the individual himself..."</p>
   <p>The above comment is probably sharp, but it is honest in principle and irrefutable. However, the Naujienos might wish to refute it. It offers a good opportunity for a quarrel. It would be a shame if the Naujienos does not take advantage of it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
