<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 2,
<date when="1901-01-11">Jan. 11, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">In the Affairs of the Oppressed Nations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1) (Polish)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>, Vol. IX, No. 2,
<date when="1901-01-11">Jan. 11, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE AFFAIRS OF THE OPPRESSED NATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish Zwiazek-Alliance supports the plan that by  their united power the oppressed nations could publish in English language a newspaper, explaining the wrong done by the oppressors. They also decided to call a convention of the oppressed nations, on February 5, 1901, at Pittsburg. Pa. They elected a committee of the following members: J. H. Jablowski, president; S. Rokosz, vice-president; T. Helinski, secretary: M. Majewski, treasurer; directors; S. Lauferski, M. Steczynski, M. Zolkowski, Dr. K. Zurawski. The address of the Polish committee is: T. Helinski, 102-4 W. Division St., Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>In the articles of the Polish newspapers we see that the Poles and the Lithuanians have a different conception of this problem. It was suggested by Dr. J. Szliupas to issue a newspaper by the oppressed nations. We support the idea and we would like to see the differences forgotten, so as to go forward with this new idea, the unity of the oppressed nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0631.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It seems to us that to organize a Polish republic of the oppressed nations is a one-sided problem. Besides the Poles, we ought to take into consideration the Lithuanians, the Ruthenians and other oppressed nations in Russia, Austria and Germany. In Russia are oppressed the Latvians, Estonians, Finns, and Georgians and Armenians. In Austria besides the Poles and Ruthenians are Czechs, Slovenes, Croatians, etc. Of course in such a short time it is impossible to get at the convention the delegates of all the oppressed nations. In time we will come to a closer acquaintance in America and in Europe, and will be able to reap results. They are many enlightened Lithuanians and Poles in Russia. They can help us spread the idea of unity among the oppressed nations.</p>
   <p>Since the Russian movement started to persecute the Finnish separatists, it is essential for us to get acquainted with them. The more oppressed nations in our union, the stronger our union will be.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0632.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>By working together we must forget the past. In the past much harm was brought not only to Lithuanians but to Ruthenians and to the Poles, by the lack of unity of their own people, between the farm folks and the city intelligentsia. To the old idea that all the small nations should be under the protectorate of Poland, this would bring harm, and we could not bring the oppressed nations to the union in question.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
