<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-02-01">Feb. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Strike at Steinberg and Sopkins Brothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Naujienos</title>,
<date when="1916-02-01">Feb. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">STRIKE AT STEINBERG AND SOPKINS BROTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The female employees of Steinberg and Sopkins Brothers, 343 West Adams Street, went out on strike Saturday. The employees of this firm were on strike about four months ago. They won that strike.</p>
   <p>Before the last strike the girls worked fifty-five and one-half hours a week, and after the strike was settled they only had to work fifty hours a week. The girls' pay was also raised ten per cent. Now, however, the firm has refused to live up to the agreement.</p>
   <p>There was only one thing left for the employees to do--go on strike, which they did on Saturday. Only three girls and six men remained at their jobs out of a total of eighty workers. Most of the workers are immigrant Jewesses, Poles, and, in a few cases, Lithuanians. The spirit of the striking women <pb facs="5423970_1_0426.jpg" n="2"/>is good, and they expect those still at work to join in the strike.</p>
   <p>Steinberg and Sopkins Brothers are manufacturers of popular priced house dresses, aprons, and waists. It is a cheap type of work, but when the pay was raised it was possible for the experienced workers to our eleven dollars a week. Of course, the inexperienced workers could not make that much. When the firm reduced the pay, some of the girls could not make enough money to exist on.</p>
   <p>Strikers' meetings will be held daily at Hull House. The employees are determined to fight their exploiters to the limit of their energies. The exploiters, by breaking their agreement and lowering the wages, seem to care nothing for the rights of their employees.</p>
   <p>Workers, strengthen your organizations!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
