<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-05">Dec. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Golden Wedding Jubilee Celebrated</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423970_1_0278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-04-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-03-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>LITHUANIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Lietuva</title>,
<date when="1913-12-05">Dec. 5, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">GOLDEN WEDDING JUBILEE CELEBRATED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Bonifacas and Mrs. Elena Rutkauskas, who at present live at 3255 South Halsted Street, are, it seems, the first Lithuanians in Chicago to celebrate their golden wedding anniversary. The golden wedding was celebrated the other Sunday at St. George's Church, and the Right Reverend Deacon Matthew Krauciunas said that this golden wedding is the first in St. George's Church, which is the oldest one in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Even though they have reached their honorable age, Mr. and Mrs. Rutkauskas can be called newlyweds: old in years, they are young in spirit and health, which at such an age is a very rare occurrence. The "bridegroom" will this coming Monday be just seventy-one years old, while the "bride" reached the age of seventy-two in February of this year. Both come from the county of Kalwaria, in the province of Suwalki, Lithuania, and this summer marks twenty-five years since they came to America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423970_1_0279.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For many reasons, these two people are worthy of mention. In the first place, this pair is an honorable family. Even though they had no opportunity to secure higher education, they did understand the value of education, and they have done their best to give their children an education. They have both been patriotic Lithuanians, and have brought up their children in the same spirit. Today, one of their sons, Dr. Antanas Rutkauskas is well-known for his activity among Lithuanians. The second son, Vincas Rutkauskas, is manager of a Lithuanian store, the Halsted Furniture House, in Bridgeport. The youngest child, their daughter, Aldona Rutkauskaite [Rutkauskas], was graduated last year as a physician and surgeon, and she now has an office at 3255 South Halsted Street. Her parents live with her.</p>
   <p>The lot of the celebrants has been varied, like that of any other immigrant. They have seen first-hand the coal mines of Pennsylvania and the factories of Connecticut. Always they have had a tendency toward farming, and later on they bought a farm in Wisconsin, where they lived for ten years. Still <pb facs="5423970_1_0280.jpg" n="3"/>later, in order to send their children to school, they moved to Chicago.</p>
   <p>This is a typical pair of the older Lithuanians. They are courteous, friendly, and have sober habits, and as the saying goes, they are people "of healthy and independent mind". They are progressive, and are great lovers of the Lithuanian language and nation. We wish for the honored celebrants of this jubilee that they may live to celebrate their diamond jubilee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
