<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-04">Sept. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">On the Threshold of the School Year (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0100</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0100.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-04">Sept. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE THRESHOLD OF THE SCHOOL YEAR (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next Tuesday the doors of Chicago schools will open in order to admit small armies of little pupils,some of them old friends, some again who will be getting acquainted for the first time with those little steps toward the serious work of real life. By some of them the opening of the school doors will be welcomed with genuine joy and pleasure long and impatiently expected by their young hearts; by others with a feeling of discomfort, with a secret wish that the beginning of the school year might be indefinitely postponed. The first feeling will probably prevail in the majority of pupils who go to school for the first time, because school is something entirely new for them, something about which they have heard much at home, something they desire to learn about from their own experience. They will take with them to school a good deal of curiosity, a desire to see and listen, an ambition which will be noticeable on all their youthful faces.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0101.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Quite different and much less pleasant will be the feelings of the older pupils, boys and girls who, knowing something about school, dislike the idea that school implies certain duties, and in whom the idea of duty gives rise to a feeling of ennui and lassitude. These are the children who have always preferred fun and play to going to school, which, to them, is nothing but an institution which robs them of their free time--time which they would otherwise use to much better advantage at home or on the streets in the company of like-minded chums. The progress, or lack of progress, such children make in school is exactly in proportion to their distaste for studying.</p>
   <p>In cases of that kind it is the duty of the parents, once they become aware of such feelings in their youngsters, to inspire in them if not love for school work, at least interest in it, without which the children will reap only a very questionable benefit, if any, from their school years. It will be up to the parents to preserve and maintain love for school in children who have it, <pb facs="5418478_1_0102.jpg" n="3"/>and, in the case of children who hate school, to counteract the dislike by something that would cause in them a healthier attitude toward study and serious work. But this must be done right at the beginning, as soon as the adverse attitude toward school is recognized. Otherwise all efforts in that direction will be in vain.</p>
   <p>Of course it is true that the interest in school is and should be engendered by the teacher (by her ways of acting, her conduct, her methods of teaching, etc.), but it should be engendered at home in the first place, because the interest engendered at home will always remain the most healthy, more productive one.</p>
   <p>Someone may ask what the best way is of arousing in children an interest in school. This question we shall answer first of all in a negative way by saying, anything but violent means, to say nothing of beating. Once we see that the child does not like to go to school, that it reaches for the book with aversion, <pb facs="5418478_1_0103.jpg" n="4"/>let us not use any violent methods to make it do its duty, such as severe scolding, thrashing, or any other painful means. Nothing would be gained by that, and in all probability the condition would be aggravated, because the child would consider school a source of punishment.</p>
   <p>Hence, let us try something else. Let us point to the advantages school offers to children who like it and who like to study. Let us tell them that life without school education is quite impossible to imagine in these days, let us awaken their ambition, let us lead them to a healthy competition with other children, let them imagine how fine it would be if they would excel over the other kids in school, and promise them, now and then, a little reward--which frequently is quite sufficient to arouse a child's ambition. Should we learn that one or another subject is difficult for the child, that the child lags in it behind the other children, let us try to make the work easier. Let us not force that subject on them. It would be useless. And most of all, let there be no beating, no punishment. Let us help the child by explaining as much as we ourselves know about that subject. Our showing good will and a helpful spirit may engender <pb facs="5418478_1_0104.jpg" n="5"/>the same good will toward the subject in the child. Patience on our part will teach the child patience, and good results will gradually follow.</p>
   <p>Let us always show a friendly attitude toward the children. That alone will produce the desirable interest. And let us never put our own children to shame before other children, because that would create and nourish stubborn contrariness, which would prove most dangerous to their further development and would destroy any good results of our former efforts. If we want our children to receive the proper benefit from their school years, it is necessary to be most careful, as one faulty step may result in just the opposite of what we had wished to achieve.</p>
   <p>Parents should keep all this well in mind. And they should also keep in mind something else which we should like to impress upon them. There are many Bohemian schools here in Chicago. Our public, English-language schools are most important for the children's future. But it would be not only wrong, but also unjust to attribute a minor importance to our Bohemian schools. By doing <pb facs="5418478_1_0105.jpg" n="6"/>so we would prejudice ourselves, but first of all our children. What we want is that our children shall have a certain degree of respect, if not love, for the language of their fathers and mothers, or, at least, that they should not despise it. Even the Bohemian language will serve them in good stead some day--if for nothing else, than for use in contacts with their nearest kin, with the people in whom the same blood pulsates as in themselves. Let us, therefore, send our children not only to public schools but also to our own Bohemian schools. Let us awaken their interest in both of them. Their interest in public schools is a matter of life's necessity. Their interest in Bohemian schools is a matter of our own pride, of our hopes, which should never be nourished by the substance of which dreams are made, but by stern reality.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
