<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-15">Dec. 15, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Czech Language in the High Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0292</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0292.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-15">Dec. 15, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECH LANGUAGE IN THE HIGH SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We stand upon the threshold of an event very important to our national life: The introduction of the Czech language in our high schools is to become a reality very soon, for Mrs. Ella Flagg-Young, the superintendent of Chicago schools, promised that she will recommend in the January meeting of the Board of Education that the Czech language be introduced wherever a sufficient number of pupils apply. It must be added that no language is compulsory, but that each student has the right to choose the language which he wishes to study. Where there are no pupils it will be impossible to teach the Czech language, and for that reason a proclamation was issued by the Česko-Amerikou Národní Radou (Bohemian-American National Council) calling upon the parents of Czech children in the high schools to send their names and addresses to the Bohemian-American National Council as soon as possible so that Czech classes can be organized just as soon as Mrs. Young's recommendation has been voted on. The Council has several such applications on hand already.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0293.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is necessary, however, that all those whom it concerns should send their names.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Young's promise was made to the secretary of the Bohemian-American National Council, Professor Jaroslav J. Zmrhal, over a month ago when he was discussing with her the lectures now being given in the public schools. She spoke highly of them and showed genuine interest in the activities of the Bohemian-American National Council.</p>
   <p>"Activities such as these have been needed for a long time," she said; "up to the present the chasm between the school and the home was almost too great. From what the Bohemian-American National Council is doing for the Czechs, there will follow benefits not only for the Czechs but for the city and state as well, because from children brought up in that way there will grow up a generation of enlightened citizens."</p>
   <p>This is the first time that we Czechs have been met with such willingness.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0294.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our cause was recognized without pressure, simply on the basis of rational arguments and national equality. To be sure, there was much ork attached to it; however, it was and is a work crowned with success.</p>
   <p>Our Bohemian member of the Chicago Board of Education, Mr. J. B. Dibelka, is working diligently for the success of our cause and this week will present to Mrs. Young the representative committee of the Bohemian-American National Council which will make the formal request for the introduction of the Czech language as a course of study in the high schools.</p>
   <p>Another important activity was begun by Mr. Dibelka, in that he is investigating conditions in the high schools and gathering statistics on the Czech pupils so that the introduction of the Czech language will not remain a dead subject, but so that the organization of classes can be commenced as soon as Mrs. Young's recommendation is acted upon by the School Board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
