<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-04">Sept. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian Language in High Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0247</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0247.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-04">Sept. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN LANGUAGE IN HIGH SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On September 7, the new school year will start and our youth will again be filling the school buildings. In the Harrison High School, on Marshall Boulevard and 24th Street, the Bohemian language will be taught again as one of the modern languages, and it is up to Bohemian parents to see to it that all Bohemian classes are full.</p>
   <p>This will be the fourth year of Bohemian instruction in Harrison High School, and the interest in the Bohemian classes has been growing from year to year. Both the students and their parents realize the importance of a thorough knowledge of the Bohemian language. In the first place, the Bohemian language has a practical value as a means of contact with the Bohemians, the Slovaks, and the Poles, but, by having a knowledge of Bohemian, we also maintain our traditions and national unity which, based upon mutual help, is a guarantee of our growth.</p>
   <p>In these stirring times when it seems that the morning star of a better future <pb facs="5418478_1_0248.jpg" n="2"/>has risen for the Bohemian nation, let there be no Bohemian high-school student who will not enroll in a Bohemian class. Let him or her do it in his own interest and as a token of reverence to the nation of which he or she is a descendant.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian teacher at the Harrison High School will be Mr. Jaroslav V. Nigrin, S.B., A.M., who taught Romance languages and mathematics in high schools last year.</p>
   <p>Pupils of Bohemian schools who furnish proof of their attendance at Bohemian classes in public high schools will receive the respective credit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
