<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-07">Dec. 7, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to Czech Parents</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-07">Dec. 7, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO CZECH PARENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The request of the Cesko-Americká Národní Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), that the Bohemian language be introduced as an elective course of study in the high schools of Chicago, will be discussed at the January meeting of the Chicago Board of Education. Its request, which is not unreasonable when we take into consideration the multitude of Czechs settled in Chicago, as well as their industrial and political maturity, is supported by the National Council with a list of practical and logical reasons which will surely be taken into consideration in responsible circles. But the most convincing reason is the resolute desire of the Bohemian people that the Czech language be introduced as a course of study in the high schools, and chiefly the desire of those Czech parents who either are sending or expect to send their children to the high schools and who want to use the privilege of the study of the Czech language to their advantage. The school authorities are willingly meeting the wishes of the citizens and there is not the least doubt that the request of the Czech parents will be <pb facs="5418478_1_0296.jpg" n="2"/>granted, if sufficient interest, supported by numerous proofs, is shown in the whole idea. It is absolutely unthinkable that the school board would introduce into the educational system of the schools something which could not be appreciated and of which advantage would not be taken. It is needless to have such fears; least of all about the position of introducing the Czech language into the high schools. Today, the Bohemian-American National Council already has a whole mass of concurring and sympathetic communications from the ranks of Czech parents who welcomed the idea, not only as a new recognition of Czech rights and a new proof of our cultural maturity, but primarily as a really practical step, which aside from the educational question will mean chiefly the strengthening of our Bohemianism where it is fundamentally needed--among our student youth. Nevertheless, the desire of the Bohemian--American National Council is that the number of these concurring communications be as large as possible, so that there will not be the slightest doubt about the logic and justice of our request. For that reason, the Bohemian-American National Council turns to all Czech parents who are sending or expect to send their children to high school.... <pb facs="5418478_1_0297.jpg" n="3"/>and likewise to all our influential persons and circles taking an interest in the idea, so that, in this project--the introduction of the Czech language into the high schools--they may be of assistance. Our lodges are holding their annual meetings this month and this question ought to receive due attention and fitting resolutions should be adopted at these meetings. Where only an individual is concerned, it is sufficient to give merely the name and address, but so far as a lodge is concerned, it is necessary to give the name of the lodge or union and, is some cases, the number of members.</p>
   <p>All these concurring communications should be sent to the address of the organizer of the Bohemian-American National Council, Mr. Enrique Stanko Vraz, 1817 South Millard Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>There is not the slightest doubt that the desire of the Bohemian-American National Council will find proper response and quick fulfillment among our Czech parents and the ranks of our lodges.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
