<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-22">Apr. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">First Graduation Exercises of a New School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0398</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0398.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-22">Apr. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST GRADUATION EXERCISES OF A NEW SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Parish of the Blahoslavena Anezka Ceska (Blessed Agnes of Bohemia) which is the largest Czechoslovak Catholic Parish in Chicago, has not only a parochial grammar school which was consecrated and opened way back in 1905, but also a high school, which affords grammar school graduates an opportunity of continuing their studies....This latter school was established in 1920 at a cost of $3,000 and started out as a two-year business school. At the very start there were twenty registrants. The teacher was the revered Sister Amadea who endeavored to bring the school to a high degree of excellence. The students, too, did their best to progress. There can be no wonder, therefore, that praises and recognition began to come at the end of the first year of their study activity, and that medals and diplomas for excellence continued to be awarded to the students.</p>
   <p>The student body persevered, and with only two exceptions remained enrolled in the course for the entire duration of it. The commencement exercises are to <pb facs="5418478_1_0399.jpg" n="2"/>take place tomorrow in the hall of the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs on South Lawndale Avenue near west 26th Street. [Names of graduates are omitted in translation.] The graduation program, which was arranged by both the Parish and the school, will be rich. The school slogan is "Modli Se A Pracuj" (Pray and Work), and the school colors are blue and gold. The program itself consists of vocal and instrumental music, recitations in the Czech language, and a one-act play in the English language. Mr. Jaroslav Cermak's band is to play during the evening following the commencement exercises.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
