<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-02">May 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Board of Education Yesterday Resolved That Bohemian and Other Living Languages May Be Taught in Public Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0286</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0286.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-02">May 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOARD OF EDUCATION YESTERDAY RESOLVED THAT BOHEMIAN AND OTHER LIVING LANGUAGES MAY BE TAUGHT IN PUBLIC SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A matter, the settlement of which has long been eagerly awaited by the whole Bohemian people was finally brought to a vote in yesterday's meeting of the Board of Education. The request of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) that the Bohemian language be taught in the public schools was discussed and acted upon. As we know, the superintendent of schools, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, spoke in favor of the request, and our representative on the school board, Mr. Vaclav Dibelka, worked zealously for its approval. Their efforts met with complete success.</p>
   <p>Because the Swedes and other nationalities who have settled here expressed the same desire as the Bohemians, the motion was worded so that any living language may be taught for which there are a sufficiently large number of requests to warrant the appointment of a teacher. A large majority of the board members voted favorably on the matter, there being only four dissenting votes.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0287.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It now rests with Bohemian parents to make use of this opportunity by having their children apply for these courses. The Ceska Narodni Rada will surely give them further advice and information.</p>
   <p>It was also decided in yesterday's meeting not to teach sex hygiene in the public schools, as was requested by some persons. The motion was defeated at a private conference held in the office of the president of the Board of Education. A compromise of sorts was arrived at in that $2,500 was set aside for the teaching of parents along these lines by the holding of meetings in the assembly halls of schools.</p>
   <p>A school census will be instituted today, and it is expected that the enumeration will be completed in the course of three weeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
