<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-05">Aug. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Our Wasteful School Board</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-08-05">Aug. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">OUR WASTEFUL SCHOOL BOARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Joseph A. Holpuch, the Bohemian member of the Chicago Board of Education, testified yesterday before an investigating committee of the State Senate, whose purpose it is to study thoroughly the methods by which the School Board conducts its business, and to look into all matters connected therewith. Mr. Holpuch's depositions caused a sensation among the large audience, in which there were several members of the School Board and many teachers (women) belonging to the Teachers' Federation. According to the testimony of Mr. Holpuch, the million-dollar deficit of the School Board is due to its wastefulness, its antiquated methods, and its lack of carefulness.</p>
   <p>From Mr. Holpuch's testimony, the following is of particular importance: The School Board needs an efficiency expert. A good man would save it from $200,000 to $500,000 a year, no matter how high a salary he might be paid. The organization is so loose and so inefficient that many things are being done twice and an enormous amount of money is plainly wasted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0358.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to Mr. Holpuch, the present system is an invitation to graft in large proportions. He discussed, first of all, the department in charge of repairs, and maintained that, as it is now, the School Board pays more for repairing articles than it would cost to buy new ones. Any employee can take whatever he wants, because no record is kept of anything. He has been told that an employee of the repair department has built two houses for himself of bricks left after the wrecking of school buildings. It was Mr. Holpuch's intention to investigate this case for himself, but he could not get anywhere.</p>
   <p>Replying to a question put to him by the lawyer of the investigating committee, Meyer J. Stein, Mr. Holpuch said: "The School Board is a huge business enterprise. If it were mine I should close it down and should not start doing business until it had been reorganized. It is much more difficult to run a business with a turnover of $100,000 than to run the School Board, which spends $18,000,000 a year. This is because the Board members are "good fellows" who don't mind spending when they spend City money. Of course, they would be much more careful if it were their own money, or if it were a question of spending it in their own business enterprise."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
