<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-24">Sept. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Meeting Held by the Taxpayers Improvement Club of the Eleventh Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-24">Sept. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE MEETING HELD BY THE TAXPAYERS IMPROVEMENT CLUB OF THE ELEVENTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular meeting of the Eleventh Ward Taxpayers Club held on September 21 was fairly well attended. The committee, to which was referred the matter of protesting against the tax burden for the widening of Twelfth Street, reported that it had agreed with the Tenth Ward Club on common action and it was found that it is impossible to do anything now, before it is known how things will develop. A report was made that the West Park Board has decided to expropriate (sic) the land between Twelfth and Eighteenth Streets, and Wood and Lincoln Streets for a small park, which report was received with joy. A lengthy debate ensued about the care of alleys in which the accumulation of waste matter does not permit the drainage of water, making the alleys unhealthy. It was decided that the Department of Street Improvements should be asked to have the alleys graded in order that the water will have drainage and in order that in time the <pb facs="5418478_1_1598.jpg" n="2"/>alleys can be paved. Further it was resolved that the Board of Local Improvements should be requested to order the owners of the lime kilns, like any other mortals, to provide cement sidewalks. Also protest was made against the dumping in empty lots of street dirt which the wind carries into the neighborhood houses. It was decided that Mr. F. Svoboda should draw up the protests which should be signed by all officers and delivered to the proper places.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
