<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-11">July 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">School Board News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-11">July 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL BOARD NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When we talked with the Bohemian member of the Chicago Board of Education, Mr. Josef A. Holpuch, he told us that we should not be surprised to see him putting forth all possible efforts toward securing any necessary or desirable improvements for the new Carter H. Harrison High School. He had made up his mind, he said, to make that school one of the most perfect ones not only in Chicago but in the whole country. Evidently the school has "grown to his heart," as the saying goes, and because he knows that it will be receiving consideration only as long as there is a Bohemian on the Board, he considers it his duty to do for it all he can. Nobody knows whether he, or any other Bohemian who would take particular care of that school, will be sitting on the Board during the next term. Therefore, he wants to use the time until the end of this current term to do for the school all he can, and all that would add to the prestige of the Bohemian people in Chicago, whose children form over <pb facs="5418478_1_0114.jpg" n="2"/>seventy-five per cent of the pupils of that school. He does not do this for his own sake but for the sake of the good name of Chicago Bohemians, not only those living here now, but also those who will come after us. For them, he wants to leave the proof that he was not merely "sitting" on the Board, but that he was doing some good work there.</p>
   <p>More recently he again succeeded in securing for the school a number of advantages about which our public will be glad and interested to learn. The School Superintendent, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, because of the deficit which has been threatening the Board for some time, declared the following principle: as an economy measure, to take on no new teachers. Board Member Holpuch disagreed with this principle, and, maintaining that there must be as many teachers as are necessary, he requested a number of additional teachers for the Harrison High School. In doing this he pointed out that in that school is Chicago's most beautiful and most expensive swimming pool--it cost $150,000 to build--which is being used only by the school janitor and his family because there <pb facs="5418478_1_0115.jpg" n="3"/>are no teachers in the Harrison High School to teach the pupils how to swim. Under such conditions the pool is useless, and for that reason he requested the appointment of several swimming instructors. The finance committee, upon his most urgent demand, appropriated enough funds for two instructors, one man and one woman, who will work there half the time during eight months for the compensation of $110 a month. But the condition of their appointment is that they will teach gymnastics also. In another instance, Mr. Holpuch referred to a number of additions built to the school about a year and a half ago which were to provide for instruction in various trades and arts. So far they have not served so because the necessary machinery, etc., has not been installed, and, also because there have not been any instructors. Because of the pressure he exercised in this respect, three instructors have been approved, one for printing, one for the tinsmith shop, and one for metal plating. The appropriation for this purpose is $2,200. The subjects will be taught in four-month courses, and the teacher will receive six dollars per teaching day. In addition to this, the cabinetmaking course and the woodworking course will <pb facs="5418478_1_0116.jpg" n="4"/>be continued with the change that all pupils of the Harrison High School who have been taking such courses elsewhere, will receive their instruction in their own school. When all the courses planned for the Harrison High School are opened, the school will be attended by more than seven thousand students, and hence it will be the largest high school in the country as far as the number of pupils is concerned.</p>
   <p>When the 1915 budget was made, Mr. Holpuch succeeded in receiving the appropriation of $352,000 for the Harrison High School, this money to be used for various improvements, particularly the purchase of machinery for the established shops. He succeeded in getting this appropriation against the protest of Chairman Collins himself, who favors the schools in Austin and vicinity, because, as an owner of much real estate in these parts, he is personality interested in their reputation and advancement. Mr. Holpuch, who was determined to get the mentioned amount for his "Bohemian" school, agreed with Mr. Collins on a compromise.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0117.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>He promised to vote for Mr. Collins' requirements for Austin, and Mr. Collins agreed to his in the Harrison High School. The result was that the Harrison High School, in spite of the finance committee, which reduced the requested amount to a mere $40,000, will receive $352,000, which is more than all the other twenty-one high schools in Chicago will receive altogether. There is only one string attached to this appropriation: The purchase of the necessary machinery will be postponed until the prices of iron, steel, and other metals, now very high because of the war in Europe, drop down to normal levels.</p>
   <p>The school's immediate vicinity will soon be cleaned up. That is, there will be no buildings around it. The last of them will be expropriated at the end of this month, so that the whole site will become property of the School Board, which will have it leveled by filling or removing parts that need such treatment, and fenced. The City Hall will no doubt give the title to the alleys on the ground to the School Board, and then a huge playground will be made there, the largest for miles around. There will be a long track, tennis courts,</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0118.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>football ground, place for ball games, etc. There will be seats for spectators all around the ground, erected by the pupils learning carpentry and cabinetmaking. We call the attention of our Sokol units and other organizations to the fact that they will be able to get free use of the playground upon application to the School Board, which application it would be best to put into the hands of its member, Mr. Holpuch.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
