<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-28">May 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Twelfth Annual Convention of the United Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Ladies Win Special Recognition (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0588</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0588.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-28">May 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TWELFTH ANNUAL CONVENTION OF THE UNITED SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Ladies Win Special Recognition (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Wicker Park Hall, Milwaukee and Grand Avenues, was the scene of the twelfth annual convention of the United Societies yesterday afternoon. Mr. Kramer, the presiding officer, pointed out that it was the United Societies which thwarted almost every attempt of the prohibitionist element to restrict personal liberty by means of laws, etc.....There were 974 delegates representing 1,079 societies.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak, secretary, read the annual report, which shows an increase in membership to 253,203 in 1,099 societies and corporations.</p>
   <p>Judge Joseph Uhlir of the Municipal Court, speaking from the experience which he gained during four years on the bench, declared that most of the cases <pb facs="5418478_1_0589.jpg" n="2"/>before the Morals' Court originated in the large hotels located downtown, where hundreds of girls are being intoxicated and then seduced. Not a single similar case of delinquency among girls frequenting the decent Czech, German, or Polish halls has been brought before his court as yet. If anything can be done to protect the young women, then the first step should be taken against the big places in the Loop. The speaker urged a change in the system of dealing with girls who are on the wrong path. A special institution should be created for these girls, because the jail has a decidedly bad influence upon their characters. "Demands in this direction up to this time have had the effect of a voice in the desert," the Judge declared in conclusion.</p>
   <p>Mr. Leopold Neumann, organizer of the Societies, in making his report, paid special tribute to the activities of our Czech ladies. He mentioned Mrs. Velik and Mrs. Zenisek as particularly ardent members.</p>
   <p>A resolution against the Bismarck Garden and Bismarck Hotel, submitted by the bailiffs' organization, was referred to the executive committee. It contained <pb facs="5418478_1_0590.jpg" n="3"/>the statement that the above-mentioned corporation steadfastly refuses to deal with union labor and the United Societies.</p>
   <p>Judge Bernard Barasa of the Municipal Court declared that though certain people resented his membership in the United Societies, he felt that he adhered strictly to the law in all his decisions, and that he could not be biased by nationality, color, creed, or political party; also that no group of female reformers could make him swerve from his principles.</p>
   <p>Alderman John Toman took issue with the Barbour bill, which he terms a "corpse which has been buried ten times and dug out as often again". As the City Council was unable to do anything with it, some people carried it to the State Legislature. There are at this time twelve "wet" members on the license committee, and so the Barbour bill remains but a scarecrow. The petition against nation-wide prohibition has been signed by fifty aldermen. Seventeen refused to sign, and three were absent, Alderman Toman stated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0591.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Czech corporations and societies will be represented in the executive committee by the following Czech-Americans: John A. Cervenka, Joseph Placek.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
