<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-07">Dec. 7, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Matice VyŠŠÍHo VzdĔLÁNÍ</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Report of Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani for the Fiscal Year 1910-1911</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-07">Dec. 7, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MATICE VYŠŠÍHO VZDĔLÁNÍ</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Report of Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani for the Fiscal Year 1910-1911</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eighth administrative year of the Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání (Council for Higher Education), closed with the termination of the 1910-1911 school year. The Executive Committee hereby....renders its annual report to the public, especially to the numerous national societies and individuals who supported this organization materially and morally and who are interested in its activities.</p>
   <p>The Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání is fulfilling the task....of making loans to indigent students and encouraging Czech youth to [secure] higher education, so that they may in the future successfully compete with citizens of other nationalities with whom they will come in contact.....We report <pb facs="5418478_1_0368.jpg" n="2"/>with pleasure that this task is properly understood by our wards.</p>
   <p>In addition to many requests for information, the office of the Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání, during the past year, received a total of thirty requests for loans. It can be noticed with satisfaction that the real purpose of this organization is now better understood than was the case in the earlier years of its existence.....The largest loan received by any individual for a single school year amounted to $250; the smallest was $75; the average per student was $168. The total amount of loans made was $2,685.</p>
   <p>Aid was extended to thirteen male and three female students during the past year. According to States, students were given assistance as follows: Illinois, 3; Iows, 2; Nebraska, 2; New York, 2; Texas, 2; Pennsylvania, 1; Michigan, 1; Wisconsin, 1; Missouri, 1; and Minnesota, 1.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0369.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>According to institutions at which they studied, students were divided as follows: Illinois, 1; Iowa, 2; Missouri, 1; Nebraska, 2; Texas, 1; Wisconsin, 1; Washington, 1; Chicago University, 1; Cornell University (New York), 1; Columbia University (New York), 1; Pennsylvania State College, 1; Texas State Normal, 1; Minnesota State Normal, 1; Olivet College (Michigan), 1.</p>
   <p>Due to the generosity and support of the societies and numerous individuals, the Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání thus far has not had to refuse any really deserving case because of a lack of funds in its treasury. Nevertheless, no one should think that there is a surplus or an idle fund in the Matice's treasury. On the contrary, in this report the executive committee feels compelled to call attention to the fact that with the closing of the financial report, the treasury shows a very small balance, barely sufficient to aid students during this school year. Because this <pb facs="5418478_1_0370.jpg" n="4"/>report is issued after all students have been to their schools, we can say in passing that during the present school year, 1911-1912, the Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání is assisting sixteen students, to whom aid amounting to $2,915 was granted for this year. It must also be considered that this undertaking is growing, and that in the future more and more applications can be expected. For that reason, the executive committee hereby calls upon our Bohemian national societies and generous individuals for continued support, so that the work of the Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani may be continued with success during the next year.</p>
   <p>In presenting this annual report of the activities of the Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání during its eighth administrative year, we beg all friends, donors and people of good will, to give it their attention. At the same time, we hereby express sincere gratitude to all donors and friends for their contributions. In closing we take the liberty to again emphasize that <pb facs="5418478_1_0371.jpg" n="5"/>this undertaking can fulfill its cultural and humanitarian mission only with the effective help of our Bohemian-American people. Therefore, we take the liberty of submitting a sincere and urgent supplication for all to remain favorably inclined toward the Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání, and to support it in its efforts, both morally and materially. We are also seeking new patrons and friends and we beg them not to refuse their aid to this undertaking. We also ask all those into whose hands this report will come, to call attention to this organization and endeavor to gain many new friends for it.</p>
   <p>For the Executive Committee of the Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání:</p>
   <p>B. Šimek, chairman;</p>
   <p>P. A. Korab, secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0372.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Financial Report of the Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání from July 1910 to July 31, 1911</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: List of individual contributors, two columns, omitted.]</p>
   <p>Contributions (by States)</p>
   <p>Nebraska, $170.65; Maryland, $26,00; Wisconsin, $81.90; Ohio, $70; Missouri, $68; Iowa, $207.30; Illinois, $400.50; Texas, $290.25; Arkansas, $5; Oklahoma, $14.50; Montana, $10; Michigan, $10; North Dakota, $10; Pennsylvania, $13; New Jersey, $5; Kansas, $9; Minnesota, $21.25; California, $2; South Dakota, $10; New York, $7.95; total $1,432.30.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0373.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>New York, $400; Michigan, $200; Missouri, $200; Illinois, $310; Texas, $325; Wisconsin, $200; Pennsylvania, $200; Nebraska, $225; Iowa, $400; Washington, $150; Minnesota, $75; total $2,685.</p>
   <p>Repaid by Students (by States)</p>
   <p>Ohio, $200; Illinois, $485; Nebraska, $100; New York, $50; Oklahoma, $20; total $855.</p>
   <p>Recapitulation</p>
   <p>Cash in treasury July 26, 1910, $2,799.13; contributions from individuals $356.05. Contributions from societies: the Cesko-Slovanské Pedporujici <pb facs="5418478_1_0374.jpg" n="8"/>Spolky (Czech-Slavonic Benevolent Societies), $236.50; the lodges of the Západní Česko-Bratrská Jednota (Western Bohemian Fraternal Association), $157; the lodges of the Jednota Ceských Dam (Bohemian Women's Union), $84; the lodges of the Sesterská Podporující Jednota (Mutual Benevolent Sisterhood), $112; the lodges of the Slovenské Podporující Jednoty Statu Texas (Slovak Benevolent Society of the State of Texas), $155.50; miscellaneous lodges, $160.95. Interest from bank deposits, $78.80; interest from the Vojtech Mašek Endowment Fund, $40.40; interest from the Joseph Dusil Endowment Fund, $10.10; loans repaid by students, $885. The grand total is $5,086.43. Loans to students for the year 1910-1911, $2,685. Balance in treasury, $2,401.43.</p>
   <p>National Stamps [Seals]</p>
   <p>Cash on hand July 26, 1910, $418.70. Miscellaneous receipts for national stamps, $59.85; interest from bank deposits, $10.79. Total $489.34.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0375.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Disbursements</p>
   <p>Postage, $47.25; for journal Komensky, $195; incorporation fee, $1.50; envelopes, $1.10; secretarial work, Mr. J. Štĕpan, $75; total $319.85. Balance in treasury, $169.49.</p>
   <p>Financial Summary</p>
   <p>Cash on hand in Matice Vyššího Vzdĕlání treasury, $2,401.43; national stamps, $169.49; Bohemian-American Endowment Fund, $590.92; Joseph Dusil Endowment Fund, $250; Vojtech Mašek Endowment Fund, $1,000; total cash as of July 31, 1911, $4,411.84.</p>
   <p>Joseph Mĕkota, financial secretary;</p>
   <p>W. F. Severa, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
