<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-01-20">Jan. 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">For a New School and a New Gymnasium</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-01-20">Jan. 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">FOR A NEW SCHOOL AND A NEW GYMNASIUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Preparations for two buildings in "Czech California" are being pushed with great vigor for the edifices are destined to play an important part in the life of the Czech population of the district. One is the school, Vojta Naprsteck, on 26th and Homan ave., the other the gymnasium of the Sokol Havlicek, on Lawndale ave., near 26th st.</p>
   <p>The old school has been in need of a building for a long time, to centralize its activities and to keep the classes under one roof, again, the old gymnasium has proved utterly inadequate for the accommodation of the ever increasing numbers of the Sokol association, which began and prospered in the old locality, but now has outgrown its size. The two buildings will not only meet a pressing demand of the astoundingly thriving district, but will no doubt have a decorative effect as well.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0426.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The bids of the contractors for the school, will be opened Monday in the chambers of the Sokol Chicago gymnastic society. An outlay of $45,000 was originally planned; the sum was lowered to $25,000, as some of the leaders, Mr. Richard Dusil and a few others excepted, were afraid to go too deep into debt. The drawings were worked out in the offices of Architect Jan Klucina. They are generally acknowledged as meeting the requirements of usefulness and beauty.</p>
   <p>The school has now six classes, four on Kedzie ave., and two on Homan ave.; the six classes in the new building are to accommodate one hundred children. The building committee will be composed of Mr. Richard Dusil, president, Mr. Adolph Rys, Mrs. Marie Stepanek, and Mr. J. F. Fisher; the construction will be started toward the end of March.</p>
   <p>The site for the gymnasium is valued at $3,500. The plans were prepared in the offices of architects Ludvik Novy &amp; Son. The cost of the building <pb facs="5418478_1_0427.jpg" n="3"/>is to be $35,000, which will be contributed in shares. The gymnastic society has two hundred male members, eighty members in the women's section and about 150 members in the junior division. The preliminary work, propaganda and support, as well as the actual erection, are in the hands of a committee of twelve Sokols whose names follow: Velan, Jakoubek, Zeman, Prochazka, Benes, Kier, Krametbauer, Cermak, Zeman, Raska, Vlsen, and Martinek.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
