<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-14">July 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From the Czech Bureau</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0709</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0709.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-14">July 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE CZECH BUREAU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If Chicago Czechoslovaks were ever accorded flattering recognition, they certainly received it last Friday in a meeting of the Immigrant League. Representatives of thirty-three nationalities of Chicago were gathered in the La Salle Hotel; Mr. Felix J. Streyckman presided. Czechs were represented by Messrs. Anton J. Cermak, F. G. Hajicek, and Joseph J. Salat. Mr. Streyckman spoke of the memorable meeting at the tomb of George Washington at Mount Vernon. President Wilson delivered an address, the essence of which was the assurance that the World War, this great tragedy, will not be ended until the main purpose is attained--to wit, the utter defeat of the enemy and the liberation of all small nations now groaning under foreign rule.</p>
   <p>The press has already informed our people that Mr. Karel (Charles) Pergler was in the President's party on that significant occasion, representing the Czechoslovaks. The President was at that time assured of the infinite <pb facs="5418478_1_0710.jpg" n="2"/>loyalty of the immigrants.</p>
   <p>In the La Salle Hotel meeting, the Fourth of July celebration was discussed, and right there the participation by the Czechoslovaks was pointed out as having been the most impressive in manner as well as in compass. The celebration by the Chicago Czechoslovaks is spoken of all over the United States as of overwhelming magnitude, and is pointed out as a shinning example to all other nationalities. Professor Miller of Oberlin College declared that 75,000 immigrants took part in the New York celebration. This number is below that of the celebrating Chicago Czechoslovaks alone!</p>
   <p>Professor Miller, by the way, enjoys a world reputation. He spoke with great enthusiasm of the Czechoslovak nation. It was a real pleasure for us to hear how correctly he pronounced the word "Czechoslovak". A speech of the same tenor was made by another man who occupies a high position in American life, Mr. Middlebore, first assistant to the Adjutant General of the State of Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0711.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Representatives of other nationalities also paid remarkable attention to the cause of the Czechoslovaks. Jews, Italians, and the French celebrants symbolized the aims of the Czechoslovaks on their allegorical floats. The Czechoslovak delegates had to listen to so much praise throughout the meeting that finally Mr. Cermak deemed it fit to say a few words in response. He expressed sincere thanks for the recognition, while declaring that the Czechoslovaks did nothing but what they considered to be their duty. They do not expect to be singled out for praise. The only compensation they hope for is what really belongs to them, and that is justice.</p>
   <p>This meeting will not be forgotten.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
