<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-26">Nov. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Republican Institutions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1223</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1223.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-26">Nov. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR REPUBLICAN INSTITUTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that our republican institutions have several faults and defects which are not found in the political make-up of other countries. This has been said many times. The governments of European countries have a greater responsibility than our government. One of the points in this respect is the budgeting of appropriations and the passing of appropriations proper. In European countries, whether they have a real constitution like that of France and England or a half-baked one like that of Austria and Germany, the government, or the council of ministers, makes up the budget and carries the full responsibility for it. The ministers and other high government officials make careful computations of money that will be needed and what it will be spent for, present their budget draft to the Diet or parliament for unconditional approval, as in Austria and Germany or for minor changes, as in France and England. But no important changes are permitted, or the <pb facs="5418478_1_1224.jpg" n="2"/>government would consider it an expression of lack of confidence and would immediately submit its resignation. As a result of this system, the European governments break about even and do not run into great debt in spite of enormous amounts of money spent on the army and armaments.</p>
   <p>Here in America, the budget is prepared by the Congressmen--in other words, by about five hundred people. Of course, in each house there is a budget committee, but every Congressman has the right to correct this or that, whatever suits or doesn't suit him or his particular needs. The result is that every one of them tries to grab off the biggest chunk for himself, that is for his district and his constituents, without regard for the good of the country as a whole. Then the trading and the compromising starts. Some appropriations are cut down a bit, some passed in view of a reciprocal favor. The man with the greatest influence and following gets the most. If one of them wants the others to vote for him, he has to vote for them and their petty or pet schemes. This method leads to such scandals as last year's "pork barrel" affair, which was Democratic, but not any worse smelling than previous <pb facs="5418478_1_1225.jpg" n="3"/>similar Republican affairs, though there has been less ado about the latter.</p>
   <p>A sharp observer, Englishman Bryce, who knew America very well and wrote a long book about our institutions, has said: "Under this system, America wastes many millions every year. But the country is so rich and its assets so elastic that it can stand these methods without even feeling them. It is a young country and can afford such mistakes without particular damage."</p>
   <p>But America will not remain eternally young. The time will come when it will start feeling the results of her mistakes and her sins. Then it will be up to us--Bohemians, Poles, Germans, Americans, immigrants, and native-born citizens--to do something about it. Have our leaders started to think along these lines?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
