<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-03">July 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Czech Question in German Light (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0772</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0772.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-03">July 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECH QUESTION IN GERMAN LIGHT (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local German language papers are giving much attention to conditions in Austria, and the situation of the Czech people, its exertions and demands. Two Chicago German papers published editorials about the issue in their last Sunday editions. The Illinois Staats-Zeitung, in an editorial by an American-Austrian, exhibits rabidly anti-Czech views, blaming the Czechs for everything evil. The Sonntagspost, the other paper, was formerly read by some "also Czechs" who want to remain loyal to the "whole homeland," and are convinced that the German language is "something better," and superior to the Czech language. This paper has vanished in our community now, for we do not tolerate anything utraquistic, half-and-half.</p>
   <p>These Chicago German papers are trying to slur and discredit the activities of our Czech National Alliance, and to brand our cause as something unjust and impossible in its aspirations.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0773.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We, however, think that after the Germans have received the lesson from the Allies, they will be more willing to live with their neighbors in peace..... After peace has been established, the rabble-rousing War agitators will be out of a job. The Abendpost article defines the Czechs as the trouble makers: "If they reach their goal of a united Bohemia and Moravia, there will be many Germans ruled by them and their paths will not be bedded with roses." The writer thus admits that as the Germans have treated the Czechs, so they are liable to be castigated for their deeds..... Too much tolerance and indulgence exercised by the Czechs has not brought good fruit.....</p>
   <p>Civilization is the product of collaboration among nations. Our Czech culture is also the result of the work of two nations; it could be enjoyed much better if the exertions of the other nation were not split and part of them used for the purpose of oppressing our people. This oppression forces the Czechs to defend themselves. When there is order in Czech lands as promised to us by the Allied nations, co-operation will bring splendid results.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
