<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-09-20">Sept. 20, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Report of the Executive Committee of the Association for Higher Education</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-09-20">Sept. 20, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE OF THE ASSOCIATION FOR HIGHER EDUCATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The executive committee of the Association for Higher Education takes this opportunity to present its customary annual report on the activities and condition of the Association.</p>
   <p>First, the committee expresses its pleasure at the increase in membership of the Association; between February 1 and July 9 fifty-six persons applied for membership.</p>
   <p>During the year, all the business of the Association progressed quite satisfactorily. Loans were made to thirteen students; these loans are classified according to the institutions: Iowa State University, two; Iowa State Normal School, two; Iowa State Agricultural School, one; Nebraska State University, one; Nebraska State Normal School, one; Texas State Agricultural School, two; Case School of Applied Science, in Ohio, two; Northwestern University, in <pb facs="5418478_1_0177.jpg" n="2"/>Illinois, one; University of Chicago, one.</p>
   <p>There are two girls among these students. All the students are doing well and send favorable reports of their progress to the committee. The committee takes pleasure in announcing that two wards of the Association have completed their studies this year and received their diplomas.</p>
   <p>More precise details on finances are given in the reports of the treasurer and secretary, which were recently published. The committee, however, calls attention to the following table of receipts and loans covering the Association's whole period of existence. This list has been compiled according to states:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Receipts</cell>
     <cell>Disbursements</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Iowa</cell>
     <cell>$2,160.53</cell>
     <cell>$975.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Ohio</cell>
     <cell>753.70</cell>
     <cell>700.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Nebraska</cell>
     <cell>488.26</cell>
     <cell>520.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Wisconsin</cell>
     <cell>399.80</cell>
     <cell>210.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Texas</cell>
     <cell>35.00</cell>
     <cell>885.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Illinois</cell>
     <cell>248.50</cell>
     <cell>630.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0178.jpg" n="3"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Receipts</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>New York</cell>
     <cell>$445.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Missouri</cell>
     <cell>560.16</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Maryland</cell>
     <cell>187.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>California</cell>
     <cell>110.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Minnesota</cell>
     <cell>95.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Michigan</cell>
     <cell>75.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Kansas</cell>
     <cell>15.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>South Dakota</cell>
     <cell>50.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Oklahoma</cell>
     <cell>35.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Massachusett</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>New Jersey</cell>
     <cell>22.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Pennsylvania</cell>
     <cell>25.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The executive committee takes the liberty of calling the attention of lodges and individuals in various states to Article V, Paragraph C of the Association's constitution, according to which the committee must see to it that where cases are equally deserving, loans are divided among the states in proportion <pb facs="5418478_1_0179.jpg" n="4"/>to the total receipts from them. No applicant who was able to comply with the requirements of the Association has been refused aid. However, it might easily happen that the committee would be forced to govern itself according to the above-mentioned paragraph. For instance, from the entire state of Texas, the Association has received thus far a total contribution of only $35, while a total of $885 in loans has been made in that state. On the other hand, the states of New York, Maryland, Missouri, etc., whose contributions have been fair, have not received a single loan, and the committee has not received a single application from these states which complied with the requirements of the Association. Therefore, it would be advisable for the lodges and our fellow countrymen in states like Texas, to contribute more liberally to the Association if they wish to preserve for their young people the advantages which they now enjoy. In states like New York they should make better use of the advantages to which they are fully entitled. Surely there are enthusiastic and capable youths in those states who are in need of this aid. They should apply for it.</p>
   <p>Aside from the work in connection with loans, the committee has done a great deal of its usual work, such as giving advice, explaining things to those who <pb facs="5418478_1_0180.jpg" n="5"/>intend to devote themselves to higher education, and urging our youth to take up more advanced study. This work has proved very useful. To a certain extent, at least, the results of this activity are obvious in the increased number of Czech students in the universities, especially in the state universities of Nebraska and Iowa, and in the organization of literary societies among the Czech students at these two universities. Besides this work, it is often necessary to give advice and encouragement to the wards of the Association. This is the main responsibility of the members of the committee.</p>
   <p>All this work takes much labor, time, and material sacrifice. The members of the committee themselves paid for incidental expenses in order to avoid drawing upon the treasury of the Association.</p>
   <p>The committee concludes its report with an appeal to the public for continued and energetic support of this noble undertaking.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
