<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-09">May 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Glorious Day in Cicero</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-09">May 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A GLORIOUS DAY IN CICERO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday was a significant day in the history of the Bohemian freethinkers of Cicero. After a period of strenuous efforts, the Patronat Ceske Svobodomyslne Skoly Tomas G. Masaryk (Board of trustees of the Thomas G. Masaryk Free Thought School) and other local organizations laid the cornerstone for a new school building which also will be a meeting place for our organization. The Patronat has long seen the necessity of an independent school building, but as long as the Cicero School Board was willing to lend its classrooms to the Bohemian school, the necessity did not seem to be so urgent. Only when the School Board excluded the Bohemian classes from the public schools did the Patronat come to the conclusion that, for the preservation of the Bohemian school in Cicero, there was no alternative but to erect its own school building, and with the aid of Bohemian organizations and individuals go to work at once. A lot was bought at the southwest corner of 57th Avenue and 22nd Place, and the contract for the erection <pb facs="5418478_1_0403.jpg" n="2"/>of the school building was awarded to Mr. Julius Kinst. The work on the school building progressed rapidly. In the near future it will be possible for our Bohemian organizations to hold their meetings in the Tomas G. Masaryk School, and after next vacation our children will attend Bohemian school classes located in the Patronat's own school building.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's celebration of the laying of the cornerstone was brilliant and worthy of the large Bohemian settlement of Cicero. Every one of the local organizations participated at this celebration and was represented either by a great number of its members in the parade or by a delegation, and enormous throngs of people gathered around the new building long before the program started. The participants in the parade met in front of the Sokol Karel Jonas Hall at one o'clock in the afternoon and, through various Cicero streets, marched to the place of the celebration. Several hundred of school children marched at the head of the parade and one group carried a large American flag. Another group of the children wore white, red, and <pb facs="5418478_1_0404.jpg" n="3"/>blue caps, resembling the Czechoslovak flag, and the rest of them carried small American flags. Following the school children marched the members of various organizations. At the site of the celebration the school children gathered in front of the speakers' tribune and to the rear gathered the members of organizations and a countless number of people.</p>
   <p>The program of the celebration was opened by the chairman of the Patronat, Mr. Jan Sebek, who with a few sincere words greeted the audience, speaking on the necessity for the Bohemian school. He then introduced Miss Maruska and Miss Marik, pupils, the first one of whom recited a poem and the other briefly addressed the audience and then gave the committee the sum of eighteen dollars as a gift from the school children. The band then played "The Star-Spangled Banner". The chairman introduced the president of the board of trustees of the town of Cicero, Mr. Joseph Z. Klenha, who, as the representative of the town, addressed the audience in the English language and said that although it is our duty to be good and loyal Americans, we <pb facs="5418478_1_0405.jpg" n="4"/>should also teach our children the Bohemian tongue. The next number of the program was a song by the Karl Marx Singing Society, after which the principal speaker of the celebration, Mr. Vaclav Petrzelka, was introduced. His lengthy speech aroused great interest and the speaker was often interrupted with applause. Miss Lastovka then recited a poem and the school children sang the Bohemian nation anthem. In conclusion, Mr. Joseph Tichava, chairman of the Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools, spoke on the progress of the Bohemian schools in Chicago and vicinity. The delegates of various organizations were then introduced. These, in the name of their societies, extended congratulations and delivered generous monetary gifts.</p>
   <p>[List of contributors and contributions as omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>After the delivery of the addresses of the delegates, the ceremony of the laying of the cornerstone began. Various documents and a list of the <pb facs="5418478_1_0406.jpg" n="5"/>donations were placed in a box and sealed in the cornerstone. The chairman of the board of trustees, Mr. Jan Sobek, then ended the celebration. The celebration was a success in every respect. The tagging, which was undertaken by a number of school children and young ladies, also helped to make it a financial success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
