<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-14">May 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Hudson Coal and Mining Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1001</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1001.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-14">May 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE HUDSON COAL AND MINING COMPANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As is known, the case of the Hudson Coal and Mining Company came up before Judge Cooper last week, and the main question dealt with was a change of venue. However, since none of the petitioners were present at the hearing, the request was stricken from the court's calendar. The petitioners state that they had requested the Judge to continue the hearing to another date, to which the Judge did not agree, and for that reason they did not appear in court. For that reason, also, they find themselves forced to make the following explanation of this case here:</p>
   <p>At one time, William R. Walleck and others signed as chief guarantors, responsible for a stated sum of money, for Joseph Kokes and others, and to pay, without discrimination, for these officers whenever necessary, including in the guarantee, their heirs and executors. This bond was put, up on May 11 in the court session in which Joseph Kokes had appeared against William R. Walleck and others, file number 2858.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1002.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Several court actions by the guarantors against Kokes and the other defendants were at issue, when the latter sought an injunction against any further court action that might be taken against them. The court granted the injunction, and an appeal is being made from this court decision. Therefore, the guarantors feel justified in asking that their bond be set aside, and for a change of venue from the court which had issued the injunction. The appeal is signed by all of the guarantors fighting for their rights.</p>
   <p>(Signed)</p>
   <p>One of them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
