<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-29">Oct. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Parade of the United Civic Societies a Call to All Bohemian Associations and Friends of Personal Liberty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I B 2 (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-29">Oct. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">PARADE OF THE UNITED CIVIC SOCIETIES A Call to All Bohemian Associations and Friends of Personal Liberty</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, November 7, has been selected by the United Civic Societies of Chicago as the day on which a demonstration for personal liberty will take place. It will be a huge parade, the purpose of which is to show the strength of the liberal element in this city to the prohibition fanatics and convince them that Chicago people will not have a few deluded individuals tell them how to organize their lives and their social customs.....</p>
   <p>It is therefore our duty to attend and participate in this parade to the last man.....</p>
   <p>The Sokol organizations from the whole city will assemble in front of the hall of the Sokol Pilsen on Ashland Avenue and 18th Street at 12:30 P. M.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0613.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Bohemian Catholic organizations from the whole city will meet in front of the Cesko-Anglicka Svobodna Skola (Bohemian-English Free Thought School) on 18th and May Streets at 12:30 P. M.</p>
   <p>Other organizations, associations, and clubs will assemble on Blue Island Avenue, between 16th and 18th Streets, at 12:30 P. M.....</p>
   <p>It is absolutely essential that all participants be on time. The parade will start marching punctually at 1:00 P. M., and there will be absolutely no waiting for those who are late.</p>
   <p>Information concerning other details of and preparations for the parade will be gladly given by Mr. Josef Placek at 2333 South Kedzie Avenue, telephone, Rockwell 2199, or by the secretary of the organizing committee, Mr. Otto T. Pergler, at 1808 South Avers Avenue, telephone, Lawndale 9738.</p>
   <p>Countrymen! Let us show the world that the Bohemians are always first when it <pb facs="5418478_1_0614.jpg" n="3"/>is a question of protecting and promoting freedom and personal liberty!</p>
   <p>For the Ceske Odvetvi Sdruzenych Spolku Pro Mistni Samospravu (Bohemian Section of the United Civic Societies),</p>
   <p>John A. Cervenka, president;</p>
   <p>Anton J. Cermak, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
