<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-15">Oct. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title><title level="a" type="sub">[An Abstract]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-15">Oct. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">[An Abstract]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Czechoslovak voters will have a last chance to register on Tuesday, October 17, 1922. The coming November election is too important for any citizen to neglect his duties and let this last opportunity slip by. The polls will again be open next Tuesday from 8 A. M. until 9 P. M., and our citizens will, therefore, have ample time to register. It is certain that more than one half of the voters in our county have not yet registered, and we may say that the greater number of these are women. This may not, however, be claimed to be so in the so-called better districts where a great many prohibitionists reside. Every woman in these districts will cast her ballot to effect a change in the now existing Volstead Act and against Mr. Anton J. Cermak who is running for the office of president and member of the County Board of Commissioners.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1302.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Much propaganda is being used to defeat our candidate at the November election. His defeat would not be a personal one but a defeat of all liberty-loving people, and for the prohibitionists his defeat would be the most decisive victory.....The question of personal freedom, however, is not the only question that hangs in the balance. Another is the taxation problem, and high taxes ought to be of great concern to every one of us. This question too, then, should compel every voter to register so as to be able to cause changes in public offices. The present grand jury investigation of the School Board is the best proof how our public offices are steeped in graft, and how the taxpayers' money is being wasted. Such waste has for its consequence a constant increase in taxation which in the end will become unbearable. Every taxpayer--and every one of us is a taxpayer, whether we own property or not--should endeavor to put an end to this kind of uneconomic mismanagement, and register next Tuesday. Such registration will enable the taxpayers to select the best candidates for public office on November 7, 1922......</p>
   <p>Alderman Cermak, as a candidate for the presidency and membership of the Board <pb facs="5418478_1_1303.jpg" n="3"/>of County Commissioners is prepared to introduce many useful changes in the administration of the county, that is, if the citizens elect him to this very important office. In his own declaration he says that his first job will be to introduce an economy of saving so that for every dollar paid in taxes the citizens will be sure to receive 100 cents worth of work. Our public highways in the county will also recieve their due attention; their upkeep requires a tremendous expenditure, and it is desirable that an attempt be made to effect some saving in this respect. Our county already has a very complex network of good roads, but their building and upkeep costs a tremendous amount of money and increases the tax burden.</p>
   <p>Among the most important offices of the state are those of the state senators. [The editor of the Denni Hlasatel has enumerated in some detail the duties and functions of the state legislature.] The Nineteenth Senatorial District, in which live tens of thousands of our Czechoslovak countrymen, the candidate for state senator is Mr. Albert B. Holecek, an attorney by profession, and well qualified to fill the office to which he aspires. Mr. Holecek is a sincere Czech, a man of the people, one who feels with the people and is ready to work for their <pb facs="5418478_1_1304.jpg" n="4"/>benefit. During the April primaries Mr. Holecek was nominated on the Republican ticket. Only by concentrating our votes on this candidate, without regard to political partisanship, may we hope to obtain a Czech representative in Springfield.</p>
   <p>.....The only chance to elect a countryman to the state legislature is to vote for him. Our voters will have the chance to choose between him and an Irishman who is the holder of that office at the present time. We know in advance what the choice of our voters will be. Every one of us will vote for Holecek in order to have somebody in Springfield who will work honestly and ably in our behalf. But to do that all of us must be registered voters.</p>
   <p>Those of our countrymen who live in the Twenty-fourth Ward, in the northern section of the Twelfth Ward, in Cicero, Berwyn, and Riverside, Illinois, and whose names do not yet appear on the voters' lists in these districts, should go to the polls on Tuesday without fail. That is the only necessary requirement to make Mr. Holecek's election a cinch, an election which will spell great victory for the entire Czechoslovak element of the District.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
