<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-20">Mar. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">In Behalf of Personal Freedom</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Protest Meeting of the Local Sdruzeni Svazu Svobodomyslnych</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-20">Mar. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IN BEHALF OF PERSONAL FREEDOM</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Protest Meeting of the Local Sdruzeni Svazu Svobodomyslnych</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The same hall, which a fortnight ago witnessed an unusually interesting debate between Alderman Anton J. Cermak and the apostle of the dries, Alderman John M. Lyle, harbored another mass protest meeting of our people. The protest was directed against liquor prohibition and all blue laws generally. This time the meeting was called by the local Sdruzeni Svazu Svobomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers) which invited some notables to address the meeting. The meeting was a success as was expected by the committee on arrangements. In spite of inclement weather, the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Company was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>During the afternoon speeches were given in the Czech and the English languages. The subject of the liquor prohibition and its evil effects was well handled by Messrs. Vaclav Petrzelka, Jan Jelinek, Joseph Proebstle, <pb facs="5418478_1_0517.jpg" n="2"/>the last-named being a secretary of the International Association of Brewery Workers of Cincinnati, Chio. Other speakers were Mr. Maclaskey, secretary of the American Secular Union, County Treasurer P. J. Carr, Senator Joseph J. Boehm, and others. All of them have tried to show that the liberal element was not particularly concerned about a barrel of beer or a bottle of whiskey, but it concentrates its efforts to defend personal freedom to choose, and the freedom of conviction [which is the] right of every man.</p>
   <p>Particularly remarkable were the arguments advanced by Alderman Anton J. Cermak....Mr. Cermak has for a number of years been the president of the United Societies for Local Self Government; he opposed the efforts of prohibition pussyfooters both in the state legislature and in the City Council, and being a man well versed in public affairs, he is surely most competent to judge the question of prohibition. In yesterday's speech he threw more light on the subject in a manner which ought to be <pb facs="5418478_1_0518.jpg" n="3"/>of particular concern to taxpayers. He revealed that during the two-and-one-half years since prohibition was introduced the city of Chicago was deprived of $20,000,000 in revenues. Today liquor is sold as before, with the only difference that neither the federal government nor the municipal administration derive any profit therefrom, and that there are only a few individuals who have gained by the system. He was sorry to say that the blame for this is mainly attributable to the indifference of the public. When, in the days past, people were warned to be on their guard against the [prohibition system], no one wished to listen to these warning voices, and everyone dismissed the subject with a "it will never happen".</p>
   <p>But what seemed to be an impossibility became a fact, and today the country groans under the yoke of reactionary laws....In Washington they point to the State of Illinois which enjoys the reputation of being the most liberal state, as being also the driest state of the Union. This was brought about by the faithless actions of those congressmen who were elected by liberal <pb facs="5418478_1_0519.jpg" n="4"/>folk whom they betrayed. Thereupon Alderman Cermak outlined a method which would serve to correct the great error. At this time there are petitions circulating among our population in which it is asked that Congress and the state legislature amend the law in such a way as would permit at least the manufacture and sale of beer and light wines. In order that this question may be handled by ballot and thus become the expressed opinion of the general public, six hundred thousand signatures are necessary. Everyone who desires, therefore, that the law be amended should sign this petition. At the same time it is important that every signer of this petition register for the polls, for the prohibition zealots will surely see to it that the petitioners' names be checked over, and the unregistered ones be stricken off.</p>
   <p>There will, of course, be another registration of voters before the November elections, but that one will be of little use as regards the present problem, since the petition must be filed before that time. The law requires that a petition be filed at least sixty days before elections, and the fall <pb facs="5418478_1_0520.jpg" n="5"/>registration will take place later. Whoever wishes to sign this petition, may do so in the real-estate office of Cermak and Serhant, 26th Street and Homan Avenue.</p>
   <p>The meaning and significance of the petition, and what it is to accomplish was discussed in a comprehensible manner by Mr. Jan A. Cervenka. He stressed the fact that the petition alone does not mean that one has cast a ballot, it is merely an expression of opinion, of the combined opinion of many people who have signified their unwillingness to have such stringent laws and wish an amendment.</p>
   <p>The meeting was characterized by much enthusiasm, and the many signatures which were appended to the petition blanks bear proof that our people are determined to remove the [prohibition evil]. Pauses between individual speeches were filled by excellent music furnished by our tambour orchestra, which played several fine compositions and reaped its reward of applause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
