<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-02-02">Feb. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Workers Are Sacrificed So That Spravedlnost and the Socialists in Particular May Continue to Agitate and Fish in Troubled Waters. the Strike Is to Be Continued Indefinitely</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1151</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1151.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-02-02">Feb. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORKERS ARE SACRIFICED SO THAT SPRAVEDLNOST AND THE SOCIALISTS IN PARTICULAR MAY CONTINUE TO AGITATE AND FISH IN TROUBLED WATERS. THE STRIKE IS TO BE CONTINUED INDEFINITELY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The millions of dollars in wages which the workers have lost, the endless suffering which has spread in countless striking tailors families, lives which have been destroyed - all this misery seems still not enough, to the fanatics, or rascals, who are gathered around Spravedlnost.</p>
   <p>With rapacity, such as is possible only with man when he is fanatical to the highest degree, they call for new victims, with a subtlety such as characterizes only the worst outcasts of human society; they strive so that these victims will come to aid them, their party, their politics, their <pb facs="5418478_1_1152.jpg" n="2"/>newspaper and their pockets.</p>
   <p>This tailors' strike, which was called near the end of September and affected more than 40,000 workers, has been felt by the whole City of Chicago and especially by our community, where about 10,000 Bohemian men and women were deprived of earnings. This tragedy will be written in indelible letters into the history of Chicago workingmen and our Bohemian community. Its consequences will be borne by many of our countrymen all their lives, and they will very likely never recover from them. This strike will be a sad chapter in the lives of hundreds and thousands of our countrymen, and all of those, who have lost their savings because of the strike; those who have suffered severe misery; those who through want became ill; all the children who for want of sufficient nourishment became <pb facs="5418478_1_1153.jpg" n="3"/>The victim of incipient diseases, which probably will cause life long suffering for them. Surely all of these will condemn those who so thoughtlessly called the strike, carried it on miserably and now prolong it indefinitely, only because it is suitable for them and their party.</p>
   <p>At the time when the tailors' strike was in its first stages, we took the liberty to point out, that this was not the proper time for such action and that there was not the proper organization to conduct it. Also we pointed out, winter was at hand and many tailors had just started to work after several weeks of enforced summer idleness and did not have the necessary means to carry on the struggle. We proclaimed that such a strike should be general in all centers of the clothing industry, so that the work lost by <pb facs="5418478_1_1154.jpg" n="4"/>Chicago tailors would not be done elsewhere, but we were silenced by Spravedlnost. It immediately resorted to its favorite tactics and proclaimed us to be traitors and obnoxious to workingmen. When we saw, that tailors in large numbers had stopped working, we did everything we possibly could, so that the struggle, which had begun under such unfavorable conditions, might be settled as honorably as possible for the workers. Our labors were sincere and unselfish in every respect but brought us only enmity from a certain part of our public which suffered losses because of the strike. This fact, our capitalists and competitors also sought to use against us. Thus on the one side, rash fanatics and on the other side sly Jesuits sought to benefit at our expense.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1155.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We do not want to mention how far they succeeded. Only so much will we add, that our public, workingmen and readers, showed rare deliberation and judgement. The intrigues and plans of our enemies failed completely. All this however is beside the point - let us return to the strike itself.</p>
   <p>We think, after carefully following the course of the tailors' strike, after taking into account all circumstances and details, that we are justified in saying, thousands of workers and their families and the whole city of Chicago have become the victims of unscrupulous socialistic politicians. They were on the eve of an election, in which they had great hope. Public opinion had to be stirred up as much as possible; labor, agitated to the utmost degree, so that the Socialists could get up and shout, "Salvation is to be had only through us." Because properly <pb facs="5418478_1_1156.jpg" n="6"/>organized Labor would not allow itself to become a tool, because it had its own agreements, arbitration committees and like arrangements, these unconscionable politicians chose the tailoring workers, the majority of whom belonged to no organization. The large numerical strength of the tailors suited their purposes excellently. They knew the tailors had unsettled grievances and demands and upon this they built their plans. This succeeded very well for themselves in the beginning. About 45,000 tailors quit working, some of them willingly and others through fear of violence.</p>
   <p>How the strike, called from such motives, was carried on, was told in Saturday's Denni Hlasatel by an enlightened worker, Mr. Uzlik, who followed <pb facs="5418478_1_1157.jpg" n="7"/>it diligently and is familiar with the details of all the deliberations of its leaders. The answers by Spravedlnost to his charges and to our Sunday article were so weak and lacking in spice, that they really were an admission of everything written in Denni Hlasatel.</p>
   <p>Yesterday, however, Spravedlnost decided to discharge their biggest gun and as usual loaded it with mud and slime and hurled the entire charge at Hlasatel, because we published the advertisement, of the Clothing manufacturers Employers Association, inviting their employees to return to work. If in our opinion Spravedlnost was worthy of any explanations from us, we would call its attention to the last mass meeting held at Pilsen Pavilion <pb facs="5418478_1_1158.jpg" n="8"/>and to the words of Mr. Balvin. He, with rare ecstasy of truthfulness proclaimed that the strike was over. We also were of the same conviction. When we understood why the strike was called; when we convinced ourselves how it was being conducted, and we saw how futile it was under the circumstances to continue the struggle - which, to be sure, only supports a few Socialists - we published the advertisement of the Clothing Manufacturers Employers Association, who were offering their employees the same conditions embodied in the agreement by which the strike was ended at Harts (Hart, Schaffner &amp; Marz). Our contention is, that if the Jews could return to Harts under those conditions, then the Bohemians can also return to their contractors and to their firms, when these are offering them the same advantages. These things are stated in the advertisement and the only condition required is, that Kostka, Balvin and others of their ilk have no part in the negotiations. <pb facs="5418478_1_1159.jpg" n="9"/>Now there is light. Clearly our workers see that in the future they must guard against people who set themselves up as their leaders and who are in fact their betrayers. They must see it they do not fall into the clutches of the most unconscionable politicians under the sun, the Socialists. Other politicians fatten upon the large corporations, the Socialists, however, wish to build their power through the suffering and despair of the workers.</p>
   <p>Spravedlnost now wants to continue the strike.</p>
   <p>"Why, you yourselves have lost it, you yourselves broke it!" Do you not <pb facs="5418478_1_1160.jpg" n="10"/>have enough victims, did not enough blood run, were not enough tears shed, was not enough despair caused through your fault? What more do you want, you insatiable raven?</p>
   <p>Tailors must and will have an organization. That is as certain, as that with the aid of organization they will achieve the fulfillment of their just demands, the introduction of healthy conditions in workrooms and factories. But, such an organization must free itself from the domination of the Balvins, Kostkas and particularly of the people who do not work for the interests of the tailors, but for those of Spravedlnost and the Socialists. Toward this and the organization will have the enthusiastic support and help of Hlasatel.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1161.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Something more comes to our mind. Soravedlnost, as we have come to know it, is capable of the greatest scoundrelism. What if the advertisement of the Clothing Manufacturers Employers Association, which appeared in large letters on its first page, was explained as paid advertising, and the trash and babble about Hlasatel was thrown in for the purpose of concealing the true aim of the advertisement? It would conform fully with the conception of honesty of the Spravedlnost people, and with the tactics used by them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
