<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-05">Mar. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">To the Attention of Our Countrymen in Cicero, Berwyn, and Oak Park!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-05">Mar. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE ATTENTION OF OUR COUNTRYMEN IN CICERO, BERWYN, AND OAK PARK!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friends! While the great war raged over Europe, and while the thunder of guns accompanied the birth pains of the liberated lands of Czechoslovakia, all the loyal adherents of our nation living abroad united under the revolutionary flag of Czechoslovakia and labored for the realization of our dreams, bringing financial aid or, with weapon in hand, fighting for an ideal and a duty which was indicated to us by the meaning of our history.</p>
   <p>One of the most zealous organizations in this struggle for the freedom of our nation was the Narodne Socialni Beseda J. V. Fric (J. V. Fric National Socialist Club) which, at that time, comprehended at once the significance of proganda and informative literature in our struggle for freedom. It was the countless number of copies of the Bohemian-American newspapers and pamphlets which penetrated to the far-flung parts of the world that were bringing new light to a Czechoslovakian captive, chasing away the dullness and hopelessness, and leading him to a struggle for our freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1206.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not even now is the Beseda J. V. Frie idle. There is plenty of work to be done in our Czechoslovak Republic. The government cannot, for various reasons, exercise its powers everywhere, especially in the trifling defensive work conducted in the ethnically mixed territory. Places not accessible to government intervention must be handled by our national defensive organizations, such as the Narodni Jednota Posumavska (National Union of the Bohemian Forest), the Severoceska Jednota (North Bohemian Union) and the Ustredni Matice Skolska (Central Committee on Education). The Beseda J. V. Frie will now devote its efforts to these organizations.</p>
   <p>But inasmuch as a large number of members of the Beseda J. V. Fric reside in western suburbs of Chicago, a new club is being founded for them in Cicero, and it will be known by the name "Narodne Socialni Beseda Joseph Turzicky" (Joseph Turzicky National Socialist Club). With it, the Beseda J. V. Fric honors the memory of one of its most prominent members who played such a significant role in our revolution, in our struggle for independence. Both of these organizations will work harmoniously toward the set goal. Besides <pb facs="5418478_1_1207.jpg" n="3"/>the members of the Beseda V. J. Fric living in western suburbs, any Bohemian or Slovak of either sex who is a true Czechoslovak and who sympathizes with our work may become a member of this organization.</p>
   <p>We invite you to come and work with us. Applications for membership will be received by the following members of the preparations committee: Rudolph Wlodek, 5501 West 24th Place, Joseph Plicka, 1900 South 57th Avenue; and J. J. Fekl, 5457 West 25th Street, all of Cicero, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
