<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-16">Oct. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">For Bohemian Classes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0243</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0243.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-16">Oct. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FOR BOHEMIAN CLASSES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very considerable number of people assembled in the hall of Sokol Karel Jonas in Cicero last night. They came from the J. Sterling Morton High School district and their purpose was to take determined steps to start the teaching of the Bohemian language in that school.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called by citizens who, convinced that their demand is proper, are ready to exert every effort in order that the teaching of Bohemian in the Morton High School shall be realized at the earliest possible moment. The demand is backed up by their numerical strength, their importance as taxpayers, and the fact that other modern foreign languages are being taught in the School, and there is therefore no reason why the Bohemian language should not be included.</p>
   <p>The meeting, attended also by a number of ladies of Cicero and Berwyn, was <pb facs="5418478_1_0244.jpg" n="2"/>opened by a brief and snappy talk by Mr. Kubec, in which he discussed the reasons why the Bohemian language should be taught in the Morton High School and pointed to the fine success its teaching has achieved in Chicago in the Harrison High School.</p>
   <p>Among the first speakers was Professor Bohumil Kral, who was the first teacher of Bohemian at the Harrison High School. He stressed the importance of that language and told how, three years ago, only forty pupils attended the classes, while two hundred and twenty are enrolled this year, certainly a most gratifying increase. He discussed the importance of Bohemian also from the practical point of view and urged those present to do all they can to have the teaching of the Bohemian language introduced in their high school.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jos. A. Holpuch, a member of the Chicago Board of Education, was welcomed with deafening applause. He said he had not come to tell the people <pb facs="5418478_1_0245.jpg" n="3"/>what their duty was because he knew they were all very well aware of it, and knew what to do about it. He complained, however, that there was not a sufficient interest in schools among the people in Chicago. This fact induced him to start disseminating detailed information about the activities of the School Board through the Denni Hlasatel and other newspapers....</p>
   <p>After Mr. Holpuch's speech, a resolutions committee was elected which drafted the following petition:</p>
   <p>"We, the undersigned citizens and taxpayers of the Morton High School district declare that we are the representatives of the majority of the Bohemian citizens and taxpayers of the named school district, and that it is our desire to have the Bohemian language, our mother tongue, taught in the J. Sterling Morton High School. We wish to point to the fact that Bohemian is recognized and among the modern languages taught in schools in Chicago <pb facs="5418478_1_0246.jpg" n="4"/>and elsewhere.</p>
   <p>"We further declare that the Bohemian citizens feel justified in submiting this request because the School district is inhabited by a population which is overwhelmingly Bohemian-American and which, by paying taxes in the district, help in supporting the School.</p>
   <p>"Therefore we request your body sic. No indication of the "body" to which the resolution was directed to take the necessary steps toward granting this request and to see to it that the teaching of the Bohemian language at J. Sterling Morton High School be soon started and thereafter continued indefinitely.</p>
   <p>The resolution was read by the secretary of the meeting and unanimously approved. It will be submitted with the largest obtainable number of signatures, and it would seem that it will soon bring the desired results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
