<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-03">June 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Democratic Victory in the Twelfth Ward Was Celebrated Last Night in Pilsen Park Pavilion Alderman Anton J. Cermak Presented with a diamond-Studded Gold Star</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-03">June 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE DEMOCRATIC VICTORY IN THE TWELFTH WARD WAS CELEBRATED LAST NIGHT IN PILSEN PARK PAVILION Alderman Anton J. Cermak Presented With A diamond-Studded Gold Star</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Democratic victory of April 4 was celebrated last night in the pavilion of Pilsen Park. About five hundred people took part in the celebration. The Democratic organization of the Twelfth Ward arranged the celebration, which was a success because the participants enjoyed themselves exceptionally well.</p>
   <p>At 8 P.M., the places at the tables, which were arranged in ten rows the length of the pavilion, began to be filled, and in a short time, all places were occupied. Shortly thereafter, food and refreshments were brought to the tables. Entertainment was provided by Mr. Novak's band. The speakers, singers, and soloists competed with one another to keep the participants in good humor. We must admit that they were successful, to be sure, for under <pb facs="5418478_1_1619.jpg" n="2"/>these circumstances none among the politicians were sad.</p>
   <p>The pavilion was beautifully decorated for the occasion, and in front of the stage a platform was erected, where all the officials, who were victorious on April 4, were seated. Alderman William F. Schultz of the Twelfth Ward welcomed the gathering, and explained the reasons for the celebration. Sheriff Michael Zimmer was the principal speaker.</p>
   <p>The most significant happening of the evening was the presentation of a gold star, set with diamonds and rubies, to Alderman Anton J. Cermak, a gift from the Democratic organization of the Twelfth Ward. The star, which was bought with a collection from among his political friends, is really a valuable gift, because it cost over $800. Alderman Cermak was deeply moved when the gift was presented by Sheriff Zimmer, and in thanking the organization for it, he said that he would never forget this display of friendship, and recognition of his efforts. In making the presentation, Sheriff Zimmer said that Alderman Cermak really deserved recognition, because he distinguished himself in the <pb facs="5418478_1_1620.jpg" n="3"/>City Council of seventy alderman, which is not an easy matter. Other speakers were Congressman A. J. Sabath; Judge Scully; City Treasurer Stuckart; the president of the United Societies Kellerman; the clerk of the Probate Court John Cervenka; Charles J. Vopicka; Mr. Fischer, and others.</p>
   <p>The arrangements committee was made up of the following persons: Sheriff Michael Zimmer, Alderman Anton J. Cermak, Alderman William F. Schultz, Joseph Stastny, F. W. Bewersdorf, Joseph I. Novak, Peter Jezierny, Fred Schultz, Henry Ruck and Adolph Fencl.</p>
   <p>The entertainment was attended by many political friends, and police officials, not only of the Twelfth Ward and surroundings, but from other sections of the city. The affair lasted until the late hours, and the committee is to be congratulated for having provided a very pleasant evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
