<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-09-01">Sept. 1, 1890</date><title level="a">New Catholic School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0431</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0431.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-09-01">Sept. 1, 1890</date><title level="a">NEW CATHOLIC SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday was a day of rejoicing and celebration for Bohemian Catholics of our city. They became the possessors of a beautiful new school building, of which they can well be proud, especially the members of St. Procopius Parish, who unafraid of the task, set about to build this beautiful refuge for their youth, a school such as we "Liberal minded" (Free thinkers) would not be able to provide so easily.</p>
   <p>The school is located behind the church, on Allport St. near 16th St. It is a building four stories high and well arranged for the purpose it is meant to serve. The erection of the building was under the supervision of the very conscientious and upright builder, F. C. Layer.</p>
   <p>This new Catholic institution of learning was dedicated yesterday and will be given over to its purpose in a few days. Various societies of the community attended the Catholic celebration. A parade was formed and at 2:30 P. M. the massing of people in the vicinity of the school and church was immense.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0432.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Archbishop Feehan, in the company of the Priests and Trustees, went to the school building. With customary rites the building was consecrated, the keys to the building accepted and given to the Procopius community for the purposes indicated. After these rites the gathering returned into the church for blessing.</p>
   <p>For the evening there was arranged a theatrical, a concert, and a large tablet in honor of the St. Procopius parishioners.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
