<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-22">Jan. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Slavs from Austria-Hungary in Parade</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0824</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0824.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-01-22">Jan. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SLAVS FROM AUSTRIA-HUNGARY IN PARADE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The widely advertised Austrian parade was held in the district around 20th Street and Wentworth Avenue last Sunday afternoon. It was sufficiently big to demonstrate that even among the Slavonic peoples of this city there are a number of dolts who are unable to form a clear picture of Emperor Francis I. as a ruler, man, and chiefly as the "father of the Slavonic nations." The procession, besides the automobiles, was about three blocks long. It is said that fourteen associations were represented. They were accompanied by ten bands. The procession began at the Croatian Catholic church, moved to 26th Street and Wentworth Avenue, then returned to the starting point.</p>
   <p>While they were on the way back to church, a disturbance occurred which led to the arrest of eight members of the Czech gymnastic society Sokol. There were policemen in great numbers distributed over the parade ground, <pb facs="5418478_1_0825.jpg" n="2"/>uniformed and plain clothes, on foot and mounted, some moving along with the marchers. They were there in order that the loyal subjects of the emperor should remain unhurt. The Sokols began to distribute pamphlets among the participants of the parade. The bills were printed in English, and bore the heading "The Real Francis Joseph," and below was a picture, showing the true features of the emperor. On the last page, there could be seen a multitude of widows and children moving thru a forest of crosses erected over the graves of their husbands and fathers.</p>
   <p>The instant the paraders glimpsed the handbills, they assumed a threatening attitude towards the Sokols. The police were on hand and arrested eight of the Sokols, whose followers immediately telephoned Anton Cermak and John Cervenka, to arrange for their release. They were at liberty shortly after, stating that they had been accorded most unbecoming treatment by being called "Crazy Polacks" and "Crazy Bohemians."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0826.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is to be noted that in the parade there were even a number of Sokols, but Dalmatian (another Slavonic nation) Sokols; it seems incredible that they can make the ideals of the Sokol organization compatible with the memory of the executioner of the Slavonic peoples.</p>
   <p>In the handbills, there were enumerated all of the ill characteristics and actions of the late emperor, that is his guilt in the death of Karel Havlicek in 1856; how in the Crimean War he proved an ingrate to the Russians, who saved his throne in 1848, by supporting the Turks; how he started wars, in all of which Austria lost out; that he was a double-crosser and a bad husband and father, how he persecuted any move on the part of the Slavs to free themselves, and how he crowned his misdeeds by declaring War on Servia, thereby making himself guilty of the bloody World War.</p>
   <p>The Examiner in today's report on the parade, prints details which favor <pb facs="5418478_1_0827.jpg" n="4"/>the Teutonic side, as this paper has been wont to do, without accomplishing its aim. Excerpts from the handbills, published in the report, only to serve to open the eyes of the readers, and show how the Sokols have acted merely in the name of truth and justice when they distributed the pamphlets.</p>
   <p>The reason for the rather considerable proportions the parade took on lies in the fact that representatives of the peoples from Bosnia, Herzegovina and other countries, besides many Mohammedans had appeared with the marchers, also that people hailing from Dalmatia had come from their homes in South Chicago, and still more remote settlements.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
