<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-20">Apr. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Important Notice to Czech Voters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-20">Apr. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT NOTICE TO CZECH VOTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The election of trustees of the school board will be held on April 21. The city of Cicero is growing by leaps and bounds, and so is the entire West Side. It will be necessary to devote more attention to the management of the schools than has been done before. For this reason, a greater number of Czechs should be elected to the school board. Frank J. Petru, our fellow-countryman, has yielded to the urgent demands of representatives of our language element and to a petition containing over eight hundred Czech and other Slavonic names, and has decided to become a candidate for the office of trustee. We wish to mention that the office is an honorary one with no emolument attached to it, and no political obligations either--just as it always should be.</p>
   <p>It is of paramount importance for our countrymen to appear at the polls, which will be open from 6 A. M. to 4 P. M., to cast their votes for Frank J. Petru, and to ignore completely handbills presented to them by the opposition.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1373.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Frank J. Petru was born in 1880 in Chicago. He attended the public schools, Birmingham College, and the Chicago Business Law School, graduating from the latter in 1905. He held the position of director of the real-estate department of H. O. Stone &amp; Company for ten years. He is now head of his own real-estate concern, and resides at 1345 South 61st Street with his wife and two children.</p>
   <p>Mr. Petru is a member and officer of numerous aid societies, president of the Booster's Club of Warren Park, treasurer of the Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Union, treasurer of the Czech Old People's Home, and the Czech Orphanage, president of the Aid Society Union, vice-president of the Czech Charitable Society and of the southwestern branch of the United Charities, a director of the Southwest Businessmen's Association, and a member of the Real Estate Board of Cook County.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
