<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-21">Dec. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">In the Interest of Personal Liberty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-21">Dec. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE INTEREST OF PERSONAL LIBERTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The City Council of Chicago has before it now two proposals which constitute a new attack by pussyfooting temperance mongers against the liberal element. One of these proposals would prohibit any cafe from doing business within 250 feet of a school or a church; the other would forbid the sale of alcoholic beverages in dance halls after 1 A. M.....</p>
   <p>The voting on these proposals is expected to take place in a week from today, December 28. The Sdruzene Spolky (United Civic Societies) of Chicago soon became aware of the danger these ordinances held for the liberal element of this country, and particularly for social organizations which own various public halls.....</p>
   <p>Protest meetings against these proposals are being held all over the city; <pb facs="5418478_1_0476.jpg" n="2"/>one such meeting, called by the Bohemian section of the Sdruzene Spolky, took place in the Pilsen Park Pavilion yesterday afternoon. The attendance was good, but by no means as large as it should have been, when one considers the grave menace of these proposals. Mr. John A. Cervenka presided over the meeting....attended by all the aldermen of Bohemian wards, who gave the audience their assurance that they will do all in their power to prevent the enactment of these ordinances.....</p>
   <p>The discussion was participated in by the chairman of the meeting, Mr. Cervenka, Aldermen John Toman, Felix Janovsky, Otto Kerner, Held, McNichols, Bowler, and Judge Joseph E. Uhlir.....</p>
   <p>The meeting ended with an appeal by Mr. Cervenka that Congressmen of Bohemian districts be urged by telegram to work against the adoption of Hobson's <pb facs="5418478_1_0477.jpg" n="3"/>proposal to introduce prohibition into the United States. This measure will be voted upon in Congress tomorrow.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
