<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-08-31">Aug. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The New School Year Begins</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-08-31">Aug. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW SCHOOL YEAR BEGINS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The day after tomorrow classes will start in Chicago public schools, and our school authorities expect that in all of them the enrollment will be considerably larger than in any preceding year. It even seems probable that some schools in thickly populated districts will not be able to accommodate all enrolled children. For Bohemian parents of this city, the beginning of the school year is especially important, because this is the time when they should realize that the decision of whether or not the teaching of the Bohemian language in Chicago public schools will be continued rests upon them, and, what is more, whether or not the Chicago Board of Education will continue to be of the opinion that the Bohemian language is a subject whose teaching the public really desires. It required a great deal of sincere effort--in fact a very real fight--to cause the Board of Education to introduce the Bohemian language into those schools which show that a sufficient number of their pupils are enrolling in Bohemian classes. If this decision of the Board should ever be rescinded, it would not be because of the Board's failure to do its duty, but definitely and only <pb facs="5418478_1_0274.jpg" n="2"/>because of the failure of the Bohemian public to attach proper value to the achievement of those who had made it their duty to see the Bohemian language among the subjects of instruction in Chicago public schools.</p>
   <p>Last year Bohemian classes were started in the Farragut High School, but the enrollment was nothing to be proud of. This is the time to wake up from our indifference toward a matter of great importance. If all Bohemian parents do their duty and see to it that their children enroll in Bohemian classes, such classes will become a part of the program not of only one school in Chicago, but of all schools in every Chicago district which has a preponderance of Bohemian residents....</p>
   <p>Also instruction will soon begin in our Bohemian schools. For instance, in our largest Bohemian school, the one maintained by the Patronat (trustees) Vojta Naprstek, enrollment for all of its six classes will take place September 6 and 7. It is to be expected that our parents will enroll their children in time, and thus make it possible for the school to take off with all its pupils <pb facs="5418478_1_0275.jpg" n="3"/>for the year. The minimum age limit is six years, and the day's program for pupils of public school age is arranged so that they can take part in recreational activities such as games and athletics after school hours.</p>
   <p>The gymnastic school of Sokol Plzen will again be under the direction of Brother Rudolf Styblo, whose activity in this respect is well known and generally appreciated.</p>
   <p>Also the Cesko-Delnicky Pevecky Sbor (Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Chorus) will open its vocal and violin school September 7, and just as last year, Mr. Jos. Maly will act as the school's principal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
