<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-02">Dec. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies Protest the [Proposed Amendment of The] Illinois Constitution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-02">Dec. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECHO-SLAVONIC BENEVOLENT SOCIETIES PROTEST THE [PROPOSED AMENDMENT OF THE] ILLINOIS CONSTITUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Grand Lodge of the Illinois Ceskoslovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) has voiced its decided opposition to the new constitution [sic] which is to be voted on a week from next Tuesday. It has passed a resolution in which all of the reasons for these protests are enumerated. Since this resolution speaks for itself we publish it in full:</p>
   <p>"To the liberty-loving citizens of Czechoslovak origin:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, At a special election to be held on December 12, 1922, it is to be decided by the people of the state of Illinois, whether the new constitution as approved by the delegates at the last state convention is to become the basic law of the state of Illinois; and,</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1257.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Whereas, The proposed new constitution, as presented before the voters, contains such provisions and enactments as would prove inimical to the interests of liberty-loving citizens, to wit:</p>
   <p>1. Increased tax burden on the workingmen by the taxing incomes of $500 or more of single persons, and of $1,000 or more of married persons;</p>
   <p>2. Un-American and undemocratic provisions by means of which the representation of one county is limited since its population increased enormously, and thus [by such limited representation], nullifying the fundamentals of American government which is based upon equal representation;</p>
   <p>3. The creation of a judicial oligarchy which would prevent expressions of disagreement by such means as are contrary to a republican form of government;</p>
   <p>4. The introduction of a sectarian religious book (the reading of which will surely lead to arguments and then to dissension and discord) into the public schools, which have heretofore not engaged in the teaching of such <pb facs="5418478_1_1258.jpg" n="3"/>subjects, by nature more suitable to the sphere of the private family, or to private instruction; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, the passage of these proposed amendments would become destructive to the interests of a liberty-loving, and enlightened citizenry of our state; be it therefore</p>
   <p>Resolved, That the Grand Lodge of the Illinois Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies urgently requests all of the members of its societies to agitate against the above provisions so that they might be defeated, and issues this call to all the liberty-loving citizens to vote against the [proposed revision of the state constitution] at a special election to be held on Tuesday, December 12, 1922."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
