<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-03">Apr. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Future Status of Bohemia Communication from the Czech National Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0813</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0813.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-03">Apr. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE FUTURE STATUS OF BOHEMIA Communication from the Czech National Association</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The articles by Professor Thomas G. Masaryk printed in the Bohemian Review serve very effectively to show the activities of the Czechs and Slovaks in the American press. These articles are being reprinted by the foremost American dailies, thereby contributing, of course, in an excellent manner to the spreading of knowledge about our Czech and Slovak exertions for the independence of our motherland.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian Review prints in its April issue a work by Professor Masaryk entitled "The Future Status of Bohemia." It will accomplish a great deal for our cause, and a copy of the Bohemian Review should, therefore, be available in every library, and at every club, and should be in the possession of everyone who may have the opportunity to inform Americans about our national aims.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0814.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is a map of Bohemia, Moravia, Silesia, and Slovakia in-closed in every copy, with demarcations showing the distribution of the minorities, thus giving the observer an exact idea of the nationalistic conditions.</p>
   <p>The question whether the immigrants in the United States will be loyal to Germany in case of War is answered definitely by Doctor Jaroslav Smetanka, editor of the Bohemian Review. He speaks for both the Czech and the Slovak immigrants. Karel Pergler, a lawyer, criticizes the sentence passed on Doctor Kramar and co-defendants. His conclusions culminate in the statement that the difference between American and the Austrian justice is analogous to the relation of American democracy to Oriental despotism.</p>
   <p>For the sake of variety, there are two stories included in the April issue. They are well translated from the paper, Cechoslovan of Kiew, Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0815.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Among various news contained in that particular issue of the Bohemian Review one item, headed "Triumph of Democracy," speaks of the victorious Russian revolution. Another reports about the participation of the Czechs in the Allied Bazaar in Baltimore, New York, Cleveland, and Chicago. Mr. Frontingham, of New York, friend of the Slavonic peoples, is given much appreciative space. He had contributed $5,000 to the fund for political action of the Czech National Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
