<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1885-03-12">March 12th, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemians in Chicago (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0944</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0944.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1885-03-12">March 12th, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIANS IN CHICAGO (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The article of Mr. Adams printed in Inter-Ocea under the above title was entirely destined to take us Bohemians under its protection. Mr. Adams says that the only obstacle among us is our atheism; but we do not agree with this view-point. Our opinion is that a republic ruled by atheists, would be very strong and could flourish better than in the hands of religious families. Everyone has his own opinion and we cannot consider it wrong if someone has the view-point, that only faith in God can save humanity from the downfall. The above mentioned article says: "The author of this article is a man of rare character, completely acquainted with the Bohemian tongue and customs. He spent a few years in Prague, the Bohemian Capitol in Europe, and at present is living in our city. We can entirely depend on the correctness of his statement." Chicago, like other big centers, has numerous nationalities among its population. All countries and all languages are represented here. They are here to stay. Our rights and interests are equal. It is the glory <pb facs="5418478_1_0945.jpg" n="2"/>of our government, that everyone has the right to enjoy offered privileges. And this is the reason, which is attending these millions to our shores and filling our cities. It is most important that all those different nationalities understand each other and live in mutual harmony. This reciprocal relationship cannot be effected in one day, consequently evils can often be noticed in the comunities.</p>
   <p>The author of the above mentioned article is thriving to repute some of the false statements, and he did a good job. "They (the Bohemians) are not the kind of people depicted by the misinformed writers; as a rule they bring their European customs and habits with them. If they drink beer, there is nothing wrong in it; nevertheless, it is said that they hate intemperance. Their natural sympathy is always with the working people. It would be an offence to them, if we were to say that they are in accordance with the foolish anarchists or socialists or that they even sympathise with them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0946.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Bohemians have one daily journal, Svornost, edited by Mr. Zdrubek which propagates ardently morality.</p>
   <p>The worst that can be said about this journal is that it is anti-religious, and especially the Sunday supplement is completely blasphemous. In this direction it surpasses even Ingersol himself. By the way, it is said that nothing is read by the Bohemians more diligently, than the translated lectures of Ingersol. The Bohemians have many societies among them; mutual, beneficial, building-loan education, and musical. The more educated Bohemians subscribe to the Bohemian newspapers published in Cleveland, Minneapolis, and even in Bohemia, Europe. The number of Bohemians in our city is 35,000, dwellings are situated mostly on the south side. Such an important factor in our life and in our city cannot be further misunderstood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
