<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-28">Nov. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Joyful News</title><title level="a" type="sub">We Have Hope That the Czech Language Will Be Taught in the High Schools of Our City</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-28">Nov. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">JOYFUL NEWS</title><title level="a">We Have Hope That the Czech Language Will Be Taught In the High Schools of Our City</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From what we hear from reliable sources, it is very likely, that our Czech language will be taught in the Chicago high schools. This privilege, as we well know, up to the present is enjoyed only by the Poles. To be sure, we are not as numerous here as are the Poles, but, nevertheless, we are an important part of the cosmopolitan population of our metropolis. In business, industry, and politics we achieved success and gained the attention of Americans and members of other nationalities much sooner than did our Polish brothers.</p>
   <p>We have recently been informed by a distinguished fellow-citizen and friend of our paper that recognition of our mother tongue is zealously being sought by Professor Jaroslav J. Zmrhal. Professor Zmrhal already has had a discussion on this matter with Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, Superintendent of the Chicago <pb facs="5418478_1_0301.jpg" n="2"/>Public Schools, and she is favorably inclined toward his aims (to introduce the Czech language as a course of study in the high schools). The Board of Education's Committee on Education is also in favor of this idea, so that we have good prospects that after New Year we shall have gained this prized success, which will have great significance especially for our young people in so far as they are able to dedicate themselves to higher education. The superintendent of public schools, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, will introduce a motion on teaching the Czech language in the high schools at the January meeting of the Board of Education, and we hope that her powerful recommendations and perhaps the help of other favorable elements will succeed in bringing about these aims, even though they meet with opposition from circles unfriendly toward immigrants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
