<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-05">Feb. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">More Interest in Czech Classes Urged (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0234</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0234.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-05">Feb. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MORE INTEREST IN CZECH CLASSES URGED (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The introduction of the Bohemian language in Harrison High School may be considered one of the greatest of our national achievements in Chicago, but the results at the present time do not show that we enjoy our success too much. We might have fairly well expected that there would not be room enough for all the students crowding in to learn the language of their fathers, and also that there would be insufficient help from the part of the staff of teachers. The enrollment is, however, so weak that one of the classes is in danger of being dissolved. This news seems incredible, and does not, beside other points, serve to bring much credit to the Czech element of Chicago. It is about time that Czech parents became aware, at last, of the importance of the instruction in the Czech language, and see to it that their <pb facs="5418478_1_0235.jpg" n="2"/>children take advantage of the opportunity offered at Harrison High school. The school board, in a meeting last week, decided that students from other high schools shall be allowed to attend the Czech classes at Harrison High school. Now, Chicago is a town big enough with a strong Czech population so that no danger should arise that even one single Czech class would be closed on account of an insufficient number of students.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
