<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-01">Apr. 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Language Instruction in Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-01">Apr. 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">LANGUAGE INSTRUCTION IN SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. J. C. MacMahon, a member of the Chicago Board of Education, talked before the Irish Fellowship Club about a most important question which, due to the initiative of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) has come before the said Board. The problem is that of instruction in modern languages in Chicago public schools if there is a sufficient enrollment for the classes. Mrs. MacMahon is in favor of this request but desires that Gaelic also--the now almost extinct language of the Irish--be taught.</p>
   <p>Said she: "One of the reasons why our principal, Mrs. Young, has agreed with the plan, according to which more attention should be given to the teaching of immigrants' native languages, is the attitude of their children. In many cases the children are ashamed of their parents; they want to forget their origin, and they are in no way trying to learn the language which is spoken in their homes. There is no reason why the <pb facs="5418478_1_0289.jpg" n="2"/>children should not be proud of their parents' native country and tongue Making them familiar with the history and literature of the country of their origin would keep the children closer to their mothers and fathers. When the instruction of such languages is introduced into the schools, Gaelic must not be omitted. It is a modern language and one from which all other tongues have developed."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
