<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-11">Sept. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Not Enough Pride</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-11">Sept. 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">NOT ENOUGH PRIDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In order to determine the effectiveness of the appeal to Bohemian parents to have their high-school children enroll in the Bohemian department, we visited the Farragut High School yesterday. By the way, since the beginning of this term, the school has been called the Carter H. Harrison High School.</p>
   <p>We were received by the school principal himself, Mr. F. L. Morse, and when we told him the purpose of our visit, he assured us most kindly that he would be very happy to give us any information we might wish to have. What we heard from him, however, and the confirmation we later received from Professor B. Kral, who is in charge of the Bohemian department, was infinitely less pleasant than our reception. Only thirty-five pupils have enrolled in the beginners' class this year; four of them are not even of Bohemian descent. [The article lists the names of the pupils.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0267.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last year this department started with forty pupils.... of whom only thirty remained in February, when fifty-eight new pupils joined the class. Of these, thirty-six enrolled for the second-year course, and of the original class, only sixteen pupils enrolled in the third-year, that is, the advanced class. Thus, all in all, there are eighty-five pupils in the Bohemian department this year. The beginners' class consists of thirty-five, the second-year class of thirty-four, and the advanced class of sixteen pupils.</p>
   <p>The enrollment in the beginners' class was smaller this year than it was at the same time last year. As against this [record], the German department of the same school opened two beginners' classes, each with thirty-two pupils. Two beginners' classes with an equal number of pupils were opened also in the Latin department. The fact that in both of these departments there are also children of Bohemian descent makes the comparison that much more disappointing, nay, baffling.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to underestimate the value of any language. All of them have <pb facs="5418478_1_0268.jpg" n="3"/>their importance and meaning in this world. But nobody can accuse us of chauvinism if we say that as far as we ourselves are concerned, the Bohemian language must be our primary interest. We are far from any chauvinism, but we do hate the necessity of raising the accusation that the first ones to underestimate the value of Bohemian, their own native language, are the Bohemian parents themselves. If that were not the case, they would do all they could to see that their children learned that language in which they could best talk to one another from heart to heart, from soul to soul..... If the parents do not care whether or not their children learn to speak, read, and write Bohemian, the children themselves will care still less. On the other hand, if the parents would instill in their children, from their very earliest age, a healthy interest in the Bohemian language, and would keep it up, that interest would grow and develop into love and affectionate reverence, and the Bohemian department of the Harrison High School would have not eighty-five, but three or four hundred pupils. The school is in the very center of one of the largest Bohemian settlements and--according to its principal--between seventy and seventy-five per cent of its pupils <pb facs="5418478_1_0269.jpg" n="4"/>are of Bohemian origin.</p>
   <p>When Mr. Morse says he deeply regrets the fact that the Bohemian department of his school is far behind other departments, and that he cannot find any explanation for this phenomenon, all we can say is that this sad state of affairs is for us Bohemians exceedingly embarrassing and puts us to deep shame.</p>
   <p>Mr. Morse frankly admitted that he had expected a much larger enrollment, and that he had also been ready to open two classes for the beginners. He had made all the necessary arrangements with Professor Kral, and had never failed to show his own strong personal interest in the success of the Bohemian venture. His disappointment is keen. Now he knows that our parents are indifferent, and consequently their children are disinterested. In fact, he seems to have noticed that the children are even ashamed of their parents' language. What a sad observation! And how much more sad it is when made <pb facs="5418478_1_0270.jpg" n="5"/>by an outsider and supported by figures which need no interpretation.</p>
   <p>When he took us into the classroom of Professor Kral--empty at that time because of lack of students to listen to the Professor's lecture--he remarked that he would be happier if something could be done to change the sad state of affairs. There was still time to attempt it, he thought. We now again address an appeal to Bohemian parents of the Harrison High School students to awaken their children to an interest in the Bohemian department of the school, and to see to it that they apply for enrollment. If we have a large enrollment in that department, we won't be doing the school a favor, nor will we be doing the Chicago Board of Education a favor; the only ones who will profit by it will be ourselves. We will profit because the younger generation will be strengthened and because we will awaken the self-respect on which so much depends.</p>
   <p>Now, let us do our duty. Let us not permit ourselves to be put to shame by <pb facs="5418478_1_0271.jpg" n="6"/>a few non-Bohemians who also send their children to the Harrison High School. Let us prove that we appreciate the fact that the Bohemian language may now be taught in any public school where there are enough pupils who want to study it. Let us not permit things to come to such a pass that non-Bohemians in America will be able to say that they were more interested in, and had a greater appreciation of the Bohemian language than we ourselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
