<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs Appreciate Chicago Journal's Attitude</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0821</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0821.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-10">Feb. 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS APPRECIATE CHICAGO JOURNAL'S ATTITUDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Daily Journal is really the only paper which takes a more intense interest in our affairs and often prints editorials or other articles of importance to us. One such article appeared in last night's issue. It contains one of the most sympathetic manifestations of a real grasp of the situation in which the Czech people find themselves. It is captioned "Sufferers Left by the Wayside," and runs as follows:</p>
   <p>"Much, but not a single word too many, has been written about the two unhappy countries, Belgium and Serbia, whose people are being beaten down by the originators of the war in Berlin. There is, however, one more plucky little country whose martyrdom passes so to say unheeded, Bohemia. By this we mean the Czecho-Slovak nation which comprises Bohemia, Moravia, and the northwestern part of Hungary. This nation of ten million souls has an ancient and rich culture, and possesses an indomitable love of <pb facs="5418478_1_0822.jpg" n="2"/>freedom. It withstood the Germanizing onslaught of the Hapsburgs, remained a Slavic nation, and a friend of France and England, the protagonists of liberalism among the European powers, and loyal to Russia, the protector of the Slavic nations. For this reason, the Czecho-Slovaks were oppressed even before the war as a subjugated nation, but since the outbreak of the War, their lot is pitiable. Before the first year of the war was ended, more than two-thirds of their newspapers were suppressed, and many of their editors were imprisoned or executed. No Bohemian musician was permitted to play the great works of Smetana and Dvorak; no Czech was allowed to read or propagate Tolstoy or Emerson. All of the Sokol societies were dissolved. The Germans were intrusted with the administration of the police in Czech cities, the Czech language was banished from the railroads, and was not even to be used for telegraphic messages. These ordinances are being enforced with fiercest rigor, and, according to the official report of a semi-governmental Vienna newspaper, there were not less than 1045 civil executions in Bohemia and Moravia up <pb facs="5418478_1_0823.jpg" n="3"/>to December 1916.</p>
   <p>The Czechs resisted this tyranny as well as they could. When they were forced by their torturors to fight their own friends, they surrendered at every opportunity that offered itself during battle. The twenty-eighth regiment (infantry) went over to the Russians as a unit, and now valiantly fight on the other side. The 8th, 30th, 88th and 102nd regiments went over in great numbers. Thousands of defiant Czech soldiers were executed, the properties of families, whose members had allowed themselves to be taken prisoners, were confiscated, yet the defiance of the Czech did not abate. A people so courageous and daring cannot be downed, and should not be held in slavery. When the War is ended, there should arise an independent Czech republic."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
