<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-21">Aug. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of Taxpayers of Lawndale</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-21">Aug. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF TAXPAYERS OF LAWNDALE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting was called to order at 8:30 o'clock, August 19, at Mr. Denemark's place on 23rd and Homan Streets. Before the meeting began, many new applications for membership were received. After they had paid their fees and dues for one month in advance, dues were collected from the older members. The meeting was then called to order by the chairman Mr. Anton Kaspar. The names of officers and committee members were read. The minutes of the previous regular meeting and of the special meeting were read. Both were accepted as read. The secretary Mr. Palacek announced that he had written to the president of the West Parks Commissioners, but had not received a reply <pb facs="5418478_1_1603.jpg" n="2"/>up to the present time. A bill for $2.25 for the purchase of 100 tickets was presented. Mr. Denemark presented a bill covering two cases of beer which the members of the club had ordered and which were consumed that evening. Bills were approved and ordered paid.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stauber, an officer of the entertainment committee, spoke briefly about preparations that have been made for the Taxpayer's Picnic to be held on September 17, in Daisy Park. A committee from Sokol Karel Havlicek appeared before the meeting. The committee asked whether or not the Club would be willing to give up their previously engaged Sunday, September 17, for the holding of festive cornerstone-laying ceremonies of the new building of Sokol Karel Havlicek. In exchange, the Sokols wanted to allow the Club to use Sunday, October 8, in the same park. The Sokol committee reasoned that <pb facs="5418478_1_1604.jpg" n="3"/>if the Club allowed them to use the earlier date, the Sokols could begin with the actual work of construction and much could be accomplished in those three weeks. The Sokol committee expects that the building will be finished by Christmas. A general debate ensured and at last Mr. Sebek announced that the Club would be willing to accommodate the Sokols, providing the Sokols would be willing to reimburse the Club for all expenses incurred in making preparations for their picnic. The Club would then give up the Sokols would be willing to reimburse the Club for all expenses incurred in making preparations for their picnic. The Club would then given up the picnic idea altogether..... The Sokols would have to pay forty dollars; this seemed to them to be excessive and failing to come to an agreement, the committee withdrew from the meeting. Tax bills wore then distributed to the taxpayers who had protested to Assessor Miller against excessive, unjustly assessed taxes; some of the taxpayers were given reductions in their tax bills as high as fifteen dollars. Mr. Bambas announced that 150 pretests <pb facs="5418478_1_1605.jpg" n="4"/>had already been received and more were expected. It is hoped that in some cases reductions of as much as fifty per cent would be obtained with the aid of Attorney Kerner . . . . . Mr. Sebek announced that many people hesitate to protest or sign similar papers because they fear that they will have to pay for something; others because they think these are only political matters. Some members complained that they are not notified of meetings. Remedial action will be taken. The meeting then proceeded to elect officers and to appoint committees for the picnic to be held on September 17. New members were then admitted; their names read and unanimously accepted. Receipts of the evening were $11.60, disbursements $5.25, after which the meeting adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
