<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-08">Apr.8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Austria Must Be Partitioned Communication from the Press Bureau of the Bohemian National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0808</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0808.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-08">Apr.8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AUSTRIA MUST BE PARTITIONED Communication from the Press Bureau of the Bohemian National Alliance</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the debate on the authorization of President Wilson to declare War on Germany, Senator John Sharp Williams delivered a brilliant address in which he especially emphasized the urgent necessity of declaring war on Austria also, and the ultimate elimination of the houses Habsburg and Hohenzollern as ruling powers. The Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Czech National Alliance), in order to point to the imperative necessity of the dissolution of the Austro-Hungarian dual monarchy, sent the following telegram to Senator Williams:</p>
   <p>"Congratulations to your correct declaration that the United States must perpetuate the war until the guaranty is given that the Hohenzollern <pb facs="5418478_1_0809.jpg" n="2"/>and the Habsburg dynasties shall not rule over Germany and Austria-Hungary any more, and also, until Turkey is driven back into Asia. Austria is equally guilty with Germany, and the partitioning of Austria is unconditionally necessary for democracy. Austria is an artificial state, and has no right to exist. It should be broken up into an independent Czecho-Slovak republic, a free Jugoslavia, and a free Hungary.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian National Alliance in America.</p>
   <p>Doctor Fisher, president."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
