<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-11">Apr. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0802</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0802.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-11">Apr. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Ceterum Autem Censeo, Carthaginem Esse Delendam" - Cato of ancient Rome concluded each of his speeches with these words which mean: "---in conclusion, it is my judgment that Cartage be destroyed." Similarly, each speech, each article, concerning the War should wind up with "Austria must be destroyed!" Not her nations by any means, but the Austrian state. If the statesmen intend to remove the teutonic danger and render impossible a repetition of the present War, they must destroy Austria, for only with the latter can Germany be dangerous to the rest of Europe. Austria-Hungary is a monster, where a German-Magyar minority rules, the majority consisting of Slavic, Italian, and Roumanian peoples, where services are required not for our own people, but for the aggrandizement of Germany.</p>
   <p>Austria must be killed, and a community of free central European states <pb facs="5418478_1_0803.jpg" n="2"/>put in its place. That means a Czecho-Slovak, Serbo-Croatian-Slovenian, and a Hungarian state. As to the Germans living in the Alpine countries, let them keep their Habsburgs or join with Germany. The arrogance will thus have been banished forever into narrow borders, from within which it will not be able to menace anyone. Our statesmen, and those of the Allies, should therefore, concentrate their reasoning upon this consideration and say, similarly to Cato of ancient Rome: "Ceterum Autem Censeo Austria Hungarian esse delendam!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
