<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-18">June 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The United States Supreme Court Decides against the Prohibitionists (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0662</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0662.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-18">June 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNITED STATES SUPREME COURT DECIDES AGAINST THE PROHIBITIONISTS (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Supreme Court of the United States has made a decision lately which will not particularly please our prohibitionists, and the result of which will be that some states, in spite of their dry laws, will not be dry.</p>
   <p>The decision concerns the so-called Webb and Kenyon law prohibiting the transportation of alcoholic beverages into dry states. This law was passed by Congress, and the prohibitionists were happy because they thought it would stop the transportation of even a drop of alcoholic beverages into some of the states. But our transportation companies have been disregarding this law and have been delivering beer, wine, and whiskey to anybody who would give them an order. That resulted in <pb facs="5418478_1_0663.jpg" n="2"/>a lawsuit, and the Adams Express Company was heavily fined for transproting alcoholic beverages from Tennessee into dry Kentucky. The Company kept on appealing the decision, and the case was carried up to the Supreme Court of the United States, where it was decided in favor of the Express Company. The Court ruled that every citizen, in dry as well as in other states, has the right to order alcoholic beverages for his own use, except in states where the laws [forbid] the ownership or consumption of such beverages. Thus, the drinking in dry states will go merrily on, the dry states will be as wet as other states where the people are sensible enough not to put prohibition laws on their own necks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
