<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-27">Sept. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Our Cicero Taxpayers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1537</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1537.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-27">Sept. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CICERO TAXPAYERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ceskoslovensky Poplatnicky Spolek (Czechoslovak Taxpayer's Association) held a special meeting September 17 in which the question of the proposed four branch high schools was taken up. The meeting was very well attended, not only by members of the association but also by many nonmembers, men and women interested in school matters. Of the members of the School Board, there were present J.J. Sherlock and O. E. Rix. Also present were H. V. Church, principal of the high school, and his assistant, W. C. Robb, O.M. Schrantz, school treasurer, Mr. Stritesky, instructor in Harrison High School, and others. Both the members of the School Board and the high school principals advocated the building of branches in Grant Works, Hawthorne, and in North and South Berwyn. They called attention to the great distances and poor transportation from those communities, as well as from Stickney and Lyons.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1538.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The question whether the building of these branches would necessitate an increase in the school tax was answered in the affirmative, but that the increase would not be large because, according to the law, that tax must not exceed two and three quarters per cent of the total of taxes paid. The cost of the building of all four school branches would be about $480,000, and as there is already $72,000 in the treasury, a bond issue of $600,000 would cover the cost and leave some $190,000 for the equipment of the schools.</p>
   <p>Treasurer Schantz spoke against the building of the branches and was in favor of building an addition to the J. Sterling Morton High School. Mr. Stritesky expressed the same opinion. He said that the dividing of the school would be of no advantage to the students, because it would be impossible to give them as complete and perfect instruction as they get now when everything is centralized in one school; also that the expenses would be much higher.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1539.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After various expressions of opinion of those present as to how to solve the problem of insufficient space, and also the problem of better transportation, it was decided to put pressure to bear upon the School Board to place on the ballot both proposals, that is, the building of four new high schools, and the building of an addition to the present high school building. The secretary was charged with broaching this subject to the board.</p>
   <p>The meeting then took up the question as to when the Masaryk School would be made available to various associations for their meetings. It was decided to open the School for that purpose every first Saturday of the month.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held October 1. Discussion of the proposed banquet will be on the program, and other questions that concern our community will be taken up.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
