<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-19">May 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Court Trial of Picha and Beranek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-19">May 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">COURT TRIAL OF PICHA AND BERANEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before a jury in Judge Bowles's criminal section of the Municipal Court in the City Hall, the case of Mr. Karel Vondras, a baker residing at 1540 West 18th Street, versus the editor-in-chief, Karel H. Beranek, of the daily Spravedlnost and Karel Picha, one of the principal leaders in the camp of the "reds", was decided against the latter two, and the lecture which they received will not soon be forgotten by them. After a conference lasting two hours, the jury found the two guilty of criminal libel, and it is now up to the judge to sentence them. The penalty may amount to as much as six months in jail, the maximum in this case, and also a maximum fine of $1,000. The jury was composed of men of intelligence, and included four unionists, one of whom was an agent of a carpenters' union.</p>
   <p>After the sentence was handed down, the legal representatives of the defendants made it known that they would seek a new trial, and the hearing of pleas was set for Saturday, May 23. If the judge should refuse the pleas, the case will probably be taken before the Appellate Court.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1054.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have referred to the substance of the case before. Mr. Vondras claimed that he was visited by Mr. Picha, who was then a business agent for the International Bakers' and Confectioners' Union No. 13, and Mr. Picha threatened to deprive Mr. Vondras of his union label because, as the agent claimed, Mr. Vondras had broken the union rules. Mr. Vondras claimed that Mr. Picha proposed to "fix" the difficulty for fifty dollars, to which Mr. Vondras refused to agree, and Mr. Picha thereupon carried away several boxes of union labels from Mr. Vondras's bakeshop.</p>
   <p>In order to conform to the rules of the city weighmaster, Mr. Vondras began to paste the labels of the Bohemian Bakers' and Confectioners' Union No. 2 on his bakery goods. This union is incorporated under state laws and has a duly registered trade-mark.</p>
   <p>But with this arrangement, Mr. Vondras fell into disfavor with his comrades, who began to "fire away at him," as it were, and the brutal acts grew in intensity day after day. Many handbills were distributed in which Mr. Vondras was pictured as an enemy of union labor; and the Circuit Court <pb facs="5418478_1_1055.jpg" n="3"/>was asked to stop Mr. Vondras from using the labels of the Bohemian union, because it was claimed that the design is an imitation of the copyrighted label of the International union. Judge Windes decided that the two labels are of vary different design, and he simply denied the petition of the unionists.</p>
   <p>The trump card played against Mr. Vondras by the Spravedlnost was in the November 23 issue of last year, under the caption, "Vseodborova Hlidka" (Sentinel of Industry). In this incendiary article, he was accused of being untrue to his customers by his use of counterfeit labels. The writer of this marked and easily discernable insinuation was, we are told, Mr. Picha; and therefore Mr. Vondras instituted court proceedings for the protection of his honor and good name. Mr. Vondras sued not only Mr. Picha, but also the editor-in-chief, Karel H. Beranek, who is responsible for the contents of the article in the Spravedlnost.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vondras felt justified in suing these men, because his character as well as his business was blighted. Therefore, it was quite natural for him to <pb facs="5418478_1_1056.jpg" n="4"/>seek redress in court.</p>
   <p>The action was brought before a jury in Judge Bowles's court on Friday afternoon and ended yesterday with the sentencing of the two defendants. Mr. Vondras, with the aid of witnesses, proved that he employs members of a union which is duly incorporated and has its authorized trade-mark; that any falsifying of labels is out of the question. As to the offer of Mr. Picha to adjust the difficulties for a fifty-dollar consideration, Mr. Vondras had witnesses to back up that assertion. The moot point of the correct translation of the objectionable words was given to the jury by the attorney for the prosecution, Mr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka, whose competence in making translations no one could doubt because of his thorough training in both the Bohemian and English languages.</p>
   <p>Mr. Beranek for the defense stepped into the witness chair and was followed by Professor Jaroslav J. Zurhal, who informed the jury that the translation of the objectionable article, as it was arranged by the prosecution, was incorrect in substance, and in translation entirely different words could <pb facs="5418478_1_1057.jpg" n="5"/>be used--words much milder in meaning, but expressing the same thought. Professor Zurhal also proved himself an authority and master of the two languages, but upon cross-examination by Attorney J. B. Brillow, representing Mr. Vondras, Professor Zmrhal had to admit that there was a great difference between the words "somewhat similar" and "counterfeit," and the word "counterfeit" was used in the article printed in the Spravedlnost.</p>
   <p>From the evidence presented, the members of the jury became convinced that the purpose of the article was to cast suspicion upon the well-meaning baker, Mr. Vondras, and not, as the defense claimed, to show him up as an enemy of labor. For that reason the jury found the two editors of the Spravedlnost guilty of defamation of character.</p>
   <p>The defense in this case had no easy work of it, because the sense of the article was so clear that its meaning could not have been changed by technical subterfuges, and Mr. Picha's behavior did not do him credit in the least. He wisely refrained from testifying.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
