<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-04-07">Apr. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Bohemian-Slovak Movement (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0841</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0841.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-04-07">Apr. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A BOHEMIAN-SLOVAK MOVEMENT (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the present war started raging in Europe, the whole Slavic element here in America, all members of the oppressed nations in Europe, realized suddenly that the historic moment is near that will give them an opportunity to throw off the foreign yoke. At the same time, they realized that they must not stand idle and wait for what the future will bring--what new state formations will rise from the sea of blood that is being shed. The Poles, the Lithuanians, the Serbs, the Slovenes, all came to the conclusion that they are being called upon to lead the liberating movement. we have to confess that it is among us, the Bohemians, that this movement is least successful. As to the reasons for this, there are several. At first it was the unfortunate controversy between the advocates of the so-called "relief movement" and the so-called "liberating movement".</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0842.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first movement was a failure; there is no doubt about that any more. The few dollars that were collected are a permanent reproach to the American Bohemians' indifference rather than a substantial relief fund of which we could be somewhat proud.</p>
   <p>The second movement did not do so well either, being ridiculed and attacked by various people who, partly because of ignorance and partly because of offended pride, have succeeded in splitting public opinion in Bohemian-America, and even in filling it with indifference, nay, disgust with the whole matter. This has been going on even though it is clearly apparent that only political action, an action directed toward the formation of new states on the ruins of the rotten Hapsburg Monarchy, has a promise of permanent beneficial results. A relief movement may alleviate misery, but it can never abolish it if the causes of that misery are not removed. There probably will be no difference of opinion among us about the statement that the struggles between Austria's nations, Vienna's blood-sucking policies, and the Hapsburgs' yoke have been the principal reasons for the lamentable economic status of Austria's nations. In principle, the <pb facs="5418478_1_0843.jpg" n="3"/>relief movement is a matter of sentiment, of the heart, while the political movement has its roots in common sense, in the brain. Which of these two is of greater value is easy to decide.</p>
   <p>A great improvement, however, has been taking place recently. It may be late, but it is better late than never. A central body for the whole of Bohemian-America has been organized to take over the leadership of the movement; contacts have been effected with Bohemian committees in Russia, France, and England; a more effective publicity campaign is being conducted to acquaint the world with our desires, our hopes. We have gotten rid of the spirit of inertia, of those lazy and cowardly people who would not attempt anything that could not be realized tomorrow, or better still, who would attempt nothing at all. We have come to realize that anything that can be achieved tomorrow and with little effort is not worth having, and that only by setting for ourselves a great goal, an ideal that is seemingly impossible of achievement, can we get ahead. Now, we have to come to the realization that, being the whole nation's most ardent lovers of liberty--we came to America because we would not bear political or <pb facs="5418478_1_0844.jpg" n="4"/>economic oppression--we should be the leaders in the fight for that nation's liberation. Now, what do we want to achieve by our political movement?</p>
   <p>We want the foundation of an independent Bohemian-Slovak State on a federative basis following one fixed policy towards its neighbors and other nations, with utmost liberty and freedom within, with a republican form of government. This goal, whenever we have thought of it, included both the Bohemians and the Slovaks. That this is the case was clearly shown at the Paris Slavic congress where it was especially stressed that Hungarian-Slovakia should become a part of the future independent Bohemian commonwealth, because the congress realized that it will not be the Slovaks, but the Bohemians who will derive the greatest benefit from this union. The Slovaks are in a position to give the Bohemians much more than the Bohemians can give the Slovaks. They can help in restoring purity to the Bohemian literary language which was corrupted by Jungman [first modern Bohemian grammarian and lexicographer]; they can have a purifying influence upon the national aims of the Bohemians which have been defiled by false cosmopolitanism; they can instill into us some of their energy and vitality <pb facs="5418478_1_0845.jpg" n="5"/>steeled by their struggle with their Hungarian oppressors. In exchange for all this we can offer nothing more than a modicum of modern civilization which, after all, is a poor kind of gift if we realize that it has led the world to such disaster as the present war, and that such civilization may be achieved in one generation, while the rare qualities of the Slovak people took centuries to develop.</p>
   <p>Under such conditions it would be only natural that it is the Bohemians who should be first in working for co-operation between American Bohemians and American Slovaks in an effort to create an independent Bohemian-Slovak state upon the wreckage of the putrid realm of the Hapsburgs; a state which would be based on complete equality of rights of both component elements in the inner affairs of the state; a state which would be bounded by national borders and would forget the silly border lines as we remember them from our school atlases; a state which would draw the line of demarkation between the Slovak and Bohemian autonomous administrative spheres along the line of territory inhabited by one or the other national element. That is to say, that, within the common state, the <pb facs="5418478_1_0846.jpg" n="6"/>Slovaks would form one autonomous unit, no matter whether they are now in Moravia or in Hungarian-Slovakia. Let us not forget that there are about one million Slovaks in Moravia. To sum up briefly: The American-Bohemians should be at the head of the action aiming at the formation of one common Bohemian-Slovak state with complete autonomy for the Bohemians and for the Slovaks within; the demarkation of the autonomous spheres drawn along language boundaries.</p>
   <p>Instead of this, we see that it was from the Bohemian side only that voices have been heard urging Bohemian action quite separate from the Slovaks, and without regard for whatever the Slovaks might do. Thus, after a long struggle of eight months, when, in principle, the political movement has been recognized as correct and proper, we come to the sad phenomenon of some puny, small-minded people making fresh attempts against that action, people who prefer a tiny backyard as long as it is exclusively their own, from which to call "Hands off!" They prefer this to working as equal and full-fledged partners on one great undertaking; this is the phenomenon of efforts on the part os such puny and small-minded people to wreck the whole movement in order to satisfy their own petty personal <pb facs="5418478_1_0847.jpg" n="7"/>pride. The Slovaks may be sure that that is not the Bohemian position; that that is not the position of even a small minority of the Bohemians. It is the position of one individual, a position that must be fully and strongly repudiated and denied. All Bohemians agree that we have to form a united front with the Slovaks, that we have to work together with one another, and that we call "Hands off!" to the man who would like to spoil this co-operation because of trifling selfish and reprehensible reasons.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
