<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-29">Mar. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Support Slovak Affairs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0816</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0816.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-29">Mar. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S SUPPORT SLOVAK AFFAIRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In these portentous times which have united the Czechs and the Slovaks under one flag and with the same aim, that is Czecho-Slovak independence, our Slovak brethren have demonstrated repeatedly that they are sincere about the unification. They proved it not only by the utterances of their speakers and articles in their papers, but by their actions as well. Suffice it to point to their willingness and sacrifices at the very beginning of the struggle for Czecho-Slovak independence, in which the Slovenska Liga (Slovak league) worked hand in hand with the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni (Czech National Association). The Slovaks lent us a helping hand, which was evident and appreciated during the bustle in the Czech Bazaar. The Czechs thanked them and promised to reciprocate their friendly support on the very next occasion.</p>
   <p>Well, the best opportunity to show our gratitude will be offered next <pb facs="5418478_1_0817.jpg" n="2"/>Saturday, when we can at least partly return what our Slovak brethren and sisters have done to enhance the cause. There will be a theatrical performance under the auspices of the Ochot. Druzstuo T. Slov. Amer. Sokol (Amateur group of the Slovak American Sokol) in the hall of the Sokol Chicago on March 31. May our fellow countrymen prove that Czech-Slovak unity does not mean only a slogan to them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
