<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-02">Feb. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Societies Lose in Crash</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0987</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0987.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-02">Feb. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH SOCIETIES LOSE IN CRASH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The main committee of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Association of Czech Ladies) held a meeting last night for the purpose of fixing or estimating the amount of obligations owed the association by the "Notary Public," Robert Pitte &amp; Son, the firm which, through the law firm, Sabath, Stafford &amp; Sabath, plead voluntary bankruptcy recently. There were rumors current that the association is liable to lose a large amount of money, as its death benefits have been handled mostly by the defunct firm. One of the first questions to be tackled by the association was one of the reliability of these reports, and their possible dubbing as mere gossip.</p>
   <p>Our own information indicates that the Pittes have been handling the death benefit cases of the association for a long time, even when Robert Pitte's wife, an arduous worker for the association, was living. There was no secrecy about the business, so that it is hardly possible to single out any one person to be brought before a court. It is evident from last night's meeting that the <pb facs="5418478_1_0988.jpg" n="2"/>association looks at these conditions in the same light as we do.</p>
   <p>In the discussion directed by President Mary Liska, it was found that the Pitte firm owed the association the round sum of $5,000. The activity of Mrs. Mary Smrcek was then put under scrutiny, but was found within the by-laws of the association. It was resolved that the discrepancy be made good from the building fund and the "main committee" fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
