<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-20">Aug. 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Taxpayers Improvement Club of the Eleventh Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1606</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1606.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-20">Aug. 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE TAXPAYERS IMPROVEMENT CLUB OF THE ELEVENTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Club held its regular meeting on Thursday, August 17, in the Pilsen Sokol Hall. The program outlined at the previous meeting was only partially accomplished. The committee was not able to visit the Tenth Ward Club and has not as yet come to an understanding with the protesting citizens of the Twelfth Ward. It is expected that this will be accomplished before the next meeting. In regard to the small park the Club was not able to start anything because Alderman Danish did not notify the committee so that it might take part in the protest by Polish residents against the creation of a park in the neighborhood of Twenty-second Street.</p>
   <p>Attention was directed to an article in Hlasatel, which stated that the promoters of the widening of Twelfth Street mean that the city would pay half and the adjoining property owners half of the cost of the widening.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1607.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was explained that in fact the neighboring Wards would be taxed twice; once by a general tax, and then again by a special assessment. It is regrettable that such general indifference is shown toward a matter so important to every property owner; today he saves a dime and later he will pay not only dollars, but hundreds of dollars.</p>
   <p>Fred Svoboda.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
