<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-10">Mar. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">United Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0558</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0558.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-10">Mar. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Czech branch of the United Societies was held in Mr. Joseph Plaček's hall last Friday. A very large number of delegates from Chicago Czech organizations took a lively part in it. Mr. John A. Cervenka presided after an absence of some time, and he was heartily welcomed. He called on those present to devote their energies to the fight against prohibitionist elements, for the preservation of self-government in Chicago, and for the personal liberty of its citizens.</p>
   <p>A remarkably large number of Czech organizations was announced as having joined the United Societies recently. Chief Bailiff Anton J. Čermák, secretary of the Societies, called attention to the prohibitionist petition, which is now kept in the offices of the election commissioners, and to the many forged signatures and false names. He solicited the good will of all honest voters, urging them not to fail to appear at the places of registration. He declared that the situation is very serious, and reminded the gathering about their duties as <pb facs="5418478_1_0559.jpg" n="2"/>citizens. Every single vote cast means additional protection for personal liberty against increased taxes and against fanaticism. Mr. Čermák stated that in typical prohibition districts, every married woman and every girl is registering, and that their number fully equals that of male voters. Their efforts are bent on crippling our city, devaluating property, and raising the taxes which are unduly high just now anyway.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Velik reproached those men of unsound reasoning who are hampering anti-prohibitionist agitation. When women are urged to register, men of this type address them in a vulgar manner with such trite phrases as "Women should stay at home and wash the dishes".</p>
   <p>Mr. Plaček, chairman of the campaign committee, announced that he has appointed more members to the committee. They are Mr. Jakob Fink, Mr. Straka, and Mmes. Ženíšek and Vacík. The committee, he said, is awaiting directions from the main body of the United Societies to initiate proper action.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0560.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Čermák stated that if the prohibitionist elements succeeded in enforcing their schemes, the city, according to figures compiled by the City Council, would lose fully eight million dollars in yearly revenue. If on May 1 the saloons are closed, the city will suffer an additional loss of six million that was counted on in the appropriations. This gigantic decrement would have to be made up by taxes, imposed mostly on trades and business. This would result in a further rise in prices of food and other necessities.</p>
   <p>Mr. Venceslaus Řehák stressed the real intentions that lie at the bottom of prohibitionist efforts. It does not essentially matter to them--particularly to William Jennings Bryan--whether saloons are open or alcohol is dispensed, or even whether they contribute to the delinquency of the habitual drunkard's family. They use these issues only as a screen to conceal their ultimate aims, i. e., to usurp the power of government in all its branches, and to establish a dictatorial domination headed by such mountebanks and prevaricators as Bryan, Billy Sunday, and their consorts.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0561.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Cyril Jandus declared that these explanations were on the right track. He enlarged upon them in pointing to the alarm with which prohibitionist women view the education of youth in our camp, while, as a rule, they themselves expend their educational energies on the training of cats and dogs.</p>
   <p>After disposing of some routine business, the meeting was closed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
