<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-09-19">Sept. 19, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">To the Honor of the Bohemian Nationality in Chicago (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-09-19">Sept. 19, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE HONOR OF THE BOHEMIAN NATIONALITY IN CHICAGO (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>America, or rather Chicago, is upset that a Bohemian attained the distinction, which many rich and prominent Americans, Germans and Irishmen hopefully expected.</p>
   <p>In the last session of the Board of Education, a Bohemian, Adolf Kraus, a lawyer, was nominated as Chairman of The School Board. This distinction is so great, that an English newspaper mentioned it in long articles.</p>
   <p>To a certain degree, the president of the Board of Education is a more educated person than the Mayor himself, who is a politician elected by the voters, whose votes must be gained by different ways and means.</p>
   <p>The Board of Education is an office of honor, and its members are chosen and selected men of excellence and confidence; they are trusted with the problem of the education of all the younger generation in our city, and their previous merits authorize them to run for the position of chairman of The Board of <pb facs="5418478_1_0199.jpg" n="2"/>Education.</p>
   <p>It is a great honor to be a member of the Board in a large city like Chicago. Adolf Kraus was a member of the Board and he represented, with dignity, the Bohemian Community of Chicago two years, participating in deliberations and decisions together with other prominent citizens of Chicago.</p>
   <p>This time the members of the Board of Education called the blameless member, Mr. Kraus, to preside over them, knowing that he is the most irreproachable, capable and prominent man for this office.</p>
   <p>The appointment of Mr. Kraus to the presidency is in recognition and honor, of the Bohemian population in Chicago, which numbers over 40,000 people.</p>
   <p>We were greatly pleased, when two years ago the Bohemian lawyer, A. Kraus, was nominated by the Mayor for office in the Board of Education, and this proved a real success for our nation and greater honor, then if three Bohemian candidates should have been appointed to paying positions in some other office where everything is connected with profit and the making of a living only, and nothing more.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0200.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When our candidate and representative was elevated to the presidency of the most important board in the city we should radiate with much greater happiness than ever.</p>
   <p>It means that he is entrusted by all the citizens with their schools, their ambitious children and their confidence. We should be proud, that the citizens can choose from among us such trustworthy men, who are serving the City unselfishly in most important and dignified positions.</p>
   <p>We are absolutely sure that the Chairman of the Board of Education, our Adolph Kraus, will perform his duties to the honor, not only of himself but to honor of our whole Bohemian community. Should he not act with dignity and should he not respond to the confidence put in him, he would cast shame on our nation, as one who is not able to handle this kind of an office.</p>
   <p>If he responds in every way to his responsibilities he will procure for us honor and pride; he will prove that he is of our blood, educated and raised in our midst and elevated by his own merits. Thanks to his energetic efforts he wholly mastered the English language, gained the full confidence of our people during his so journ among us and received complete acknowledgement of his ability in all our social and official circles.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0201.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He deserves the elected elevation to the high office.</p>
   <p>We congratulate Mr. Kraus on his elevation, we ardently congratulate ourselves for this product of our social group. Our whole community, those previously despised "Bohemians" will gain tremendously in the opinion of the Germans, Irishmen and Americans, who have always insulted and ridiculed us.</p>
   <p>We can prove, now, that a Bohemian is the chairman of their most important institution and the fact will remain, for a long time, in the memory of all, that a Bohemian has occupied this high position honorably, honestly, and to the satisfaction of all citizens of Chicago.</p>
   <p>We know that Adolf Kraus will not forget the interests of the Bohemian nation here in regard to the Sokols and the more convenient location of our schools in considering the education of Bohemian children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
