<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-12-18">Dec. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">United Societies Prepares Petition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-12-18">Dec. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED SOCIETIES PREPARES PETITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak, in his capacity as secretary of the United Civic Societies of Chicago, declared yesterday that, shortly after New Year's, petitions would be put into circulation for presentation to the election commission, asking to have put on the "small ballot" at the April election the question whether cities should be given the authority to regulate their own affairs in regard to saloons, including the question of closing them on Sundays. The petition will require about 170,000 signatures, the same number as are necessary for the petition of the drys for the complete abolition of saloons in Chicago. While the prohibitionists will have trouble in securing the necessary number of signatures of registered voters, it is certain that the liberal element will in two or three weeks have more them than are needed. The question that the United Civic Societies want to see on the ballot--and since they wants, they will get it--reads like this:</p>
   <p>"Should the State legislature amend the law regarding the administration of cities and towns so that cities and towns availing themselves of that privilege would <pb facs="5418478_1_0603.jpg" n="2"/>have the right to make their own regualtions concerning saloons, including the closing of saloons on Sunday?"</p>
   <p>The result of the voting on this question will not, of course, compel the legislature to pass a law of that kind, but the large majority of ballots with votes in favor of such a law will influence not only the State legislature but also the City administration. City autonomy and the closing of saloons on Sundays will be among the principal matters with which the coming session of legislature will deal. The United Civic Societies will require every candidate for the office of alderman to make a definite and binding statement concerning his standpoint on these questions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
