<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-17">Jan. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of Two Bohemian Taxpayers' Associations of Cicero to Effect a Merger</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1533</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1533.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-17">Jan. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF TWO BOHEMIAN TAXPAYERS' ASSOCIATIONS OF CICERO TO EFFECT A MERGER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committees of the two taxpayers' associations, Clyde and the Česko-Slovenský Poplatnický Spolek (Czechoslovak Taxpayers' Association), held a joint meeting last Sunday in the T. G. Masařýk school for the purpose of combining the two bodies into one organization. The meeting was presided over by Mr. H. Krček and the duties of the secretary were performed by the treasurer of the Clyde association.</p>
   <p>Various opinions of this project were expressed. As far as the financial situation of the members of the Clyde association is concerned, the representatives of that body assured the meeting that should there be a merger of the two associations, the members of the Česko-Slovenský Poplatnický Spolek would effect a financial settlement with the Clyde association.</p>
   <p>The committee of the latter group announced that their association will call <pb facs="5418478_1_1534.jpg" n="2"/>a meeting next Sunday, at which their members will decide by a vote whether the two taxpayers' associations should unite to form one body. Should the results of the meeting lead to such a union, it will be celebrated by some sort of an entertainment for the proposed combined membership of the two bodies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
