<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-09">Dec. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Circle at Harrison High School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-09">Dec. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH CIRCLE AT HARRISON HIGH SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Czech community probably does not know that Carter Harrison High School is attended yearly by more than one thousand girls and boys enrolled as regular students. Among these there are many who are gifted with various talents. This was evident at the concert which was given by the Czech students' club Beseda (Circle) on December 5 of this year. The event created a sensation and made many friends for the Czechs. The young amateur artists feel gratified and encouraged to such a degree that they even speak of appearing before larger public audiences.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it will not be out-of-place if we attach a picture in which some of the foremost adepts of dancing, singing, and instrumental music can be seen. Miss Helen Frish, one of the best known students of the school, is of Czech descent. She is the enthusiastic director of the singing branch of the Beseda. She renders the piano accompaniment for all musical events of <pb facs="5418478_1_0059.jpg" n="2"/>the school. She gives piano lessons, but she is also a gifted actress. The Harrison High School Dramatic Club selected her for the main role in the light play "Getting Engaged," which is to be given as the students' annual theater performance on December 12 and 13. Other pupils of Czech descent who will take part in the performance are Messrs. M. Ostoma, E. Jelínek, F. Jindra, T. Besta, and Jan Klaus.</p>
   <p>Miss Florence Polák is undoubtedly the best singer of whom the Harrison High School can boast. Her voice was magnificent in several Dvořák songs at the last concert.</p>
   <p>Miss Milada Krametbauer is the third young lady seen in the picture. She is a leader in the dancing group.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
