<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-03">Nov. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Mayor Rages On</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0604</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0604.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-03">Nov. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAYOR RAGES ON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The nearer the day of the Sunday demonstration of the United Civic Societies is, the greater becomes the nervousness of "Big Bill," former cowboy who, by dispensation of the liberal-minded citizens of Chicago has become the Mayor of our metropolis. How he will carry on when he sees the immense parade Sunday it is difficult to imagine. No doubt he now realizes that he has dug for himself his own political grave, and before he lies down in it, he certainly will treat the Chicago citizens to a series of true cowboy stunts.</p>
   <p>Yesterday Mayor Thompson sent to every municipal judge a letter attacking Superior Judge Olson, who had dared to refuse his demand to take steps toward depriving the chief bailiff of the municipal court, Anton J. Cermak of his office, and on top of that, ridiculed him, the mayor, for his prohibition fits. On that occasion, Judge Olson had something to say about sots playing "prohibition".</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0605.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Mayor, in his letter, requested the judges to take under consideration, in their next monthly meetings, the activities of Chief Bailiff Cermak, the leader of the liberal-minded element of Chicago, and the actions of Superior Judge Olson, who evidently approves of Mr. Cermak's attitude. "Big Bill" offers municipal judges these suggestions:</p>
   <p>"The judges should take into consideration the question as to whether or not the municipal bailiff may be trusted with the proper discharge of his duties in regard to the enforcement of the law requiring the closing of saloons on Sundays, in view of his publicly known attitude.</p>
   <p>"If Bailiff Anton J. Cermak's point of view has the approval of Judge Olson, the least the judges of the municipal court should do is to adopt in their meeting the rule that no cases of transgression of that law should be heard in Judge Olson's court."</p>
   <p>Copies of this interesting letter, which again indicates the extent of the <pb facs="5418478_1_0606.jpg" n="3"/>Mayor's rage when he realizes that what was to put him at the zenith of his political power and glory has become the instrument of his political death, were handed to Judge Olson and all judges of the municipal court yesterday at five o'clock in the evening.</p>
   <p>Judge Olson got a big "kick" out of the letter. Said he: "This letter reminds me of the letters we used to receive from Hadrian H. Baker, who was later indicted for molesting judges and other officials by sending them letters. Every time I see a fat envelope or a long letter, I suspect something of that kind. There is a rule in my office according to which all fat envelopes are put in a certain place and opened and read by my bailiff, because I do not care to waste my own time that way. This fat envelope was one of those few that have been made exceptions of; because it carried the stamp of the Mayor's office, I thought it might be something of greater importance.</p>
   <p>"The whole affair is nothing but a cheap political trick of a man who took <pb facs="5418478_1_0607.jpg" n="4"/>several months to decide that he was going to enforce the law. It is an attempt to put me under suspicion of being not interested in the enforcement of the law. Ever since the establishment of the municipal court nine years ago, all its judges have considered the Sunday saloon-closing law valid and have been instructing their juries accordingly.</p>
   <p>The next regular monthly meeting of the judges will be held November 26, but it is possible that Judge Olson will call a special meeting prior to that date, at which the Mayor's letter will be discussed and the proper reply to him drafted.</p>
   <p>It may safely be expected that Mr. Cermak also will react properly to the Mayor's attack. Said he yesterday, when he heard about that letter, but prior to reading it: "As soon as I have read the letter I shall issue a public statement and shall try to make quick work of 'cleaning up' on the Mayor. When he reads my letter, he will either jump out of his own hide or--out of the City Hall. I have learned various things about him which I have so far hesitated to tell <pb facs="5418478_1_0608.jpg" n="5"/>the public, but I shall not keep them to myself any longer. He will get a reply that will make him wish he had never touched this matter. The weapon he is wielding will be knocked out of his hand and it will bash his own skull."</p>
   <p>Mayor Thompson's new attack is aimed not only against Mr. Cermak and Judge Olson, but also against all the liberal-minded people of Chicago. These will give him their answer on Sunday, and it is certain that that answer, which will be in the form of an immense, stately demonstration, will quiet him down for good. The Bohemians will be represented in the parade in proportion to their numerical strength in the city and the strength of their conviction that their city must be administered according to principles of personal liberty and autonomy. All our associations have requested their members to assemble in front of their meeting places shortly after noon next Sunday; from there they will march to the place where the parade will be formed. Every member should be there. The interest of their own association and the interest of our own city requires their presence.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0609.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Nobody should be discouraged from participation because of the circumstance that the Mayor has refused to view the parade. The citizens, men and women, in the parade, will, by his absence, be spared the embarrassment of being reviewed in march by the man whom they have helped to elect, whose promises they had trusted, and who has deceived them in such a shameful way. When "Big Bill" could review the diminutive parade of the prohibitionists, half of which was composed of children, he should consider it his duty as the Mayor to attend a demonstration in which at least fifty thousand men and women, all Chicago citizens, will take part. But his absence will not be regretted by any one of them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
