<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-29">Oct. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 1 (Slovak)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-29">Oct. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>......The most valuable support which could be given to a candidate was practically assured to Mr. Albert B. Holecek, candidate for state senator in the nineteenth senatorial district. This happened when the Spolky Ceskych Hvezd (Bohemian Star Societies) unanimously agreed that they would support Mr. Holecek, in every possible way, to insure his election. The Ceske Hvezdy, one of this group, is an organization of mothers, wives, and sisters of Czechoslovak war veterans. When our women set a goal they certainly achieve it. In this organization there are some 650 Czech women and girls who are now working with enthusiasm and zeal to make Mr. Holecek's election a success. At the last meeting of the Spolek Ceskych Hvezd, Mrs. Josefa Karas, of 2750 South Central Park Avenue, presented a resolution which was enthusiastically supported by Mrs. Barbora Brun, of 2631 South Avers Avenue, president of the Hvezdy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1291.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The resolution points out that Mr. Holecek is an outstanding young Bohemian lawyer, that he organized the Lawndale-Crawford Post of the American Legion, being also its first commander, that he is a personal friend of thousands of former soldiers, but, above all, that his qualifications for office are of the best. It is known that Mr. Holecek is acquainted with the needs of the people, among whom he was born, and in whose midst he now resides, and it is well understood that he is going to work for them when he is elected. His election will be assured if all Czechoslovak voters, men and women, support him. The Ceske Hvezdy, therefore, urges all countrymen and countrywomen to place a cross in front of his name on the day of the election and thus secure, for the Czech voters of the district, a Czech representative in Springfield.</p>
   <p>The ladies declared unanimously, at their last meeting, that there should be no divergences of political opinions among Czechs and Slovaks, and that every good Czech or Slovak should work and vote for Mr. Holecek irrespective of the <pb facs="5418478_1_1292.jpg" n="3"/>political party to which he, or she, may belong. The Ceske Hvezdy decided, in the same meeting, to vote for our countrymen on the Democratic ticket: Mr. Anton J. Cermak, who is a candidate for the office of president of the board of county commissioners, and Mr. Josef Mendl, who is a candidate for the office of alderman. The members of the Spolky Ceskych Hvezd will place crosses in front of the names of these two men......</p>
   <p>A Bohemian ladies' Democratic club was organized recently. This club supports unanimously the entire Democratic ticket, and is now very active politically. The new organization will have its first public meeting on Thursday, November 2, 1922, in the Pilsen Park pavilion, West 26th Street and Albany Avenue. A program of entertainment will be combined with the purely political matters to be discussed. Admission will be free, but to prevent congestion at the entrance gates it will be necessary to secure tickets from any of the following ladies: Mesdames Paulina Prince, Josefina Sedlacek, B. Ludvik, M. Filip, <pb facs="5418478_1_1293.jpg" n="4"/>A. Brychta, R. Nedved, K. Vrchota, M. Liska, F. Janovsky, K. Smolar, F. Schejbal, M. Smrcka, A. Stolfa, C. Raz, M. Hora, A. Velik, J. Cepak, Josefina Beranek, Otto Kerner, A. Sokol, J. Forman, A. Kafka, A. Veprek, A. Hlina, Tejcek, Komorous, Straka, Hrodej, Mohlbeck, Kostohryz, Zapotocky, C. Krajicek, A. Zenisek, Bican, Hrdina, A. Sedlacek, Sistek, Dvorak, Jieserny, Kuflewski, Spatny, Docekal, Anna Hepil, and M. Peterson.</p>
   <p>Large Democratic meetings will be held tomorrow in the Pilsen Park pavilion and the Cesko-American Sin (Bohemian-American Hall) on West 18th Street, and both of these meetings should be well attended by our Czechoslovak people. It is desirable for our voters to show the greatest possible interest in the coming elections, for these will be of the utmost importance to every voter, man or woman, who desires to introduce economy into public offices, remove graft, and to decrease, or make more bearable, the tax burdens imposed upon the taxpayers of this county.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1294.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Both meetings will be addressed by able speakers and by the Democratic candidates. Our citizens, both men and women, should attend to hear the reasons why they should vote for the Democratic ticket. Among the speakers will be Alderman Anton J. Cermak, Congressman Adolf J. Sabath, Mr Josef A. Mendl, and many others.....On Tuesday next there will be a great Democratic meeting, in the Sokol Karel Jonas in Cicero, Illinois, in which there will also be speeches by our foremost Democratic candidates. All these meetings begin at 8 P. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
