<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-29">June 29, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Tenth Ward Taxpayers' Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1613</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1613.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-29">June 29, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">TENTH WARD TAXPAYERS' MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the Tenth Ward Taxpayers was called to order by the chairman, Mr. Tom. Zahour. The minutes of the previous meeting were read by the former secretary of the organization, Mr. F. C. Souhrada, which were approved as read, and the chairman announced that the meeting had been called to protest against the widening of Twelfth Street (Roosevelt Road).</p>
   <p>"As you know gentlemen," said the speaker, "there was appointed among others, by the past infamous Busse administration, a commission for the so-called Chicago beautiful, which proposed the widening of Twelfth Street, or the direct joining of the western part of the city with the eastern part. Who is behind this plan? That is hard to answer. There are various conjectures, but the most likely are that either we are to support financially the Illinois Central Railroad, which intends shortly to build at Twelfth and Canal Streets, or we are expected to support the <pb facs="5418478_1_1614.jpg" n="2"/>speculation of certain capitalists, who intend to convert their properties in that neighborhood at good prices. Indeed, here the improvement of the city is spoken about, but no attention is given to the flanking streets. What will be left to us, gentlemen, of our streets, such as Blue Island Avenue, Eighteenth Street, Twenty-first Street, and others, if as it is said, Twelfth Street becomes the business centre? Surely, they would remain dead. How then would we profit by the widening of Twelfth Street? No more than that we would have to pay more. Though nothing has yet been accomplished, the commission has spent about $15,000, which again we had to pay, and now a new commission has been appointed. Who will pay for this one? Again we, the taxpayers. For that reason, I say we must take radical steps to oppose such exploitation of the taxpayers. It has been about six years since the widening of Halsted Street was being considered, and at that time, it was the taxpayers of the west side who defeated that plan. We are in no way concerned perhaps with defeating efforts to improve the city, but primarily, who is to pay for it? <pb facs="5418478_1_1615.jpg" n="3"/>Experience teaches us that we must not care about what is told us. For instance, it is said that the projected widening of Twelfth Street would cost about three millions of dollars. Can we believe this? Never! Before the construction of the drainage canal was begun it was said that the expense would not exceed sixteen million dollars, and today this construction already has "swallowed" sixty millions of dollars and still it is not finished."</p>
   <p>Mr. Sima, a member of the Board of Public Improvements, was then asked for advice and an explanation. Mr. Sima called attention to the fact that in this matter nothing could be done at present, because the proposal of the committee had been voted upon on the so-called small ballot, and the only course remaining is for the taxpayers to put pressure upon their aldermen, so that they will not allow this proposition to go through. Further, Mr. Sima states that the way the plan is proposed the city would pay fifty per cent, twenty-five per cent would be paid by the taxpayers, and twenty-five per cent would be covered by a bond issue. The fact that <pb facs="5418478_1_1616.jpg" n="4"/>there is such haste to widen Twelfth Street is not at all surprising to M. Sima, because the longer it is put off, that is, if it is really to be done at some time, the more it will cost, for property values are increasing each year. Mr. Svoboda announced on behalf of the taxpayers of the Eleventh Ward, that they are absolutely against the widening of Twelfth Street, and in that connection a resolution had been sent to the Mayor. It was also decided to ask taxpayers societies of the western Wards to unite into one whole and protest as a body. Mr. Mertlik replied to this, saying that a resolution protesting the widening of Twelfth Street had been sent out from the last meeting, and he did not favor the sending of a new resolution. He added to Mr. Svoboda's proposal that a committee be appointed, which would maintain contact with the taxpayers' clubs of surrounding Wards and in time of necessity that joint action be taken. The reasons which influenced former Mayor Busse to withdraw his proposed widening of Halsted Street because of energetic protests, will, of necessity, happen now if we work harmoniously and in <pb facs="5418478_1_1617.jpg" n="5"/>common. Following this, there ensued a debate taken part in by Messrs: Hajicek, Souhrada and Doctor Lorenz. Then came the approval of the motion to appoint a committee, and the task of selecting the committee was turned over to the executive committee. In the matter of paving Center Avenue, between Eighteenth Street and Twenty-first Street, it was decided to endeavor to secure a twenty per cent rebate, because the street at that point is, so to speak, an arterial link between the south and north sides. The pavement is to be of granite. With that the meeting was ended, and refreshments were served in honor of the club's new secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
