<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-05">Sept. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Night Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-05">Sept. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">NIGHT SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As in past years, evening classes will be held in Chicago public schools this year. They will start tomorrow, September 6, and end January 2, 1922. Classes will be four evenings a week and the instruction is free. Classes will be held in the following schools [Translator's note: Here follows a list of three schools on the North Side, six on the Northwest Side, ten on the West Side, eight on the North Side, names of which are omitted in translation].</p>
   <p>These night schools offer to everyone an excellent opportunity to learn the following subjects, or to become more proficient in them.</p>
   <p>Instruction is given in the English language, which is of special importance to the immigrants. Those who for any reason were unable to attend or to finish the elementary school can complete their knowledge of the English language at the night school.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0445.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides this, these night schools take up such subjects as are taught in high schools.</p>
   <p>Instruction will be given in dressmaking and domestic science, etc., for girls other subjects are bookkeeping, designing, machine engineering, and various crafts. Immigrants, or those who have not yet acquired American citizenship, may receive instruction in civic matters, some knowledge of which they must show to pass the citizenship examination.</p>
   <p>The Chicago School Board urges all immigrants and noncitizens to attend night schools, because there they can learn English and everything else a citizen of this country is required to know. The Board also urges all employers to send to the night schools all their minor employees who have not finished elementary school.</p>
   <p>For housewives, and such girls and women as are unable to attend night schools, there will be special day classes in various schools. Of these the following <pb facs="5418478_1_0446.jpg" n="3"/>are in, or close to, Czech settlements [Translator's note: A list of fifteen schools is omitted in translation].</p>
   <p>There are also many factories where daytime classes will be held for employees who want to acquire additional education. Some of these factories are also in Czech neighborhoods.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
