<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-24">Mar. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Democratic Campaign Among Czechoslovaks Will Assume Tremendous Proportions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-24">Mar. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Democratic Campaign Among Czechoslovaks Will Assume Tremendous Proportions</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As became evident from the course of the meeting held yesterday by the Czechoslovak Democratic Campaign Committee in the lower hall of the Sokol Chicago, all our efforts shall be directed to influence all of our Czechoslovak Democrats to go to the primary polls as one man, and thus help to nominate Mr. Anton J. Cermak, and the entire ticket set up by the regular Democratic organization.</p>
   <p>One hundred and fifty persons attended the Campaign Committee meeting yesterday, and these were mostly representatives of Czechoslovak organizations. All parts of Chicago and Cicero were represented. Able speakers explained the situation and stressed the necessity for the most painstaking effort in the ensuing primaries, so that every Bohemian vote will go to the <pb facs="5418478_1_1349.jpg" n="2"/>support of Mr. Anton J. Cermak and the rest of the candidates offered by the regular Democratic organization. For this reason, too, the interest of all the Czechoslovak voters of Cook County, estimated at 25,000, must be aroused. To all of them appropriate letters shall be mailed as soon as possible. On the Sunday before the primaries, which will be on April 9, a great mass meeting will be held in the Sokol Chicago, but before this meeting will be called, other work will be done in each separate district. All the men who attended the meeting yesterday, agreed to organize meetings in their own neighborhoods and arouse the indifferent and sleepy voters, filling them with enthusiasm and zeal. Under such circumstances, of course, the results of the primaries will be happy and honorable for all the Czech Democrats and their leader, Mr. Cermak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
