<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-02-27">Feb. 27, 1880</date><title level="a">Bohemian in Public Schools Unrecognized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 b (German)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-02-27">Feb. 27, 1880</date><title level="a">BOHEMIAN IN PUBLIC SCHOOLS UNRECOGNIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The petition of 258 parents and guardians of children attending the Throop School, for the inclusion of the Bohemian Language as a study, which was referred to a special committee for consideration some two weeks ago was the cause of considerable debate on the part of the School Board yesterday.</p>
   <p>The readers of Svornost know who the favorable members of the Board were and who were unfavorable. The way we indicated the last time we mentioned this matter is just the way it happened. Of the committee two members, Stiles and Stone, recommended favorable action by the School Board, whereas the obstinate German member, Vochke, who happened to preside over the committee, stood out against the introduction of the teaching of Bohemian in the Throop School.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stone said that the petition for the introduction of the study of the Bohemian Language in this school, is signed by more than half of the taxpayers of this school district and that the petitioners have just as much right to request the teaching of Bohemian as have the German citizens to have German taught in the public schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0333.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In opposition to this, Mr. Vocke claims that there is a great deal of difference between Germans and Bohemians, or in other words they are superior. He does not wish the Germans to be given any privileges before other nationalities, but the Bohemian Language is so unimportant that it must not be compared in the least with German. Use is made of the Bohemian Language in only two of the Educational Centers of the world, that is at Prague and Vienna, while the German Language must be considered as a major basis of culture. The knowledge of German is sufficient for every business man to carry on all transactions with benefit and advantage anywhere.</p>
   <p>In this same manner Mr. Richberg spoke, moving, in conclusion, that the Board proceed to vote on Mr. Stones motion that the teaching of Bohemian be permitted in the Throop School. The vote brought out the following results:</p>
   <p>For the introduction of Bohemian: Stone, Brennan, Frake, Curran and Stiles (5). Against:- Vocke, Richberg, Keith, Bartlett, Frankenthal, Delaney and Hayne. (7).</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0334.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore, by a majority of two votes the just petition of Bohemian Citizens was rejected and unrecognized.</p>
   <p>How easily could this petition of ours have been acted on favorably had it not been for the old, (still from the old country) German obstinate hatred which, in a contemptible and shameful manner, vented its spite on everything Bohemian even in this land of freedom. If these three Germans, Vocke, Richberg and Frankenthal had voted for the teaching of the Bohemian Language, we could be rejoicing today in the just disposition of our petition.</p>
   <p>We seek in this land of freedom, in this where the Bohemian element is second in numbers only to the Germans, only the recognition of our rights, Whether the Bohemian tongue is used in one or ten world centers does not concern us in the least; we are interested only in the preservation of our language and nationality, in the same manner that it concerned, and still concerns the German people. And since they have been given the privilege, why should they take it upon themselves to prevent us from acquiring a like privilege.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0335.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Finally, since impudence, selfishness, obstinacy and insolence is excessively rooted in the minds of all Germans, almost without exception, how then could we expect, even in this land of freedom, to receive any support from them? If, at some time or other, they seem to incline toward friendship, it is only because they want some help in some cause, but if they have an idea that they may be able to accomplish their objective without us, then all we get from them are dirty sneers and scorn and opposition to any effort whatever on our part.</p>
   <p>Our attempts, efforts, requests, and hopes for the teaching of the Bohemian language in the public school where over half of the pupils are of Bohemian parentage, were, since yesterday, destroyed, unrecognized and for the time being, we must submit. Perhaps we shall find other ways and means by which we shall finally receive our just rights.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
