<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-20">Jan. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To the Czech People in Chicago (From the Committee of the Czech National Alliance in Chicago)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0713</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0713.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3) (Slovak)</item>
     <item>III H (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-20">Jan. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CZECH PEOPLE IN CHICAGO (From the Committee of the Czech National Alliance in Chicago)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Slovaks, our brothers, are making preparations for the bazaar which they will hold in the halls of the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Park, January 27 to February 3. The Slovaks of Chicago have always been in the forefront whenever we Czechs have held a celebration, festivity, or bazaar. They have shown their sympathetic attitude toward us by extending financial and moral support and immediate participation. The Slovaks have thus helped us to make our enterprises brilliant successes. We are deeply indebted to them.</p>
   <p>Our Slovak brothers in Chicago are busy with arrangements for a big bazaar. This affair promises to become a grand demonstration of love for their distressed motherland. It proposes to demonstrate that Slovaks, just like us Czechs, are ready to put forth sacrifices for the liberation of beautiful Slovak lands.</p>
   <p>The Slovaks did not approach us directly for support. Yet we feel that Czech <pb facs="5418478_1_0714.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago is under a great obligation from a national and patriotic point of view, and that we are honor-bound to participate in their noble work.</p>
   <p>We urge the Czech people of Chicago, members of the various branches of the Czech National Alliance, and all friends of the Slovaks to participate in large numbers, and so reciprocate all that the Slovaks have contributed to our successes. All donations from Czech friends to the Slovaks, our brothers, will surely be accepted with the greatest joy. They should be addressed to The Slovak Bazaar Committee, 710 West 18th Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>We expect that the Czech public of the City of Chicago will participate in multitudes and contribute generously to the brilliant success of this bazaar which is sponsored by the Slovak League.</p>
   <p>Signed: The District Committee of the Czech National Alliance in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
