<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-10">Feb. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Warning to Our Countrymen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0973</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0973.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-10">Feb. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">WARNING TO OUR COUNTRYMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the kindness of Messrs. Mayer and Smrž, of the Kašpar Státní Banka (Kaspar State Bank), which is located at Blue Island Avenue and West 19th Street, we were informed yesterday about the business dealings which a certain Western Land and Operating Company is conducting mainly among Lithuanians and Slovaks. This company, which is now also trying to approach Bohemians, has its representatives and henchmen in all the large cities and towns of the Middle West. Its central office is located in Denver, Colorado, and its Chicago branch is at 127 North Dearborn Street. This company placed on the market a large number of so-called participating certificates, which are supposedly guaranteed by real estate which the said company already owns or intends to purchase in the future. For every one thousand dollars invested in the company, there is a parcel of land containing five acres.</p>
   <p>The prospective buyers are lured by promises that for each thousand dollars, the company will give them 12 per cent interest in the form of coupons, which will <pb facs="5418478_1_0974.jpg" n="2"/>be issued semi-annually--that is, six coupons for every half year. Besides this, the company also promises to pay 25 per cent in monthly dividends. The first coupon and the first dividend are always paid. The company refers in its dealings to the First National Bank of Denver, Colorado, which bank is said to pay for the coupons and the dividends. But the rest of the coupons and dividends are not paid. The company sends a check for them, of course, but the check is not honored by any bank. The checks are worthless, since the company does not have sufficient deposits in the bank to which it refers and which is supposed to pay for the coupons and the dividends.</p>
   <p>The Kašpar Státní Banka ascertained this to be true in several cases. And because it wished to understand clearly how things really stood, it wrote a letter to the said bank in Denver, Colorado, asking for information about the company. The answer came the other day and was as follows:</p>
   <p>"In response to your query of February 2, we beg to inform you that the Western Land and Operating Company is not, according to our opinion, a responsible <pb facs="5418478_1_0975.jpg" n="3"/>enterprise. The information which we have about this company is of a decidedly unfavorable character. As we ourselves know the background of the propositions made by it, we believe that it is necessary to be extremely careful in having business dealings with the said enterprise, and we ourselves do not recommend dealings with it under any circumstances.</p>
   <p>"Yours sincerely, D. J. Gourley, assistant cashier."</p>
   <p>By request of the Kašpar Státní Banka, we offer this warning to our readers in the hope that they will act accordingly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
