<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-03-25">March 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">State Politics. (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-03-25">March 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">STATE POLITICS. (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are politicians, who can never get over a defeat, and to these belong the supporters of the latest blue-law, the prohibition of smoking in the street cars. Naturally, the United Societies for Local Self-Government, and the Freedom League, which is affiliated with them, are in the first place, made responsible for it, especially "Tony" Cermak, a co-founder of the United Societies, who is scourged because he dared to give advice to a few friends at the City's Council meeting, held the day before yesterday.</p>
   <p>The chief clerk of the Magistrate's Court, declines decidedly, to claim the whole honor for the victory of personal liberty, and at the same <pb facs="5418478_1_0679.jpg" n="2"/>time, he lets it be known, that one or the other city father, who voted against the ordinance in fear of the women, has not altogether fallen into disgrace.</p>
   <p>The opponents of smoking in the street cars and those enjoying nicotine in general, might, figuratively speaking, cost the secretary of the United Societies, his scalp. His opponents will not rest, till the United Societies will disappear entirely from the picture of our city's development.</p>
   <p>A prominent representative of a prohibitionist newspaper, even made the remark in the City Hall, in the presence of several aldermen, that the United Societies, figuratively speaking, are on their last leg. A few aldermen were brave enough to point to such prophecies as remarks, during the charter fith of the year 1907.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
