<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Where They Brew Beer (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0583</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0583.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE THEY BREW BEER (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Where They Brew Beer, There It Is well to Live!" It must have been a vague musical premonition that whispered into the ears of four Chicago detectives that they were on the right track when they leisurely sauntered upon the premises whence issued the strains of the vigorous old Czech drinking song. It was in the Pilsen Brewery Park, Albany Avenue and 26th Street, where a multitude of members, male and female, of the Cesko-Americti Lesnici (Order of Czech-American Foresters) with countless friends, had gathered for a picnic on Sunday, June 22 of this year. As if guided by a clue--an art perfected by years of assiduous exercise--the four plain-clothes men automatically found themselves in front of a bar where Messrs. Vojta Sindelar and Emil Vicha catered with great zeal and dignity to the thousands who sought relief from the heat.</p>
   <p>One of the sleuths ordered a full size stein. A few moments later he was smacking his lips, rubbing his tummy, and rolling his eyes. Another detective also <pb facs="5418478_1_0584.jpg" n="2"/>ordered a stein; then, all four displayed their stars and invited Messrs. Vicha and Sindelar to follow them to the station, there to be booked for violation of the Sunday closing law. "It's near-beer!" the bartenders protested. "It's the real stuff!" retorted the sleuths.....They also extended their invitation to Mr. Zigmund Chobotsky, chief forester of the Order, and to Mr. Jan Budilovsky, his aid. To make the party merrier, they also took the private park watchman along.</p>
   <p>The company was joined by Mr. Vaclav E. Marek, formerly a deputy bailiff of the municipal court, who volunteered to furnish the bail; but when the prisoners arrived at the police station on 23rd and Robey Streets, Marek was declared under arrest himself. The police claimed that he had "become fresh with them," and they wanted to assert their authority.....The comedy closed with only Marek's and Vicha's being booked and finally boiled out after police had denied them that right for several hours.</p>
   <p>The case came up before Judge William Gemmill of the municipal court, whose personal bailiff Marek had once been. The defendants claimed that it was near-beer <pb facs="5418478_1_0585.jpg" n="3"/>Detective Dalesky, one of the officers in the raid, declared it was genuine Olympia brew. The verdict of the court was not guilty, but the question of whether near-beer or Olympia brew was served at the Czech-American Foresters' picnic still remains unsolved.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
