<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-11-04">Nov. 4, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Prokop Hudek for Senator.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-11-04">Nov. 4, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">PROKOP HUDEK FOR SENATOR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian citizens settled in the 11th senatorial district, which comprises the 5th ward and part of the 6th ward, will have an opportunity to cast their votes for the Bohemian candidate for State Senator, proposed by the Workingmen's Party in October, and supported by every progressive citizen of other parties.</p>
   <p>The coming election for county and state officers will be held on Tuesday, November the 7th, and our Bohemian candidate is Mr. Prokop Hudek, well known in Chicago in Bohemian and American circles.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hudek's candidacy for senator was without his personal solicitation and without his knowledge. The progressive republican citizens nominated him unanimously and have not placed other candidates against him. Considering his honesty, prudence and willingness, they will support his election to the fullest extent.</p>
   <p>We have our Bohemian candidate for the State Senator, and if all Bohemian citizens will fulfill their duty as good citizens and good Bohemians, we will have next Wednesday our own senator, the first Bohemian State Senator in United States history.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Nobody can deny that Mr. Hudek is a most capable man for senator; that is known by our republican friends of other nationalities, and that is why they decided to support his election harmoniously and zealously, regardless of the fact that Hudek was not their candidate but proposed by workingmen only.</p>
   <p>We hope our Bohemian citizens won't be indifferent to our countryman, but will all appear at the polls to make his election certain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
