<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-03-28">Mar. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">An Enthusiastic Political Meeting at Sokol Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-03-28">Mar. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">AN ENTHUSIASTIC POLITICAL MEETING AT SOKOL CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian public which came at the end of the present political campaign to hear the reasons why the Twelfth Ward should elect two Bohemian Democrats to the Chicago City Council, filled the Sokol Chicago Hall last night to overflowing. The meeting had an added interest in that it was attended by United States Senator J. Hamilton Lewis who, in an excellent speech, urged the public to give its full support to the Democratic ticket at the coming election. Chairman Janda opened the meeting with a few brief remarks about the importance of the election and introduced the ward chairman, Mr. Stelka, who stressed the fact that, although the Democratic organization is composed of a very great number of citizens, it takes care to put up for election only the most able candidates. This policy is demonstrated in the nomination of Messrs. Otto Kerner and Jos. L. Novak as candidates for the office of alderman of the Twelfth Ward. In these two candidates the voters are offered men of great ability and proven honesty who may be confidently expected to protect public interests conscientiously.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1408.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The next speaker was Alderman Schultz, who explained that he did not accept a nomination only because he has been offered a higher office than that of an alderman. The precinct captains have therefore selected Mr. Kerner as his successor.</p>
   <p>After Alderman Schultz's talk, Mr. Jos. L. Novak was introduced to the audience as the candidate for the short term. He spoke in Bohemian and English about the abilities and sterling qualities of his colleague, Mr. Kerner, and gave the pledge that if elected, both he and Mr. Kerner will do all that is in their power to promote the interests of their ward. With this purpose in view, they propose to establish a special office which will be centrally located in the ward so that it will be easily accessible and will facilitate prompt dealing with all wishes and complaints. After Mr. Novak, ex-Alderman Brennan presented a fervent address in the interest of the whole Democratic ticket and especially the Bohemian candidates.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Otto Kerner appeared on the platform. Having first made a few complimentary <pb facs="5418478_1_1409.jpg" n="3"/>remarks about his running mate, Mr. Novak, he outlined his program in an extended Bohemian and English speech, elaborating on some of the most pressing needs of the ward. He also assured those present that they will have in him--if he is elected--an officer who will devote all his time and energy to the interest of the ward and to the needs of all his constituents. He referred to his experience as city prosecutor, which he will be able to make use of in serving the public. His speech was frequently interrupted by bursts of enthusiastic applause which proved the great popularity of both candidates.</p>
   <p>While Mr. Kerner spoke, the newly elected Senator J. Hamilton Lewis entered the hall and was welcomed by a stormy ovation. It was late, almost eleven o'clock in the evening when he came, but the audience waited patiently for his arrival and gave a most attentive ear to his talk. After all, perhaps he alone was not responsible for this delay: it may be said sub rosa that the greater fault lay with his escorts, Messrs. Sedlak and Stoklasa, and possibly also with a stein or two of genuine imported Pilsen.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1410.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As always, his speech was an accomplished work of art. He spoke about his election as senator to Springfield and discussed in detail the coming municipal elections, urging those present to give their vote to the whole Democratic ticket, and especially to the two Democratic candidates For the office of Alderman.....In addition to excellent speeches there were several vocal selections and comedy acts. The meeting disbanded in an enthusiastic spirit, and if the general interest shown the candidate is any indication, both Mr. Kerner and Mr. Novak will celebrate a great victory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
