<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-03-11">Mar. 11, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Struggle for the Bohemian Language</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-03-11">Mar. 11, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE STRUGGLE FOR THE BOHEMIAN LANGUAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That we Bohemians cannot accomplish anything without a struggle was proved again in a concrete manner recently. Last December when the secretary of the Ceská- Americká Narodní Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), Professor Jaroslav J. Zmrhal, secured the aid of Superintendent of Schools Mrs. Ella Flagg Young for the Bohemian cause, especially for the introduction of the Bohemian language in the high schools, it seemed that at least once we accomplished something without bitterness and strife. However, although ordinarily the recommendation of the Superintendent of Schools in educational matters is the deciding factor, the recommendation pertaining to the Bohemian language met with opposition on the part of Mr. Bennett, vice-president of the Board of Education, who demanded that the entire matter be laid over to the next meeting of the Board. It was not, of course, the intention of the majority which brought about the postponement, but the well-known rules of courtesy according to which any member of the Board can succeed in postponing or bring about the reconsideration of any matter by merely expressing a desire for such <pb facs="5418478_1_0170.jpg" n="2"/>action. Mrs. E. Flagg Young reassured the Ceská- Americká Narodní Rada that she would not allow the matter to be forgotten.</p>
   <p>The impatience of the Bohemian people and the doubts so often expressed were fully unjustified. As we have stated over and over again in our reports, our cause is in good hands and has been practically decided since last December when the secretary of the Ceská- Americká Narodní Rada received an oral and later a written assurance from Mrs. Young that the whole matter would be favorably settled.</p>
   <p>However, the Ceská- Americká Narodní Rada, though pleased with the stand of so important a worker as the superintendent of Schools, was well-aware of the need for convincing the other members of the Board of Education. The Narodni Rada sent special letters to the Board members in which the importance and merit of the whole matter was briefly but comprehensively explained. After several conferences, Professor Miller agreed to write in favor of the Bohemian cause from a sociological point of view to the chairman of the Committee on <pb facs="5418478_1_0171.jpg" n="3"/>Education, Mr. W. Summer. He could take that liberty because he is personally acquainted with Mr. Summer, and the word of a sociologist always means a great deal to Mr. Summer. Also, there was individual action within the Board itself, where our Bohemian representative, Mr. James Dibelka, strove successfully with genuine determination for our cause.</p>
   <p>The result of this activity was that our cause met with favor on the part of the Committee on Education, and that the president of the Board of Education together with several other members promised in writing to support our cause when it came up for consideration.</p>
   <p>The entire matter is now postponed to the next meeting when, according to all indications, it will be approved. The Ceská- Americká Narodní Rada will not stop working feverishly and energetically until the matter is decided.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
