<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-23">Oct. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Evening Instruction at Harrison High School Bohemian and Spanish Classes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-23">Oct. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">EVENING INSTRUCTION AT HARRISON HIGH SCHOOL Bohemian and Spanish Classes</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While the classes in drafting rooms are overcrowded, there is much vacant room in other classes. One of these is the Spanish class, which convenes only twice a week and offers the students an excellent opportunity to learn the fundamentals of a language whose importance for America is growing, and which gives those who know it a possibility of making good in South American trade.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian class is doing very well indeed. Attendance is much larger than last year, and a number of last year's students have enrolled again, a circumstance which proves their interest in the Bohemian language. The present class is composed of students who know Bohemian but who wish to perfect themselves in that language. There have been many requests for a beginners' class, and it is probable that such a class will be started. In accordance with a ruling of the Board of Education, at least twenty-five students must be enrolled before a new class may be established.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0242.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among those who have asked for such a class was an Irishman who is married to a Bohemian girl, and a number of American businessmen. The majority of the pupils study the Bohemian language for practical reasons, but many also for credits for their high school diploma. That the Bohemian classes do fill a need may be seen from the following interesting instances.</p>
   <p>An American-born girl has said: "I am a member of a Bohemian ladies' association and they want to elect me president. I attend these classes in order to learn how to write and read Bohemian correctly so that I can perform properly my future duties as president.</p>
   <p>Another student was born in Georgia and has almost entirely forgotten the Bohemian language. He has come to Chicago to learn Bohemian again to please his mother. Thus our classes are preparing workers for our national purposes among local youth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
