<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-18">May 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Duties of the American Czechs Toward Their New Homeland (Address by the Reverend Jan Rynda in the Memorable Meeting of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-18">May 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DUTIES OF THE AMERICAN CZECHS TOWARD THEIR NEW HOMELAND (Address by the Reverend Jan Rynda in the Memorable Meeting of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Paul, an apostle of the nations, while imprisoned, created a state of awe among the Roman and Jewish soldiers by his determined bearing. On being asked by a Roman high official whether or not he was a Roman citizen, he answered: 'I am.' It was then, and ever before considered an honor for him who could say of himself that he was a Roman citizen.</p>
   <p>"There is no higher title which could be bestowed on man or woman than that of American citizen. We are American citizens and proudly attest to our loyalty to the flag which is the symbol of liberty ..... After the Civil War, when freedom was established, men and women from all the <pb facs="5418478_1_0749.jpg" n="2"/>oppressed European countries flocked to the shores of America, where they found 'a government of the people, by the people and for the people,' as President Lincoln defined it. We have no dictators or monarchs...</p>
   <p>"My fellow-countrymen! Whatever we have accepted from anybody constitutes and obligation, and to meet it, should be a point of honor to us. Is there anything better and more sublime than what America has given to us, the civil, political, and religious freedom? The sense of justice and gratitude has not left our Czech hearts. We feel that we have obligations which we owe America, its Constitution, and its colors. I appeal to your patriotism, I challenge your loyalty. I consider it treason if anyone forgets his duties toward this country, and foolishly gloats in the saying, 'Ubi Bene, Ibi Patria' (Where there is good living, there is my country). It is not sufficient to say I love my country.' The mere singing of the anthem, the wearing of the colors, frenzied shouting in meetings--all this does not by far prove true love of one's country. It is merely an emanation of <pb facs="5418478_1_0750.jpg" n="3"/>natural impulses, and it would mean a fatal error to call this fulfilling one's duties.</p>
   <p>"The great English thinker, Samuel Smiles, condemns this sort of patriotism as follows: 'The major part of what in our times is being termed patriotism contains but hypocrisy and narrow-mindedness. It exposes itself in vainglorious boasting, in vulgar clamor, flag waving, and a constant reiteration of wrongs committed recently, or long ago. Patriotism such as this is perhaps the worst curse upon any country. There is no more dignity in it than in the howling of the wolves.'</p>
   <p>"Patriotism may be likened to a magnificent structure. It cannot be built up out of slogans or high sounding phrases, and cannot be erected by shouting, but solely by work and sacrifice in which everybody should carry his share . . . . . There are thousands of people who, though they do not know how to talk on patriotism, are nevertheless filled with the genuine sentiment, <pb facs="5418478_1_0751.jpg" n="4"/>because they act as loyal citizens ..... And what is the source of unselfish, pure patriotic inspiration? Religion is that source.</p>
   <p>"The Roman king, Numa Pompilius, in striving to uplift Rome, fostered a religious cult. In order to make Rome the eternal city, he first transformed it into a holy city. This king well knew that patriotic virtues, such as willingness to sacrifice, moderation, cleanliness of habits, justice, loyalty, obedience to laws, and others would find the staunchest support in religion, for with its growth the virtues also begin to bloom. George Washington, the Father of the Country, proclaims in his farewell address: 'Religion is the foundation of the State. He, who undermines the mighty pillars of human society, cannot lay claim to the name of patriot and loyal American.....'</p>
   <p>"George Washington also laid stress upon the necessity of education. Enlightenment <pb facs="5418478_1_0752.jpg" n="5"/>and liberty have become the beacon lights to the trend of our time. The work and the efforts of the human mind concentrate upon them. Nobody will pay attention to a nation which in the near future will not have a sufficient number of educated and prosperous people. Epictetus, the Roman sage, clothed in the rags of a slave, proclaimed that one can render the best service to the people not by lifting the roofs off their houses, but by uplifting their souls.</p>
   <p>"Do not give riches to your children, give them an education. It is high time that we Czechs advance from the back seats to the front seats, and be represented in the Legislature, in Congress and other offices of importance.</p>
   <p>"After our duty to the Lord, it is to our homeland, its welfare and prosperity, which should primarily occupy our minds and souls. The ballot should play a prominent part in our life, for it gives us supreme power.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0753.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>'The crowning fact of freedom is the foreman's veto,' an old politician used to say.</p>
   <p>"It is not my intention to give a talk on politics. I am merely mentioning the right to vote because it has not received the proper attention from our people. It is our duty to vote for the good of the country, and for our own ....."</p>
   <p>The speaker closed with a mighty appeal for coöperation and generous contributions for the successful prosecution of the War.</p>
   <p>[Translator's Note.--For report on the meeting, see Denni Hlasatel, May 17, 1917.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
