<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-25">Jan. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Notice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-25">Jan. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN IMPORTANT NOTICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We deem it our duty to call the attention of all voters to the agitation of certain reformers who have made it their task to collect one hundred thousand signatures on petitions for prohibition in our city. Should they succeed, their propostion will be placed upon the ballot and voted on in the next election. Their plan for the fight is about as follows:</p>
   <p>Volunteers and paid agents are distributed all over the city. They will look for voters who have changed their addresses or have obtained their second papers only recently. They will offer to accompany these people to the central registration office, and then ask them to sign their "dry" petition.</p>
   <p>It behooves the taxpayers and citizens of our city to oppose this propaganda, which has proved impractical and obnoxious wherever it has been put to a <pb facs="5418478_1_0573.jpg" n="2"/>test, and has added additional burdens to the obligations of taxpayers.</p>
   <p>The liberal-minded element in our societies should do everything in its power to combat this infringement of the personal liberty of individuals.</p>
   <p>It is wise to point out that the appetite to amend our customs, as displayed by these paid agitators, will by no means be stilled even after the closing of saloons in Chicago. No, indeed, it will tend to render impossible are entertainment given by our organizations if liquid refreshments are dispensed there.</p>
   <p>The only way to resist these activities is to refuse to sign the "dry" petition, Should the "drys" still succeed in bringing the question before the voters, then it is imperative that every man and woman manifest his or her will through the ballot. Read the official information very carefully:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0574.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: The information is printed in full.]</p>
   <p>For the United Societies for Local Self-Government: The Executive Committee.</p>
   <p>For the Czech Branch of the United Societies:</p>
   <p>John A. Cervenka, Chairman.</p>
   <p>Joseph F. Bolek, Acting Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
