<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-03-30">March 30, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">Josef Soukup Proposed to Be West Town Appraiser for Third Term.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-03-30">March 30, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">JOSEF SOUKUP PROPOSED TO BE WEST TOWN APPRAISER FOR THIRD TERM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, the Democratic Convention of West Town was held in the Wallov Hall, corner Adams and Halsted streets. The convention itself was unusually large and very significant for us Bohemians, because there was nominated our countryman Josef Soukup, as candidate for Appraiser's office. There were proposed three more candidates for the same office. One of the delegates, I cannot recollect his name right now, was of the opinion that the Bohemians who form, on the West Side, the major part of the citizens and taxpayers should have in the appraiser's office their countryman Mr. J. Soukup because he had been in this office for two full terms already and because he was again proposed by the Bohemians. This argument was decisive and Mr. J. Soukup was nominated as candidate with a majority of 38 votes.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the convention was Mr. Wilhelm McClure; proposed candidates for the office of West Town Appraiser were: J. Soukup, J. O'Brien, M. J. Hayes, and John O'Brien. The victor with the majority of 38 votes was Mr. J. Soukup.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1469.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As we hear, in the 6th ward there will be nominated a Bohemian candidate to the City Council; the local Independent Democratic Club taking into consideration that Mr. Kalal refused the proffered candidacy. We were not able to verify if this were true. It is strange anyway because the club mentioned has already nominated somebody else in place of Mr. Kalal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
