<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-05-08">May 8, 1896</date><title level="a">Against the Bible in Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-05-08">May 8, 1896</date><title level="a">Against the Bible in Schools</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian Liberal Community decided at its last meeting on Sunday, to ask the Chicago Board of Education to make a decision to eliminate from the Chicago schools the reading of the Bible. The petition was as follows:</p>
   <p>Honorable Board of Education:- The Bohemian Liberal Community in Chicago made a unanimous decision at its last meeting, May 3rd, 1896, which is hereby brought to the attention of the Board:</p>
   <p>Whereas - many Christian sects have introduced to the public schools the Bible, with the purpose of having it read by the school pupils, it is decided to present this honest and reasonable petition. Your educational body should have as its main problem the protection of our present free schools, which are an inheritance of a free nation, against any misinterpretations and misunderstandings, and consequently it should be prohibited from reading the Bible, for or by the children in the schools. We are sure the Bible reading would spoil the young hearts of our children, would deprive them of pity for humanity, good fellowship and tolerance to others, of morals, liberty, and education. Examples from the past are proving this.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0430.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our children should be taught in the schools equality, fraternity, freedom for all peoples, justice and the duties of good citizenship, without the Bible, no matter whether Jewish, Christian, Mohammedan, or Mormon. - F. B. Zdrusek - President, F. Nadherny - Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
