<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-15">Sept. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Nedelni Beseda (For Reading on Sunday) (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0550</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0550.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-15">Sept. 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NEDELNI BESEDA (FOR READING ON SUNDAY) (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Can you imagine how Chicago will look at Christmas time, and how you will be preparing to celebrate Saint Sylvester, the last day of the year? Visitors from out of town from "dry" districts may be able to give you an idea--yet they will probably not know what is going to happen to Chicago in the future, when all sources of the hop and malt beverage will be sold out. Thirsty people from the State of Indiana used to need only a few steps to be in Chicago at the fountain.....</p>
   <p>After December 1, or when all supplies are consumed, it will be hard to find a "wet" spot here. All the breweries will close, and not even the famous Pilsner beer will be allowed to come into America....After June next, general prohibition will be introduced, and thirsty people will have to wait till our soldiers come back from the war, unless they prefer <pb facs="5418478_1_0551.jpg" n="2"/>to quench their thirst with a rotten drink of perfumed water from Lake Michigan.</p>
   <p>Chicago certainly is not used to this kind of innovation, and many protests are on record. But the war compels us to accept manifold changes in our standards of living and to adopt habits never dreamed of before. Many more economizing measures are expected in the consumption of food and gasoline, as well as in clothing, than are in effect today....even stones from plums and peaches have become war supplies, being used for gas masks; patriotic housewives are expected to save and deliver them to collecting stations.....</p>
   <p>No one knows when Chicago will be emptying its last mug of beer....When this has happened, our people will stop singing "Kde Se Pivo Vari..." (Where they brew beer, there it is good to be!), and scores of other songs in praise of that beverage, for what is the use of praising a thing of which there is nothing left but the sweet memory of its taste....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0552.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What is going to happen to all those who made a living in the beer business? They will, however, not be the only sufferers: Thousands of prohibition evangelists, and reformed drunkards who hit the sawdust trail, and who are now exhibited as warning examples, will be looking for a job, because there will be nothing left against which they could direct their vilifications. Just think of what is going to befall the regiments of the "Billy Sundays" who are making a comfortable living from abusing and slurring saloons and drinkers.</p>
   <p>....Besides the "Billy Sundays," "Volivas," and "William J. Bryans," there are hordes of people who first fill their tummies to capacity, and then display in prohibition meetings "the terrible consequences of drunkenness and the ravages of alcohol". All these people will be thrown out in the street--unemployed--because they are deprived of their means of livelihood. Prohibition politicians, also, will find their business undermined. They will resemble a physician who has cured his patient too early, or a lawyer who won the case for his client prematurely, and so dried up the <pb facs="5418478_1_0553.jpg" n="4"/>source of his regular income.</p>
   <p>This proves that to every evil there is attached an ounce of good. It depends from what angle people view an issue like this. But these considerations are only of minor importance.</p>
   <p>The Government says that no beer must be brewed during war time. That is final. If prohibition can contribute to victory over the Germans, then every decent citizen should regard beer as an unnecessary commodity, and gladly substitute a drink of sparkling water from Lake Michigan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
