<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-07-25">July 25, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">Against German in the Public Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 b (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-07-25">July 25, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">AGAINST GERMAN IN THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting in protest against the continued teaching of the German language in the public schools was called by "Tel. Jed, Sokol," "Cechie" (Gymnastic Union Sokol, "Bohemians") on last Wednesday. Because of some misunderstanding of late the meeting was not fully announced, consequently the attendance was rather small.</p>
   <p>A motion, that the chairman appoint a committee of three, for the purpose of preparing a resolution of protest against the compulsory study of the German language in the public schools was adopted.</p>
   <p>The resolution, which follows, was approved and unanimously accepted.</p>
   <p>1. Whereas, in view of the insignificant minority, the German language has been introduced as a subject of study in the public schools of Chicago.</p>
   <p>2. Whereas, it is known, that in many of our local schools, because of insufficient room, only a half day is devoted to the study of English subjects; <pb facs="5418478_1_0320.jpg" n="2"/>that part of the time used in the unnecessary study of German, whose teachers are paid with public money, could be used to better advantage in the study of other English subjects.</p>
   <p>3. Whereas we, as American citizens, feel ourselves deprived of our rights, and if the Germans are to have the privilege of having their language taught in our public schools, we are logically entitled to request the same consideration for our nationality and likewise every other nationality represented here in sufficient numbers is entitled to the same consideration. Therefore be it resolved:-</p>
   <p>1. That the School Board of the City of Chicago, in regard to the above reasons acknowledge the same rights of all nationalities represented in Chicago, and when petitioned, provide for the study of their language in the public schools, and if the School Board does not want to accede to these requests, then the teaching of the German language be also discontinued, as it is a deliberate insult to the other nationalities, which are just as good citizens as the Germans, if not better. And if the School Board of the City of Chicago will not fulfill this request, be it further resolved:-</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0321.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>2. To petition the Legislature of the State of Illinois to forbid the teaching of any other language, except English, in our public schools, to influence our State Representatives and Senators, that such a law might be presented and passed. If however, even this should be of no avail, be it further resolved that: -</p>
   <p>3. A petition be sent to the Congress of the United States, so that it may put a stop to the curtailment of our rights as citizens, and in case of necessity, that the whole matter be taken before the Courts for decision.</p>
   <p>4. Be it resolved, that the representatives elected to the central committee of "Sokol" Unions, with other committees according to the needs of this gathering, do everything possible so that the aims of these resolutions may be successfully accomplished.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
