<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-16">Oct. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The First Dry Sunday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-16">Oct. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST DRY SUNDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first dry Sunday in Chicago is over, and it must be admitted that it was a very quiet and peaceful one. Quite against the expectation of some people, there were no disorders, and the reason there were none was because the saloon men themselves, upon the advice of the United Civic Societies, acted exactly in accordance with the law which Mayor Thompson unearthed, in order to show the whole population what a really dry Sunday in Chicago looks like. There were just a very few transgressions of that law which, in proportion to the number of saloons in Chicago, are not worth speaking about. And in fact these were not real transgressions of the law closing saloons on Sunday, but rather failures to close the saloons at the hour specified by the police, a regulation that has always been sinned against.</p>
   <p>Well then, the first dry Sunday in Chicago was quiet. But that does not mean that the people of Chicago agree with the Mayor's decree, or that <pb facs="5418478_1_0629.jpg" n="2"/>they have forgotten about it in their many other cares and troubles. By no means. The people disagree and do not forget, but the organization which defends their personal liberty is trying, within the limits of the law, to find ways and means by which to annual and void the Mayor's decree.</p>
   <p>In pursuance of this end, the United Civic Societies holds its convention tomorrow. The convention will call attention to the conception of honor shown by Mayor Thompson as the highest executive officer of the second largest city in the United States, a city which is more cosmopolitan than New York itself; how he can keep his word, and how he can deny a pledge to which he attached his own signature. There will be discussion of the question whether the Mayor's decree could not be made invalid by spontaneous demonstration of the people. The Civic Societies also expect to put the question of dry or wet Sundays on the ballot at the next municipal election.</p>
   <p>We do not know whether or not the United Civic Societies will find means <pb facs="5418478_1_0630.jpg" n="3"/>to accomplish anything of that kind. All we know is that the law upon which Mayor Thompson has based his ordinance is a State law, and can be changed only by the State legislature, either by repeal or by amendment.</p>
   <p>In our opinion, the most practicable amendment would be one providing that cities with a certain specified population and over should have the privilege of deciding for themselves whether they would be dry or wet. Undoubtedly, cities with fifty thousand people or more should have greater rights than those which are much smaller. Consideration should also be given to the fact that large cities have a much more heterogeneous population than villages or small towns. This circumstance, of course, is also of moment.</p>
   <p>It is not only recently that Chicago's right to antonomy has been talked and written about. The subject has been discussed for many years, and the opinion expressed that Chicago should be permitted to settle all its own important problems. As it is, all questions concerning Chicago and its <pb facs="5418478_1_0631.jpg" n="4"/>welfare are decided by the State legislature. In consideration of the fact that Chicago is by far the largest city in the State, and that it pays the largest amount of taxes, every unbiased person will admit that it should have the right to decide on all matters of its own concern. It is well known that different customs and different needs prevail in a small town or a little community from those in such large cities as Chicago. If small towns decide to be dry because they do not feel any need to be otherwise, why should Chicago, which feels the need to be wet, be dry like the small towns? As it is, Chicago is powerless, because the small towns have a majority in the State legislature, and the small town legislators have made up their minds to keep not only their own communities, but also Chicago, dry.</p>
   <p>But the question of dryness and wetness is not the only one in which Chicago is concerned. There are many other very important issues that are being decided by the legislature against the will and interests of Chicago. We believe that the present state of affairs is unjust, <pb facs="5418478_1_0632.jpg" n="5"/>unjustifiable, and unsound. A strong campaign should be started in the very near future to liberate Chicago from the supremacy of small towns and rural districts, and to put it in a position where it would be master within its own borders. This could be done by having the people express an opinion in favor of autonomy at the next election. It would be therefore an issue of that campaign to bring this question before the people.</p>
   <p>This is a democracy, and the will of the people is the supreme ruler. Hence conditions are in the hands of the people, and if these conditions are not appropriate, it is up to the people to change them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
