<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-01-19">Jan. 19, 1880</date><title level="a">Bohemian in the Public Schools Discussion of This Matter in Yesterday's Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0340</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0340.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 b (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-01-19">Jan. 19, 1880</date><title level="a">BOHEMIAN IN THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS DISCUSSION OF THIS MATTER IN YESTERDAY'S MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mass meeting held yesterday afternoon on the premises of J. Sedlack was not attended so well as the purpose of the meeting required.</p>
   <p>The meeting was brought to order at 3:30 P.M. by Leo Meilbek. Fr. Dvorak was elected Chairman and Mr. Fiala as secretary. Thereafter Mr. L. Meilbek read a speech in which he laid stress on the need for a halt in the constant organization of new Bohemian Lodges to the detriment of our public, but that those existing should be improved for the general good. In his speech he argues that all Lodges and individuals should join forces in order to secure the instruction of the Bohemian Language in our public schools, and first of all in the Throop Street School where over half the pupils are of Bohemian extraction. with this thought in mind the following resolution was accepted unanimously--</p>
   <p>We American Citizens of Bohemian descent gathered in mass meeting on the premises of Citizen Jos. Sedlack, corner morgan and 19th Street, adopt the following:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0341.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(1) We call upon and urgently request all Bohemian Benevolent Associations and Lodges, whether public or secret, that they require all persons seeking membership in organizations, to become citizens of the United States and that the present members of these lodges and associations should likewise become citizens, in order that we may work in unison to secure equal rights in the public schools of Chicago, so that the teaching of the Bohemian Language may be adopted as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>(2) We urge citizens to join Political Parties, for it is our duty to discuss the various political questions arising from time to time. We must necessarily have public meetings for this purpose, for everyone knows that the discussion of politics in the meetings of our various lodges and associations is not permitted.</p>
   <p>(3) There shall be elected at this meeting a committee (composed of as many members as are decided on by those present) for the purpose of securing signatures of all our Bohemian countrymen who would like to have the Bohemian Language taught in our public schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0342.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That a committee of two be selected at this meeting, who are capable of working out the details of this matter and together with the signed petitions to present it to the School Board and further that this committee shall do all that they consider proper and of benefit to this cause and they shall from time to time call meetings so as to report on the progress of this matter.</p>
   <p>Then so that the first step in the matter might be an accomplished fact the petition to the School Board was drawn up as follows:</p>
   <p>Chicago, Jan. 19th 1880</p>
   <p>To the Honorable Board of Education of the City of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>We, the undersigned parents and guardians of children attending the Throop School, would most respectfully petition your Honorable Board to introduce the study of the Bohemian Language in said school for the following reasons: There are now attending this school 430 pupils of Bohemian parentage or about one-half of the total attendance, and as your Honorable Board <pb facs="5418478_1_0343.jpg" n="4"/>caused the German Language to be taught in several schools, we as citizens and taxpayers demand the same recognition as is accorded to other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Finally it was decided to hold another meeting at this same place next Wednesday night, to which meeting all parents who are sending children to the Throop School are urgently requested to come. At this meeting the committee for the circulation of the above petition will be elected. Mrs. L. Meilbek and M. Baumruker were appointed to the committee which is to take the question up with the School Board.</p>
   <p>The importance of yesterday's meeting and those to come is plainly evident. It is for the individuals now and for our various Lodges especially to do their part, for if the German people can have their Language taught in 18 of our public schools, why can't we Bohemians in those sections of the city inhabited mainly by us have our mother tongue taught in the public schools?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
