<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-19">Jan. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">Professor Veleminsky Studies American Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0160</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0160.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-19">Jan. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Professor Veleminsky Studies American Schools</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our distinguished guest, Professor Karel Veleminsky [of the University of Prague], recently began a thorough study of the American public school system, in which study he enjoys the willing co-operation of local school authorities. School Superintendent Mrs. Ella Flagg Young brought the visit of the well-known educator to the attention of school principals, and directed them to provide Dr. Veleminsky with all the information he desired and to facilitate his studies in every respect. He is being accompanied on his visits by our school board members. [Jaroslav] Zmrhal and [J. B.] Dibelka. We do not doubt, therefore, that he is being well taken care of.</p>
   <p>On Friday, morning and afternoon, the William Penn School arranged a very fine little festival for its pupils. School Principal Mrs. Bertha Benson profited from the presence of Dr. Veleminsky, who was studying modern methods of instruction in her school, and asked him to address the numerous Bohemian <pb facs="5418478_1_0161.jpg" n="2"/>children who are the school's pupils. Together with Mr. E. S. Vraz, the president of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), Professor Veleminsky was welcomed by the assembled Bohemian pupils of the higher grades who sang the Bohemian national anthem for him in their own language. Then the Professor addressed the more than one hundred assembled pupils, explaining the differences between schools in the United States and schools in Bohemia, and the various subjects taught over here and over there. He described the gay and cheerful spirit he found in the schools of the United States, and urged the students to love their new homeland, all the while maintaining full appreciation for the language of their parents, using it at home and perfecting themselves in its knowledge. Mr. Vraz addressed the teachers in the English language and thanked them for preparing this pleasant occasion, and urged the children to grow up to be good American citizens.</p>
   <p>In the afternoon, two hundred and fifty of the youngest pupils were called to the school assembly hall. Professor Veleminsky recommended that they <pb facs="5418478_1_0162.jpg" n="3"/>study and educate themselves with full seriousness, and that they request their parents to keep them in schools just as long as possible. The school principal and teachers took exemplary care in arranging for Professor Veleminsky's visit. They prepared an exhibit of the school's handiwork, the best of which, along with a group photograph of the pupils, was presented to him as a souvenir. They also saw to it that Prof. Veleminsky received a thorough idea of the school's work by arranging the day's program so as to make it as diversified as possible.</p>
   <p>Through the kindness of Mr. Dibelka and Professor Zmrhal, Professor Veleminsky was also received by other schools. He attended the gymnasium classes of our Mr. Joseph Cermak at Medill High School, and the classes in the Bohemian language at Harrison Technical High School. In the club of Bohemian students of this school created by the efforts of the teacher of Bohemian language, Mr. B. Kral, the Professor entered the discussion and again urged the young people not to permit their affections to become estranged from their native tongue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
