<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-28">June 28, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Abolish the Death Penalty!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0906</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0906.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-28">June 28, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">ABOLISH THE DEATH PENALTY!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.4--In no other part of the world is so much said or so much printed about executions, as in this country of ours, which we flatter ourselves by calling the most progressive and the best civilized on earth. Our newspapers print daily reports of executions. If the accused be a colored man, and the crime an ordinary murder, only brief mention is made of the occurence.</p>
   <p>If, however, the condemned man belongs to that class of criminals whose misdeeds create a sensation on account of peculiar circumstances, whole columns are devoted to the story for the "education" of the public. Readers must be informed about the details of crime, about the trial, about the startling points in the testimony, and about all the practical and unpractical juristic motions made by the defense to save the defendant's life. No one believes that such reading elevates the morals or promotes the perfection of mankind.</p>
   <p>All this would be different if our law did not cling to an ancient medieval rule: "An eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth, a life for a life."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0907.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Science has so far tried in vain to demonstrate to legislators by pointing out the congenital defects of the human mind and the influence of environment and circumstance how little man is responsible for what he is and does. Capital punishment, in most of our States, is apparently here to stay. In some States, truly enough, it has been abolished; for example, in the neighboring State of Wisconsin. But the States where the rule of Moses, "An eye for an eye" does not prevail are still very few.</p>
   <p>But there are other considerations, not of a scientific nature, which ought to be taken into account. We have read an article in a certain paper printed in English the gist of which we wish to communicate to our readers.</p>
   <p>"One of the consequences of the legalization of the death penalty, says this article, is the excitement created by the publication of details which might better be kept from the public. Even people with mature minds do not derive any benefit from such reports of the struggle for existence, whereas persons of hysterical tendencies and those who are afflicted with a morbid predilection for sensational stories are weakened thereby both morally and mentally.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0908.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"In the States which have abolished the death penalty those who read the accounts of murder trials are not wrought to so high a pitch of excitement. When the trial is over, and the verdict has been found, the interest ceases. Whatever is undertaken thereafter to obtain a new trial, an appeal, or a pardon fails to attract the attention of either the public or the press. The contention that capital punishment has a deterrent effect upon people who would otherwise be tempted to commit murder was refuted years ago by criminologists of the first rank. There have been times in which the ax, the rope, fire, or the sword was used to mete out punishment for crimes much less grave than murder; it was supposed that men would be deterred by the fear of punishment from committing such crimes.</p>
   <p>In our day the most progressive of our States have discarded medieval criminal laws and abolished capital punishment."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
