<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1879-02-20">February 20th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[Pre-Election Activity of Bohemians]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SVORNOST</title>,
<date when="1879-02-20">February 20th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[PRE-ELECTION ACTIVITY OF BOHEMIANS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In view of this year's city and township elections, there is manifest a pleasing activity among Chicago Bohemians, not only, that they will vote as a bloc with the Socialist Party, but they are becoming members of this party so that they may participate more actively. The membership of the Bohemian section in the 6th Ward increased considerably and in the 8th Ward there was organized a section which 30 citizens joined immediately and which it is expected that all honorably minded working men and business men, of the ward will join at to-morrow's meeting. This section has called a mass-meeting for next Sunday to be held in the hall of "Telocvicna Jednoto Sokol" (Gymnastic Society Sokol). The regular meetings are held in the same hall on Fridays. Numerous countrymen of ours in the seventh ward are also thinking about organizing a Bohemian Section and are holding a meeting for that purpose in the private premises of Citizen Josef Kadic.</p>
   <p>Also numerous Bohemian citizens of the fourteenth ward are contemplating the organization of a Bohemian section either by the end of this week or early next week with many ardently active members, as enlightened citizens of the Northwest side agree throughout with the principles of the Socialist Labor Party.- We trust the numerous Bohemian citizens of the Southside, in the fifth ward, will not lag <pb facs="5418478_1_1499.jpg" n="2"/>behind and we shall rejoice in the fact that we have five strong Bohemian Sections in the Socialist Party which will work for the realization of labor's just cause. If we glance backward in retrospect we must admit the opposition is stiffening. For a long time there has been only one Bohemian Section in our city, that was in the Sixth Ward, and its activities were limited because of a small membership. The appearance locally of leaflets, furious and slanderous, of some of the fallen leaders and their adherents helped to awaken the laboring classes more than some people think. For this same reason it is bringing together honest Bohemian citizens, who although they previously supported the principles of the Socialist Party did not actually become members of it.</p>
   <p>The movement which in this regard has among up among Chicago Bohemians is most welcome, because until now there never was among us such pre-election activity as at present. Would that our here-tofore inaction and unconcern had vanished, for we used to take no interest in public matters except before elections and then only to lapse into indifference again after elections.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1500.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us conscientiously attend lectures on Science and on Economics. Let us arrange public discussions, debating timely questions and let us appear in the election arena, fully prepared and decided on what action to take in order that we shall not be like a shall boat, which the waves of the political seas toss about at will.</p>
   <p>Activity! Ardent unselfish activity is for the good of all honestly sincere leaders among us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
