<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-04-18">Apr. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Important Lectures at the Chicago Teachers' College</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-04-18">Apr. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT LECTURES AT THE CHICAGO TEACHERS' COLLEGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A good deal has already been done for the Bohemian cause in this country by our pioneers, by our many institutions, and by individuals, who laid the foundations for further successes. But there is still much more for which we must strive and work, especially in the scientific and cultural fields.</p>
   <p>Therefore we should be delighted at the prospect that in the proposed series of lectures for students of the Chicago Teachers' College, which in some respects is the largest of its kind in the United States and perhaps in the world, topics which refer to the people and country of Bohemia will be included.</p>
   <p>The Ceska-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) accepted the invitation of this institution (The Chicago Teachers' College) gratefully, because the Bohemians will be given a chance to represent themselves in an important position. This series will be a center from which the light of <pb facs="5418478_1_0151.jpg" n="2"/>understanding for young America and a source of public appreciation in the future is to be disseminated.</p>
   <p>The credit for the recognition tendered us by this invitation belongs to the Narodni Rada, which through all the years of its existence has tried consistently to place us among the important nations in this country in order that we may gain due recognition and not be slighted continually with silence, smirks, and insults.</p>
   <p>Therefore, this matter is of great importance to us, and we hope that the Narodni Rada, feeling the great significance of the goal which is to be attained, will carry the plan through to a successful conclusion, and thereby render a service to our Bohemian-American branch and to our nation. This is another success from which we can all draw a feeling of joyous satisfaction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
