<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-09">Sept. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to Czech America [From the Cesko-Americka Matice Skolska (Czech-American Central School Association)]</title><title level="a" type="sub">I.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-09">Sept. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO CZECH AMERICA [From the Cesko-Americka Matice Skolska (Czech-American Central School Association)]</title><title level="a" type="sub">I.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We all agree that the present time is ominous and that, unless energetic steps are taken at once, before long there will not be a trace of Czech nationality remaining in America.</p>
   <p>Czech associations feel most poignantly that this is slowly coming to pass. Members were easily gained in former times, and several new ones were inducted at almost every meeting. It takes several months, today, before one single person can be induced to join. At closer observation it becomes evident that more members withdraw than there are won.</p>
   <p>Our aid societies and brotherhoods are, perhaps, the worst sufferers from <pb facs="5418478_1_0042.jpg" n="2"/>these conditions, more than our Sokol and other organizations. This cannot be denied, and there is no use withholding the truth about it. It is time for action on our part to remedy these conditions.</p>
   <p>One of the first steps necessary for the rescue will, without question, be the unification of all brotherhoods. This merging of our aid societies is now in progress and will soon be accomplished--because it must be accomplished. The creation of one mighty body of aid societies is one of our first aims, for it will mean a firm foundation for the Czech element in America, and a pillar of strength for its perpetuation. Brotherhoods, united, will be better able to resist any onslaught of adverse circumstances than single, isolated units ever could.</p>
   <p>To attach independent brotherhoods to the body--that is the second step toward a cure. If we merge, we have to do the merging thoroughly. We are the American branch of the Czech nation, but divided into parties, the Free Thought, <pb facs="5418478_1_0043.jpg" n="3"/>the Catholic, and the Protestant. We should, at least in one point, form one powerful whole. We should not attempt to unite Freethinkers, Catholics, and Protestants while their camps are at variance with each other. Such a union would not be of any permanent value. It would fall apart at the slightest impact.</p>
   <p>A third remedy to prevent the disintegration of the Czech branch in America will be found when every Czech man and woman becomes a member of some aid society, unless he or she is a member already. Any fellow countryman of ours, who chances to meet another, whom he does not know to be a member of some brotherhood, should ask:</p>
   <p>"Pardon me, my fellow countryman, for asking to what society you belong."</p>
   <p>If the answer be "To none," then all power of persuasion should be used to win a new member for one of the various groups. It is easy. Everybody <pb facs="5418478_1_0044.jpg" n="4"/>should acknowledge that our aid societies are mainstays of our Czech schools here, and of the perpetuation of Free Thought principles; that they have munificently supported every Czech national enterprise here, and across the ocean; that they have laid one of the cornerstones for our foremost national institution, the Czech National Alliance. If these institutions become weak, if they totter and finally crumple, it would mean not only the downfall of Czech schools, in America, and of the Czech National Alliance, but of the Czech element altogether. Every sincere Czech man and woman should, therefore, consider it a duty to become a member of some of our Czech brotherhoods.</p>
   <p>We should perform this national work for the sake of our forebears; this is the kind of task which the Czech-American Central School Association urges us to take upon our shoulders.</p>
   <p>II.</p>
   <p>In times past, when new immigrants came to America in throngs, Czech schools <pb facs="5418478_1_0045.jpg" n="5"/>were not institutions of such towering importance. In recent times, however, no one from the country districts in Europe goes to America. European countries are even preparing laws to restrict emigration. The Czech schools have remained the only fountain from which Czech-American public life can draw its strength, its new workers.</p>
   <p>This undeniable fact stands out as a warning to all Czech settlements that have no Czech schools.</p>
   <p>What does it avail if Czech life surges in your settlement in mighty streams and whirls today, if one of its two sources is dried up and the other is dammed in by stones and clogged by brushwood and dust? How long will it be before the accumulated water has run out, and both sources fail?</p>
   <p>That first source is the immigration from Bohemia. We are through as far as its supply is concerned. That second source, choked and plugged up, consists <pb facs="5418478_1_0046.jpg" n="6"/>of our children, born here, who have seen no Czech schools!</p>
   <p>Does every one of you grasp now that, to maintain the Czech branch in America, to preserve the results of Czech activity in America, it is absolutely necessary for every Czech settlement here to possess Czech schools? Does every one understand that he is grossly at fault, who does not try everything in his power to support a well-established and conducted Czech school in his settlement? Do our associations comprehend, do our Czech patriots know now?</p>
   <p>We hope that they understand, for we hear echoes in this direction from everywhere, and we are receiving demands for information on how to found Czech schools.</p>
   <p>We hope that every one of our settlements without Czech schools will contact the Czech-American Central School Association, Box 46, Little Ferry, New Jersey. It will supply information, and send an organizer who will approach <pb facs="5418478_1_0047.jpg" n="7"/>the public, speak on the mission of the Czech school, and put it on a firm basis. Our Association will watch over the school, and see that it performs its duties properly.</p>
   <p>It may become a matter of expediency for the organizer to introduce improvements in schools already existing.</p>
   <p>We recommend that, before schools are opened next school year, each settlement call a public meeting, by which the highest possible attendance of the school may be guaranteed.</p>
   <p>We also advise that each settlement with a Czech school form a committee, which should speak to parents who do not send their children to the Czech school. Those fathers and mothers should be admonished at least not to detain their children from attending, for what sort of a Czech is it who would not let his child frequent the Czech school already existing in his <pb facs="5418478_1_0048.jpg" n="8"/>settlement?</p>
   <p>We recommend to arrange for at least three public appearances per year, for they are the best agitators for parents and for pupils. They induce the former to send their children to school, and stir the pride and incite the ambition of the pupils. we emphasize the fact, that all pupils, even the smallest, should be given an opportunity.</p>
   <p>We further counsel our schools to send us samples of work performed, and show the methods they use. This should be done at least every quarter of the school year. It is obvious that with the present state of affairs it is impossible for certain communities to employ trained teachers. The Czech-American Central School Association has expert teachers available, who will give advice and show the way to attain the best results.</p>
   <p>Our school tends to prepare our youngsters for membership in our brotherhoods <pb facs="5418478_1_0049.jpg" n="9"/>and other organizations. When they grow up, they will have a foundation in the history of the Czech people. They will love that nation, adhere to its ways, and proudly proclaim allegiance to it.</p>
   <p>Our purpose is to educate our adolescents so that they associate with Americans, and spread information among them regarding the Czech nation and its national aims. Our youth will in this way be doing more for the cause of the Czechs than we ourselves could accomplish. This aim is sublime, and difficult to attain, yet the possibility is here, if we do not economize unduly.</p>
   <p>Na Zdar! (Success)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
