<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-26">Apr. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Committee of the Bohemian Charitable Association Has Secured the Aid of the State Officials in the Search for Ella Paroubka</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1227</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1227.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-26">Apr. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE COMMITTEE OF THE BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION HAS SECURED THE AID OF THE STATE OFFICIALS IN THE SEARCH FOR ELLA PAROUBKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Municipal Judge Uhlir, Alderman A. J. Cermak, Municipal Judge Thomas Scully and other distinguished citizens, almost all of whom are members of the Bohemian Charitable Association, visited Governor Deneen at Springfield yesterday, and requested the aid of State officials in the search for the missing Bohemian girl, Ella Paroubka. First of all, the committee wanted the State to offer a reward for the finding of the missing child. The Governor consulted with State's Attorney Stead, who informed him that under existing law the State was not allowed to offer any rewards for the finding of missing persons, except in cases where it concerned the capture of a murderer.</p>
   <p>However, a method has been found whereby the State will be empowered to take action, and participate in this instance. Steps will be taken by the State <pb facs="5418478_1_1228.jpg" n="2"/>Legislature to amend the law in such a manner as will permit the posting of a $200 reward to anyone who finds the missing child, and brings an end to the tortures endured by the parents of the child. Aside from that, the State authorities will aid in other ways in the search.</p>
   <p>Chicago police are more and more inclined to the belief that the missing girl was not carried off by gypsies, but that she lost her life in the drainage canal.</p>
   <p>Yesterday, detectives made a search among the Italian organ-grinders. It is said that the police found two girls yesterday who stated that they saw Ella Paroubka playing along the banks of the drainage canal on the afternoon of the day on which she disappeared. A search will be made along the old canal, (so called Mud-Lake) which in former days claimed so many victims among Bohemian children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
