<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-02-19">Feb. 19, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Conference of Bohemian Socialists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1634</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1634.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-02-19">Feb. 19, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE OF BOHEMIAN SOCIALISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All local sections were represented by twenty-four delegates in last Sunday's meeting of Bohemian Socialists, which was held in Soustka's Hall. Comrade Fr. Petr was elected Chairman, and Comrade Ad. Uzlik, Secretary.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the previous meeting were accepted as read. The reports of the executives, the press, and the auditing committee were postponed until the end of the second year of Spravedlnost.</p>
   <p>In regard to the election of executive, press and auditing committees, editor and manager of Spravedlnost, the motion of Comrade Hlavacek that all sections hold elections at their earliest meetings, was accepted and, therefore, the comrades should take notice and attend their next meeting in full strength. Further, in this meeting, the following resolutions and corrections were unanimously passed: That the editor and manager of Spravedlnost be not elected to <pb facs="5418478_1_1635.jpg" n="2"/>other offices, as they had enough work in their own office. Salaries of officials were given over to the executive committee for adjustment. A motion that the minutes of this meeting be sent to all local papers was passed.</p>
   <p>A resolution was presented by Comrade Wimren, that the National Committee of the American Socialist Party be requested to grant autonomy to the Bohemian Socialist Party of America and further, that the members of this party be not required to pay any dues aside from a small payment to the National Committee, because the members of the Bohemian sections are already burdened with their own personal expenses. However, they should not be denied the right of making decisions in matters pertaining to the party, or in national, state, or local elections. This motion was unanimously passed.</p>
   <p>Among the many practical and impractical motions, the cooperative undertaking in the Town of Lake was especially recommended, and that every Comrade should become a member thereof, or morally and materially support it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1636.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thereafter the meeting was adjourned.</p>
   <p>Ad. Vzlik</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
