<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-08-10">Aug. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">For the Attention of Bohemian Catholic Parents of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0400</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0400.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-08-10">Aug. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE ATTENTION OF BOHEMIAN CATHOLIC PARENTS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In this vacation period we again call the attention of the Bohemian Catholic parents to the fact that it is their duty to send their children to Catholic schools. A preference for Bohemian parochial schools should be given by them wherever these schools are in existence. A Catholic home and a Catholic school are the foundations of Christian life. In this country we have a large number of excellent high schools where your children can acquire an education which would place them in the ranks of the Bohemian Catholic intelligentsia.</p>
   <p>We especially call your attention to St. Prokopius College in Lisle, Illinois, which college is under the direction of the Bohemian Benedictine Fathers. There is still a very small number of our children who seek to acquire a higher education.</p>
   <p>Today, before the beginning of a new school year, there is an opportunity <pb facs="5418478_1_0401.jpg" n="2"/>for us to remind you again of this duty. As soon as the time arrives for the registration of the children, they should be registered only in Catholic schools. For that purpose only you had your parochial schools built.</p>
   <p>The Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku</p>
   <p>(National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
