<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-24">Apr. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Pupils Allowed to Tear Out "Kaiser Page"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0769</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0769.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-24">Apr. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PUPILS ALLOWED TO TEAR OUT "KAISER PAGE"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The pressure exacted upon the School Board by the Czech-American community is beginning to bear fruit. When it became evident that a strong agitation was being carried on against the authorities, Mr. John D. Shoop, superintendent of Chicago Schools, finally began to heed the sentiment of the parents in regard to the story, which eulogizes the German Kaiser and is resented by the patriotic Czech-Americans and parents from other nationalistic groups.</p>
   <p>When Mr. Shoop was informed about the method of protest to be employed, as recommended by the Czech National Alliance, he declared it to be a simple solution of the embarrassing question and in explaining his point of view <pb facs="5418478_1_0770.jpg" n="2"/>added: "Allow the children to tear the page from the school book. The book is their own property. They may handle it the way they desire."</p>
   <p>This would mean that the extirpation of the story has met with semi-official approval. However, it should not stop our agitation by any means. The Chicago School Board is a very unreliable institution, at least some of its former members. We Czechs, at least, could sing a nice song about this. It is known that the School Board had allowed some of the school rooms to be used for evening classes in which the Czech language is taught. When the school budget was debated on last fall, this accommodation would almost have been taken away from the Czech American parents if it had not been for the resolute demand of the Czech member of the Board, Mr. Holpuch. The rooms <pb facs="5418478_1_0771.jpg" n="3"/>continue to be at the disposal of the Czechs. The force with which we stand in our demand for the elimination of the "Kaiser Story" must not decrease. The excitement of the public might slacken. There are evidently some members on the Board who desire to retain the objectionable story. A future edition might contain it anew.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
