<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-08">Oct. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters the First Central Union of Bohemian Women Endorses Anton J. Cermak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-08">Oct. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS THE FIRST CENTRAL UNION OF BOHEMIAN WOMEN ENDORSES ANTON J. CERMAK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Alderman Anton J. Cermak, who is a candidate for the office of president of the Cook County Board of Commissioners,....received the wholehearted support of our foremost Bohemian women's organizations. These organizations recognize the importance of the office which Mr. Cermak desires to fill, and the great good which would result from his filling it, for he is an able and experienced man.</p>
   <p>In one of our recent issues we made known the fact that the grand lodges of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies Union) and the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Sisterhood) have fully endorsed the candidacy of Mr. Cermak. We have just received the news that a similar endorsement is to be given Mr. Cermak by the board of directors of the Ustredni Jednota Ceskych Zen (First Central Union of Bohemian Women), the president of which is Mrs. Marie Dusicka; Mrs. Marie Hora is the secretary. The First Central Union through its Grand Lodge urged the members of all its subordinate lodges to be sure to register, <pb facs="5418478_1_1306.jpg" n="2"/>and on November 7 to vote for Mr. Cermak whose great ability and wide experience as a public servant certainly entitles him to the confidence of all citizens. If any member of these women's organizations neglected to register yesterday, she may do so in the second and last registration which will be on October 17, 1922.</p>
   <p>The First Central Union also endorsed the soldiers' bonus bill.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
