<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-31">Oct. 31, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1280</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1280.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-31">Oct. 31, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>.....Our Cicero citizens ought to attend a meeting which is to be held tonight in the Sokol Karel Jonas, West 25th Street near 55th Avenue. This is going to be a large Democratic rally. Our great Cicero community is very much interested in the outcome of the forthcoming elections, by which the conditions of our country are to be improved and a more economical management introduced into all political offices, thereby leading to a lowering of taxes. It is equally important to us that a well qualified, experienced, and recognized man be elected to the office of president of the Board of County Commissioners. Such a man is Mr. Anton J. Cermak, an experienced, and a recognized, champion of American freedom. It is therefore desirable that our Czechoslovak voters, both men and women, come to the Sokol Karel Jonas this evening, to hear speeches by the outstanding Democratic candidates and able Czechoslovak orators. Amongst others there will be Mr. Anton J. Cermak, Mr. Josef Mendl, Mr. F. J. Novak, Mr. J. F. Triska, and other Democratic candidates.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow night there will be another Democratic meeting in the F. B. Zdrubek <pb facs="5418478_1_1281.jpg" n="2"/>Bohemian Free Thought school at 4624 North Crawford Avenue. Among the candidates who will address the meeting there will be Alderman Anton J. Cermak, Mr. Josef A. Mendl, and other excellent speakers. The Czechoslovak citizens of Irving Park should attend this meeting in large numbers.</p>
   <p>We cannot sufficiently emphasize to our countrymen who live in the nineteenth senatorial district that it is only by voting unanimously for Mr. Albert B. Holecek, the Republican candidate for state senator, that we may hope to secure his election and thus delegate to the upper house of the state legislature in Springfield, Illinois, a sincere countryman of ours, a man who possesses all the qualifications necessary to act in our behalf and do honor to the nationality to which he belongs. The nineteenth district is a gigantic area as regards both its extent and the number of its inhabitants. It is estimated that there are 90,000 registered voters in this district. Let us suppose that 30,000 of these are Czechoslovaks in origin. This leaves a balance of 60,000 of other foreign-language groups. If, of this latter number, only 20,000 voted straight Republican, or gave votes to Mr. Holecek, prompted <pb facs="5418478_1_1282.jpg" n="3"/>by the recommendations made by the voters league, and by other considerations which make Mr. Holecek a desirable candidate, it is certain that with the help of the Czech votes he would receive a majority and be elected. But all Czechs and Slovaks, irrespective of their political party, must be his supporters and must place a cross in front of his name. No matter who tries to influence them, or how such an influence is exerted upon them, let them pay no attention and act as befits good citizens and true Czechoslovaks. Mr. Holecek's election will be a victory for all of us; all of us must, therefore, work for it and endeavor to make it a reality.</p>
   <p>There are many indications that our Cicero community is showing an unusually great interest in the Democratic ticket; the fact that this is so will be borne out at tonight's meeting which will be held in the Sokol Jonas hall on West 25th Street and 55th Avenue, Cicero, Illinois. The preparations for this meeting were extensive, so much so that every effort was expended to make the meeting both interesting and instructive. The best public speakers will address the meeting. They will be Messrs. Anton J. Cermak, Josef Mendl, Josef J. Janda, Rudolf Hurt, <pb facs="5418478_1_1283.jpg" n="4"/>James Dailey, Edmund K. Jarecki, Otto K. Fuerst, and others. The meeting will start at 8 P.M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
