<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-19">Sept. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">From the Klub Poplatniku Lawndale</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-19">Sept. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE KLUB POPLATNIKU LAWNDALE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>....One of my duties as secretary of the Klub Poplatniku Lawndale (Club of Lawndale Taxpayers) is to keep the Bohemian newspapers informed about the doings of the organization. I have accepted this duty, hoping that if everybody knows about our activities, they will soon apply for Club membership. I feel sure that the seeds I have been trying to sow have fallen on fertile ground, and that most of those who have been reading my articles in the various periodicals where they were published have come to the conclusion that it is not well to leave the management of political matters to a few individuals, and that it is desirable to follow closely the activities of public officials and try to determine whether or not their work is commensurable with their pay. But not everybody is in a position to do this. It requires both time and opportunity.</p>
   <p>At this time I want to call attention to the fact that the streetcar company <pb facs="5418478_1_1578.jpg" n="2"/>pays about ten million dollars a year for its privileges. This money, or most of it, is accumulated from the poor who use the streetcar for transportation to and from work. It would be only proper and just if this money were used for some purpose which would benefit--morally or financially--those who made the accumulation of that huge amount of money possible. What benefit shall we derive from a boulevard whose cost is estimated at from seven to ten million dollars? We have to contribute one third of this amount, and what shall we gain? I do not propose to analyze these sad figures, but I am sure that the whole boulevard will not mean more to me than a red cent.</p>
   <p>At the same time we need a playground badly. For this we received three thousand dollars from the city two years ago. This amount is just enough to build and equip the playground. But it will never buy the necessary piece of real estate. Let us all now concentrate on a way to secure the ground and thus help our children who have to play in the streets under the peril of their physical and moral well-being.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1579.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Another thing that should be investigated is the refuse-burning ovens. I have not had much personal experience with the odors gracing that particular neighborhood, but I am sure that any other odor is a sweet-smelling attar of roses in comparison with the perfume produced by these evens.</p>
   <p>And now a bit about our woman-suffragists. Having the right to vote, they should become interested in political matters in order to use their ballots to best advantage and according to the results of personal knowledge--not, as most men do, according to what they are told or paid for by political agents.</p>
   <p>The Lawndale Taxpayers Club herewith issues an invitation to all friends of public order to its meeting on Saturday, September 20, at 8 P. M. at the Vojta Naprstek School, 26th Street and Homan Avenue.</p>
   <p>Fr. Krumpos, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
