<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-11-06">Nov. 6, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Political Scene</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1437</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1437.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-11-06">Nov. 6, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLITICAL SCENE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bohemian Pilsen [on Chicago's Southwest Side] will demonstrate this afternoon that it is still a Democratic stronghold. The Democrats have always been fair to us Bohemians: they have granted us representation; they have been solicitous of the welfare of our community; and in city, county, and national politics, they have pursued politics which have been satisfactory to us. For these reasons, the Bohemian people have been ardent supporters of the Democratic party. That they have retained their faith in the party will be shown at the Democratic rally which will be held at two o'clock this afternoon in the auditorium of the Bohemian-American Liberal School on 18th Street. The Bohemian candidates on the Democratic ticket, [Charles J.] Vopicka and [Adolph J.] Sabath, will attend the meetings; several distinguished speakers will appear; and there will be so many enthusiastic Democrats present that the hall will hardly be large enough to accommodate them all. The popular Hovorka quartet will entertain the gathering.</p>
   <p>The campaign is nearing a close; the voters will go to the polls on Tuesday.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1438.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They should therefore come to today's meeting, where it will be proved to them that they can best protect their own interests by casting their ballots for the Democratic party.</p>
   <p>The present campaign is concerned chiefly with the question of imperialism and its accompanying militarism, and with the issue of the trusts and the high tariffs enacted for their benefit. The Democrats, as always, are the guardians of the interests of all the American people, whereas the Republican party serves, as it has always served, the interests of a special class. We Bohemians are decidedly with the Democrats on the question of imperialism. We have come here from the old country, where imperialism and militarism exist by decree. We know what they mean. We also know what the German, French, and English people have to endure as a result of the power politics which their governments practice. We know the terrible burden under which European nations groan and bleed. And because we know these things, we do not want the same fate to befall the American nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1439.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We must also agree with the Democrats on the issue of trusts and high tariffs. The Republican high tariff has been the foundation upon which the capitalistic monster [the trust] has been firmly erected; it is a necessary condition for the continued existence and success of the trust. Whoever is for a high tariff is advancing the interests of the trusts; that is a truth which even the cleverest Republican partisan cannot deny. Bohemian voters will show on Tuesday that they are interested in the welfare of the American people, that they know how to protect their own interests against big capital and against all who would like to hurl them into material and political subjection. They will vote the Democratic ticket.</p>
   <p>Countrymen! Do everything within your power, during these last few days before election, to help elect sincere Bohemians, proven and capable men like Vopicka and Sabath. Both of these men give every assurance that they will perform the duties of their office in such a way that we may be proud of them. The Fifth Congressional District will send the first Bohemian to Congress; let us see to it that this Bohemian shall in everything and at all times be an honor to us. If we elect Mr. Vopicka, we shall have such a man in Congress.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1440.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The office of County Recorder, which Mr. Sabath is seeking, is one of the most important offices which the citizens of the county have to offer. The Recorder's office employs many officials, and it is necessary that they should serve the interests of the voters and taxpayers. This office has hitherto been conducted for the benefit of the million-dollar companies....Mr. Sabath will see to it that this condition is brought to an end. Everyone who has any business to transact in the Recorder's office will benefit as a result. Aside from this consideration, we Bohemians will have the proud awareness that it was our countryman who was responsible for bringing about these reforms. Let us all, therefore, vote for Mr. Sabath.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
