<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-09">Aug. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To Czech Students</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-09">Aug. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO CZECH STUDENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani (Mother [or center] of Higher Education) will again accept applications from students of both sexes who are gifted, and who desire to continue of finish their studies, but are without means to do it.</p>
   <p>Part of the expenses, not exceeding $250 for one year of academic study, will be loaned without interest, merely upon their word of honor, to students, who can meet the requirements prescribed by the Executive Committee. These requirements are printed below for the careful perusal of prospective applicants:</p>
   <p>"They [applicants] must, regardless of sex, be of Czech descent, must have a command of the Czech language, and be conscious of their Czech descent. They must be leading a decent moral life, and must be able to pursue the more advanced studies. Only students without sufficient financial means to continue their studies independently will be accepted. They should enclose their photographs, <pb facs="5418478_1_0361.jpg" n="2"/>and should state which institution of higher learning approved by the Executive Committee they wish to enter.</p>
   <p>"Before the loan is accorded to him, the student must prove his qualification by one half year's work at that institution. He must declare his intention of completing a full academic course, and agree that the faculty of his institution send reports on his progress to the Executive Committee at certain intervals."</p>
   <p>Only academic, teachers', or engineering courses are on the list approved by the Committee.</p>
   <p>The "academic" courses are termed in University catalogs "Collegiate Courses," "College of Liberal Arts," "College of Arts and Sciences". The respective lectures are on modern languages and literature, history, philosophy, agriculture, exact and natural sciences. In teachers' and engineering colleges, the related subjects are taught.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0362.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Students should give particular attention to preparatory studies in English grammar, to which great importance is attached. Czech students are frequently deficient in this branch and do not pass in other subjects on account of insufficient knowledge of the language in which all lectures are delivered.</p>
   <p>The Committee lays particular stress upon proficiency in the English language, and insists upon proof in the form of examination papers from accredited high schools, or other schools on the same level.</p>
   <p>Applications must be sent to the Executive Committee on or before September 1. They should contain references from fellow citizens and teachers. Address the applications to P. A. Korab, Iowa City, Iowa. For the Executive Committee of the Matice:</p>
   <p>B. Simek, chairman;</p>
   <p>P. A. Korab, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
