<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-05-12">May 12, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Organization Question.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1091</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1091.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-05-12">May 12, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE ORGANIZATION QUESTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the working men of some trades organize themselves into a union, when those belonging to some branch of business or industry compose themselves into an association it is generally recognized as reasonable and beneficial.</p>
   <p>But in no way can our countrymen become reconciled to the idea, that Bohemian-American newspapermen should also organize in their own interests. When even a few editors or reporters in the employ of competitive papers meet in a public place, and talk together in a proper and friendly manner, everyone who witnesses it takes notice as though something improper were being done, and as though it was to be understood, that the employees of various publications must argue and fight among themselves.</p>
   <p>This is a sad phenomenon. The "Society of Bohemian Journalists of America" has taken as its aim: The rectification of this misunderstanding, the formation of an "editors and reporters" organization, the gaining for the newspaper business of public respect and the proper esteem of the employers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1092.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But, the work of the society is being destroyed by the indifference of the newspapermen themselves, and by the pre-judgement of a large following of citizens. Only the editors of Hlasatel and Narod, and of several weekly papers belong to the "society of journalists." The most peculiar thing about it is that people, who call themselves the most enlightened, who preach the organization of various workingmen, disregard the organization of their own particular following. Rural editors apparently have an altogether indifferent attitude, as not one of them has recognized the joining of the society as a good thing.</p>
   <p>When we see the indifference, yes, the dislike, which a great number of newspapermen show toward their own organization it seems to us that it is indeed a truthful saying, "that every man on earth prospers according to his merit," newspapermen also.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
