<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-09">Dec. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovak Taxpayers' Association Opposed to the Proposed New State Constitution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1254</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1254.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-09">Dec. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAK TAXPAYERS' ASSOCIATION OPPOSED TO THE PROPOSED NEW STATE CONSTITUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Spolek Ceskoslovenskych Poplatniku 26te Wardy (Czechoslovak Taxpayers' Association of the 26th Ward) has also taken a stand against the proposed revision of the Illinois constitution which is to be voted on next Tuesday. The Spolek issued the following proclamation to its members:</p>
   <p>"The election of December 12, 1922, is very important for our Czechoslovak people, for the citizens will be faced with the duty of accepting or rejecting the proposed new state constitution of Illinois which will be decided by vote on that day. Should the new provisions be sanctioned and enacted, our people would be at the mercy of racketeering corporations and other unsavory elements. First of all, the constitution as amended takes away the people's right to select and elect their judges, giving that right to the Supreme Court which could and would select and appoint the judges whom the people would then be compelled to accept. In this way our judicial system would degenerate into <pb facs="5418478_1_1255.jpg" n="2"/>a tyranny in place of an unbiased and just agency for the prosecution of the law which it now does. Second, the new taxation system is so organized as to impose the greatest burden upon the working classes while easing the tax burden of the rich. According to the new provision any man earning, say, $10 a week would have to pay a tax on his earnings. Third, the newly proposed constitution makes autonomous government impossible, takes away the freedom of the people who alone decide what is necessary for their welfare....and concentrates this power in a few persons representing the interests of the rich and the profiteers.</p>
   <p>"Because of the reasons stated above the Spolek of the 26th Ward (formerly the 10th) urges all citizens, male and female, in the interest of a just government and good public order, to come to the polls next Tuesday, December 12, 1922, and definitely vote against the proposed new constitution.</p>
   <p>"For the Spolek Poplatniku 26te Wardy,</p>
   <p>"Mr. Albert Kakuska, president</p>
   <p>"Mr. Jan Rezek, secretary."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
