<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-01-02">Jan. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Garment Workers to Rally</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-01-02">Jan. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">GARMENT WORKERS TO RALLY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Happy New Year," the wish so common on January 1, can hardly be accepted this year by the garment workers. Could they be grateful for any benefit during the past year? The garment workers cannot but regard the past year through a gloomy light. All throughout that time, they were bled by the greedy capitalistic interests, hardly being able to bear the misery and humiliation imposed on them by the bosses, and often by people of low moral standards, who tortured their bodies and defiled the souls of their young girls.</p>
   <p>The present strike is for the purpose of preventing similar indignities from becoming rampant by forcing foremen, especially, to use decent ways in their treatment of girl workers. It is a just fight for which all decent elements should wish success, so much the more as it has cost up-to-date thirteen weeks of privation and three lives in the ranks of the strikers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1170.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Is it not desirable to earn money enough to eliminate the necessity of sending one's wife out to work, thus making her fail in her destination to the detriment of future generation?</p>
   <p>What is in store for a girl who, at a tender age, is forced into the unhealthy atmosphere of an overcrowded garment workers' shop? The horrible scourge of the twentieth century, - tuberculosis, - is way-laying her, and, if it does not annihilate the bud in its prime, it surely will leave a lifelong mark.</p>
   <p>Where are we heading? Let us meditate and ponder in this new year. We call on all of you to quit work if there is a glimmer of self-respect and humane feeling left in you! We hope that in this new year, you will come to your senses. Strike, and so help us on to victory!</p>
   <p>The Strikers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
