<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-25">Mar. 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czechoslovak Democratic Activity in Cicero</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1350</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1350.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-25">Mar. 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czechoslovak Democratic Activity in Cicero</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night there was a meeting of the Czechoslovak women who have rallied under the Democratic banner. The meeting took place in Horalek's Hall, 56th Avenue and 25th Street, Cicero, Illinois. When one considers that Cicero was hitherto always looked upon as a stronghold of Republicanism, the great number of our women who attended this meeting is astonishing. The Hall was filled to capacity, and there was great enthusiasm among our Czechoslovak people who are ready to work for the Democratic party. This party has always given the Czechs recognition. This is shown by the candidacy of Mr. Anton J. Cermak for the office of president of the Board of County Commissioners. There are other countrymen of ours who are listed on the [primary] ticket and may become useful to our people.</p>
   <p>The meeting was presided over by Mrs. Kopstein; Mrs. Voborsky was the <pb facs="5418478_1_1351.jpg" n="2"/>secretary. It was ascertained that all Czech precincts of Cicero were represented. The speakers were Messrs. Anton J. Cermak, John Toman, Rudolf Hurt, Otto R. Fuerst, and others. Their speeches were loudly acclaimed, particularly those of Messrs Cermak and Fuerst. Mr. Cermak gave all the valid reasons why we should belong to the Democratic party and propagandize the work of its candidates. Mr. Fuerst, whose oratorical ability is unexcelled, gave us much food for thought in a manner both enlightening and satirical. After the adjournment refreshments were served.</p>
   <p>Tonight there will be another meeting of the Czechoslovak Democratic Campaign Committee in the lower hall of the Sokol Chicago on Kedzie Avenue.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
