<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-26">Oct. 26, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">We Must Not Use Beer as Medicine</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-26">Oct. 26, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WE MUST NOT USE BEER AS MEDICINE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Things in Illinois a state which we have been in the habit of calling among the most progressive and liberal, have come to such a pass that we shall not be able to use the good beer for improvement of our physical condition, as medicine, in spite of the fact that this is permitted according to the decision of the Treasury Department in Washington. In Illinois, the search and seizure law adopted by the last Legislature and signed by Governor Small prevents that. Attorney General Brundage declared yesterday that that law makes the Washington decision inapplicable in the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>That law specifically prohibits the use of wine and beer for medicinal purposes, forbids physicians to prescribe it, and drugstores to sell it. According to regulations issued by Secretary Mellon, "medicinal" beer may be sold only by licensed pharmacists. According to the Illinois law, pharmacists who sell such beer, and physicians who prescribe it are liable to lose their licenses and in addition may be fined and jailed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0537.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Local prohibitionists, however, fear that the new decision of the Department of the Treasury will cause an increase impillicit beer traffic in Illinois, because the State has no money for the enforcement of the State search and seizure law, Governor Small having crossed out from the budget the item that would have permitted the Attorney General to hire spies without which the enforcement of such noble laws is impossible. The various assistant state's Attorneys declare that they are fully occupied with the supression of crime and have no time for the enforcement of the search and seizure law.</p>
   <p>The drugstores were being visited yesterday by very many people who do not feel well and believe that good beer would help them. They came to put in their orders for a share in the coming beer shipment. But their hopes of getting any part of any shipment were squelched by the declaration of Attorney General Brundage. Druggists, physicians, brewers, do not know where they really stand. Some say there will be beer, some say there will be none. But the fact seems to be that any physician who prescribes anything with more than one half of one per cent alcohol in it, any druggist who <pb facs="5418478_1_0538.jpg" n="3"/>sells anything like it, any brewery that makes anything like it, and any patient who uses anything like it will be in danger of prosecution for infringement of that state law.</p>
   <p>Levy Mayer, attorney for the "wet" forces, upon being asked yesterday about his opinion, declared that there is no doubt about the validity of the State law, which in this case could not be made void by a mere "regulation" of a department of the Federal Government. But he has serious doubts about the constitutionality of that law because it prohibits the physician from prescribing for his patient a medicine which he believes would be beneficial for the patient.</p>
   <p>Many physicians and pharmacists were asked yesterday what standpoint they would take. A large part of them declared they would respect the Illinois State Law. Most of them are waiting for an opinion from Washington about the situation in Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
