<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-07-31">July 31, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">[German in the Public Schools]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 b (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-07-31">July 31, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">[GERMAN IN THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In regards to the question of the teaching of the German language in the public schools, the strange standpoint of Bohemian defenders of German can be explained only by the fact, that they probably hope, that they will succeed in getting the instruction of the Bohemian language in the public schools if they remain content with the German. From the very beginning we pronounced such ideas as nonsensical.</p>
   <p>That which can be accomplished in some community in which Bohemians are in the majority, is impossible of accomplishment in a city such as is Chicago. We knew, in the beginning, that the Germans would always be the first to oppose the requests of the Bohemians, and that we were not mistaken is proven by excerpts from the local Staats-Zeitung.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0310.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although the editors of the above mentioned paper recognize the Bohemians as the most cultured branch of the Slavic nationalities, they still deny to Bohemians the right to aspire to a place in the American public schools. The Staats-Zeitung answered our German-Bohemians in the manner which we expected of it.</p>
   <p>We expressed our sorrow for those who dared to hope, that in a city like Chicago, the Bohemian language could be introduced as a subject of study in the public schools, and we would have to be even sorrier for those who would request it, for we know they would become the subject of poisonous puns and vulgar insults from the German press.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0311.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the present agitation, let our countrymen, who have placed themselves at the head of the anti-German movement, often recollect, what Bismarck said, when the inhabitants of Alsace petitioned him to have the French language, which in their children's later years is as necessary to them as is the German: (in fact more necessary, than the German in America) taught in the public schools.</p>
   <p>Bismarck replied to his petitioners: "The public school must teach only one language - that is the language of the nation. To introduce into it another language would be against all reasonable educational principles. Whoever wishes to learn French, will find opportunity to do so in the higher schools, otherwise they must accomplish it at their own expense. The public schools are not for such purposes."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0312.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We maintain the same about local schools: to introduce into them another language is against all reasonable educational principles. whoever wants to learn German, will find an opportunity to do so in the high schools, or they must accomplish it at their own expense; public schools, which are attended by the children of immigrants, are not for such purposes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
