<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-18">Oct. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago People Protest the United Civic Societies Prepare a Huge Demonstration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0625</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0625.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-18">Oct. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO PEOPLE PROTEST The United Civic Societies Prepare a Huge Demonstration</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the presence of a multitude of people of both sexes, the President of The United Civic Societies of Chicago, Mr. Landau, opened a special convention by explaining that it is being held in order to deal with the Mayor's decree to close saloons on Sundays. The meeting was held in the great hall of Sokol Chicago......</p>
   <p>The floor was then given to ex-Mayor Carter H. Harrison......</p>
   <p>His speech was frequently interrupted by applause......</p>
   <p>Secretary [Anton J.] Cermak read the resolution of the United Civic societies by which the calling of this convention was ratified. The resolution<pb facs="5418478_1_0626.jpg" n="2"/>deals with the detrimental effects of Mayor Thompson's breach of pledge, and urges the people to undertake a strong demonstration of its displeasure over the breaking of the Mayor's promise and the violation and limitation of the personal liberty of the citizens. The credentials committee reported the presence of 2,341 delegates representing 969 associations....</p>
   <p>The resoltions committee presented the text of six resolutions it had drafted........</p>
   <p>All resolutions were unanimously adopted......and ex-Alderman Felix Janovsky delivered an enthusiastic speech.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0627.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Cermak explained that the matter of the public demonstration had been discussed by the committee for political action, and, that it was up to the delegates to make it the greatest ever held in Chicago.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
