<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-05">Feb. 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">United Societies Spurred to Act</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-05">Feb. 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED SOCIETIES SPURRED TO ACT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1--A strange procession moved through the down-town yesterday, --men, women, and children singing hymns, shouting in praise of the Lord, and jumping, wriggling, and writiing with joy. When the ancient Israelites besieged the town of Jericho, they could not have made more noise than the prohibitionists when they carried their petitions to the offices of the Board of Election Commissioners.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the drys entered and presented 74,805 names on their petitions, 14,000 more than the law requires, in order to insure for themselves a place on the ballot. Chicago has never witnessed a similar manifestation of such magnitude. It gave one the impression, that we are living in the Middle Ages, when swarms of fanatics peregrinated from town to town and gave went to their religious emotions in the most absurd fashion.</p>
   <p>Representatives of the United Societies, will call on the Commissioners today with local option as their main object and also to demand an examination <pb facs="5418478_1_0492.jpg" n="2"/>of the drys' petitions to ascertain how many names on them are fictitious or belong to non-voters, and how many repetitions were fraudulently used.</p>
   <p>These petitions, as is well known, are for the purpose of getting on the ballot the momentous question of whether the saloon shall be allowed to exist in Chicago. The United Societies, in which the majority of our Bohemian societies and clubs are included, done very little up to the present to meet the issue effectively. It is to be hoped that from now on they will apply themselves vigorously to combating the drys, so that the rejoicing of these latter may be changed into gnashing of teeth on election day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
