<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-05-26">May 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of the United Societies of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1584</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1584.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-05-26">May 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF THE UNITED SOCIETIES OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The well-attended annual meeting of the United Societies of Chicago was held in the North Side Turner Hall yesterday afternoon. The Bohemians were very well represented and took a lively part in the discussions. President Landau opened the meeting, and following the reading of the minutes of the last meeting, a credentials committee consisting of eleven members was appointed, of which three were Bohemians: Mr. John Sebek, Mr. F. J. Zahroboky, and Mr. Ferd. Svoboda.</p>
   <p>From the secretary's report it was learned that during the past year, five societies have resigned their membership, as against twenty-eight societies that have joined the organization. Consequently, the United Societies now has 754 members.</p>
   <p>The executive committee found it necessary to undertake a number of interventions during this past year and file protests against infamous legislative <pb facs="5418478_1_1585.jpg" n="2"/>proposals aimed at the curtailment of personal liberty. The recently adopted police ordinance was passed only because of the pressure which the United Societies brought to bear upon the Chicago City Council.</p>
   <p>The committee on legislation is now engaged in vigorous action against the Woodward Bill concerning special one-hundred-dollar licenses for dispensing alcoholic beverages. The committee is doing everything in its power to prevent this Bill from becoming a law, and there is every indication that the action will be successful.</p>
   <p>The political activities of the United Societies prove to be most beneficial and successful. It was because of these that the present State's attorney, Maclay Hoyne, and the municipal court bailiff, Anton J. Cermak, were elected. Of the fifty-seven candidates for Congress whom the organization recommended, forty-seven were elected. In the municipal elections in April, twenty-six out of twenty-nine of the organization's aldermanic candidates were elected.</p>
   <p>Also, the committee on taxation was very active. It held several conferences <pb facs="5418478_1_1586.jpg" n="3"/>with tax experts, and its report to the executive committee is most satisfactory. It is interesting to note the report of this committee concerning the total valuation of all railroad property in Chicago. It was assessed at five million dollars, but the Northwestern Depot alone had cost twenty million dollars to build. Due to this committee's efforts, the necessary steps were taken against the railroads, which now have made a tax settlement covering the past twenty years. If the big corporations would be made to pay their taxes in the same manner as the little man, Chicago would smile at several million dollars in its treasury instead of moaning over empty coffers.</p>
   <p>Congressman Burns, who spoke at the meeting, concerned himself principally with the ticklish problem presented by the bill on initiative and referendum which is now pending in the legislature. In connection with this, Mr. Cermak reported upon his visit to the legislature and explained to the audience in what way the bill is detrimental to the interests of Chicago. He declared <pb facs="5418478_1_1587.jpg" n="4"/>that if it is passed, it will put serious limitations on Chicago's autonomy and also on the rights of Cook County.</p>
   <p>Dr. Weimer presented an excellent discussion dealing with the danger threatening the interests of Chicago. It is a shame, he said, that the mayor of such an immense metropolis as Chicago has to beg in the State legislature for the protection of his constituents' rights of citizenship and personal liberty. In this respect, Vienna, Berlin, St. Petersburg, and Moscow are in a much better position.</p>
   <p>Between the speeches, the German Singing Society Harmonie presented two beautiful choral selections. There followed the presentation of reports of other committees. The representatives at the meeting elected as their chairman Mr. John A. Cervenka; vice-chairman, Dr. J. Uhlir; and secretary, Anton J. Cermak.</p>
   <p>Among the resolutions adopted by the United Societies is the one giving <pb facs="5418478_1_1588.jpg" n="5"/>the executive committee the right to publish a magazine under the name of Monthly Bulletin, the United Societies' official organ.</p>
   <p>At the end of the meeting, a board of eighty electors was appointed to select the president, the secretary, and all other officers of the United Societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
