<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1900-02-14">February 14, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Political Resolution in 9th Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1900-02-14">February 14, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL RESOLUTION IN 9TH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We citizens of the 9th ward, present at the political meeting on Sunday, February 11, 1900, held in Sistkov Hall, corner 12th and Paulina streets, approve the nomination of the Bohemian candidate, Mr. J. Smejkal, for alderman of the 9th ward and we recommend him to all the voters of different parties of the 9th ward. We enforce this with the following remarks:</p>
   <p>It is of great importance for all solid citizens of Chicago to watch that all affairs of our city be placed in good and honest hands, consequently it is our duty to help with all our power such a candidate only who is worthy of our confidence. Mr. Smejkal can prove his spotless past; his honest name was never connected with the slightest shadow of dishonesty in political or social activity, and that is why in this electoral campaign he is the man who should be supported by us.</p>
   <p>On the other herd, we ought to support Mr. Smejkal as our countryman, who in our national and special life was always honest and unselfish. It would be a disgrace for us not to be able to elect a countryman in a ward populated mostly by Bohemian citizens. So much more since we all know his character <pb facs="5418478_1_1453.jpg" n="2"/>and his correct action and we can be assured that he will represent our racial group in the City Council with full dignity and honesty.</p>
   <p>We must mention, dear citizens, that in the past election we have succeeded in electing Mr. Hurt as alderman only by giving him all Bohemian votes, Republican and Democratic without exception, because he was a respectable and capable man.</p>
   <p>Are we not able to achieve the same now by voting for Mr. Smejkal? Certainly we can, because he is a thoroughly respectable man and he won't disappoint our confidence and will represent his ward with dignity. Don't lock for other nationalities. We must fight this year as we did last year and obtain the same for Mr. Smejkal that we obtained last year for Mr. Hurt. We must prove that we are a majority in our ward; that we are a decisive element and not a bunch of voters of a "certain" nationality, which does homage to the power of minority instead of the majority and which is neglecting our own rights.</p>
   <p>The main thing is that you citizens of Bohemian origin all come to the polls, and that you start from today to agitate zealously for our candidate, Mr. J. Smejkal.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1454.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This resolution was signed by twenty-two members of the resolute committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
