<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-01-17">Jan. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Bohemian Candidate for Office of Judge of the Circuit Court.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-01-17">Jan. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A BOHEMIAN CANDIDATE FOR OFFICE OF JUDGE OF THE CIRCUIT COURT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2--For the first time in the history of Cook County a Bohemian is slated for the office of judge of the circuit court. All of the Bohemian lawyers of Chicago recommend Mr. F. J. Karasek as a candidate well equipped for the position of judge since he has had eleven years experience and is a lawyer of good standing. It is certain that he will also be recommended by the Cook County Bar Association and by many prominent citizens. It is our duty to help our fellow-countryman to win the nomination, for the names of the fourteen candidates of each party who obtain the highest number of votes in the primary election will be placed on the ballot to be voted for in the regular election. No others can be elected.</p>
   <p>It will surely be an honor for us Bohemians if Mr. Karasek wins. This, however, will not be easy since there will be many candidates in the primary election. We should therefore turn out in as great numbers as possible to vote for our compatriot.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1430.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among our countrymen who are ambitious to win political office is our own Mr. Klinenberg of the Town of Lake, whose petition to enter the primary as candidate for the Democratic nomination for alderman of the twenty-ninth ward has been in circulation for a long time and is being signed by numerous residents of that ward who classify themselves as Bohemian Democrats. The office of alderman seems to have lost much of its attraction recently, notwithstanding the fact that our city fathers are apparently about to succeed in raising their salaries to the handsome figure of $3500.</p>
   <p>Some aldermen who have been in office for years announce that they will not be candidates for re-election.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
