<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-05">Aug. 5, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of Taxpayers of the Thirty-Fourth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1608</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1608.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-05">Aug. 5, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF TAXPAYERS OF THE THIRTY-FOURTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A protest meeting was held last night in Kafka's Hall on Twenty-sixth Street and Avers Avenue. The meeting was presided over by Mr. Vaclav Marek, who explained the purpose of the meeting. According to a decision of the City Council, a big drainage ditch is to be constructed, which will be one mile from the community which will carry the greatest burden. This ditch is to cost $475,000 although an outlay of $200,000 would be sufficient. The difference is graft. Judge Girley, of the Superior Court, before whom hearings were to be held, postponed this case until Monday when he heard that the citizens were protesting against it. Mr. Marek moved that an attorney be employed who would attempt to defeat this graft.</p>
   <p>One of the citizens present announced that a meeting was held in the Twelfth Ward at which Alderman Anton J. Cermak was present. The participants of that meeting were unanimous in making known their disapproval. Attention was called to the fact that assessments would <pb facs="5418478_1_1609.jpg" n="2"/>be $32 on a three-story building; $29 on a two-story building; and $27.10 on an ordinary cottage.</p>
   <p>One of the citizens asked whether or not the aldermen of the Wards had been invited to attend the meeting. Mr. Marek explained that he had not invited them because he saw in them only arrogant people who close the door to petitioners and never in their lives do anything for our people. Mr. Kostner's actions were also criticized. It was his duty to explain this matter to the citizens, but he did not think it well to do so. The meeting was called by the Lawndale Taxpayer's Club. The Club knows that the politicians are all in favor of this project and their presence at the meeting would be useless.</p>
   <p>Upon the invitation of the chairman Mr. Bicek, a lawyer, explained that holding meetings will not help, but that at the proper time a protest must be filed with the courts after which it must be proved that the proposed improvement is unnecessary and a reduction of the assessments <pb facs="5418478_1_1610.jpg" n="3"/>might be secured. Anyone who does not enter a protest can not expect any advantage because by their silence they give their consent. Mr. Bicek then announced that he would be willing to take the case with the understanding that if he secured a reduction of nine dollars he would be paid three dollars; a reduction of six dollars he would be paid one dollar, from each taxpayer. Should the reduction be less than three dollars he would make no charge for his services.....</p>
   <p>The offer of Mr. Bicek was accepted and now everyone who wishes to protest should give Mr. Bicek a full description of their property; the best way to do this is to give him the deed or tax receipts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
