<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-23">Apr. 23, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol V Chicagu</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-23">Apr. 23, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE SDRUZENI CESKYCH SVOBODOMYSLNYCH SKOL V CHICAGU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following are the minutes of the regular meeting of the Sdruzeni Svobodomyslnych Skol v Chicagu (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools of Chicago), held April 16, 1921:</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by Mr. Joseph Tichava, chairman, in the presence of all the officers and only about forty-five delegates. After the delegates were greeted by the chairman, the minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read. The minutes of the last meeting of the executive committee, as read by Mrs. Radesinsky, were also approved. The reading of communications followed.</p>
   <p>The Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova (Bohemian National Cemetery Association), in its communication, informs the Federation that the Sbor appropriated the sum of five hundred dollars for the benefit of the Bohemian Free Thought schools of <pb facs="5418478_1_0410.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago. The Sbor also asks that an appeal be made to the parents of the children who attend the Free Thought schools to pay a larger tuition fee because everything is more costly nowadays, a fact acknowledged by everybody. The contents of the communication were taken into consideration and the secretary was instructed to send a letter of thanks to the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova and, at the same time, inform the Sbor that the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol does not receive one penny from tuition fees because the boards of trustees of individual schools keep the collected amounts for rental and cleaning expenses.</p>
   <p>The reading of a letter sent by the school children who attend the Vojta Naprstek School followed. These children sent the sum of $3.12 for the benefit of the Bohemian Free Thought schools. The children of the said school undertook a collection for the purpose of buying a floral piece for their deceased comrade, Edward Hess, and they are sending the remaining sum for the benefit of Bohemian schools. It is surely a beautiful example. We doubly appreciate the <pb facs="5418478_1_0411.jpg" n="3"/>gift because it came from our school children of whom we may be proud. The secretary was instructed to send a letter of thanks to the teacher of the Vojta Naprstek School, Mrs. Hulka, and her pupils.</p>
   <p>The Patronat Ceske Svobodomyslne Skoly v Morton Park (board of trustees of the Bohemian Free Thought School of Morton Park, Cicero, Illinois), in its communication, announces the names of its new delegates, Mr. Fr. Gruener, 1537 South Fifty-seventh Avenue, Mr. Joseph Holy, 2241 South Fifty-eight Court, and Mrs. Barbora Laibl, all of Cicero, Illinois. The next secretary of the aforesaid board of trustees will be Mr. Stanislav Snaider, 5527 West 23rd Place, Cicero, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Further, it was resolved that those teachers who accompany the school children to a theatrical performance which will be given for the benefit of the Bohemian Free Thought schools, May 23, shall receive their regular salaries. The teachers, first of all, should ascertain how many of the children will attend <pb facs="5418478_1_0412.jpg" n="4"/>the performance. If the majority of them go, classes need not be held and the teachers will go with the children. But if only a small percentage of the children should attend the performance, the teachers will hold their classes as usual. The teachers are requested to speak to the school children and create an interest for this performance, and in that way help to make the success of the theatrical performance possible.</p>
   <p>The annual report of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol and a printed resolution will be sent to every society or organization either through their delegates or by mail.</p>
   <p>The chairman, Mr. Joseph Tichava, then reported that the committee for the Posvicenska Slavnost (Country-wake Festival) asked him for the addresses of all the secretaries of the boards of trustees of the Bohemian Free Thought schools. Inasmuch as we do not have all the addresses on hand, all the secretaries are requested to send their correct addresses to the secretary of the executive <pb facs="5418478_1_0413.jpg" n="5"/>committee, Mrs. Katerina Radesinsky, 3550 West 26th Street, Chicago, Illinois.....</p>
   <p>Lately, delegates of many societies and organizations do not attend the meetings regularly. Therefore, it was resolved that in every meeting the names of all the delegates will be read at roll call and should any delegate be absent twice in succession then the society or organization he represents will be notified. As there was no other business to be transacted, the reading of receipts and disbursements followed, and then the meeting was adjourned by the chairman, Mr. Joseph Tichava.</p>
   <p>Karel Soukup, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
