<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-05">May 5, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian Language in the High Schools Efforts of the Česko-Americká Národní Rada Crowned with Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0282</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0282.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-05">May 5, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN LANGUAGE IN THE HIGH SCHOOLS Efforts of the Česko-Americká Národní Rada Crowned with Success</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the annals of cultural attainments of Chicago Bohemians, there should be entered a new grand success of which we have every reason to be proud--and that is the introduction, at last, of the Bohemian language as an elective course of study in the local high schools.</p>
   <p>The movement, which was started by the Česko-Americká Národní Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) and which seemed to be almost hopeless in view of the many obstacles, at last has met with success. Today we have before us the actual fact that the Bohemian language, as the result of a resolution of the Board of Education adopted in a meeting held on May 1, 1912, will be taught in all high schools where a sufficiently large number of pupils apply (that is, at least thirty).</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0283.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today it depends only upon Bohemian parents to make use of this advantage in order that with a sufficiently large number of Bohemian students, the teaching of the Bohemian language may be given a permanent place in the educational system of our schools. The larger the number of students studying the Bohemian language the more convincing the proof that the demand of the Česko-Americká Národní Rada was a just and warranted demand and that this representative body of ours, in its endeavors to have the Bohemian language introduced into the Chicago school system, voiced the wishes of all our Bohemian people.</p>
   <p>The struggle for the introduction of the Bohemian language into the school system was not easy and required much work and effort on the part of enthusiastic workers united in the Česko-Americká Národní Rada. It was necessary to place before the Board of Education convincing reasons for the introduction of the Bohemian language. Pressure was exerted upon the members of the Board by various petitions and written requests. The situation was <pb facs="5418478_1_0284.jpg" n="3"/>complicated in no small measure by the fact that no sooner was the demand of the Česko-Americká Národní Rada known than the representatives of other nationalities began to send petitions of a similar nature to almost every meeting of the Board of Education. There were times when it seemed that all this effort would come to naught and that the requests for instruction in all foreign languages would be rejected; but thanks to the persistence of some of the more farsighted members of the Board of Education, first among whom was the Bohemian member, Mr. James B. Dibelka, and likewise the Superintendent of Schools, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, opposition faded day by day. Finally, in the meeting held on May 1, 1912, when the question of teaching foreign languages came to a vote, a motion in that sense was approved by a large majority.</p>
   <p>Aside from the success in having the Bohemian language introduced as a course of study, the Česko-Americká Národní Rada deserves credit for the fact that the Bohemians were first among the various foreign nationalities to bring <pb facs="5418478_1_0285.jpg" n="4"/>this important movement to life and to make possible its accomplishment. This success is just added proof of the satisfactory results which can be achieved by persistent effort, in the first place, and by a central organization which, as a representative of the whole, is able to compel respect and recognition and secure the approval of its requests which undoubtedly would be ignored under other circumstances. The successful fight to have the Bohemian language taught in the high schools and the alacrity with which the lectures arranged by the Česko-Americká Národní Rada are welcomed in our local public schools proves unmistakably that with proper representation, it is possible for us to accomplish results in non-Bohemian circles which seemed impossible a short time ago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
