<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1884-10-09">Oct. 9, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">Citizens Without Representation (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0950</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0950.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1884-10-09">Oct. 9, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">CITIZENS WITHOUT REPRESENTATION (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Catholic newspaper, the True Witness, edited in Chicago at 168 E. Randolph Street, gives an article in its last October copy about us Bohemians. This article was written by a certain W. Mungavin, and is worthy to be given notice, especially, as in contrast with the libelous article published not long ago in the Protestant missionary report of the local missionary society. We print a copy of this article below in full.</p>
   <p>Dear Editor, taking cognizance of your independence as regards political problems, with your permission, I intend to bring before the public the terrible injustice that is constantly being perpetrated over a highly honorable, law-abiding and industrious race. The Bohemian-Americans are taking an important part among the numerous nationalities that compose the population of Chicago. The last published school census shows that the Bohemians hold fourth place in Chicago's population. Besides they are pronounced as the most temperate, frugal and diligent citizens among all foreign nationalities. Consequently their number and respectability <pb facs="5418478_1_0951.jpg" n="2"/>entitles them to be accordingly represented, not only in state and county offices, but in national offices as well. They pay us political attention to corrupt professional politicians, and every impartial citizen should consider that because of their honorable behavior they should be represented in local and national governmental offices. The injustices practiced against the Bohemian-Americans in our city is purely aggression. This evil is worse in some specific wards and districts. Ward sixth is an example of what I mean. In this ward the Bohemian element surpasses every other nationality in the proportion of four to one. Notwithstanding their numerical and material majority they have not even a district senator, alderman or representative. There is no other nationality which would submit so long to such a situation. The author of this article is convinced that there was another cause for this prolonged injustice and not only the restrictive activity of the politicians. After many inquiries I have found that jealousy among the societies helped very much to create the <pb facs="5418478_1_0952.jpg" n="3"/>differences which were exploited very successfully by the politicians.</p>
   <p>Now an entirely new spirit reigna over the Bohemians, they are uniting with the purpose of self-preservation and of representation.</p>
   <p>The last Sokol convention held here in Chicago had very beneficial consequences. All existing disagreements, which were in the way of the development of different societies, now are resolved fortunately, and the Bohemian-Americans will work hand in hand for a prosperous future. They soon will make good and turn aside the scorn, sticking to the nation without the representation. I hope their efforts will be crowned with a complete victory. I remain,</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>(Signed) Wm. Mungavin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
