<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">'Raus Mit Kaiser! Some Defenders of the Bloodthirsty Hohenzollerns in the Chicago School Board</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0778</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0778.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">'RAUS MIT KAISER! Some Defenders of the Bloodthirsty Hohenzollerns in the Chicago School Board</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"President Wilson's recent message to Congress is a document of high historic importance, and one to which every sound-thinking man will revert with a burning interest, even after decades, when the present bloody struggle with all its sufferings and terrors will be an event of the past. In the message the President sets forth the ideas of a great statesman, great philosopher, and above all, of a great human being. He was facing the gravest problems met by any President since Lincoln's time. He was forced, true enough, by circumstances to allow the United States to be dragged into the war, but he justified his actions in an emphatic manner which was acclaimed on all sides: The United States is not entering a war of aggression; neither is it interfering with the German people. As a free and purely democratic country, it <pb facs="5418478_1_0779.jpg" n="2"/>aims at the destruction of frenzied kaiserism which is the main exponent of autocracy, oligarchy, and of that militarism which saps the strength of all nations.</p>
   <p>Like other diplomats, President Wilson, with an acute mind, perceived that there can be no thought of anything like a permanent peace as long as the German throne is occupied by a beast in the shape of man whose might and sickly greatness are supported by pyramids of guns and bayonets, and who, by a single stroke of his pen, has reduced civilization to a primitive stage."</p>
   <p>A story, "The Making of the Kaiser", containing purely sentimental much, has been fouling the textbooks used in the grades from fourth to eighth of the Chicago schools for the last years. It is an insult to the intelligence of every American citizen, and of all the parents who are sending their children to Chicago schools, excepting Germans.</p>
   <p>William II, that despot, whose unsound propensity for shedding blood has sent <pb facs="5418478_1_0780.jpg" n="3"/>millions of young men to a premature death, that megalomaniac, who has dragged the whole civilized world into the most terrible war in the history of mankind, that degenerate, whom no humane feeling can permeate, that same one is being represented as a shining example for our school children.</p>
   <p>The responsibility for the removal of the story from the books as yet is to be unquestionably placed upon the shoulders of Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, former superintendent of schools. With all her pedagogic ability and talents, she has exposed herself as possessing a narrow horizon by not insisting upon the removal of the story from the sight of the susceptible pupils. There had arisen a strong movement for the extirpation of the story. German influence in the Board, still strong, always brought the exertions to naught.</p>
   <p>A new opportunity offered itself by the proclamation of war, and another attempt was made to purge the books of the story about the kaiser. A strong deputation of our Czech fellow-countrymen appeared in the offices of the School Board in <pb facs="5418478_1_0781.jpg" n="4"/>the Tribune Building yesterday. Other nationalities, represented by leaders, also took part. Besides newspapermen, there were in the group, Doctor J. Rudis-Jicinsky for the Sokols [gymnastic societies], Doctor J. B. Bitek, and Doctor J. F. Smetanka for the Czech National Alliance. There was the Polish National Alliance and others. A forceful protest by the Slavonic nationalities was to be made. It can be said that the opinions of all unbiased Americans were voiced. A joint resolution worked out by Doctor Smetanka was to be presented.</p>
   <p>After the School Board had finished its routine business, the speaker [name not given], representing the Czech National alliance, stepped forth, and supporting his explanations by weighty reasons, declared the story about the kaiser to be a pretense, and a make-up, utterly intolerable in the books, aside from the fact that America and Germany are inimical toward one another. The speaker, in proclaiming that the story should have been expunged long ago, gave a drastic demonstration of what should be done with similar trash, with a dramatic gesture, he tore the page with the obnoxious story from the <pb facs="5418478_1_0782.jpg" n="5"/>book and crumbling it up in his fist, tossed it on the table. It was a moment of great tension and was followed by spontaneous applause from the delegation.</p>
   <p>The passionate words of the speaker invoked a reaction on the members of the board which could be seen already in the beginning of the protest. One of the Board members, Mrs. Sethness, attempted to interrupt after the speaker's first words. Another member, Mr. Piggott, however declared it a necessity that the delegation be given a hearing, as they were entitled to it. Mrs. Sethness is not one of the little girls who allows herself to be discouraged by momentary obstacles, She raised objection after almost every word of the protest, and was efficiently supported by the chairman of the Board, Mrs. Vosbrink. Mr. Shoop, the superintendent of the Chicago schools, was present, but took no part in the controversy. All other male members of the Board, excepting Mr. Eckhardt, also declined to participate. Eckhardt limited himself to the statement that a new book is being prepared without giving any assurance that the kaiser story would be omitted in it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0783.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The speaker of the delegation remarked that promises have been held out for two years, but that no one has moved a hand toward their fulfillment as yet. The story, the speaker said, treats about the life of him who coined the brazen phrase "Deutschland Uber Alles," and it is poison for the mind of our children. "By permitting this with a quiet conscience, you are committing downright treason" the speaker thundered into the faces of the astonished Board members. "Just read what President Wilson says of that kaiser---"</p>
   <p>Here the speaker prepared to read the salient passages from the President's message, but he did not get that far. His fascinating words created a commotion among the members of the Board which resembled chaos. Mrs. Vosbrink, chairman, wielded the gavel most vehemently, coming dangerously near smashing it, and Eckhardt, who had, at least apparently, kept his composure, suddenly revealed now his true descent. With a face which had taken on the hue of ashes, he objected to the expressions just used by the speaker. "We want to point out to the speaker that we are precisely as loyal citizens as the <pb facs="5418478_1_0784.jpg" n="7"/>members of his delegation, and that we shall not suffer to be called traitors to our country! I request the chairman to withdraw the privilege of the floor from the speaker until he has duly retracted his last statement. I am requesting the chairman most emphatically."</p>
   <p>The speaker of the delegation there upon turned toward the recorder asking to be shown the passages with which he was said to have insulted the Board. Meantime, however, an uproar, hard to depict, arose in the hall. No one, ever so well acquainted with the influence wielded by the Germans, would have expected encounters of like impact. The ensuing turmoil was brought to an end by a motion made by Mrs. Sethness to leave the final decision to Superintendent John D. Shoop, himself. The lady evidently intended to spare the Board any responsibility in this burning question. The motion, seconded by Mr. Peterson, member of the Board, carried unanimously, and the session was declared closed by Mrs. Sethness. Superintendent Shoop will now have to decide whether the story is to remain or whether the despotic kaiser will receive the well deserved kick.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0785.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The resolution of Czech National Alliance has thus failed to be formally presented, which fact, however, will not count too much in this affair. The Slavonic population of this city refuses to have its children taught eulogies about the kaiser, and its wishes must be respected, notwithstanding any opposition of Teutonic members of the School Board and their followers. It might not be amiss to sent the textbook with the trumped up kaiser story to President Wilson, so that he will take official action against this, and similar material used for the education of our children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
