<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-16">Dec. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Affair Dibelka</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-16">Dec. 16, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">AFFAIR DIBELKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. J. B. Dibelka, the Bohemian member of the Chicago Board of Education and one of the five members of the Board whose ouster was effected by Mayor Harrison after the election of the new chairman of the Board, sent a letter to Mayor Harrison Yesterday. In it he said that he (Mr. Dibelka) would consider himself a member of the Board until his case was submitted to the judgment of impartial persons, Mr. Dibelka was in Peoria Saturday and Sunday on business, and therefore could not join the other ousted members in their reply to the Mayor. For that reason, he made an individual reply yesterday. Mr. Dibelka, whom the Mayor calls his political and personal friend, kids the Mayor ironically in his letter, and says that the expressions used in the Mayor's letter can be explained only by the fact that the new germs of the "petticoat craze" have already found their victims in the City Council [an allusion to the ex-superintendent of public schools in Chicago, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, who was defeated in the elections].</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0156.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Dibelka writes in his letter to the Mayor: "I have known you as a calm individual, and I cannot understand your thoughtless action. Even a Southern Negro gets a chance to confess his built before he is lynched. But in this enlightened, effeminate, and sissified city, a man's good name can be destroyed in a way that would make the Mexican guerrilla warfare appear to be like a Sunday school picnic."</p>
   <p>Mr. Dibelka states that he is ready to resign from the Board if an unprejudiced jury finds that his accusations against Mrs. Young are unfounded….."This jury is to be composed of nine members, three to be nominated by me, three by Mrs. Young, and three to be agreed upon by the first six. If Mrs. Young succeeds in refuting my accusations, i shall be ready to resign my membership on the Board in shame and humiliation," he says in his letter.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dibelka's accusation revolve around the following points: Our grammar schools are not what they should be. MRS. Young's administration is reactionary; it demoralizes our teachers, and costs too much money. Our high schools <pb facs="5418478_1_0157.jpg" n="3"/>are the most expensive delusions our taxpayers have had to face. Mrs. Young has been guilty of political intrigue, conducted for the purpose of tying the City Council's hands. She lacks the qualifications of an executive officer.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dibelka is ready to prove these accusations and to make them specific. He states that he is not trying to make his fight personal, but that he is fighting the reactionary system maintained by Mrs. Young.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
