<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-02-22">February 22, 1892</date><title level="a">Bohemians of the Eighth Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-02-22">February 22, 1892</date><title level="a">BOHEMIANS OF THE EIGHTH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bohemian Democrats of the Eighth Ward held a meeting yesterday afternoon in the hall of the Bohemian-English Liberal School. Alderman Dvorak announced that for the purpose of instructing Bohemian voters that there will be printed in Bohemian 20,000 circulars containing instructions and explanations of the Australian Ballot.</p>
   <p>Chairman "Kriz" announced that in accordance with the decision of the previous meeting, the former chairman of the club, Mr. Macal had prepared a communication on the recommendation by the club of Mr. J. Sindelar, as candidate for the office of alderman. Mr. Macal delivered the communication in person to the chairman of the ward committee, Mr. Morgan Murphy. It was expected that Mr. Murphy would announce the contents of the communication at Friday's meeting of the precinct committees, but to the great surprise of the Bohemian-Democratic club members, he failed to do so and in fact denied having received any such communication. Citizens Kriz and Sindelar pointed out the incident <pb facs="5418478_1_1462.jpg" n="2"/>as the beginning of political intrigues, whereas citizen Panoch excused Mr. Murphy's action on the grounds that he did not consider the communication as proper for Friday's meeting, but that he will read it at the next meeting of the ward committee.</p>
   <p>It was decided that the committee, appointed at the last meeting of the club take the necessary steps to find out whether the Democrats of the Eighth Ward cannot agree upon one candidate. As has been publicly asserted, Mr. Sindelar, despite the fact that he had been recommended by the Bohemian Club, has met an unexpected rival in the person of citizen Loefler, who announced himself as a candidate for the same office. Discussions were then turned to the affairs of West Town. Citizen Panoch stated that at the last meeting Alderman Dvorak and former County Commissioner Stainer both announced themselves as candidates for the office of Town Collector. He added that it would be proper if the committee called upon each candidate in an attempt to convince one of them to withdraw. If they both insist on remaining on the ballot, it is almost certain that a Bohemian will not be elected and that the office will fall to some Pole. Alderman Dvorak promised to withdraw if the club <pb facs="5418478_1_1463.jpg" n="3"/>will recommend Stainer for the office.</p>
   <p>Before the meeting adjourned, a committee was appointed for the purpose of selecting seven capable citizens as delegates to the County Convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
