<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-01">June 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Judge Joseph Sabath Is the Only Bohemian Candidate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1311</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1311.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-01">June 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE JOSEPH SABATH IS THE ONLY BOHEMIAN CANDIDATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The average citizen does not pay much attention to judicial elections although he should regard these as important as all others. Especially at the present time, when crime activity in Chicago has reached a new high making it necessary to add one thousand new men to the police force, every voter should realize that it is also necessary to secure good and honest judges who would be tireless in their efforts to suppress crime....Our country needs firm and conscientious judges who, at the same time would be humane, and who would be able to understand the life which the poorer classes of our population lead; who could sympathize with the poor, and who, besides being judges, could also be the counsellors of the people.</p>
   <p>Such a judge is Joseph Sabath, who has been an active member of the Superior Court for several years. During this time he has gained the reputation of <pb facs="5418478_1_1312.jpg" n="2"/>being one of the best and most humane judges. He has been a judge for twelve years, having been elected to the Municipal Court bench in 1910. He proved himself to be such an excellent judge that before the expiration of his term, the former governor, Dunne, appointed him to the Superior Court. In 1916 he was elected to the same office by an overwhelming majority, and by his activity he has gained such a popularity that the election returns next Monday should bring him a still greater majority of votes.</p>
   <p>All Bohemian voters should especially regard it their duty to go to the polls on Monday and give him their votes. He is the only countryman of ours who has gained such a high office, and the Czechoslovak voters should see to it that he retains that office. He has the confidence of the entire country. Every Czechoslovak voter in Cook County should vote for Joseph Sabath. All the voters should remember that it will be for the good of the whole community to go to the polls and place a cross in front of the name <pb facs="5418478_1_1313.jpg" n="3"/>of Judge Joseph Sabath besides voting for five other judges.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
