<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-31">Jan. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Most Urgent National Duty Lack of Appreciation of the Introduction of the Bohemian Language in Schools Would Prove This Privilege Undeserved</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-31">Jan. 31, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">MOST URGENT NATIONAL DUTY Lack of Appreciation of the Introduction of the Bohemian Language in Schools Would Prove This Privilege Undeserved</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A good old Bohemian proverb says that one who is ashamed of his native language should be generally despised. For our American conditions this can be amplified by saying that one who does not give his children a Bohemian education is not a Bohemian.</p>
   <p>It would be impossible to imagine that a descendant of one of the most highly educated people of Europe, a people whose history teems with gallant deeds and self-sacrificing efforts toward human progress; a son of a country abounding in rare beauties; a scion of a nation which has a great past and is awakening to face a great future, could be ashamed before his children of his mother tongue.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0279.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Is it possible that Bohemian parents would not gladly and enthusiastically welcome an opportunity to give their children a knowledge of the Bohemian language; to make them aware of its beauty, its rich literature; and to be happy in the thought that they will be able to talk with their children--even when the children grow up--in the beloved, pleasing, and harmonious language which is their native tongue?</p>
   <p>A Bohemian language class will open at Farragut High School (Carter Harrison High School) on Monday, February 3. If all parents who were interested in the introduction of the Bohemian language in our high schools at the time when the Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) was fighting for its acceptance as one of the subjects of instruction, and who gave a written approval to that organization's efforts, will also now, when the desired end has been achieved, do their sacred duty, the class will be overcrowded with Bohemian pupils.</p>
   <p>We all know that it was somewhat difficult to arrange the schedule so that <pb facs="5418478_1_0280.jpg" n="3"/>it would be convenient for all students. But this matter is too important to permit neglect because of any slight inconvenience. Should this great gain become lost through indifference? Would not our nationality become ridiculous in the eyes of the American public?</p>
   <p>The significance of a discontinuation by the high schools of the teaching of the Bohemian language would be easy to imagine. It would indicate our indifference toward the way we are being treated. It would prove that for us our nationality is meaningless, that we do not care. It would be a blemish which no amount of washing could remove from our record.</p>
   <p>Besides, it should be taken into consideration that the Bohemian language is both of cultural and practical value even here in America. There are well-known Bohemian-American scientists whose success is due to their thorough knowledge of the Bohemian language. There are many who profit by it in their daily life, in business, in their contacts with people, in politics, and in countless other ways. The fact that the Bohemian language <pb facs="5418478_1_0281.jpg" n="4"/>can be used as a key in the study of other Slavonic languages--languages in which great literary and scientific works are written--is also important.</p>
   <p>Hence, the Bohemian language is of considerable cultural value, and the knowledge of it is just as much an evidence of higher education as the knowledge of any other modern language.</p>
   <p>Parents of children of school age, let us not deprive our children of this rare opportunity! Let us fulfill our duty toward them, toward ourselves, and toward our nation!</p>
   <p>Let us enroll our children in the Bohemian class today!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
