<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-11-28">Nov. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Taxpayers Vs Corporation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1013</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1013.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-11-28">Nov. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH TAXPAYERS VS CORPORATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2 -- The long drawn fight of the taxpayers of Volesna against the Barrett Company ended in Judge Chettlain's court last night with a victory for the taxpayers. Volesna is the name of a Bohemian district between Sacramento avenue and Troy street, from Twenty-Eighth street to the Canal. As is known to our readers from former reports, the Barrett Company, a concern manufacturing tar paper, bought lots on Sacramento avenue, and immediately began to fence in the property, thereby closing the traffic on several streets. The taxpayers rose in protest not only against the clogging of the streets, but against the erection of a tar factory in their neighborhood as well. At a few meetings, held in Mrazek's hall, the ways and means to oppose the rich corporation were discussed, Anton Cermak, alderman of the Twelfth ward, and Michael Zimmer, sheriff of Cook county, attending. It was decided to place the case in the care of attorney Joseph Sabath, and to continue the uneven struggle in the courts. Mr. Sabath instantly established contact with the city attorney, who proceeded by filing suit to keep the Barrett Company from obstructing traffic, and to prevent the use of the property acquired for the manufacture of tar. At the first hearing the court, overruling the <pb facs="5418478_1_1014.jpg" n="2"/>objections of the defendants, granted permission to attorney Sabath to function as special city attorney in this case.</p>
   <p>In its findings the court acknowledged the right of the city to the property prior to the purchase, thereby annulling the sale of the lots, and restoring them to public ownership. The Barrett Company was instructed to clear the streets for traffic. Attorney Sabath requested that a lot, which had been selected for a small park prior to the purchase, be relinquished by the Barrett Company. The attorney for the latter, however, refused on the grounds that no definite agreement has been reached as yet between his client and certain property owners as to the space necessary for the monument of a man who lays claim to popularity and leadership in the neighborhood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
