<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-03-29">Mar. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Political [Meeting]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-03-29">Mar. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL [MEETING]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Slovanska Americka Sin (Bohemian-Slavonic American Hall) hasn't had as large a crowd as it had yesterday for many years. It was the site of the meeting of the Democrats of the Tenth Ward, called to give Mr. Robert M. Sweitzer an opportunity to address the voters of the Ward before the election in which he is a candidate for the office of mayor of the city of Chicago.....</p>
   <p>The program began with an introductory address by Mr. J. A. Menel, who presented the speakers of the evening. When Mr. Roger C. Sullivan was introduced, he received an ovation which seemed never to end. Mr. Sullivan stressed the importance of having an able man in such a high office as mayor of Chicago, and added that he could think of no one who would fill the office better than Mr. Sweitzer. He said that the Democratic candidate for mayor is a truly democratic man and a popular man, who has always lived in Chicago, and has preserved within himself the customs he inherited from his parents, the customs of all immigrants. Throughout his life he has been in contact with <pb facs="5418478_1_1568.jpg" n="2"/>naturalized citizens, and, therefore, knows how to appreciate what they love most in this country, liberty and freedom. He is a sincere supporter of personal liberty, and will remain loyal to his principles when he is mayor.....</p>
   <p>Among the other speakers there were also a number of candidates for minor offices. Mr. W. Dobias and several others spoke in Bohemian.</p>
   <p>Before the end of the meeting, information reached the chairman that Mr. Sweitzer would be unable to come because there were twelve other meetings that he had to attend that same night....but he would be sure to participate in tomorrow's meeting at the Thalia Theater, where a theatrical performance will be given exclusively for our ladies. The program will include a speech by Mr. Sweitzer and addresses by other candidates on the Democratic ticket.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
