<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-06">Nov. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. HoleČEk's Campaign Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-06">Nov. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MR. HOLEČEK'S CAMPAIGN SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Albert B. Holeček, the Republican candidate for state senator from the Nineteenth Senatorial District, can say that he has done all to acquaint the citizens of his district with his candidacy, and to convince them that it will be in their own interest if they vote for him tomorrow.</p>
   <p>Mr. Holeček has an excellent chance to win if the Czechs and Slovaks living in his district give him their votes irrespective of party affiliations. They must remember that they are Czechs and Slovaks first and that political partisanship is secondary; their chief concern should be to elect a candidate who is a whole man. The Czechs and Slovaks are the deciding element in the Nineteenth District. The District includes the entire old Thirty-fourth Ward, the northern part of the Twelfth Ward, Cicero, Berwyn, and Riverside, Illinois. Now then, all the Czechs and Slovaks, men and women, who are entitled to vote, should place a cross in front of Mr. Holecek's name tomorrow. This predominant Bohemian district should have at least one Bohemian <pb facs="5418478_1_1260.jpg" n="2"/>representative in Springfield, and this will be the case when Mr. Holeček is elected.</p>
   <p>The following organizations have promised their most active support to Mr. Holeček: The Československý Legionářský Svaz (Czechoslovak Federation of Legionnaires), České Hvezdy (Bohemian Stars), which is an organization of mothers, wives, and sisters of former soldiers and sailors, the Voters League for the State Legislature, the Chicago Retail Druggist Association, the Chicago Medical Society, the Lawndale Auto Club, the Dovre Club, and the Spolek Českých Právníku (Bohemian Bar Association). His candidacy was also endorsed by the Women's Roosevelt Republican Club and other women's organizations because Mr. Holecek is an advocate of an eight-hour working day for the working women of Illinois.</p>
   <p>That is sufficient proof that Mr. Holeček is a man of unblemished character; that he possesses the necessary education for a state senator; and that, he has all the experience necessary to fill that office. The Czechs and Slovaks <pb facs="5418478_1_1261.jpg" n="3"/>of his district who will help to elect him, may rest assured that they will always be able to point to him with pride as their countryman. It will be easy to find his name on the ballot; it is the tenth name counting from the top in the first column.</p>
   <p>Do your duty tomorrow, therefore, all of you, and make a cross in front of his name. By so doing you will not do any harm to any other Czech or Slovak candidate whose election concerns you, and it will result in our having a representative at Springfield, to which we are rightfully entitled.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
