<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-10">Feb. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Czechoslovak Taxpayers' Association of Cicero Merges with the Clyde Taxpayers' Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-10">Feb. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECHOSLOVAK TAXPAYERS' ASSOCIATION OF CICERO MERGES WITH THE CLYDE TAXPAYERS' ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular meeting of the Česko-Slovenský Poplatnický Spolek V Cicero (Czechoslovak Taxpayers' Association of Cicero) took place in the hall of the T. G. Masaryk school. The attendance at this meeting was tremendous. The number of members could easily have been estimated at 430, and all of them followed the proceedings of the meeting with great interest. One of the chief events of this meeting was the merging of the above-mentioned association with the Clyde Taxpayers' Association, and twenty-six new members joined the newly formed organization. In this way, the Česko-Slovenský Poplatnický Spolek becomes an important [civic] factor in the community of Cicero, where it will seriously concern itself with all problems relative to the community and its taxpayers.....The former members of the Clyde Taxpayers' Association were greeted with a thunderous "Na Zdar!" (Greetings!). The newly admitted members were advised by Citizen Krzek to become not only regular members, but also zealous workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1528.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Professor Skritecky, who teaches in the Harrison High School, was present at this meeting. His opinion in regard to the problem of building new schools was that at the present time, it is not necessary to build four high schools at once. He is of the opinion, however, that it would be desirable to build an annex to the J. Sterling Morton High School to relieve whatever pressure there may be due to an [increased] number of pupils; also he made no secret of the fact that Morton has too many offices, some of which could be converted into schoolrooms. Professor Stritecky also pointed out that the Harrison High School has 110 instructors and 3,000 pupils, while the J. Sterling Morton High School has 85 instructors for 1,300 pupils.....</p>
   <p>It was [also] decided that the taxpayers' association should request the community council, as well as the Cicero Medical Society, to co-operate in having a hospital built, because it is badly needed for the large number of people in Cicero.....[Specific] instances were cited which showed that such a hospital is necessary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1529.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this meeting, a protest was also voiced against the projected building of a dairy plant on 23rd Street and 58th Court, which is a residential zone. A complaint was lodged against a dance hall and a restaurant, both of which are connected with a hotel situated on 22nd Street and 48th Avenue. The council was informed about certain infractions of the building ordinance, as well as the disorderly conduct that exists in the dance hall.....Because of a recent crime wave, the Česko-Slovenský Poplatnický Spolek V Cicero will ask the police department to increase its vigilance.</p>
   <p>The meetings of the Spolek take place on the first Saturday of each month and are open to all citizens. All complaints should be presented two weeks before each meeting in order that the [members of the] executive committee may be able to investigate them and prepare their opinions and recommendations in the next regular meeting.</p>
   <p>Signed: Vàclav Rous, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
