<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-10">Apr. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-10">Apr. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The splendid campaign for Mr. Anton J. Cermak ends today. Yesterday the spacious hall of the Sokol Chicago witnessed a throng of Czechoslovaks who came from every part of Chicago to take part in this huge Democratic meeting. These men and women will do their utmost to help Mr. Cermak win the election. They will also vote for Mr. Josef Mendl and the rest of the candidates on the regular Democratic ticket. For the victory to be complete, Mr. Cermak's running mates must be elected too. Even the weather aided us in yesterday's efforts. The automobile parade which traversed the main streets of the Bohemian California district reminded all our voters that the moment had come for them to demonstrate their Democratic convictions and their Czechoslovak feelings, and to prove their decision to use every means of assuring victory for their candidates. After the parade was over the masses of our countrymen thronged the hall of the Sokol on Kedzie Avenue. Soon the hall was so filled that hundreds of late comers overflowed into the street. The course of the meeting <pb facs="5418478_1_1318.jpg" n="2"/>was enthusiastic and dignified. Choice speakers, among whom were our candidates, addressed the voters making clear to them the necessity of casting every single Czechoslovak Democratic ballot. the certainty of our victory must not lull any of our voters to sleep for the opposition is bending all efforts to prevent such a victory. The Irish and the Germans are, for the most part, unreliable people, and therefore the Czechoslovaks must turn out in their full number, and unanimously go to the polls to insure victory and to make that victory a decisive one. The reasons every Czech and Slovak Democrat should vote for Mr. Cermak and his colleagues were indicated times without number in our newspaper. The speakers who were present in our mass meeting yesterday mentioned these reasons again, and we need not, therefore, repeat them here. . . . . The same may be said of those men and women who, as Czechoslovaks, are of Republican persuasion. Those men and women will go to the polls tomorrow and cast their ballots for our highly qualified young countryman, Mr. Albert B. Holecek who is a candidate for the <pb facs="5418478_1_1319.jpg" n="3"/>office of state senator from the Nineteenth Senatorial District. .</p>
   <p>In yesterday's edition we mentioned all the candidates for whom our Czechoslovak men and women ought to vote for tomorrow. Everbody receives his or her sample ballot sent by this or that organization. Study these sample ballots accordingly. By doing so you will be sure to help those men whose election will insure the protection of your interests. Go, therefore, all of you to the polls tomorrow and perform your citizen's duties for your own gain and happiness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
