<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>.
<date when="1890-07-26">July 26, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">On a Slippery Road. Bohemians Oppose German Instruction in the Public Schools.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 b (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>.
<date when="1890-07-26">July 26, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">ON A SLIPPERY ROAD. BOHEMIANS OPPOSE GERMAN INSTRUCTION IN THE PUBLIC SCHOOLS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Amongst the Bohemian "Turnvereins" the question has been debated for some time as to what languages besides English, and what languages in particular, should be taught in the public schools. The three associations answered this question, in their last sessions, which were held yesterday and the day before. A request shall be made, so they declare, that the school board of Chicago give the same right to the Bohemians which the Germans now have: that the Bohemian language shall be taught in the Bohemian districts, and if this is not feasible that German instruction shall be eliminated. A long-winded resolution conforming with the above dictum found unanimous favor at the Thursday meeting of the North Side Turnverein, Cechie, in which the West Side Tumverein, Telocvicna Jedvota "Cesko American Sokol" concurred. Thelatter was present at the gathering of last Thursday, at the Turner Hall, comer Taylor and Canal streets.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0314.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Turners entered occupying the seats which were proffered to them. The chairman suggested that their delegates speak.</p>
   <p>Turner Jens Christensen made the opening address... "Mr. Chairman Gentlemen: It is not my purpose to make a long speech tonight... One fact I wish to call to your attention is one which, in my opinion, confronts every immigrant. I mean the fact, that regardless from which European country we came, we are all confronted by a common enemy. This adversary is "knownothingism," that aloof product of American patriotism, which considers all who are not born in this land as crooks or dullards. I have no adverse comments for true patriotism, but, that form of "patriotism" which intends to dictate to us where and when, or why, we may not drink beer; a "patriotism" screaming itself into hoarseness, in order to enforce the Sunday closing of the projected world exposition; which prescribes that nothing stronger than soda-water shall be consumed, such a pusillanimous "patriotism," which intends to subjugate us to the long forgotten ideas of past centuries and the present modern cranks; that kind of "patriotism" I abhor and despise.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0315.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"This 'knownothingism' does not ask whether we are Bohemians, Germans, or Scandinavians. It considers us only as G...d... foreigners, creatures of a lower order, who require consistent motherly guidance.</p>
   <p>"In retrospection of this attitude I say: 'We must not fight each other, we must show a united front against the mutual enemy!'</p>
   <p>"The German element of this city has fought for many years to obtain German instruction in our public schools. Finally we were successful. Our children are now enabled to learn English and also their mother tongue. It is not compulsory and we always have emphasized, that English, being the national language, is entitled to precedence. No one, I believe, can object to this principle.</p>
   <p>"I have been informed, that some of our Bohemian co-citizens are not satisfied with these arrangements; that they desire the discontinuance of German instruction in the public schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0316.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Their argument is on the following basis: 'We Bohemians must contribute to the school-fund from which the German teachers are paid.'</p>
   <p>"Why can we not also demand, that our children shall have an opportunity to learn their hereditary language? Are the Germans better than we are? Why should they be on the preferred list? No, gentlemen, the Germans are not better than you, and they should not be shown any form of preferment. In a republic, equality should prevail for all.</p>
   <p>"But, on the other hand, is this a reason why you should rob us of the liberty and victory we obtained after prolonged fighting?</p>
   <p>"Would it not be infinitely better, if you also would try to procure recognition for your language, in those districts where a large percentage of the school-children are of Bohemian parentage?</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0317.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"If that is your goal, then you can be assured of our most cordial co-operation. But, don't fight against us! Rather, fight with us for your rights, for our rights, against political corruption and stinting nativism. Our victory will then be assured!"</p>
   <p>After Mr. Christensen's speech, which was well applauded by the German Turners, Mr. Moehle addressed the audience: "A certain Anglo-American element considers everyone a criminal, who can speak any language besides English.</p>
   <p>"Will you, Bohemian Turners, identify yourself with that class? You are on that path if you adopt your resolutions in practice. You are on treacherous ground. If you continue in this manner, you will live to see the time, when Irish policemen will belabor you with clubs when you speak - Bohemian".......Turner Gloy said:" ...Why this attack, after twenty years of peaceful concordance?.....It is undoubtedly caused by gossip.....This German said this.....and....the school-board concurred.....These certain Germans are considered the "elite" by the Bohemians....It is a mistake.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0318.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"In truth these men are only 'servants who became prosperous.' The real representatives of genuine Germanism can be found amongst the Turners............." Editor Stulik of the Bohemian Daily Svornost demanded equal rights for all, in a passionate appeal....Editor Jicinsky, virtually the moving spirit of the resolution, commanded an ample supply of cynicism. He is a masterful actor and used his gifts to the detriment of the Germans......He showed that the Bohemian children are bamboozled into confusion by studying three languages, (German, Bohemian, English) simultaneously.</p>
   <p>He regards the efforts of the German press to help the Bohemians as "much ado about nothing."</p>
   <p>The original Bohemian resolution passed amidst an uproar of approval.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
