<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-03-25">Mar. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Proposed School Legislation (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-03-25">Mar. 25, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROPOSED SCHOOL LEGISLATION (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A number of legislative proposals have been submitted in Springfield, the purpose of which is the introduction of far-reaching reforms in the school system in our State. Some of these are of special importance only to parents of children of school age, but others are of interest to both such parents and all other citizens.</p>
   <p>One bill provides for a higher school-age limit, and two bills deal with the teaching of crafts in schools of Chicago and of other cities in our State in general.</p>
   <p>It is expected that all these bills will be strongly contested, particularly the latter ones, which have a large number of determined opponents who <pb facs="5418478_1_0140.jpg" n="2"/>maintain that the bill, if passed, will do more harm than good. Especially undesirable is the bill providing for the so-called double school system which is considered undemocratic, against all principles of American schools, and, in addition to all this, a very expensive innovation.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Federation of Labor has refused to support this bill because it considers that it is directed against workingmen, and would give the control of the schools into the hands of rich manufacturers. It would mean the creation of an entirely new school system, and lead to a class distinction between pupils of more wealthy parents who can send their children to college and university, and less privileged children who start working after having acquired the prescribed minimum of school education. One speaker in the meeting of the Chicago Federation of Labor in which these bills were discussed, declared that the children of poor parents would be made to work while yet in school, and that a sharp distinction would be made between them and the children of well-to-do parents.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0141.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>No doubt it is necessary to start trade education in our schools, but the way the legislature would do it, by adopting Cooley's proposal, is wrong and should be opposed by all citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
