<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-31">Dec. 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Isolationists</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-12-31">Dec. 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR ISOLATIONISTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The present European war may accomplish one thing: convince the Americans that our country, though rich, is not sufficient unto herself, and that she is dependent in many respects on foreign countries. The war has caused a crisis which America cannot overcome alone, no matter what may be done to that end. The cities are full of unemployed, and the "good times" of which millionaire Schwab has been talking these days may be expected only by those industrialists and workers who manufacture war materials for Europe.</p>
   <p>Many branches of industry have cut down their output simply because there is no export market to Europe, and no new markets have been found. This causes suffering not only for industrial workers, but also for our Southern planters who have no market for their cotton. Planters and farmers elsewhere may benefit somewhat by higher prices of grain and meat exported to Europe, but they will <pb facs="5418478_1_1203.jpg" n="2"/>lose this benefit through decreased sales in America where, because of unemployment, consumption is decreasing. The old economic rule finds here its verification, that need in one place generates need in other places, and that no one can profit by the misery of someone else. Prosperity spreads generally throughout the world, and in times of plenty there is comparative prosperity everywhere. To acquire the markets in South America and in China, now abandoned by Europe, which some economists claim will replace lost markets in Europe, will take too long a time to do us any good.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
