<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-16">Dec. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our Societies (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-16">Dec. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SOCIETIES (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The agitation of the enemies of our societies and clubs has begun again. Only this time it is assuming a more threatening form, for the foes of our social activities are now addressing themselves to the State Council for National Defense. This authority, as well as the chief of police and the aldermen, has been informed that soldiers attend entertainments, which in itself is neither a harmful nor unlawful act. The soldiers are said, however, to be drinking alcoholic beverages and are even said to have been seen intoxicated in many halls. This is a very serious matter, in view of the critical times, the reformers declare. The soldiers and sailors are forbidden by law to indulge in alcohol while in uniform. The vendor of the liquor is subject to severe punishment.</p>
   <p>The prohibitionists demand of the authorities that dance halls be closed. It would not surprise us if they succeeded in having them closed. Many rumors <pb facs="5418478_1_0576.jpg" n="2"/>about the soldiers are exaggerated. Such rumors tend only to incite the public and the city council against our social activities. We hope that these activities will remain undisturbed. The occasional outcries from the reformers against our entertainments should nevertheless have a salutory effect. They should warn owners to operate their places according to standards of decency. We are calling this to the attention of the Czech public because some of the halls on the black list are owned by Czechs, who will do well not to trifle with the authorities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
