<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-03-07">Mar. 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Teaching of the Bohemian Language Administrative Committee of the Board of Education Adopts a Resolution to Bring Our Mother Tongue into the Public Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-03-07">Mar. 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE TEACHING OF THE BOHEMIAN LANGUAGE Administrative Committee of the Board of Education Adopts a Resolution To Bring Our Mother Tongue into the Public Schools</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An important resolution which is the result of the energetic agitation of our Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council), the endeavors of the Bohemian member of the Board of Education, Mr. J. B. Dibelka, and a true understanding on the part of the Superintendent of Schools, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, was adopted by the Administrative Committee of the Board of Education and presented for approval at yesterday's meeting. It was decided that in the future, whenever at least thirty pupils apply for instruction in any modern language at any school, that language will be introduced as a subject of study. Mrs. Young was an ardent supporter of the plan which met with the agreement of the majority of members of the Board of Education.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0291.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is no doubt that Bohemian parents will see to it that Bohemian becomes one of the languages, since the demands for its instruction have been most numerous. We have an advantage in that our children are concentrated in a small number of schools, and we hope that not only thirty but more than one hundred pupils will apply at each of these schools for instruction in the Bohemian language.</p>
   <p>To be sure, there was strong opposition to this proposal.... On the basis of this opposition the recommendation of the Administrative Committee was returned for further consideration.</p>
   <p>It will be necessary for Bohemian parents to exert great pressure upon the members of the Board of Education in this matter. The recommendation of the Administrative Committee concerns only the high schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
