<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-04">Sept. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Taking on Reason</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Anti-Tobacco Movement Afoot] (Editorial--Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-04">Sept. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TAKING ON REASON</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Anti-Tobacco Movement Afoot] (Editorial--Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Many indications tend to show that the fanaticism of the prohibitionists has reached a climax, and that a gradual decrease in that sentiment is on its way. The trend is now turning back toward personal liberty. Those drastic laws which destroyed decent and legitimate business and replaced it with shady and illegal transactions have created a reaction by which the people can justly profit…..</p>
   <p>There is, however, a new movement afoot to prohibit the use of tobacco in any form. Again those freakish pastors are at work. Just as they are in the foreground acclaiming prohibition, they are decrying any enterprise which identifies itself with progress. Those good men do not stand up for peace and well-being of the people; they are only 'good to themselves'.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0580.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They are trying to gain control over the people and use prohibition as a means to that end.</p>
   <p>The head of the Non-Smokers' Protective League of America submitted to President Wilson a proposal against the distribution of tobacco in any form among soldiers and asked for the diversion of tobacco fields to the cultivation of grain and other victuals. This document declares that the distribution of tobacco among army men is a crime and accuses the American Red Cross of being an accessory to it…. Pastor Cannon, chairman of the national legislative committee of the Anti-Saloon League, is one of the chief agitators of the lobby which has been making life miserable for many of our congressmen….Many influential American newspapers now openly criticise the activities of the 'drys'. This is highly gratifying to us, indeed. Sound reasoning is slowly coming into its own….."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
