<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-14">May 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Defeated Hypocrites</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-14">May 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">DEFEATED HYPOCRITES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The prohibitionists pussyfooters, whose principal speaker in the City Council is Alderman Charles E. Merriam, and whose main trouble shooter is the notorious, sly Arthur Burrage Farwell, of the Law and Order League, have received at the hands of Municipal Bailiff Anton J. Cermak a thorough lesson and a moral humiliation that they will not soon forget. It happened yesterday in the City Hall during the session of the licencing committee which was to decide on Merriam's amendment to the ordinance regulating the issuing of licenses for dance entertainments. Because this was quite an important question, the session was attended not only by many protagonists of personal liberty, but also by many old women, both in skirts and trousers, from the aristocratic wards, whose feelings when listening to Mr. Cermak's words would be very difficult to describe.</p>
   <p>The ordinance covering the issuing of the so-called "special bar permits" was <pb facs="5418478_1_0665.jpg" n="2"/>to become effective yesterday. This ordinance is identical with the old one providing for the issuance of licenses for dances, except that it requires that the request for the license be filed fifteen days before the date of the dance, thus giving the police sufficient time to investigate the kind of entertainment planned and determine its actual sponsors. If this ordinance were to be enforced as strictly as the United Civic Societies of Chicago propose that every ordinance should be enforced, it would mean the end of all entertainments of a dubious character, because all such entertainments would have strict police supervision. The drastic provisions of the ordinance, however, do not seem to satisfy our rabid "Aquarians," because Alderman Merriam offered an amendment prohibiting the sale of any alcoholic beverages at such entertainments. What would be the results of such an ordinance anybody with a bit of sense can easily imagine. It would bring to ruin all social and civic centers which derive the greatest part of their income from renting their halls to various societies, clubs, and lodges that give dances for their members and friends. The discussion of this amendment was on the agenda of yesterday's <pb facs="5418478_1_0666.jpg" n="3"/>meeting of the licencing committee whose chairman is Alderman John Toman, and which has in its membership a number of inveterate "water lappers".</p>
   <p>The speakers of the prohibitionist reactionaries were Aldermen Merriam and A. A. McCormick who were valiantly seconded by Farwell and a large female audience. Merriam explained that he was prompted to introduce this amendment by a report of the commission investigating the vice conditions of the city, and by a report of the League for the Protection of Minors, both of which go to prove that many young girls have lost their virtue as a result of drinking at dances. The speakers of the more liberal element, particularly Mr. Cermak, endeavored to prove the fallacy of making no distinction between various kinds of dances. If there are any halls where youths are being spoiled, it is up to the police to close them up. In this activity the police will nowhere find more ardent supporters than among the friends of personal liberty. But there are many decent halls, halls in buildings where members of national groups assemble for their entertainment <pb facs="5418478_1_0667.jpg" n="4"/>and social life, where the people also dance and drink, but where the most clever prohibitionist spy would not find one single reason for complaint throughout an entire year.</p>
   <p>The whole affair is not an effort for improvement, but a clear prohibition propaganda conducted by people who are not even in a position to explain satisfactorily where the city would get money with which to pay its current expenses if it should come to the closing of cafes, a step they most ardently desire. It is an attempt to vote in prohibition by men who believe they have been put into this world to reform any and everybody, but who should first look around and see what is going on under their own noses. For instance, there is local prohibition in Hyde Park, but in that section of the city even a little child can buy liquor in any drugstore, and it has happened many times that young boys have come home totally drunk on whiskey they had bought in drugstores.</p>
   <p>These conditions have come to Mr. Cermak's attention by a letter from a young <pb facs="5418478_1_0668.jpg" n="5"/>girl whose brother had come home intoxicated several times. Hence Mr. Cermak decided to make a thorough investigation. He took an automobile ride through the aristocratic, prohibitionist Hyde Park with Alderman Bowler last Wednesday afternoon. They took along a young girl who succeeded in buying liquor in any drugstore she entered. But in order to secure still stronger proof, they sent to a drugstore a young boy who was playing in the street with Alderman Merriam's little son. The boy, hardly ten years of age, returned in a short while with a quart bottle of whiskey for which he paid $1.25. Eight drugstores were visited in this way, and in each of them either the boy or the girl could purchase as much liquor as they would ask for. The whiskey is being sold in the immediate vicinity of schools and churches, right next to the Merriam and Farwell homes, and in no case did the druggist inquire whether the liquor was needed for medicinal purposes. It may be well to mention that, according to city ordinances, a druggist is not supposed to sell more than six ounces of whiskey at any one time, and each sale is to be reported to the police. But ordinances do not mean a thing to the elite in Hyde Park. Anybody can get <pb facs="5418478_1_0669.jpg" n="6"/>as much whiskey as he cares to buy in that section, and it is being sold freely even to minors. Little wonder that drunkenness among the youth is growing to such large proportions in that district. Mr. Cermak presented several bottles of whiskey to the licencing committee yesterday; all of them had been purchased in Hyde Park by minors on the day before, and each of them carried the name and address of the druggist from whom it was bought and the time of the purchase, so his evidence is staggering.</p>
   <p>What effect this episode had upon those assembled is easy to imagine. The puritanic temperance hypocrites looked like wet hens after this moral spanking, but from the benches occupied by the liberal element there came frequents bursts of loud applause. As a result of Mr. Cermak's argumentation, the amendment was defeated by eleven votes to three. In an effort to wash this moral licking off a little bit, the honorable aldermen from the aristocratic wards, together with Mr. Arthur Burrage Farwell, made notes of the names of the druggists in whose stores the whiskey had been bought, and declared they would see to it that <pb facs="5418478_1_0670.jpg" n="7"/>anything like that would not happen again. They could not have suffered a greater shame than by having their attention called to such irregularities in their own neighborhoods by those whom they would like by all means to reform.</p>
   <p>It is certain the licencing committee, having such a resolute chairman as Alderman Toman, and a decided majority of members immune to infection by prohibitionist lunacy, will just as definitely and decidedly throw back any other attacks against personal liberty it may be called upon to deal with.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
