<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-07-13">July 13, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-07-13">July 13, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a meeting of the Bohemian-Democratic organization of the 10th ward, which was held on July 10th, in Cervenka's Hall, and to which the citizens of the 11th ward were invited, the following resolution was adopted.</p>
   <p>In as much as more than 75 per cent of Bohemian democracy of Chicago consists of enlightened and liberal minded citizens, whose sympathies are for the broadest school education and everything that favors it, who from conviction and from principle, not only take a general interest in the growth of our public schools, but also recognize their great value by sending their children exclusively to them; and in as much as this class of citizens have made known to Mayor Harrison, by countless resolutions, adopted by almost all societies, lodges, clubs, gymnastic and singing societies, labor organizations and various clubs (with the exception of religious societies) their agreement and their satisfaction with the good work of the former member of the school board, Mr. Walleck, and at the same time made known their wish, that Mr. Walleck be further retained in his office, which Mayor Harrison did not satisfy; and in as much as this class of Bohemian democrats, in other branches of the city's administration, not only does not receive the recognition due it, but as a <pb facs="5418478_1_1447.jpg" n="2"/>matter of fact is disregarded with impudence and ignored on every occasion, even though among Bohemian taxpayers they pay the most taxes; for these reasons, be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, that we, the members of the Democratic clubs of the 10th and 11th wards, gathered in public meeting, positively condemn and term as un-Democratic, undignified, and unjust, the action of Mayor Harrison and his prime minister, Bobby Burke, for in this manner is born and spread not only dissatisfaction, ill-feeling and conflict among our people, but also can cause, if it is continued, the thinning and weakening of the ranks of Bohemian democracy; further, be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, to request local papers to be so kind as to publish this resolution, and that a copy be sent to Mayor Harrison.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
