<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-07-24">July 24, 1890</date><title level="a">The Germans and Us</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0322</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0322.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 b (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1890-07-24">July 24, 1890</date><title level="a">THE GERMANS AND US</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the question of schools, the standpoint that we have taken is familiar to all our readers and it is unnecessary to further elucidate. We are not in the habit of sputtering words and phrases; we speak clearly, openly and above board, for we are convinced that we defend a just cause; we are convinced that we express the wishes of the large majority of our Bohemian people.</p>
   <p>For what reason have we come out against the German Language which has been introduced into the lowest primary grades of our Public Schools? For reasons, which must be acknowledged by every educated person, which must be acknowledged by every reasonable person.</p>
   <p>The children of Bohemian parents enter English schools, in order to learn the language which is used in this land, and is an unavoidable necessity for everyone who wishes to lay the foundation for his future here.</p>
   <p>The children of most Bohemian families attend only the primary grades, a few of them graduate from the grammar schools, and those few years of attendance are not enough for the thorough learning of the English language.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0323.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Isn't it a crime against these children then to force the study of German on them? They cannot learn it and it only makes the familiarization with the English language more difficult in so few years.</p>
   <p>Our Bohemian countrymen in the homeland have fought against the compulsory study of the German language, by children, for many years. Bohemians of America have been of great assistance to them in this fight; but even at that the German Language is much more useful in Austria than it is in the United States. Nevertheless, there have been found Bohemians here defending the use of the German language in our schools.</p>
   <p>We do not know what opinion is held by "Pilsen Sokol" on this subject today; but we know that a month ago they appointed a committee to work with committees from other Sokol units against the use of the German Language in the primary grades. They were in agreement with our viewpoint then and we think they still are, for among "Sokols" opinions are not changed daily, like coats.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
