<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-29">May 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Against Militarism (Editorial) (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0740</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0740.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-29">May 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AGAINST MILITARISM (Editorial) (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The War waged by the United States is directed not only against many evils, under which subjugated nations are groaning, but also against militarism. It is, in fact, militarism which is to be destroyed in the first place. The oppression of other nations, and autocracy with its exploitation of the working classes, are bound to fall with the destruction of militarism. In consideration of this, our radicals, pretending to be deeply concerned with the welfare of the laboring classes, ought to be in the first ranks of our warriors .....</p>
   <p>A Chicago German Socialist paper printed an article on militarism which we have translated for the benefit of our readers. What we are unable to comprehend <pb facs="5418478_1_0741.jpg" n="2"/>is the reluctance of the German Socialists and the American Socialist organizations controlled by them, to join in the fight to down militarism.</p>
   <p>"The last bulwark of capitalism is the army with its cannons and rifles and rigid discipline ..... Is this not a devilish institution? .... ," the article reads.</p>
   <p>Militarism is a sore which undermines the happiness of the nations .... it is a monster.</p>
   <p>Among all the monsters, the militarism of Germany and Austria is the ugliest. It is being obediently served by the Socialists of Germany, and also by those of the United States, who place every obstacle in the way of our Government in its combat against militarism. Why do not the Germans follow the example of Russia, whom they have dubbed "backward," <pb facs="5418478_1_0742.jpg" n="3"/>and why do not the Austrians do as the Czech and other Slavonic soldiers? They refused to obey their commanders when they were ordered to kill! Why do Austrian and Hungarian regiments fire at those objectors, when they themselves count many members of that party who condemn War?</p>
   <p>The present War could be quickly stopped if the German people only would emulate the Russian people who got rid of the Czar; they should depose the Kaiser, destroy militarism, and blast their pan-Germanistic dreams. All other nations are anxiously waiting for this to happen, so that they can extirpate militarism and everything with it which has made this horrible War possible ..... Until the Germans themselves decide to take steps such as these, the fight against them must be continued. The United States deserves the praise of the whole world for having taken part in the struggle, for it is rendering invaluable service to all the nations. He, who works against this War, prompted to do so under <pb facs="5418478_1_0743.jpg" n="4"/>whatever slogan, damages the cause not only of America, but of all the nations, especially of those enthralled under the yoke of Germanism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
