<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1879-05-05">May 5th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial) Foreign Language in Public Schools.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SVORNOST</title>,
<date when="1879-05-05">May 5th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial) Foreign Language in Public Schools.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The prevalent rule in Chicago is that the German language shall be taught in all our schools. In its district the parents of about 60 children requested it and the German citizenry has managed so well that their mother tongue will be taught in fifteen schools.</p>
   <p>In Chicago we number at least 25,000 Bohemians diving for the most part in one section of the city. According to our viewpoint we should be entitled to have our Bohemian language taught at public expense in at least five schools for we pay for the up keep of the school system the same as do the Germans. If we contribute less we would be expecting smaller advantages.</p>
   <p>Thus far we have maintained through our own finances and work our own schools for teaching the Bohemian language. The Germans are smarter than we, for they are much more able to maintain ten schools to our one, but why should they do so when they can have taxpayers of other nationalities maintain them with apparent pleasure? Germans are continually pushing into the foreground and with this activity of theirs, the <pb facs="5418478_1_0348.jpg" n="2"/>constant boring in they have gained a nice privilege. We Bohemians continually shrink into the background and whenever there are any proceedings going on where it would serve to our benefit if we were to speak up, we all have our mouths sewed up.</p>
   <p>Our well informed associates to whom the maintenance of the Bohemian nationalism should be of prime importance should take heed of our admonition on this matter and begin to work for the teaching of Bohemian, at least in the schools where most of the children are of Bohemian parentage.</p>
   <p>Will any one of our many Lodges and Societies take notice of our motion in this matter? Which one will be in the lead?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
