<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-05-13">May 13, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">[Bohemians Not in Need of Missions]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0930</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0930.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-05-13">May 13, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">[BOHEMIANS NOT IN NEED OF MISSIONS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We expressed our own judgement on the ways used, by some local, also Bohemian reverends who are humbuggers and quacks, to make the Bohemian better acquainted with the local Better English classes. The major purpose of their activity is only the filling of their own pockets. These people treated the Bohemians like ignoramuses, rebels, half cannibal, and tried to persuade them that they are in need of missions and some other means for their conversion.</p>
   <p>Last Saturday, there was an article in a local newspaper. The Inter-Ocean, stating that so long as the Rev. Adams edited the journal, Pravda, Chicago's Bohemians were controlled and held on the bridle, but now that the newspaper Pravda is discontinued the local Bohemians are subject to anarchistic propaganda and literature. The Inter-Ocean suggests there should be found somebody to pity the Rev. Adams, to subsidize him, that he would be able to save the Bohemians in Chicago. It seems that Adams has participated in this article himself, publishing this shameless lie, and should publish an immediate revocation of same. In case he will not do that he can be quite certain that we Bohemians in Chicago will look at this article as at a dirty business trick.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0931.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago Bohemians are not anarchists and ignoramuses and this can be proved by the fact that they refused to accept all the trash in this form of publications by Chicago's Bohemian reverends, and forced them, in this way, to disappear.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
