<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-02-21">Feb. 21, 1882</date><title level="a">Wanted: a Bohemian Alderman in the 6Th Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1483</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1483.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-02-21">Feb. 21, 1882</date><title level="a">WANTED: A BOHEMIAN ALDERMAN IN THE 6TH WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have heard this wish expressed for the past six or seven years or more, but so far there has been nothing much accomplished in this regard. On April 4th the citizens of Chicago will elect eighteen aldermen to the City Council, and here is added again, that the Bohemian Citizens of the 6th ward again are making it known that they want their ward, which is settled by Bohemians nostly, represented in the City Council by a Bohemian. This time it was our countrymen in the lime quarry section who took the initial steps toward the accomplishment of their desires.</p>
   <p>They held a public meeting on the premises of Mr. A. Skvora and resolved to support unanimously a Bohemian candidate and already they have picked a man whom they intend to carry through victoriously in the coming election. He is Mr. Josef Lalak, who has lived in America since he was nine years old and is well-known, not only among our own countrymen, but to the public of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>We take it for granted, that there will be meetings in other precincts of the 6th ward soon, in order to decide about the coming election, whether <pb facs="5418478_1_1484.jpg" n="2"/>a candidate should be set up in opposition to the renowned Ed. Cullerton, who, to secure his election again, is fighting tooth and nail. If a Bohemian candidate is to be offered it is desirable that all factions in the 6th ward come to some understanding soon. With that we add that a second independent political meeting will be held on Sunday, February 26, on the premises of Mr. Skvora.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
