<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-07">June 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Membership of the Czechoslovak Taxpayers' Association of Cicero Is Growing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-07">June 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MEMBERSHIP OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK TAXPAYERS' ASSOCIATION OF CICERO IS GROWING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Saturday, June 3, 1922, a meeting of the Ceskoslovensky Poplatnicky Spolek V Cicero (Czechoslovak Taxpayers Association of Cicero, Illinois) was held in the T. G. Masaryk School. The meeting was opened by Mr. Krcek, and the secretary V. Rous, read the minutes of the previous meeting.... Ten new members were accepted by the Association. A member of the executive committee moved that the payment of $50, the expenses connected with the suit against the tax collector, Mr. Buckley, be approved. The motion was carried....</p>
   <p>It was decided in this meeting that no public official may be elected to the office of president of the Association unless he was a member of it for at least one year, and further that no such official may become a member of the executive committee unless he was a member of the Association for at least six months. In this meeting the parliamentary procedure was also adopted.</p>
   <p>The picnic committee announced that an excursion will be made on Sunday, Aug. 20, 1922. The members will start from the T. G. Masaryk School, and upon arriving <pb facs="5418478_1_1516.jpg" n="2"/>at the picnic grounds [not specified], the committee will see to it that sufficient entertainment is provided. At this picnic a large number of new members will be inducted in an attempt to increase the membership to one thousand.....</p>
   <p>The school for citizenship will probably begin this week. The teachers will announce all particulars as to hours and places of instruction. The principal of the high school was requested to furnish teachers free of charge, and it is probable that this request will be granted.</p>
   <p>Urged by the president, the zoning laws were explained to the assembled members by Mr. Frank Matousek. According to the plan, as explained by the speaker, certain streets in Cicero will be reserved for factory uses, others will be residential. Complaints about the poor condition of 50th Avenue, north of 22nd Street, were given to the executive committee which will make efforts to have the street improved. Another complaint was made about school children who have to wait for the opening of the school building often until 8:45 A. M. and <pb facs="5418478_1_1517.jpg" n="3"/>in all kinds of weather. Mr. Solar, who is a member of the School Board, was present when this complaint was made, and, urged by the president, gave explanations of why the school building is locked until that time. He assured the members that this practice will be discontinued [so that the school children may enter the buildings in bad weather].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
