<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-10-28">Oct. 28, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Political Meeting of the Bohemian Citizens in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1882-10-28">Oct. 28, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN CITIZENS IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Three prominent Chicago citizens, Mr. V. Kaspar, Adolph Kraus, and August Geringer called a political meeting of the Chicago Bohemians last night.</p>
   <p>The meeting was held on their special invitation in the Houdkov Hall, corner Bunker and Desplaines Sts. and its purpose was to enlighten the Chicago Bohemians and induce them to promote political adherence and representation. The meeting was represented by the most prominent Bohemian citizens, without discrimination as to which party they belonged. There were Republicans, Democrats and workingmen and it is stated with pleasure that yesterday's meeting was marked with complete attention and patience, something that seldom happens in a Bohemian meeting in which two or three parties are represented.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by V. Kaspar who explained its purpose and expressed the hope that this meeting would be distinguished by the fullest attention to the speakers.</p>
   <p>The first speech was made by A. Kraus, who pointed out that we have two big <pb facs="5418478_1_1478.jpg" n="2"/>parties and while the Bohemians worked for both of them, what benefit have they had from it? None, as long as not a single Bohemian was placed on the district electoral ticket of one of the parties. Until now we have elected on other tickets, Mr. Kakuska, Constable on the Republican ticket: Mr. Chladek as Clerk on the Democratic ticket and Mr. Meilbek to the Legislature on the workingmen's ticket.</p>
   <p>We should expect and demand a representative.</p>
   <p>No one from the present audience is demanding employment for himself, although there are among the Bohemians many capable of filling some of the positions. - Should we act, as we did until now, we will arrive nowhere, we must show our power to the parties, we should not dare to be afraid of the party nor let our conscientiousness rule us. Every one's duty is to support the other party in case of necessity.</p>
   <p>It is easy to prove that we have the decisive power in our hands. After ripe deliberation we should elect, today, from both electoral tickets the best man and create in this way our own ticket. -</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1479.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is not reasonable, that in the pre-electoral conventions the people are paying much attention if the candidate is an Irishman, German or Scandinavian. We are Americans, and should equally take into consideration our nationality, as the others do.</p>
   <p>We must show to the parties, that they do not have us in their power; let us elect our candidates from both parties, and in case they should pass the election, we will gain their respect. Let us show the parties that we have teeth, that we know how to bite, and then they will fear us.</p>
   <p>Second speaker Frank Fucik: "With regard to politics, I have a bitter conviction and my experience is dreadful. It was stated correctly that we first should learn politics, and in case we should achieve something that we first must learn to regard ourselves with mutual reverence. As long as we insult each other we will not go far. The political conditions among the Bohemians were deplorable, the majority always oppressed the minority.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1480.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We were not able to lead politics in an honest way. The general opinion prevailed, that politics and thievery must go together. We should prove that it is not so. I, myself, was once accused of corruption, but I will not excuse myself because my conscience is clear. I have no idea, how we can select the candidates of both parties without dispersing the votes, but I think it is compulsory for us to take part in politics, decently, and honestly, and not to blame each other.</p>
   <p>Our work for any good cause must be harmonious and our first Bohemian ticket can not be instantly overturned and in consequence our work killed.</p>
   <p>Then K. Lusk, a Bohemian lawyer, declared himself as a one hundred percent Bohemian and that many knew him from his articles published in Svornost.</p>
   <p>The Bohemians have not shown, until now, any real political activity, although their desire always has been to have a leader in one of the parties.</p>
   <p>We control about 3,000 votes and we now have an opportunity to appear independently.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1481.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>He suggested, for our future benefit, to organize Bohemian political clubs, to open new clubs in all districts of the city, and to develop a wide propaganda for the Bohemians to take out their citizenship papers and to take a vital interest in political activities. The Bohemians should take an example from other nationalities.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hudek, candidate for Senator, states that the Bohemians have power and are receiving more and more recognition.</p>
   <p>His candidacy was proposed by the workingmen of other nationalities and approved by many Republican clubs. - Today's meeting made an "impression" on him as called by professional politicians. Mr. Kraus answered that this meeting was called by a Republican, Kaspar, a Democrat, Kraus, and an Independent, Geringer, and that he is very much surprised, that Mr. Hudek expressed his suspicion in this direction. The originators of today's meeting are not professional politicians at all. The position of District Commissioner was proposed to Mr. Kaspar, but he refused.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1482.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Personally I am not willing to accept even a big political position, because my business occupies all my time and everybody knows very well, that Mr. Geringer does not care for any position. Everybody knows us and our good intentions, that's why I cannot understand how Mr. Hudek can throw such calumnies."...</p>
   <p>After a few unimportant speeches the meeting was closed. The lawyer, Mr. Lusk, immediately requested the audience to wait a while and he read the following resolution, which was unanimously accepted:</p>
   <p>Whereas, a meeting of prominent Bohemian men was called with the purpose of mutual deliberation and the formation of political union, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, there existed some suspicions that this meeting was called to the advantage of individuals; be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, that said meeting was called for respectable, honest purposes and that between Bohemians there exists complete harmony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
