<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-10-11">Oct. 11, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation of the ČEsko-AmerickÁ TiskovÁ KancelÁŔ</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0866</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0866.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-10-11">Oct. 11, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION OF THE ČESKO-AMERICKÁ TISKOVÁ KANCELÁŔ</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář (Bohemian-American Press Bureau) requests us to publish the following proclamation:</p>
   <p>"The Spravedlnost of October 10 carries an article entitled 'Slováci A Češi' (Slovaks and Bohemians) which begins as follows:</p>
   <p>"'Our Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář protested last year against including Slovaks with the Bohemian-Slavonic people in the census report of the Immigration Bureau, giving as a reason the alleged fact that there are among them many illiterates. Thus, our Bohemian nationality was happily saved through the efforts of two of our prominent scientists, Mr. Ales Hrdlicka and Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan.'</p>
   <p>"The writer of this article is guilty of the worst kind of misstatement, and no doubt Spravedlnost has accepted this article as a part of its avowed policy <pb facs="5418478_1_0867.jpg" n="2"/>of fighting the Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář whenever and wherever there is an opportunity. In printing it, however, the Spravedlnost assumes all responsibility for the article. But the truth is altogether different.</p>
   <p>"The Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář published a news item in Bohemian newspapers of February 19, 1911, stating that Dr. Aleš Hrdlička had sent a proposal, upon the request of Rozhledy (Reviews) and Americká OsVĕta (American Culture), to the General Immigration Commissioner, Mr. Daniel J. O'Keefe, for a new division of immigrants as reported in the publications of the United States Immigration Bureau. The proposal calls for division into five groups, the third of which would be 'Bohemians, Moravians, Silesians, and Slovaks'. To this, the Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář added the following:</p>
   <p>"'Mr. Hrdlička's proposal is correct from the ethnological point of view, but from the national-economic point of view, two columns are necessary, one for the Bohemian-Slavonic people and one for the Slovaks. At that, the attitude of the Bohemian people at the present time is to grant the Slovaks an <pb facs="5418478_1_0868.jpg" n="3"/>independent national development. This is undoubtedly the proper attitude, particularly since the Slovaks have decided for it. The separation is now a fact, even if it is a regrettable one, and there is nothing to be gained by reopening old wounds. In the national-economic respect, the Bohemian-Slavonic people live in Cisleithania [territory to the west of the river Leita, or Litava, dividing the old Austro-Hungarian Empire into the Austrian part and the Hungarian part], and the Slovaks in Transleithania [east of that river]. Each half of the Empire has different national-economic and political conditions, and therefore the pooling of immigration statistics would not be advisable. Also, it would cause new confusion. It is only since 1882 that there has been a separate column for "Bohemia;" later on it was changed to "Bohemia and Moravia," which designation, of course, could also include the Germans from these two lands, although this is not likely, since the Germans always indicate "Austria" as the country of their origin. Finally, the separate column for "Bohemians and Moravians" was instituted in 1899.</p>
   <p>"Thus, we have had a precise, well-defined classification for eleven years <pb facs="5418478_1_0869.jpg" n="4"/>only--a classification which identifies the exact number of Bohemians admitted into the United States. A pooling with Slovaks would cause new difficulties in the national-economic respect.</p>
   <p>"The writer of the article published in the Spravedlnost (disregarding the fact that he erroneously uses the expression 'census' in talking about yearly reports and monthly bulletins issued by the Immigration Bureau, even though the census is taken only once in ten years) has permitted himself to squeeze four untruths into two sentences:</p>
   <p>"In the first place, the Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář did not protest against Dr. Hrdlicka's proposal; it only expressed arguments against it.</p>
   <p>"In the second place, there was no talk at all about illiteracy. (Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář was considering only national-economic and statistical reasons, and here we may add to all that has been said before that the Bohemians rarely return to the old country to live, while with the Slovaks, <pb facs="5418478_1_0870.jpg" n="5"/>this is frequently the case. Thus, if there were a common classification, it would be impossible to tell how many of those returning were Slovaks and how many were Bohemians.)</p>
   <p>"In the third place, there was no question of protecting our Bohemian nationality, but simply a question of scientific exactness, which of course, the writer does not know anything about.</p>
   <p>"Finally, there was no question of a combined pressure or influence, but just the reverse: The question of the divergence in the opinions of Dr. Hrdlička and Dr. Vojan. Furthermore, how important it is to be most careful in matters pertaining to nationality was shown on the occasion of Dr. Štefanik's visit. When the Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář called this prominent astronomer a Česko-Slovenský (Bohemian-Slovak) scientist (because, although he is a Slovak, he was graduated from the University of Prague and feels warmly toward the Bohemians), the Pittsburgh Slovak newspapers protested against this nomenclature, maintaining that Štefanik is purely a Slovak scientist and that the added <pb facs="5418478_1_0871.jpg" n="6"/>designation 'Česko' is just as unfair as when the Germans make Germans out of Bohemian scientists and artists. However, we do not propose to deal with this matter now, because the Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář made its respective point of view sufficiently clear in its reply of June 23, 1911, to the attack of Mr. Petr Kompiš of Pittsburgh against the Bohemians.</p>
   <p>"The article in the Spravedlnost might have engendered the Slovaks' antagonism toward the Česko-Americká Tisková Kancelář. Fortunately, however, the Slovaks will not believe the distortions contained in the article, and the case will again prove the truth of the old Bohemian proverb that 'a lie walks on short legs'."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
