<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-11">Sept. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Leave Your Children in School! (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0093</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0093.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-11">Sept. 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LEAVE YOUR CHILDREN IN SCHOOL! (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A week ago today we devoted an editorial to the beginning of the school year and to the children attending elementary public schools. In addition we dealt also with the children's parents. Today we turn to the schools again, but this time it is not public schools, but colleges and other institutions of learning whose school year has yet to begin. By doing so we should like to remind the Bohemian parents whose children graduated from public schools last year, that their duty is not limited to sending their children to school for those few years required by the law, but that it extends further. They should, if possible, give their children an opportunity to acquire the best and the most complete education within their reach.</p>
   <p>We are living in a period which itself is based on education which makes requirements of a magnitude which none of us could have dreamed of some <pb facs="5418478_1_0094.jpg" n="2"/>years ago. This, however, is not surprising if we consider that there is an abundance of human intellect for any branch of endeavor, and that the degree to which one is qualified determines his or her ability to vie with one's competitiors. This applies also in occupations where it is least expected. Experiences not only in America but in the old country as well, support this statement. We know that such vacancies as that of a village policeman or night watchman have been filled in various "Vystrkovy" [a name given to unimportant small places, comparable to "Podunk," or similar] by men of real education and intelligence--even university men were being preferred--and there were cases where the village policeman or night watchman was mentally far above the mayor and members of the village board. The very lowest rank of a public official in the old country is the one of a scribe, or "amanuensis," equivalent to that of a messenger, a flunkey, who is frequently better off because there is no responsibility connected with his job. And we know very well that such jobs as that of a scribe have been given only to the most intelligent of applicants. At this time it may be somewhat different, and probably will be still more different after the war, <pb facs="5418478_1_0095.jpg" n="3"/>when, no doubt, a shortage of workers will prevail. But such were the conditions before the war, as very many of our readers can well remember.</p>
   <p>Now, are the conditions any better in this country? They are not and will not be. If a man wants to get somewhat decent employment--and it may be far from being profitable--he is required to prove that he is educated, that he has had schooling; lacking it, as well some "uncle" to give him the necessary "pull," he has no chance whatever. Labor is plentiful and, consequently, the employers are "choosy". Even for manual, unskilled labor they make their choice among the most likely men, and we know that in spite of the prevailing "prosperity" there is still an oversupply of labor and that unemployment, instead of diminishing, is steadily increasing.</p>
   <p>The parents certainly are or should be concerned about the future of their children. They should always try to assure a better economic future for their children. This applies particularly to our immigrants whose past has been anything but rosy. To say, "I am a laborer, unskilled worker, and the same <pb facs="5418478_1_0096.jpg" n="4"/>lot should be good enough for my child," is not only entirely wrong but also quite a confession of inferiority. All of us should have at least some ambition, should try to work for the attainment of the better things in life. These better things may not be attained and enjoyed by us, but we should be happy to see our children enjoy them, and they will in turn be appreciative of whatever we have done to make their lives easier, more agreeable, and more prosperous.</p>
   <p>Again, to say, "I have been working hard, and there is no reason why my son shouldn't," is to be devoid of logic, it is heartless and unloving. This our parents should realize. They should not be so stupid as to send elementary school graduates to work because they have complied with the law. Nor should they be still more stupid, and do it because the children's earnings would be helping their parents to pay off the mortgage, to buy better things, to take it more easy--something we meet with, unfortunately, quite often among our countrymen. There are cases where the parents have several children.  One after the other they grow up past the school age, and the <pb facs="5418478_1_0097.jpg" n="5"/>father, feeling that he has slaved long enough to meet all the bills, quits work and sends his children to sweat in various shops with the idea that they all will "get along" somehow, with the children earning the money and the mother taking care of the house. The mortgage on the "shanty" will be paid off, and he will be just "hanging around" the house, taking it easy, as on the Vymenek [certain rights and a share of a farm's income reserved by the old peasant in the old country when he passes on the actual running of it to his son], sipping his beer and sitting for hours, for days, thinking how bad it was when he had to take care of everything himself--with "mother" only--forgetting that "mother" still has to plug along, and will have to plug along perhaps to her very end.</p>
   <p>But most important of all, he forgets that he robs his own children, depriving them too early of their childhood, which should be the most beautiful period of everybody's life. How long is childhood? One answer is, as long as one manages to preserve it. But that answer is not quite correct. A man is not <pb facs="5418478_1_0098.jpg" n="6"/>always a free agent. Circumstances frequently decide for him. we should say, therefore, that childhood lasts as long as one goes to school and as long as he is free of all cares except those easy ones connected with one's school work. Once a child quits school and comes in contact with real life, he is no more a child. He is on his way to early maturity, which will deprive him of the beautiful charm of innocence, the most precious characteristic of childhood.</p>
   <p>Parents should try to preserve that charm in their children as long as possible; certainly they should not wilfully take it away from them. They should leave the children in school as long as they possibly can afford it. The reward for their unselfishness is a hundredfold--if in nothing else, in the knowledge that they have done well their most important, most sacred, most beautiful duty. Do not deprive your children of school! You would be depriving them of their childhood and their opportunity for education, the need of which is being increasingly felt.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0099.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>By keeping your children in school you will do them the most good. You may leave them money, but that will be spent. You may leave them a fine residence, it may burn; it may deteriorate sooner or later. You may leave them a farm, but a cyclone, may turn valuable property into a desert. But give them an education, and there is nothing in the whole world that can take it away from them. They will keep that all their lives, and with that their gratefulness to you, their beautiful memories of their parents. Education is a most valuable dowry. Without it their life struggle will be hard; with it, comparatively easy.</p>
   <p>Do not stop with primary schools. Send your children to higher schools, send them to colleges, and you will never have to worry, never have to fear that life will be unkind to your children. You will never have to reproach yourselves that you have denied your children the education which you could have given them, even if it had meant sacrifices on your part; that you have deprived them too early of their youth, their childhood, the memories which would remain with them for life, just as they remain with you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
