<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-07">Dec. 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Slavic Barbers Form a New Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-07">Dec. 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">SLAVIC BARBERS FORM A NEW ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of Slavic barbers, about which we already printed a short advance notice, was held on the premises of Mr. Mírko Vadjina at 1118 West 18th Street, in our Pilsen district, last Thursday night. The attendance of barbershop owners was very large.</p>
   <p>It was agreed that the barbers in this part of the city are unable to raise their prices as barbers in other localities do now, because their customers are almost exclusively workingmen who cannot pay more for their shaves and haircuts than they have been paying. Therefore the barbers cannot go along with the decision of the downtown organization, whose members work under entirely different conditions.</p>
   <p>In view of these facts, it was deemed necessary to start a new organization, and this action was realized in the meeting. The name of the organization is not given.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1063.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following officers were elected: Mirko Vadjina, president; Fr. Kolář, vice-president; Emil Kolář, treasurer. The meeting adopted a resolution signed by Geo. L. Lukič, Jan Marich, Jos. A. Hušek, Fr. Zornák, and Karel Hampl which, among other matters, sets the working hours as follows: Daily from 7 A. M. to 9 P. M., except Saturday, when the shops will be open until 11 P. M., and Sunday, when they will be open from 7 A. M. to 12 noon.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held in the same place on December 12, and its organizers hope that the owners of barbershops will attend in large numbers so that the organization can be perfected and put on a firm foundation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
