<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1923-04-01">Apr. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation to the Czechoslovak Voters!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1923-04-01">Apr. 1, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION TO THE CZECHOSLOVAK VOTERS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A decisive moment has arrived! The voters of our city will have to decide that very important question of whom to place at the head of their city government. This decision will be made on Tuesday April 3, 1923.</p>
   <p>We believe firmly that our people are well aware of the seriousness of the situation, and that they will be able to face a reality which is now before us. Our friends, the Republicans, again wish to deceive us with promises and empty talk. As usual they claim that the only salvation of the people of Chicago lies in the election of one of their kind to the office of mayor. These are the same, the very same Republicans (yes, there are even Czechoslovaks among them) who recommended Thompson to us eight years ago. Then, as now, they used the same methods. We believed that these people would have a sense of shame for what they perpetrated at that time but we were mistaken and today these selfsame people address our Czechoslovak voters hoping to gain a hearing, a hearing and a confidence for which they had to pay so dearly in the past.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1245.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They are trying to tell us to vote for Lueder--a man, who in the presence of 400 preachers, promised that he would never intervene to have Volstead's 18th amendment changed.</p>
   <p>Chicago lived for eight long years under the Republican regime. Are our people satisfied with the way things were managed at the city hall during those eight years? Do they wish that regime to continue?</p>
   <p>We are convinced that the interests of the citizens were not protected as they should have been; the taxpayers' money was thrown away; it became the booty of politicians, and used that these politicians might entrench themselves still more. As a good example we need only to look at our "highly accomplished" school board and the million-dollar "expert-assessors".</p>
   <p>These same people come to us again in a different guise this time asking to be given another chance and promising to correct their past mistakes! We firmly believe, however, that our people will not let them pull their legs again.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1246.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For all of the above reasons we ask our Czechoslovak voters to come to the polls next Tuesday, April 3, [1923] to get rid of this riffraff and to help elect Messrs. William E. Dever, John A. Cervenka and A. F. Gorman, all of whom are on the Democratic ticket.</p>
   <p>For the Ceskoslovenska Demokraticka Liga Okresu Cook. (Czechoslovak Democratic League of Cook County) [Here follow the names of 57 well-known Chicago Czechs. The above proclamation, printed in bold type, occupies seven-columns-half a page.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
