<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1274.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>.....It is unnecessary to remind the readers that the prohibitionists would be overjoyed if they succeeded in defeating Alderman Anton J. Cermak who is a candidate for the presidency of the County Board of Commissioners. They do not wish him to be elected, and it is for this reason that they agitate so wildly in behalf of Mr. Cermak's Republican rival. Even if Mr. Cermak were not an abler man than his Republican rival, every Czechoslovak citizen should vote for him if they do not want to see a sworn prohibitionist to get the office. Nor is it necessary to make known the fact that the Anti-Saloon League does not recommend Mr. Josef A. Mendl as a candidate for the office of member of the County Board of Commissioners. The League does not want any Democrat getting any offices. For this reason our Czechoslovak voters should support the friends of personal liberty and help elect them to these county offices. They should vote for these men irrespective of their political affiliations. In other words, they should vote for the entire Democratic ticket, and place a "Yes" on the small ballot dealing with the permit [for the sale and manufacture] of light wines and beers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1275.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Spolek Ceskoslovenskych Lekaru, (Bohemian Medical Society) to which all our physicians of Chicago and Cook County belong, passed a resolution warmly recommending Mr. Anton J. Cermak as president of the County Board of Commissioners, and Mr. Josef A. Mendl as member of the same Board..... It is unnecessary to remind our readers that our physicians are not prompted by any political motives; on the contrary, their motives were purely humanitarian. They, of all people, are best fitted to point to the importance of such institutions as the County Hospital, the home for the indigent old people, and the tuberculosis hospital, at Oak Forest, Illinois, as well as other institutions controlled by the County Commissioners. The officers of the county are required to look after these county institutions, to give them their greatest care. It is necessary that the Board of Commissioners be headed by an able and experienced man; one who also has a compassion for the suffering and the poor who are compelled to seek charity in these charitable institutions. It is for this reason that [our doctors] recommend Messrs. Cermak and Mendl, and our voters should follow such a recommendation, for it comes from the midst of professional intelligence, from men who are especially well acquainted with the needs of our county institutions.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1276.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A good example of the methods employed by the foes of our Mr. Cermak came to light yesterday in connection with a raid made by the prohibition agents who selected a number of saloons located in the Bohemian California district as the goal of their activities. The afternoon papers announced that Mr. Cermak is a saloonkeeper. This was probably done to arouse public opinion against Mr. Cermak who will thus be branded as a person who represents his own private gains in his candidacy for a public office. In making a saloonkeeper out of Mr. Cermak, his fight against prohibition would thus obviously be prompted by personal motives. The news item reported a raid upon "Cermak's stronghold," with an additional remark made by the newspaper to the effect that "the prohibition agents have not disturbed Cermak's saloon located at 3534 West 26th Street". There really is a saloon owned by a certain "Cermak" at the address given, but that man is not our candidate, nor is the saloonkeeper in any way related to our candidate. The rumors that someone in the prohibition offices is "after Cermak," have been circulating for some time. It was believed that behind this rumor were the prohibition fanatics who are the avowed enemies of Mr. Cermak. But the raid was postponed until the end of the political campaign, and when it <pb facs="5418478_1_1277.jpg" n="4"/>was finally staged it was found that it was directed by a prohibition agent who is the friend of a certain Republican leader on the West Side. It is therefore believed by Mr. Cermak and his friends that behind the raids made in Bohemian California yesterday can be found the political enemies of Mr. Cermak. The result of this will be that our Czechoslovak people will give still stronger support to Mr. Cermak and to all that he represents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
