<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-12">Mar. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Czecho-Slavonic Taxpayers' Association of Cicero, Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-12">Mar. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE CZECHO-SLAVONIC TAXPAYERS' ASSOCIATION OF CICERO, ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is heartening to notice how our Czechoslovak taxpayers in Cicero, Illinois, are beginning to interest themselves in the Česko-Slovanský Poplatnický Spolek v Cicero (Czecho-Slavonic Taxpayers' Association of Cicero). For it is in this organization that they may jointly discuss and deliberate their individual problems bearing upon the needs of the community; where they may seek protection and aid whenever such measures are necessary. That the interest in this group is growing was fully borne out by the large attendance of Czechoslovak taxpayers at the last monthly meeting, which took place in the spacious assembly hall of the T. G. Masaryk school.</p>
   <p>The president, Mr. H. Krček,....opened the meeting and greeted the ten new members. Mr. Anton J. Čermàk also attended this meeting, and upon request, addressed the audience. His remarks touched upon the present methods of taxation, and he pointed out such graft and dishonesty which occur in the <pb facs="5418478_1_1523.jpg" n="2"/>licensing system. Mr. Čermàk also mentioned the fact that some large corporations try to evade the payment of taxes; and while small taxpayers are required to pay every penny, these rich corporations pay a ridiculously small tax. Mr. Čermàk is well known for his championing of personal freedom, and he did not let this occasion pass by without mentioning the results of prohibition. His remarks were to the point. He said that far from reducing the crime rate, prohibition increased it, and for this, prohibition alone is to blame. It demoralizes and deprives the individual of his rights. Mr. Čermàk announced in this meeting that a petition will soon be circulating among the citizens who are to express their approval or disapproval of the prohibition system. It is surely expected that a great majority of the votes will be against prohibition ....which is such a disorganizing factor in our present social order.</p>
   <p>Mr. Čermàk further stated that he is a candidate for the office of president of the County Board of Commissioners, and he requested all of our countrymen <pb facs="5418478_1_1524.jpg" n="3"/>to aid him in this campaign. He assured them that should he be successful in winning the office, he will discharge his duties faithfully, and that he will not bring shame to our [Czechoslovak] colony.....</p>
   <p>The next item on the program was the problem of civil service which is to be established in our community and is to include the police and fire departments. It was pointed out that at present, neither firemen nor policemen are properly protected in their work; that they are at the mercy of certain politicians, and that while such conditions prevail, it is impossible for them to render honest service to the citizens. Should civil service be established, every employee would not only feel more secure in his position, but he could render more efficient service, which would be advantageous to the citizens and the community. [It was therefore decided] that proper steps should be taken to establish civil service for policemen and firemen.</p>
   <p>The question of building a hospital for the Cicero community was discussed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1525.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There is no doubt about the fact that a hospital is needed, although some people object.....Every large community should have its own hospital..... An appeal will be made to the County Board of Commissioners to aid our community in building an appropriate hospital here.</p>
   <p>For several years past our taxpayers' associations have been waging war against the evil of selling fireworks used in the Fourth of July celebrations. Every year complaints and requests have been made to the County Board of Commissioners to prohibit such sales, but thus far all these efforts have been in vain. And yet the citizens of Chicago have been successful in obtaining a law prohibiting such sales. This year we shall try again, but this time we believe that our efforts will meet with success.</p>
   <p>The issue of the election of officers to the school board was the next item on the program, and it was decided that the Cesko-Slovansky Poplatnicky Spolek <pb facs="5418478_1_1526.jpg" n="5"/>v Cicero will co-operate with other taxpayers' associations of Cicero in choosing the right candidates.....The Poplatnický Spolek has recommended as one of the candidates Mr. Frank J. Petru, who is the present president of the Spolek.</p>
   <p>At our next meeting, which will be held on April 1, 1922, there will be a lecture about the rights of citizenship and the ballot law. Since this lecture will deal with a very important subject which is of interest to every citizen, it is expected that all members of our organization will attend and bring their friends with them.....</p>
   <p>Vàclav Rous, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
