<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-29">Dec. 29, 1913</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-29">Dec. 29, 1913</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting called by a citizens' committee for the purpose of acquainting the general public with the muddled situation prevailing now in the Chicago Board of Education was held yesterday afternoon. The affairs of the Board have become so complicated that a true picture of them, given by men who know, was also expected to be of unusual interest to the Bohemian public.</p>
   <p>The meeting had a fair attendance, mostly men. There were just a few ladies. It was opened by Mr. John A. Sokol, who was elected chairman, Banker James F. Stepina, and its secretary Dr. O. Baumrucker.</p>
   <p>Mr. Štěpina briefly addressed the meeting and requested Mr. J. B. Dibelka to inform those present about the recent doing in the Board of Education. Mr. Dibelka's speech was most interesting. He explained that he never cared to become a member of the School Board, and accepted the membership only after having been twice requested to do so. He accepted it knowing that his wide <pb facs="5418478_1_0153.jpg" n="2"/>experience in school matters would put him in a position to be of considerable service to our schools and the whole school system. Upon his nomination he was requested to sign a resignation. He was told that the signing of this resignation was just a matter of form; that the resignation would be used only in case of controversies resulting from political differences. With this understanding he attached his signature. However, he would never have signed it had he suspected that he was giving his signature not to a man, but to an old woman.</p>
   <p>Then he discussed very thoroughly the whole school system and his many sad experiences with the school superintendent, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young. He pointed out many faults and mistakes of the system, faults which call loudly for improvement. Whenever he talked about then with Mrs. Young he was cut short. All his efforts for improvement shattered on her stubborness and obstinacy. He called her attention to the tremendous losses of time in the schools by useless, impractical things…. No insisted on a reform in teaching deaf and mute children…. but the "most perfect educator of young people," Mrs. Ella <pb facs="5418478_1_0154.jpg" n="3"/>Flagg Young, would not hear at all…. and no reforms were made until the whole matter had become a topic of discussion in the daily press…. [Here follows a column of talk about Mrs. Young's shortenings, etc., which are irrelevant.]</p>
   <p>By electing Mr. Shoop to her office, the first step in the right direction was made. The fact that he resigned that office does not put an end to the whole affair, because the second election of Mrs. Young is illegal, it is a sign of anarchy which will never get the sanction of the law….</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
