<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-03-16">March 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Alarm Among Catholic Knights.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0940</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0940.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-03-16">March 16, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">ALARM AMONG CATHOLIC KNIGHTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whenever there appears among the free-thinking people some swindler who absconds with money entrusted to him, our Catholic citizens raise a hue and cry and almost tear themselves to pieces pointing out what scoundrels people are who do not want to believe in the Heavenly Kingdom and how dangerous it is for a poor man if he has himself insured by such unbelieving societies. These gentlemen do not like to admit that there are scoundrels among the Catholics as well as among the free-thinkers. Yet it is proved that there are among the Catholics more people who perpetrate all sorts of fraud and who have the idea that by confessing all everything is well again.</p>
   <p>The incident which we mention here is proof that Catholic gentlemen see the faults of others but are unable to see their own.</p>
   <p>There is an organization of Catholic Knights in America which is directly under the control of the priests. All officers from the chairman down to <pb facs="5418478_1_0941.jpg" n="2"/>the last clerk are under the supervision of the gentlemen in the Capoches (priest's garment). The devoted lambs believed that every penny which they deposited into the central treasury was well protected. However, in the month of October of last year, the board of trustees examined the books and announced to the much surprised Knights that there was some trifling shortage. Little attention was given to it in the beginning, for how could anything irregular occur in a society which was managed by such Godly servants of the Lord?</p>
   <p>A somewhat more serious attitude was taken toward the whole affair when it became known, after a thorough examination of the books, that the trifling shortage would amount to $71,000, and that there was a possibility that it might be much greater, probably as much as $200,000.</p>
   <p>And where is this money? Catholic Knights have a membership of about 25,000, and they all pay dues into a central treasury for insurance in the event of death. According to their laws, the treasurer is required to pay the death benefits of the deceased within sixty days after the announcement <pb facs="5418478_1_0942.jpg" n="3"/>of death.</p>
   <p>Under these circumstances, the treasurer was able, being hand in hand with the reverend fathers, to profit thereby. Recently, people have been dying more numerously than heretofore and Mr. Treasurer seemed to think it the best time to provide for his future. The more money that accumulated in his hands, the greater was his love for it. When there had accumulated in the treasury almost $200,000 he was completely enraptured. He knew, to be sure, that this money belonged to poor forsaken widows and orphans. He knew that he would commit a great sin if he were to steal this money - but the money seemed to promise him a nice, comfortable life on earth, so why wait for the blessed life after death? Therefore he kept the money and the reverend fathers are now trying to find a way to arrange it so that they will not be forced to take Mr. Treasurer before the courts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
