<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-17">Oct. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">This Is Our Fight! (Front-Page Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-17">Oct. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THIS IS OUR FIGHT! (Front-Page Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechoslovaks of the old homeland fight for the social reforms of their country. They try hard to bring order into chaos, to contribute to the happiness of the whole [national] community. We, as citizens of this new homeland, should follow the example of our brothers beyond the seas, and unite in an effort to combat the forces of fanaticism, forces which in this land of liberty are more and more gaining control in an endeavor to influence the rest of the population and to dictate to it what it may or may not do. The aim of these fanatics is to shackle the masses, thus making it impossible for them to act independently and to think freely. But as long as we are here their plans shall miscarry. The Czechoslovak men and women voters know their responsibilities to the whole society and to the nation whose citizens they have become, and they are aware of the responsibilities <pb facs="5418478_1_0503.jpg" n="2"/>to themselves. And the responsibilities which they have assumed they aim to discharge till the very end.</p>
   <p>The first of these responsibilities is that of registering, and every one of us who has his citizenship papers and who has lived at least one year in this state, three months in the country, and thirty days in his precinct inclusive of election day, ought to go to register at once in order to be able to join our fighting ranks and to be entitled to use his weapon-- the ballot.</p>
   <p>Today is the last registration day. Whoever neglects this day to have his name entered on the register of voters, is lost to the cause so dear to us all, so important to all of us. And should the outcome of our struggle be unfavorable, the guilt would chiefly fall upon the shoulders of those who, in a decisive moment, by their indifference and procrastination, <pb facs="5418478_1_0504.jpg" n="3"/>abandoned their brothers before the battle started.</p>
   <p>In the forthcoming November election we are chiefly interested in certain principles which we wish to see victorious and which we shall therefore support; we are also interested in certain individuals whom we know to be honest and who will work with all their energies for the well-being of all the citizens, and because of whose work we, the Czechoslovaks of Cook County, shall gain the respect of the rest of the citizens. The gain will be everybody's.....</p>
   <p>We Czechoslovaks have always fought that justice should be done where justice needed to be done, and as for liberty, we have never hesitated to sacrifice our substance and our lives that it might be. These same ideals have now also become our objectives as citizens of Chicago and Cook County. It is these ideals that will be our monitors as we go to the registration <pb facs="5418478_1_0505.jpg" n="4"/>of voters today, and as we go to the ballot boxes three weeks hence.</p>
   <p>The fanatical "drys" recognize in Anton J. Cermak their bitterest enemy; they recognize him to be the leader of liberals, the champion of all those who long for liberty. It was these fanatics who issued a call to all their partisans not to fail to register their votes so that Mr. Cermak might be defeated in his candidacy for the most important office--that of the president of the country board of commissioners. Such a call must not be allowed to go unchallenged by us who stand back of Mr. Cermak and all that he represents.</p>
   <p>Let us see to it that every one of our countrymen who failed to register ten days ago, registers today. And those of us who will go to our precincts to perform this duty, should awaken the sleepy ones and the <pb facs="5418478_1_0506.jpg" n="5"/>lackadaisical and the deaf. Let us lead the [politically] blind who happen to live in our neighborhoods.</p>
   <p>There will be other countrymen of ours besides Mr. Cermak, whose candidacies and election should be equally important to us. It is most important to us that our state representatives personify all that which has become our credo and the basis of our [political] convictions. We must have men in the legislative branches of our government who are of us, who understand us, who know what we want, and who can defend our interests within their spheres of activity. All that for which Mr. Cermak and the rest of us who are behind him, stand, may be gained only by legislative means. It is therefore absolutely necessary that by today's registration and by the November election we help to secure the victory for Congressman Adolf J. Sabath, whose long record in the Congress of the United States is without blemish. From the nineteenth senatorial district we desire to elect Mr. Albert B. Holecek, who by his entire upbringing, his thorough education, and his spotless <pb facs="5418478_1_0507.jpg" n="6"/>character, gives us a guarantee that always and in all places he will defend us, the poor folk, the foreign-language groups and the Czechoslovak people to whom he has always been sincerely devoted. Let us meet today, therefore, at the registration desks, and three weeks hence at the polls!</p>
   <p>The registration offices will be open today--Tuesday--until 9 P. M. to give an opportunity to everybody who has not yet had such an opportunity. At the last registration [ten days ago] more than 400,000 voters were registered, which is about one half of the people of the country who have the right to vote. The reason for this discrepancy is most probably the inclement weather, and also perhaps the fact that Saturday is not a particularly good day for the womenfolk. Besides that, thousands of voters imagined that there was time to do it later, and delayed registering till the next day. It is therefore probable that they will do their duty today..... [Translator's note: Forty more lines (about one-fifth of a column) continue <pb facs="5418478_1_0508.jpg" n="7"/>in this vein, but since they are constant repetitions of the importance of registering, I have omitted translating them.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
