<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-01">Oct. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation to the Czechoslovak Citizens of Cook County!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1307</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1307.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-01">Oct. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION TO THE CZECHOSLOVAK CITIZENS OF COOK COUNTY!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Citizens and countrymen! The county elections of this fall, from which we expect so many changes, are almost upon us. It is evident that they are of the utmost importance to us, even if we overlook the fact that among the candidates there is a great number of our countrymen.</p>
   <p>It is necessary, above all, to effect certain radical changes, for the present conditions, under which the Republican politicians squeeze taxes out of our citizenry on the one hand while they squander public funds on the other, have become unbearable. The Republican regime which, by means of unscrupulously high taxation, is able to amass hundreds of thousands--yea even millions of dollars--just to hold together its political machine, must come to an end!</p>
   <p>You can prevent the continuance of that regime only by registering your votes. Due to a recent change in ward boundaries every voter must register; that is, <pb facs="5418478_1_1308.jpg" n="2"/>if he desires to vote at the November election! Registration of all voters will be on Saturday, October 7, 1922, and every Czechoslovak man or woman should do his duty! The polling places will in many cases be moved to a new address; this was done chiefly to confuse the citizens but it ought not frighten away anyone of us! Look for your polling place next Saturday, October 7, and register your votes; for only in this way will you be able to give expression to your will at the November election!</p>
   <p>For the Czechoslovak Democratic committee,</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>John A. Cervenka, president;</p>
   <p>Josef Stastny, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
