<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1899-05-06">May 6, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Local Politics - City and County.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1638</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1638.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1899-05-06">May 6, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">LOCAL POLITICS - CITY AND COUNTY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian-Republican Club "Lincoln" of the 10th ward belongs to the organizations which do not stop their activities after election day. On the contrary the members of this club have their regular meetings and although the election excitement may have ceased long before, they are enlarging their organization and preparing themselves for future activity in the political club can exist and be useful.</p>
   <p>At last Sunday's meeting the members deliberated upon the existing conditions in the Philippine Islands, a question most vital at present, and interesting to all American people. A unanimous resolution was adopted, which should be published for the information of all Bohemian-Americans. Resolved:</p>
   <p>Whereas, we are certain that the Spanish-American War for deliverance of Cube was started and conducted with the approval of the whole American people because the peace-loving President of the United States, William McKinley, <pb facs="5418478_1_1639.jpg" n="2"/>hating the bloodshed, failed to avoid it, although he used all diplomatic influences to assure the freedom of the Cuban people; therefore we decide that being American citizens we are obliged to carry bravely the consequences, whatever they may be.</p>
   <p>We decide further that after the victorious battle in Manila Bay and annihilation of the government on the Island of Luzon (the Spanish government), it is an absolute necessity that the Americans keep order until the American Congress will make a decision as to what kind of government should be applied in this territory.</p>
   <p>The local tribes, being unconscious of the situation, or instigated by some leaders, turned their weapons against the people (the American soldiers), who in disregarding their own lives, liberated them from long Spanish slavery.</p>
   <p>Making this statement we manifest our confidence in the Federal government and in the American people and the promise that after the end of the war there will be done everything possible to assure freedom and prosperity for the oppressed local populations. We do absolutely believe it will be a real benefit for the local population if the American people will decide to take them under their <pb facs="5418478_1_1640.jpg" n="3"/>protection and they can be assured that, exactly as during the battles Americans were humane and just with them, so, after the war is over they will be treated with more humanity and justice by Americans than by any other government in the world. We will not agree with some of the Bohemian newspapers which proceed too far, calling it simple murder and a state of tyranny of the Philippine population. We deny that the American government tyrannizes over anyone, anywhere. We, ourselves, immigrants to this country not so long ago, like other nations are the best proof as to what American liberty and American institutions are, because we enjoy all the liberties and privileges alike, with the American-born population.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
