<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-12">May 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-12">May 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Besides the Czechs, our brothers, the Poles, are the first to offer themselves in largest numbers for the defense for the country. One single recruiting station in the Polish settlement of Milwaukee, Wis., has registered 637 men for Uncle Sam's Army, all young, well built boys, who just seem to have been born for the uniform. This remarkable result has naturally attracted the attention of the English language press, which showered lavish praise upon the Poles and Czechs.</p>
   <p>Such appreciative manifestations are gratifying, even if they seem belated. with somewhat more sincerity than they have shown heretofore, the English language papers now admit that they have been treating the Slavonic immigrants with no particular favor. They have slighted them, and omitted news about their community life, except something uncomplimentary. The Slavonic people within the populace of Chicago have their own traits, and they have <pb facs="5418478_1_0755.jpg" n="2"/>missed no opportunity to demonstrate that they belong to the most desirable class of immigrants, and their flaming patriotic enthusiasm is therefore no ephemera, but originates from a deep, idealistic conviction. We, the Slavonic people, have always been doing our duty, and it is not our fault that at least, a small amount of recognition has not been shown us before. Be it as it may, better late than never.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
