<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-28">Oct. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago School System</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0087</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0087.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-28">Oct. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SCHOOL SYSTEM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago school affairs have been given greater attention by the general public in recent times than ever before. This attention has been fully justified. No other department of city or state administration is of greater importance than the schools. But the majority of citizens pay no attention to such matters except when something extraordinary is happening, when there is a disagreement between the School Board members, or some more serious difference between the Board and the school superintendent.</p>
   <p>Recent cases in point are the decision of the Chicago Board of Education to destroy the Teachers' Federation, and the news about the resignation of the present school superintendent, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young.</p>
   <p>The first affair has caused a great deal of excitement because the Board was accused of trying to destroy an important organization which the teachers had founded for their own protection, and in the defense of which <pb facs="5418478_1_0088.jpg" n="2"/>they have received strong support from the Chicago Federation of Labor. This dispute will have to be decided by the courts. It involves the principle as to whether or not the Chicago Board of Education has the right to tell the teachers to which organizations they may or may not belong.</p>
   <p>The question of Mrs. Young's position has been a sore spot in the Chicago school situation for years. A year ago the School Board elected another superintendent to replace Mrs. Young, but she stayed in office because of the Mayor's intervention, and the strong pressure of women's organizations and the English-language press. Next December, when another election will be held by the School Board, Mrs. Ella Flagg Young, as she has stated, will not be a candidate. The School Board accuses her of assuming rights belonging exclusively to them, and in general, of trying to run the schools and everything in connection with them, herself. As it is, nobody can deny Mrs. Young's great ability, and her reputation among educators is well known and fully recognized. But the Chicago schools have suffered because she could not get along with the Board. Therefore, her resignation <pb facs="5418478_1_0089.jpg" n="3"/>will be an advantage, but the Board will put the whole school system in a worse condition than it has been during Mrs. Young's superintendency if it fails to elect a man of real abilities, both as educator and as executive.</p>
   <p>The superintendent of schools in Chicago receives, out of the taxpayer's money, ten thousand dollars a year as salary, a very decent sum and more than is being paid to many a man whose office is considered, although often wrongly, of much greater importance. However, it is not the highest salary paid to school experts in the United States. Our large cities are always trying to engage the services of the very best educators, as is evident in New York, where, in addition to a full-time superintendent, Mr. Wirt of Gary, Indiana has been engaged. He devotes to the New York schools hardly one third of the time spent on Chicago schools by our superintendent, although he, too, receives ten thousand dollars for his services. And New York has yet another expert who gets ten thousand a year. It is New York's endeavor to develop as perfect a school system as possible no matter what it costs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0090.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But the superintendent is not the only person on whom the success of the school system depends. There is also the school board, which in reality is never what it should be. And this applies to Chicago as well as to any other large city, and, for that matter, to the small ones, also, where the members are elected directly by the citizens. The appointment of school board members in Chicago, is a matter of politics, and the office is considered a part of political spoils. Small wonder, then, that these important offices are not always filled by men of real ability and sincere interest in schools and educational matters in general.</p>
   <p>Many proposals have been made lately to remedy this situation. One of them calls for a board of a smaller number of members, who would be fulltime officials with a fixed salary. Another idea frequently propounded is to take away from the mayor the opportunity to barter with such offices. But it is not to be expected that either of these proposals will be adopted, even though the idea of a smaller board has been very widely recommended. Many cities which formerly had large school boards have come to the conclusion <pb facs="5418478_1_0091.jpg" n="5"/>that large boards are impractical and have changed their inert, slow-moving boards to a small board of a few members, and in that way have improved their efficiency. The Chicago Board of Education consists of twenty-one members; this, in the opinion of many people, is too large a body, and cannot work as well as a smaller one. Whether such a change would be for the better would depend entirely upon the quality of men who held these important offices, Nor is it certain that more able men would get on the Board if they were to receive regular salaries. Of course, it is true that in that case many really able men could afford to take the office who cannot do so now when it is an honorary function. But it does not follow that such men would be appointed; in fact, it is even more likely that these offices would be considered a most desirable bartering subject for politicians.</p>
   <p>However, this is neither here nor there. The fact remains that the Chicago school system is in bad need of reform, and that Chicago citizens could bring it about if they would show at least as much interest in school <pb facs="5418478_1_0092.jpg" n="6"/>matters as they show in other public affairs. They should not forget that the education of some three hundred and fifty thousand children is in the hands of the superintendent and the Board, that over sixty-five million dollars is invested in Chicago school properties, and that the running of Chicago schools costs thirteen million dollars a year. If all this were receiving the proper consideration, and if Chicago citizens would pay more attention to their school matters, the desirable reform would certainly be brought about.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
