<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-03-26">Mar. 26, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemians Compare Themselves to the Boers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0921</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0921.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-03-26">Mar. 26, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIANS COMPARE THEMSELVES TO THE BOERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several hundred of Chicago's citizens of Bohemian extraction gathered at the Pilsen Turner Hall yesterday to express their pro-Boer sympathies, Mr. John Habenicht, the chairman of the meeting, compared the fate of the Boers to that of the Bohemians. He said, that Britain is trying to enslave the Boer nation just as the Germans are doing with Bohemia. He asked for intervention by our federal Government in the war in South Africa, To this proposal the meeting responded with loud applause. Mr. Frank Cesvacek, publisher of the newspaper Spravedenost, and William Kronziker of the Svornost delivered speeches to the same effect. Mr. William Naseman of the Onze Toekomst, thanked the Bohemians in the name of the Dutch for their expression of sympathy for this South African nation. - The following resolution was then read and passed: "This assembly thus expresses its sympathy and its deep admiration for the courageous Boer nation which is fighting to defend its independence. We, the descendants of a glorious nation which has for centuries lived under the yoke, sympathize with the Boers, whose only desire is to remain masters of their own country. The Bohemians are a peace-loving nation, respecting the rights of others. We are, therefore deeply concerned about the so-called enlightened tendency of the powerful nations of the earth which tolerates the absorption of smaller nations and the extinction of their native tongues.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0922.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Peace Conference at The Hague, which was supposed to be an intermediary in international disagreements, is a sorry burlesque in the case of the present conflict.</p>
   <p>Yes, Bohemian's sons fight, too, for their liberty, and will continue to do so until the day dawns when they will lift the yoke and be a free nation again. As citizens of this country we appeal to the government of the United States to exercise its influence toward the speedy termination of this horrible war and to protect a small nation which is so honorably defending its liberty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
