<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-12">Oct. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Social Service Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0439</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-27">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0439.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-12">Oct. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL SERVICE WORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Czech Catholics) has been paying a great deal of attention lately to social service, and one of its achievements is the Czechoslovak department in the Catholic Immigration Office in New York, which was organized by the National Catholic Welfare Council. The Narodni Svaz will send to this department very shortly a Czechoslovak young lady, a social worker who will devote all her time to Czechoslovak immigrants exclusively. The work along this line is very important and our nation has been in great need of it. Now, however, the problem is being dealt with by the Narodni Svaz and will be solved by the appointment of a Czech worker.</p>
   <p>This, however, is not all we have in mind to do. The need for trained social workers is steadily growing, particularly for workers who are also trained in civic and social economics and are otherwise well equipped for social and charity work in all branches. The importance of this <pb facs="5418478_1_0440.jpg" n="2"/>work cannot be denied and it is our desire to see many more of our girls and women in it; ladies who like this kind of work will find in it their best and most complete satisfaction. For this reason the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku has appointed a special committee under the chairmanship of Dr. M.E. Lorenz, who is a well-known Czech physician. The committee has made contact with the social department of the National Catholic Welfare Council in Washington and a number of the foremost American universities having a department of social service. One of these universities is the Loyola University of Chicago located on Clark and Randolph Streets. The Svaz's contact with this university has resulted in a letter which we are proud to publish in its original reading [English].</p>
   <p>Loyola University</p>
   <p>"Dr. M. E. Lorenz, % National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics [sic].</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0441.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"My dear Dr. Lorenz:</p>
   <p>Relative to our conversation I take this occasion formally to repeat my offer to your National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of two scholarships in the Social Service Department of this school, provided the young ladies are at least eighteen years of age and have not a high school education, or are over twenty and have the equivalent of same.</p>
   <p>"With every best wish,</p>
   <p>"Sincerely,</p>
   <p>"(Signed) Frederic Siedeburg, S.J."</p>
   <p>A fine success, this! We have two scholarships already which must be given to worthy and desirable girl students. They will receive a complete training for social service free of any charge. With their studies completed <pb facs="5418478_1_0442.jpg" n="4"/>they will receive a diploma and engage in that service, either in the sphere of immigration, industry, charity, health railway, or any other. Girls who have an inclination for such work should send their applications directly to the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku, 3207 West 22nd Street, Chicago, Illinois. The application must contain information as to the applicant's age, education, and experience. If you do not, at this time, receive the above-mentioned scholarship, your application will remain on our files for future reference. It is our wish to see our girls engaging in social work, a field where we miss them now.</p>
   <p>For the Narodni Svaz Ceskych katoliku,</p>
   <p>Ant. Vaclav Tesar, office manager.</p>
   <p>All those who want to join the expedition of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku to Czechoslovakia next year please send us their applications.</p>
   <p>The Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku is making reservations for the <pb facs="5418478_1_0443.jpg" n="5"/>participants in the expedition to the old country in the year of 1922.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
