<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-24">Oct. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Political Matters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-24">Oct. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL MATTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An organization named the Cecho-Slovacka Demokraticka Liga (Czechoslovak Democratic League) was founded by our countrymen in the spring of this year, before the April primaries. The Liga operated in Cook County, and its aim was above all the nomination of our countrymen [for office], such men as Alderman Antonin J. Cermak, Congressman Adolf J. Sabath, Mr. Josef Mendl, and others, and to promote their election. When the efforts of the Liga had met with undoubted success, it continued to operate, not only to secure as many Czechoslovak votes as possible for the above candidates but also to persuade our countrymen to vote Democratic at the forthcoming election, on Tuesday, November 7, 1922. We had occasion to say much about the Liga and its work during the primary campaign, and we told our readers that in it are represented our numerous societies, merchants, and workingmen and all those people who deeply desire that our countrymen shall rise politically and become publicly known. The Liga also endeavors to secure just and merited recognition <pb facs="5418478_1_1503.jpg" n="2"/>for us all as an ethnic unit. If the work of the Liga was crowned with success at the April primaries, it will certainly be more successful now. It is with pleasure that we notice how feverish the activities of the Liga have become. It works in every precinct and in every ward throughout the County, looking up Czechoslovak names. To these persons letters will be sent in which special stress will be laid on the voter doing his duty as a citizen, but above all he will be urged to follow the dictates of national honor by helping to elect men of Czechoslovak origin to responsible public offices.</p>
   <p>It is certain that one of the most effective campaign devices is the holding of meetings, in which people obtain much information which would otherwise be overlooked by the public. Meetings influence many to vote otherwise than they originally had planned.</p>
   <p>Fully aware of this, the Liga has decided to arrange for a number of such <pb facs="5418478_1_1504.jpg" n="3"/>meetings in various parts of the City and the County. It is self-understood that all these meetings will be held in districts and localities inhabited by Czechoslovaks, and that they will be located in the most accessible places. At the time of this writing we have not yet obtained the complete list of meetings nor the names of the speakers who are to address them, but we may assure the interested readers of this paper that they will soon be fully informed about every meeting to be held. In the meantime we are able to make the announcement that the Liga is to hold a meeting this coming Wednesday, that is, on October 25, at 8 P. M. in the downstairs hall of the Sokol Chicago on Kedzie Avenue, and it is desirable, nay, highly necessary, that all members of the organization be present. Time passes, and there remain only a few more days before the election, and there is still very much work to be done. It would be well if every member of the Liga brought some of his acquaintances with him to the above meeting; the more, the merrier.</p>
   <p>Thus far we may announce the following meetings of the Liga. On October 30, <pb facs="5418478_1_1505.jpg" n="4"/>at 8 P. M., a meeting will be held in the Pilsen Park pavilion. On the same day there will also be meetings in the Pilsen Sokol Hall and in the Karel Jonas Sokol Hall in Cicero, Illinois. On Wednesday night, November 1, there will be a meeting in the F. B. Zdrubek School, 4624 North Crawford Avenue. On Thursday, November 2, there will be a meeting in the hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) at West 18th and May Streets. On Sunday, November 5, an afternoon meeting will be held in the Sokol Chicago on Kedzie Avenue.</p>
   <p>Other meetings will be held in the Town of Lake, in the New Tabor district, and elsewhere. As soon as we receive the correct information about these meetings, we will make the facts known.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
