<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-02-16">Feb. 16, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Eleventh Ward Taxpayers' Club Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1592</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1592.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-02-16">Feb. 16, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">ELEVENTH WARD TAXPAYERS' CLUB MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Eleventh Ward Taxpayers' Club held a meeting yesterday in the Pilsen Sokol hall on Ashland Avenue. The meeting was attended by many members and friends. The president, Mr. Fiala, called the meeting to order, and the secretary read the minutes of the previous meeting, which were approved as read. Mr. Hadac, chairman of the committee handling the matter in dispute between the Taxpayers' Club and the Park Board, reports that the committee had followed instructions. But, he has just been informed by the representative of Denni Hlasatel that all this was in vain for the following reasons:</p>
   <p>The first report of the changed point of view of the Park Board was given to us by the representative of Denni Hlasatel who was authorized by Mr. Kolacek, president of the West Parks Commission, to make it public. The following day our committee called on Mr. Kolacek who confirmed the report, <pb facs="5418478_1_1593.jpg" n="2"/>adding thereto that the Edison Company shop would probably be taken over by the Commission soon. The figures at which the management of the plant was willing to sell are interesting. The first time, the consideration was $275,000; the second time it was $181,000; the third time it was $165,000; the fourth time it was $165,000; but the Commission offered $120,000, and as Mr. Kolacek assures us, that is the price at which it will most likely be sold. It follows, therefore, that it will not be necessary to do anything more in the matter, and I openly admit that credit for the success is chiefly due to the efforts of Mr. Kolacek and State Senator E. J. Forst, both of whom were co-operative at all times. I also thank Governor Deneen and the Denni Hlasatel, which defended the interests of the taxpayers and willingly sent its representatives to their meetings. They did everything possible to aid the Club in attaining its goal. Mr. Fiala moved that a vote of thanks be given to these people, and the motion was unanimously approved. Senator Forst, who was present, was applauded. The chairman then gave special thanks to the committee and assured them that the Taxpayers' Club never before has had such an active group. To the committee on bylaws were <pb facs="5418478_1_1594.jpg" n="3"/>elected the following men: Messrs. Hadac, Fiala, Svoboda, Poremba, and Smrz. Receipts were $6.95; disbursements, $3.65.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
