<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-11">July 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">To Bohemian Students</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-11">July 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TO BOHEMIAN STUDENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani (Council for Higher Education) is at this time again accepting applications of Bohemian students of both sexes who desire to continue or finish their studies but lack the means of doing so. Such students who conform to the requirements of the executive committee of the Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani may receive a loan of not more than $250 for one school year. This loan is made on a pledge of honor by the applicant. The committee's requirements are the following:</p>
   <p>"The applicant--without regard to sex--must be of Bohemian origin, have a command of the Bohemian language, and feel as a Bohemian, must be known for his or her decent, moral life, and prove his ability to make a success of advanced studies. The applications will be considered only of those students who have no means of supporting themselves in their school work. The <pb facs="5418478_1_0364.jpg" n="2"/>applications must be accompanied by a recent photograph of the applicant, and a statement as to which of the institutions of higher learning approved by the committee the applicant desires to attend. The committee requires evidence of at least one semester of successful studies at the indicated institution prior to the approval of the loan. The applicant will give the committee a pledge to finish the full course of studies he is engaging in and will cause the authorities of the selected institution to report periodically to the committee on his progress."</p>
   <p>The loan may be given only to students following an academic course, a course in engineering, or preparing for a teaching career. "Academic courses" are those generally designated in university prospectuses as "collegiate courses," "the college of liberal arts," "the college of arts and sciences". In such courses the following subjects are taught: modern and classical languages, history, philosophy, political economy, exact and natural sciences. In teachers' and engineering courses, subjects germane to such professions are <pb facs="5418478_1_0365.jpg" n="3"/>being taught.</p>
   <p>The students' particular attention is called to the absolute necessity of acquiring or having, by way of preparation for the courses, a thorough command, in grammar and every other respect, of the English language. This is really a matter that it should not be necessary to mention, since every student should feel the indispensability of knowing well the language of the country, the language used in all lectures and classes. Bohemian students have, in many cases, proved to have an insufficient knowledge of English, having failed to pass in that subject, and having failed in other subjects just because of poor knowledge of English. The executive committee therefore considers it necessary that every applicant present a report (issued by an accredited high school or an equivalent institution) proving that he has the required knowledge of the English language.</p>
   <p>The applications must be submitted in a special form, the blanks for which <pb facs="5418478_1_0366.jpg" n="4"/>will be furnished upon request addressed to the committee, and must be in the hands of the committee prior to, or on, August 15, 1915. The applications must contain the names of teachers or professors to whom the applicant is well known and to whom the committee may refer for the necessary information concerning the applicant. Letters, inquiries, and applications for loans should be addressed to the secretary of the committee, Mr. P. A. Korab,  Iowa City, Iowa.</p>
   <p>For the executive committee of the Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani:</p>
   <p>B. Simek, president,</p>
   <p>P. A. Korab, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
