<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-20">Feb. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">News from the Chicago School Board</title><title level="a" type="sub">J. A. Holpuch, Member of the School Board Informs Us That our Work is not Without Compensation--Czech Folk Songs Are a Source for Good in our Public School--Military Drills in our Schools-Our School Census</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_0070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-08-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-20">Feb. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE CHICAGO SCHOOL BOARD</title><title level="a" type="sub">J. A. Holpuch, Member of the School Board Informs Us That our Work is not Without Compensation--Czech Folk Songs Are a Source for Good in our Public School--Military Drills in our Schools-Our School Census</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Josef A. Holpuch, a member of the school board, yesterday told us that our work in the interest of public schools and their teachers is nearing fruition.</p>
   <p>Formerly, when we looked over the records of our schools devoted to the preparation of our youth for the teachers' profession, we would find one or two students with Czech names; now you will be confronted with a whole column of names of Czech parentage. These young women and men are devoting their full school time to the proper preparation for a most honored profession--teaching.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0071.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the last half year records of our preparatory schools, we find to our great joy these Czech names listed as future teachers: Helen C. Dusek, Marie A. Hajek, Magdalena Marie Hitzler, Anna Teresie Kessler, Alice Antoinetta Kopal, Jessie J. Plhak, Anezka M. Polka, Helena M. Rezek, and Emilie A. Slama.</p>
   <p>When we consider the number of Czech candidates for teachers positions for only a half-year, we must come to the conclusion that next year the registration of students for the teaching profession will be much greater, and that circumstances will revert to our credit.</p>
   <p>We wish that our young men would take a greater interest in the teaching profession, so that our men would have a larger representation among school teachers.</p>
   <p>According to the records of the school board, entrance examinations to Normal College will be held on June 26 and 27.</p>
   <p>Czech parents should make a note of this announcement, and should see to it that <pb facs="5418478_1_0072.jpg" n="3"/>children with a liking for the teachers profession prepare themselves for those examinations.</p>
   <p>At the same time, examinations for school principals will be held. Examinations for high school teachers will take place for the following subjects: German, Spanish, Latin, French, English, Social Economy, Physiology and Health, Botany, Zoology, Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics, Bookkeeping, Photography, Iron moulding, Black smithing, Wagon making, Machine making, Cabinet making and many other trades. Teachers of all these subjects will be needed in both the high and grammar grades. Teachers of German will be needed in the high schools, and there also will be needed teachers of Gymnastics in both high school and grammar grades, and parental school teachers will be sought.</p>
   <p>Singing is taught in our public schools and special stress is laid upon folk songs; not only American songs are taught, but attention directed to songs of other nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0073.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Czech songs were poorly represented, because we had very few translations, of which our Czech member of the Chicago school board, Josef A. Holpuch, was well aware, and for that reason, a short time ago, when he visited New York, he bought a large number of copies of Czech national and folk songs, arranged by the Reverend Vincence Pisek and published by the Schirmer Publishing Company. These copies Mr. Holpuch distributed among singing teachers, who appreciate very much the helping hand these song books provide in the teaching of the Czech songs.</p>
   <p>Reverend Pisek's compilation of Czech national and folk songs in an extraordinary work from a musical standpoint; it is remarkable for its fine translation, which we can describe as masterly.</p>
   <p>For a very long time the Chicago school board busied itself trying to solve the much debated question of boundaries between the schools at South Center Park Avenue and West 25th Street (Burns), and that situated at South Ridgeway Avenue and 31st Street (Corkery).</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0074.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>These schools are built far from one another and there were instances where large numbers of children who attended the last named school, had to walk eight or nine blocks. The long walks to school were very unpleasant especially in inclement weather, and therefore many complaints, which of course were well founded, were registered with the school board.</p>
   <p>At the last meeting of the Chicago school board, the much needed change was finally effected with the proper demarcation of boundary districts of the two schools. The boundary line is the alley east of South Avers Avenue.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Board of Education also decided to set up a playground bordering the school at West 21st Street and South California Avenue, by removing the last obstacle: a two-story brick house with a stone foundation at 2837 West 21st Place. This building was finally bought for $860, and will be moved in the shortest possible time, so that work on the play-ground may be started, which is to be one of the best equipped and largest playgrounds where Czech children congregate.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_0075.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Referring to the question of play-grounds, another play-ground question was settled at this board meeting. The Gary Public School has no play-ground, and naturally the school board received many complaints from citizens living in the vicinity of the school which is at South Ridgeway Avenue and West 21st Street. Because the school board has no vacant ground in this locality, it opened the rooms of the gymnasium to the citizens and to the students during the winter months for the fostering of games and sports which can be played in-doors; with the stipulation that if any damage to the building or apparatus be incurred, those responsible would be held accountable.</p>
   <p>Four hundred dollars was allowed by the Board to the management of the Carter Harrison High School for a projector of colored pictures, and $118 for the equipment of rooms which will house a branch of the public library. This branch library will be the largest and best equipped of any in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Board of Education acted on the question of the teaching of military tactics to the students of high schools. On this question, which has not <pb facs="5418478_1_0076.jpg" n="7"/>yet reached a deciding point school board members Mr. Holpuch took the negative stand. He believes that the training of the body is as essential to the well being of students, as is the training of the mind; but he does not recommend military training now when the students are burdened with so many studies.</p>
   <p>Compulsory military training proved itself very unpopular with the people of Bohemia. That unpopularity would surely be manifested should we be forced to accept military training in our public schools--especially so among the Czechs. This stand taken by Mr. Holpuch seems to us to be the correct one, and we will dismiss the question without further discussion.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Board of Education will begin taking the school census March 27, the purpose of which is to ascertain the number of children living in Chicago of school age. For this work $38,000 has been appropriated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
