<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-10-21">October 21, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Election Activities Begin.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-10-21">October 21, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">ELECTION ACTIVITIES BEGIN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The election movement is in full swing and even among the Bohemians, the political organizations are beginning to stir. Parades are being arranged, meetings are being called at which speakers expound the principles of the parties and explain the advantage of one or the other platform. The election proclamations usually end with an invitation to the public to attend meetings and learn the questions around which the election battle will revolve, so that they might be able to make an intelligent decision.</p>
   <p>We have no definite information as to how many speakers have been invited to participate in the Bohemian movement, but if we are to judge by previous experiences, we doubt that the public will learn much about political questions from such speeches as the majority of our speakers make.</p>
   <p>We have advised our politicians more than once to avoid speeches such as our Irish fellow-citizens take pleasure in; they think it impossible to <pb facs="5418478_1_1457.jpg" n="2"/>make a political speech without distrust and low attacks upon the candidate of the opposition.</p>
   <p>Our people should not visit the meetings of only one party. If they hear the versions of the speakers of only one party and accept them as correct, can they say that they vote according to their best knowledge?</p>
   <p>Whoever wishes to think independently, must read and hear the explanations of both sides, and compare them in order to decide which principle is better and more advantageous.</p>
   <p>Those speakers who know how to defend the standpoint of their party and have many arguments for their assertions are never bashful in speaking to an opposition party, even if there should appear among them those who would request an explanation of some certain principle.</p>
   <p>If, at political meetings, our people would learn to request of the <pb facs="5418478_1_1458.jpg" n="3"/>speakers explanations of everything, which they do not understand, if every speaker knew that for every assertion made, he would be urged to explain the reason for it, our political meetings would be different. They would become not only entertaining, but at the same time educational. Each one would take pleasure in attending meetings, whether they were Democratic or Republican and from such meetings would spread true political education among the public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
