<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1879-03-24">Mar. 24, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[Meeting of Bohemian Labor Section]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_1_1496</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_1_1496.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1879-03-24">Mar. 24, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[MEETING OF BOHEMIAN LABOR SECTION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting called by the Bohemian Labor Section of the 8th Ward yesterday at the "Telocviene Jednoty Sokol" (Gymnastic Society Sokol) Hall was in all respects successful for the large spacious hall was overfilled, and the meeting was conducted in such an orderly manner as is seldom seen at political gatherings.</p>
   <p>The agent of the section Jiri Cvachoucek called the meeting to order and invited those present to elect a chairman and secretary. Mr. F. B. Zdrubek was elected chairman and Mr. F. Dvorak as Secretary. Citizen M. Baumrukr was the first speaker and expressed himself as very much pleased that the citizens of the 8th ward attended in such numbers in order to hear the Socialist candidates, of which he also is one. He said that he did not seek office of his own accord, but having submitted to the principles of the party and as the party picks its own servants he could not refuse to accept the candidacy. The next speaker was Harry Rubens, saying that friends of freedom are gathering together so they might decide how to bring about the end of slavery of labor. In the manner the Republican Party years ago worked to end slavery of Negroes, we now have a strong Socialist Party which is working to bring about the <pb facs="5418478_1_1497.jpg" n="2"/>emancipation of White slaves. Our Bohemian ancesters in their time overthrew the office holders of Prague, forcing them out of office, and it would be to the advantage of us if we did likewise.</p>
   <p>Citizen Meilbek expressed himself over his happiness because of the unprecedented activity among Bohemians prededing this election and over the number of Bohemian Sections organized in the Socialist Party, and further dwelled on the Socialistic Movement which now encompasses the entire world. Citizen Vytlacil made a motion that "Svornost" be made the official publication of the Bohemian Workingman. This motion was unanimously accepted as excellent.</p>
   <p>After Citizen Kozak invited those present to join the Section the meeting was brought to a close.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
