<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-26">Aug. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Discord in St. Joseph Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0800</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0800.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-26">Aug. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">DISCORD IN ST. JOSEPH PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the past two weeks information has been reaching our office that misunderstandings have enveloped St. Joseph Parish, in Town of Lake. None of these stories have been published because we have been under the impression that the differences would be settled and peace would reign once more.</p>
   <p>Since the matter has reached the columns of the American press of Chicago, we feel that we can no longer keep silent. It is our duty to acquaint our readers with the details.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's, Sunday, editions of the Times-Herald, Tribune and other papers stated that a split had taken place in St. Joseph parish and that over five hundred Polish families had decided to break away from the congregation. This group proposes to build a new church for which lots are supposed to have been purchased.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0801.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To confirm these allegations we have sent out our own reporter to make investigations. From his report we are convinced that certain differences exist in St. Joseph Parish, but that they are not as bad as the American papers allege. There are two reasons for these misunderstandings.</p>
   <p>The cost of building the new church started the misunderstandings. As is known, the present church is made of wood. The parish began to build a brick structure and the work was stopped when the roof was completed. The discontented claim that the original cost of the new church was set at $22,000 and that this cost is now placed at $40,000. This difference in cost is the root of the controversy. M. Kucharozyk, the organist, in the absence of Reverend M. Pyplatz, pastor, was interviewed by our reporter, He said that changes in plans were necessary but that he could not give the figures of the added cost. The true fact is that the leader of the dissension, Mr. Zolkowski, a local contractor, lost out on his bid for construction of the new church to another Polish contractor, It was because of this, according to some sources, that the dispute about the cost of the church was started.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0802.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The second cause of the trouble lies in the fact that Reverend Pyplatz placed Mr. Kucharczyk in charge of the finances of the new church. Many persons opposed to him demanded his removal. They demanded that somebody else manage the finances. For this or other reasons two of the young men's societies were suspended by the pastor.</p>
   <p>The dissatisfied faction threatens to sever its connection with the parish and claims that it has already purchased (or at least made a deal for) a plot of land at 46th and Paulina Streets for a new church. At least this is what is claimed by Mr. Zolkowski. This assertion cannot be taken seriously because there is no-reason for purchasing this land. Mr. Zolkowski did not wish to give our reporter the names of the persons who gave money for purchasing it, nor did he give the names of those interested in it. As to the number of the dissatisfied group, it is evident that it is a small one.</p>
   <p>From these facts one can easily gather that the situation is not as grave as <pb facs="5423968_10_0803.jpg" n="4"/>the Tribune and other papers would have it. Mr. Zolkowski plainly stated that the entire matter could be easily settled to everybody's satisfaction.</p>
   <p>A delegation is to seek an audience with the pastor. A compromise should be and will be reached.</p>
   <p>Private feelings should be set aside. The pastor cannot always choose people that will please everyone--nor can he give ear to all. As can be seen, no wrong has been done the people. In the event that the cost of the church must be increased, it is certain that this increase can be explained and understood. All that is needed is patience, consideration and understanding. The parishioners should understand that warring against the pastor, threatening to build a new church without the permission of the bishop and separating from the parish only leads to the road of schism. On the other hand, Reverend Pyplatz undoubtedly will attempt to settle these differences with tact. In this way the enemies of Catholicism will again be frustrated in their plans.</p>
   <p>We beg the residents of Town of Lake not to take any steps that will bring <pb facs="5423968_10_0804.jpg" n="5"/>about dissension, for we are convinced that no serious difficulties will result from the present misunderstandings. We have reluctantly publicized this trouble. Since other papers gave it space, we consider it our duty to clarify the situation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
