<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-15">Dec. 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Delegation Calls on Senator Lewis</title><title level="a" type="sub">Purpose of Society to Fight Dillingham Bill</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1718</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1718.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-15">Dec. 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DELEGATION CALLS ON SENATOR LEWIS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Purpose of Society to Fight Dillingham Bill</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday a session was held at Senator Lewis' office in the matter of the anti-immigration bill. Representatives of Polish organizations, newspapermen, and prominent Poles of our district took part in this session.</p>
   <p>Those present were: Bishop Paul Rhode; K. Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance; P. Rostenkowski, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union; J. Magdziarz; Election commissioner A. Czarnecki; Judge E. K. Jarecki; Alderman S. Walkowiak; Dr. A. Szwajkart; Dr. E. F. Napieralski; J. Smietanka; Dr. S. R. Pietrowicz; Mr. Szajkowski; Mr. Szwajkart, editor of Dziennik Chicagoski; Mr. Lesnicki, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy; Mr. Chylinski; Mr. Szwaba; Mr. Goralski; Mr. Kolanowski, editor of Dziennik Chicagoski; Attorney Pinderski; <pb facs="5423968_10_1719.jpg" n="2"/>Attorney Mallek; Mr. Lasecki, editor of Dziennik Chicagoski; Mr. Konopa, secretary of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>The above-named leaders met in order to submit to Senator Lewis reasons why the chauvinistic Burnett-Dillingham bill, which is insulting to the memory of great Americans, should be killed in the Senate. The purpose of the bill is to restrict immigration.</p>
   <p>Before Senator Lewis' arrival the above-mentioned group, on the motion of Election Commissioner A. Czarnecki, organized a society for the purpose of fighting immigration restrictions. They elected the following officers: president, Bishop Paul Rhode; first vice-president, Mr. K. Zychlinski, who is president of the Polish National Alliance; second vice-president, Mr. P. Rostenkowski, who is president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union; third vice-president, Mrs. A. Neuman, who is president of the Polish Women's Alliance; fourth vice-president, Mr. Najman, who is president of the Polish Alma Mater; secretary, Election Commissioner A. Czarnecki; and treasurer, Mr. J. Smietanka.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1720.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After the election was completed Senator Lewis arrived and Mr. Smietanka introduced him to all of those present. Then the session was begun.</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis asserted at the outset that he was very glad to have the representatives of the Poles of Chicago call on him, since he had requested that they kindly help him with their suggestions and advice to fight the bill, which he as an American considered decidedly inappropriate and unworthy of a free American.</p>
   <p>"I have asked you gentlemen," ended Senator Lewis, "to discuss this matter with me, because you, occupying the posts that you do and being better acquainted with the soul of the immigrant, his character, and his way of thinking, can give me reasons on the basis of which I can fight this bill successfully."</p>
   <p>The spokesman of the delegation was Bishop Paul Rhode, whose address no doubt had its effect on Senator Lewis.</p>
   <p>"We are opposed to the restrictions embodied in the bill," said Bishop Rhode, <pb facs="5423968_10_1721.jpg" n="4"/>"since these restrictions will not withstand the criticism that they are opposed to the fundamental precepts of personal freedom and the ideals of great men like Washington, Lincoln, and Jefferson. This bill demands that a Slavic immigrant submit to an examination which cannot measure the honesty and sincerety of a given immigrant, his ability to work, or his desire to become a citizen of this country.</p>
   <p>"Experience teaches that it is the educated people, to whom the immigration commissioners would not deny entry according to the Burnett-Dillingham bill, who are much less to be desired by the United States than those whom this bill would affect most.</p>
   <p>"There can be no question of too great an influx of immigrants because the United States has enough room for 500,000,000 people, and we do not yet have a population of 100,000,000.</p>
   <p>"I can understand the attitude of some labor organizations which want to <pb facs="5423968_10_1722.jpg" n="5"/>prevent foreigners from coming into the country by passing the Burnett-Dillingham bill; these organizations are under the impression that if all immigrants are allowed to enter there will be more workers than there are jobs. These organizations do not know, or do not want to know, that the immigrant who comes here has in many cases been enticed by the advertisements of American manufacturers, who through their agents and advertisements in Europe tell about the wonders of America.</p>
   <p>"We are opposed to the admission of criminals, the mentally unbalanced, and the physically underdeveloped, but we firmly maintain that we should make it easier for immigrants of good moral character, who are willing and able to work, to be admitted to America.</p>
   <p>"There is still another question," concluded the speaker, "which I want to take up at this point. The matter of the anti-immigration bill is probably now being pushed forward because of the fact that certain circles fear that after the war is ended there will be a great influx of immigrants into the United States. This argument is erroneous because after the war there will be a <pb facs="5423968_10_1723.jpg" n="6"/>greater need for laborers in Europe than here in America. For the above-stated reasons we are opposed to the Burnett-Dillingham bill."</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis stated in reply that he agreed with these arguments and, having clearly emphasized that he was of the same opinion, asked that they consider what he should do in the event that the Senate should note for certain restrictions which would act as brakes on immigration. He suggested that, in the event that the bill could not be killed in the Senate, at least some concessions be obtained for those wanting to come to the United States--namely, that illiterates be allowed to land in the United States, on condition that they agree to spend three years farming, not working im American cities, and that after three years they begin to pay for these farms.</p>
   <p>Bishop Rhode, however, was of the opinion that even such a restriction would be inappropriate, especially if such a colonizing commission were composed of people unacquainted with immigration problems. He called Senator Lewis' attention to the fact that the mere posing of the question is unfair. He did this by asking the Senator a series of questions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1724.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Bishop Rhode: "Is not such a restriction an act against personal liberty?"</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis: "It unquestionably is!"</p>
   <p>Bishop Rhode: "What will happen to the family if its provider dies before the three-year term is up?"</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis: "The mother will remain!"</p>
   <p>Bishop Rhode: "And if the mother is unable to work, as is very probable?"</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis: "This really is a difficult question to answer."</p>
   <p>Bishop Rhode: "Would the Government so group the nationalities that, for example, the Poles would not find themselves in a district of people speaking a language entirely foreign to them?"</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis: "I suppose so."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1725.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Bishop Rhode: "Will the Government appoint people to such a colonizing commission who know the Polish language and the customs of the Polish people?"</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis: "Naturally!"</p>
   <p>Bishop Rhode: "Nevertheless, no Slavs have been appointed to the Immigration Commission, which deals solely with immigrants."</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis: "No! I do not know why this was not done."</p>
   <p>Bishop Rhode: "Would it not be better, since the Government fears too great an influx of immigrants into the cities, to colonize first those who have been living in America for some time?"</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis: "In that case the farms would go to the natives, not to those of whom we are speaking. For this reason it seems to me that this would not be a good plan."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1726.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Bishop Rhode: "Your answer, Senator, confirms my earlier statement that all restrictions will cause unimaginable harm to the Slavs who want to settle here. Every modification of this bill must in its result be disadvantageous to the immigrants and, therefore, to the natives. For this reason I presume that you cannot take any other stand but that of opposition to the Burnett-Dillingham bill."</p>
   <p>After short speeches by several others of those present, Senator Lewis declared that he would do everything in his power to prevent harm being done to those coming to America.</p>
   <p>With this the session was closed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
