<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-05">Jan. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Poor Illiterates</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1708</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1708.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-05">Jan. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE POOR ILLITERATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As is well known, an amendment to the immigration laws was passed recently by the Senate. This amendment prohibits the entrance into the country of all immigrants unable to pass an intelligence test, that is, unable to read and write. So much has already been written on these intelligence tests and the nonsensical measure that it seems as if nothing more can be added.</p>
   <p>However, it is worth while to pause for a moment and consider the reasons why this measure was passed in the Senate. Sixty per cent of the senators, who are openly opposed to the Chief Executive, wanted to show their solidarity by running counter to the will of the President, who was against adoption of the amendment forbidding illiterates to enter into this country.</p>
   <p>The pressure exerted by labor unions on the Senate (this fact is openly admitted) is also responsible for the passage of this bill. The union leaders, in their blind rage at immigration in general, would rather have people perish from <pb facs="5423968_10_1709.jpg" n="2"/>hunger and abuse elsewhere than allow them to compete against an organized group of workers. The reason why the leaders of labor unions favor this bill is that they know that the less skilled immigrants are hard to fetter under the yoke of their unions. Illiteracy, which could be combated through evening schools and books, is just an excuse.</p>
   <p>It is doubtful whether this bill will ever become law. President Wilson will certainly veto it. If he does, he will find the sincere approval of the working people in the United States. The working class wants protection against exploitation by the capitalists, but is not always in agreement with the tactics and accomplishments of union leaders who grow fat on the hard-earned money of the workers. A mere knowledge of writing or reading does not determine the actual worth of an immigrant.</p>
   <p>This bill has nothing to offer in the way of improving economic conditions in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
