<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-11">Mar. 11, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Parishioners of St. Hedwig Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0905</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0905.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-11">Mar. 11, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE PARISHIONERS OF ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brothers! Once more we appeal to you, and once again we beg the parishioners who have strayed from the path of the church to return to unity!</p>
   <p>We do not hold your faith in doubt, nor do we doubt your attachment to the holy church. The mistakes which have been committed by you can easily be atoned for through sorrow and prayer. We do not hold you responsible for the scandal which was not so much your fault as it was the fault of a few leaders.</p>
   <p>Perceive, along with us, our mistakes; seek, as the blind, that which we have lost.</p>
   <p>Let us recall to mind the services that have been and are being celebrated in the old country during this Lenten period; let us recall to mind the many times <pb facs="5423968_10_0906.jpg" n="2"/>we have attended the services of the Stations of the Cross and the Psalms of Lamentation with our mothers and fathers, and compare those times with our present situation. How sad and lonely it is for us in this strange land; for instead of suffering with Jesus Christ we are giving ourselves to willfulness.</p>
   <p>Let us not crucify Christ any longer, brothers! Return to the Lord of Lords through the act of contrition.</p>
   <p>Our most reverend archbishop is ready to return to us at a moment's notice that which we have lost. He is ready to open the doors of our holy temple where as Christians we may pray in Polish.</p>
   <p>Return, therefore, from the road of condemnation, dear brothers, and harmony, unity and peace will be our blessing. With the aid of the new priests which the archbishop will assign to our parish we will be able shortly to wipe away the existing blemish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0907.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In order to realize our desires, however, we must take measures to prevent any further disturbances in the parish. Caution is now more necessary than ever, because the evil-minded people lie in wait for an opportunity to start new agitations. It is imperative to prevent this, and to separate the wild seed from the good.</p>
   <p>For this reason we declare that, in the event St. Hedwig Church is opened, only those having a ticket of admission will be admitted. Do not be offended by this procedure. This is not a sign of distrust directed at the honest and worthy parishioners. This method is directly aimed at the agitators, and it will remove them.</p>
   <p>This is the wish of the archbishop and should be respected. These tickets of admission will be discontinued when signs of harmony prevail.</p>
   <p>These tickets may be obtained at the home of A. Barczynski, secretary of the parish committee, 1030 Hoyne Avenue. Protect yourselves and stick to one flock, <pb facs="5423968_10_0908.jpg" n="4"/>and in this way you will have demonstrated that the attachment to the church was not broken.</p>
   <p>To this we wish to add that a general meeting will be held tomorrow evening at 8 o'clock in Kortas' Hall, Robey and Frankfurt Streets. All faithful sons of the Roman Catholic Church are cordially invited to attend.</p>
   <p>For the Committee,</p>
   <p>A. Glowczewski,</p>
   <p>A. Barczynski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
