<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-26">Aug. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Reverend Rogalski, C. R., Celebrates First Mass at St. Hedwig Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0805</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0805.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-26">Aug. 26, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">REVEREND ROGALSKI, C. R., CELEBRATES FIRST MASS AT ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, Sunday, members of St. Hedwig Parish had occasion to witness a touching event in their church. This was the solemn celebration of the first Mass by Reverend Stanislaus Rogalski, C. R., a priest of this parish.</p>
   <p>At ten A. M., as the bells pealed out the last call, Reverend Rogalski was escorted to the altar.</p>
   <p>The services were started by the singing of the parish choir, under the direction of Stanislaus Bieganowski. Then the parish committee, headed by its president, Mr. Fruzyna, took its place. It was followed by the school girls of the parish, dressed in white and carrying bouquets of fresh flowers. Reverend Rogalski was escorted by two rows of boys, followed by visiting priests.</p>
   <p>During the singing by the parish choir, the celebrant and his assistants, <pb facs="5423968_10_0806.jpg" n="2"/>Reverend John Piechowski, pastor of St. Hedwig Church, who acted as deacon, and Reverend Hyacinth Obyrtacz, who acted as subdeacon, were brought before the alter by Reverend Dr. Joseph Bieli, master of ceremonies.</p>
   <p>Soon afterward the Mass was started.</p>
   <p>After the reading of the gospel, Reverend Dr. Biela [sic] delivered the sermon. He spoke with reverent feeling about the value of the priesthood.</p>
   <p>After the conclusion of the Mass, Reverend Rogalski officiated at his first blessing rites when he blessed his parents and then the entire congregation.</p>
   <p>The entire ceremony was an impressive one and one that will be long remembered.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
