<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-07">May 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Fire Destroys Polish Church</title><title level="a" type="sub">Immaculate Conception Church in South Chicago Destroyed--Incendiarism Hinted</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1005</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1005.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-05-07">May 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">FIRE DESTROYS POLISH CHURCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">Immaculate Conception Church in South Chicago Destroyed--Incendiarism Hinted</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon, after the solemn service was over at the Church of the Immaculate Conception, 87th Street and Commercial Avenue, a woman remained in the church for some time after the service, and as some say, she sat there all alone, absorbed in prayer with closed eyes. Suddenly she opened her eyes and noticed that the main altar was afire. This frightened her, and she fled. A boy whose name is John Derpa saw her running out of the church, and he, noticing flames later on, alarmed the neighbors. The church committee was still in the basement finishing its daily work. The members of the committee ran out, and in a few minutes there was a crowd of people. In the meantime the fire department arrived.</p>
   <p>The fire enveloped the building with alarming rapidity. The Reverend Father Zaleski, the pastor of the church, and the sisters tried to save the most <pb facs="5423968_10_1006.jpg" n="2"/>precious and most sacred vessels and articles, but in vain. All attempts in this direction had to be abandoned, and the parishioners were obliged stand idly watching the fire. The fire department, which came not only from local stations but also from Grand Crossing, Hyde Park, and Englewood, had to limit its activities to protecting adjacent buildings against the flames. One sister tried to get into the sacristy, fell down, and sustained slight injuries.</p>
   <p>Many parishioners looked at this terrible sight with great sorrow. Some of them wept, seeing that the holy temple which they had built by their own efforts would be ravaged by flames; others made threats, suspecting a certain faction in the parish of incendiarism, and still others questioned Derpa about the woman whom he saw running out of the church, asking him where she went, and how she behaved. Many persons suspected her of starting the fire, but no one could establish her identity.</p>
   <p>The flames, as we have stated, spread with great rapidity and reached the tower, which leaned over. Several firemen were standing right under the tower, <pb facs="5423968_10_1007.jpg" n="3"/>and it looked as if it was going to fall and crush them. A loud shout of warning was raised; they were asked to stop aside. However, the firemen remained at their posts, for it was necessary in order to save the neighborhood. The tower [finally] fell toward the center of the church and injured no one.</p>
   <p>The whole church building burned down completely, and with it were destroyed pictures, statues, and holy vessels; very little was saved. The loss is estimated between $35,000 and $40,000 if we take under consideration the church furniture, etc. The church building was insured for $23,000.</p>
   <p>On that afternoon this parish was going to commemorate Kosciuszko's centennial anniversary, but after such a catastrophe the celebration was abandoned.</p>
   <p>The police, because of the rumors, have a suspicion that the fire was started by an incendiary and are still making investigations. It seems that it will not be hard to discover the identity of the woman in question, and that probably she is the incendiary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1008.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Reverend Father Zaleski has not been quite well for some time, and on that day he was so much depressed that he declined to see his friends and other callers who came out of curiosity or to express their sympathy.</p>
   <p>The parishioners have decided to erect a new brick church in place of the old one.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
