<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No.241,
<date when="1905-10-16">Oct. 16, 1905</date><title level="a">From the Parish of St. Florian</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No.241,
<date when="1905-10-16">Oct. 16, 1905</date><title level="a">FROM THE PARISH OF ST. FLORIAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon at 2 o'clock people gathered in the new school hall of St. Flerian, located at Superior and Bickerdike, to hear the paster of this new Polish Catholic church, Most Rev. Father John Zwievzchowski read Archbishop Quigley's letter giving his consent and permission to open this parish. Father Zwievzchowski explained the Archbishop's letter in full detail. Over two hundred Polish people were present at this celebration. "This was the best behaved group of people that I have ever seen," said Father Zwievzchowski.</p>
   <p>The people listened to the Father's beautiful and elaberate speech and applauded his good intentions for this parish in the future. They settled the most important business, because the beginning of such an institution calls for hard work; that is why the pastor took this opportunity to choose seven reliable men with the consent of those present, to aid him.</p>
   <p>Their duties will be to receive and set-up the altar, the pews, the pulpit etc. They were also informed to organize church societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0267.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first steps will be to organize a church society under the name of St. Florian, then the society of St.Joseph; the pastor is trying to organize societies for women.</p>
   <p>The school will be opened Tuesday under the supervision of the Nazarethan Sisters. The school is completely finished, and furnished up-to-date.</p>
   <p>Mass will begin Wednesday, for the time being they will be held in the school hall, until the church is completely finished on the interior. The blessing and consecration of this church will be held the second Sunday of November.</p>
   <p>Every one is asked to do their utmost to help this parish grow as fast as possible. Judging by the work of our Most. Rev. Father Zwierzchewski, we can see that this church will be a huge success and the debt will soon be paid off.</p>
   <p>It is hard to believe that before this church was erected, most of the Polish Catholics attended a German church, but now most of these are members of St. Florian, and many more are expected to join before long.</p>
   <p>The new church organ was installed and will be blessed at the same time <pb facs="5423968_10_0268.jpg" n="3"/>as the church. The organist is Mr. J.Banaszowski. Children between the ages of sixteen and twenty-five are asked to join the church choir.</p>
   <p>J. Zwievzchowski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
