<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No.120,
<date when="1905-05-23">May 23, 1905</date><title level="a">Polish Youngsters Marching Out to the Cemetery on Memorial Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item><item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No.120,
<date when="1905-05-23">May 23, 1905</date><title level="a">POLISH YOUNGSTERS MARCHING OUT TO THE CEMETERY ON MEMORIAL DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is known that the Polish youngsters have reorganized cadet groups at three parishes, they are: St. Stanislaus Society of Cadets, at St. Stanislaus; Society of Cadets of St. George, at St. J. Canisisis; Society of Cadets of Kosciuszko, under the guardianship of St. Hedwigs parish.</p>
   <p>These groups have promised that May 30, Memorial Day, they will visit the cemetery where many of our brothers, sisters, fathers and mothers are resting in peace;the most important part of their march is to visit and decorate the grave of our most Rev. Father Vincent Barzynski, a true Polish patriot.</p>
   <p>The program for the march is as follows: At 7 o'clock in the morning the Society of Cadets of St. George at the parish of St. John Cantius, will join the Cadets of St. Stanislaus, and then march to St. Hedwigs where they will join the Cadets of Kosciuszko. At the Norwood Park station they will unfold their flags and Polish banners and march to pay tribute at the monument of the Most Rev. Father Vincent Barzynski, where the cadets will hear a mass and a sermon, after which the cadets will fire a salute to pay honor to our most reverend father and to our Polish veterans, they they will pay honor to the heroes of American wars by firing a volley at their graves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1473.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After all the honor is paid to our heroes and our beloved, the cadets will march to the west end of the cemetery where they will eat and drink and spend the remainder of this great day in enjoying themselves.</p>
   <p>Leon Ulatowski</p>
   <p>Peter Grabowski</p>
   <p>Committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
