<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-22">Dec. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish National Alliance and the Immigration Question</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1712</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1712.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-12-22">Dec. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE AND THE IMMIGRATION QUESTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Board of Directors of the Polish National Alliance, keeping its hand on the pulse of our national life in a foreign land and carefully watching over our interests, is always the first to come forward in the defense of the rights and privileges of our emigres. The Central Board of Directors, among other things, carefully watches the immigration question now being batted about in Congress and does what it can to prevent the passing of the Dillingham-Burnett Anti-immigration Bill.</p>
   <p>Recently the Board of Directors sent its representative, in the person of Adam Gregorowicz, of Baltimore, Maryland, to the General Immigration Conference held in Washington. The report of the representative of the Polish National Alliance in this matter is as follows:</p>
   <p>Baltimore, Maryland</p>
   <p>December 13, 1914.</p>
   <p>Central Board of Directors</p>
   <p>Polish National Alliance</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1713.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>In accordance with the recommendation of December 9, of the Central Board of Directors, I was present yesterday and registered as a representative of the Polish National Alliance at the General Immigration Conference of the Southern Commercial Congress. The conference was held at the New Willard Hotel and lasted from 10 A.M. to 12 midnight. I was present at all three sessions and at President Wilson's reception at the White House, and listened to all the speeches and debates.</p>
   <p>The problem of the conference was to discuss ways and means of settling the vacant farm lands in the Southern states with immigrants from the Northern states, Canada, and Europe.</p>
   <p>About fifty people were present at the conference, for the most part representatives of Southern states, railroad companies which deal with colonization projects, and immigration societies. The speakers included those listed on the program and others among those present who <pb facs="5423968_10_1714.jpg" n="3"/>were selected beforehand and invited to the platform.</p>
   <p>From the speeches and debates I have taken down the following more important points: The Department of Labor, through its information bureau, accepts applications from persons needing employment and from farmers and factory owners who need workers. It announces this information in the form of bulletins, which are distributed to and displayed in all the post offices. Nevertheless, in the matter of farm help, the general conviction was that one cannot expect to turn the immigrants toward the farms as laborers. If we want to settle the vacant lands, we should help the immigrant acquire the land as his own property. In this direction the chief director of the Southern Commercial Congress announced that the projected law of Government help in the form of long-term loans is already in Congress. However nothing was said about the settling of Government lands. For information on that subject one must continue to inquire, as up to the present, of the Commissioner of the land office. There is very little Government land in the Southern states; the State of Florida has the most. The discussion concerned the settlement of land in general, that is, private and Government. The <pb facs="5423968_10_1715.jpg" n="4"/>greatest possibilities, from what one could deduce from the speeches, are to be found in the states of North and South Carolina.</p>
   <p>The representative of the State of Louisiana, a Frenchman, stated that in his state the social system and temperament of the inhabitants (offspring of French ancestors) more closely resemble those of Europe than those of any other state in America, and that the Italian, Belgian, and Slavic colonies already established there are developing splendidly. The climate is excellent, and the city of New Orleans, a port (on the Gulf of Mexico), has a good future because of the Panama Canal. This would be worth considering. There are about 23,000,000 acres of vacant land. For more detailed information one can apply to the Department of Agriculture, or to the State Department of Agriculture.</p>
   <p>One can receive a great deal of information about good opportunities from the railroad companies. Sixty-two railroad companies are interested in the colonization of their lands.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1716.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It was also the general opinion of those present that it is not the immigrant's fault that he does not settle on a farm. He is not informed of this by the specific states which have the right to advertise their lands--and if private individuals, colonization associations, or immigration societies were to advertise in Europe, they would be breaking a federal law and would be subject to legal suits.</p>
   <p>Therefore, toward the end of the discussion a resolution was adopted in which it was proposed to change this law so that chambers of commerce and boards of trade would be allowed to advertise the lands in their specific districts. A committee of five was also appointed which is to remain in Washington for several days and [which], taking advantage of the various ideas suggested, is to work out a plan to help the immigrants settle on Southern lands.</p>
   <p>When I receive the report of this committee and the minutes of the conference I will send them to the Central Board of Directors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1717.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>As is underlined on the program which I am enclosing, Governor Blease of South Carolina spoke. He made a fool of himself as usual by attacking the clergy and by his obscure generalizing phrases. When he was applauded it was only through indulgence. Notorious Congressman Burnett, author of the new bill, was also present. He spoke oftener than he should have, for which he received rather unpleasant remarks from those whose speeches he kept interrupting with his interpolations. He showed himself to be an ordinary ward politician--rather a demagogue. He had only one speaker on his side. The literacy clause and the contract labor clause were condemned in general by practically everyone who spoke on this subject. Senator Fletcher was chairman, and I believe that the Senate will learn of this general opinion of the conference.</p>
   <p>Remarks about Poles were rather complimentary. Dr. Roberts, especially, spoke very highly of the Poles in his speech, for which later I personally thanked him in the name of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>Adam S. Gregorowicz</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
