<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-15">Mar. 15, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">St. Hedwig Church Opened; New Agitations Started</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0900</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0900.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-15">Mar. 15, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ST. HEDWIG CHURCH OPENED; NEW AGITATIONS STARTED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>New and important developments took place at St. Hedwig Parish during yesterday and today.</p>
   <p>By an order issued by the archbishop of Chicago, which was prompted by a petition signed by a large number of parishioners, St. Hedwig Church was opened for services yesterday.</p>
   <p>Mass was celebrated by Reverend E. Sedlaczek at 8 A. M. Many members of the parish attended. After the services, Reverend Sedlaczek took charge of the parish rectory. No disturbances occurred.</p>
   <p>During the afternoon and evening, however, trouble was started anew by the deceitful agitators. Meetings were held by them at which violent threats were voiced. A desire was also expressed to stage an attack on the rectory last <pb facs="5423968_10_0901.jpg" n="2"/>night, but this did not materialize. Finally, it was decided to start an assault on the parish rectory this morning.</p>
   <p>At approximately 8 A. M. this morning a group of agitators entered the vestry just as Reverend Sedlaczek made his entrance, preparatory to the celebration of Mass. These would-be disturbers were disposed of in short order. The 8 o'clock services took place without interruption. Over four hundred persons attended.</p>
   <p>A large mob of people, mostly women and boys, gathered about the church, intent on starting some kind of commotion. The police on duty in this vicinity prevented any disturbances.</p>
   <p>No active violence occurred, and no one was hurt. The police arrested only three women and one boy, the noisiest persons in the crowd. Shortly afterwards, the crowd dispersed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0902.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the time this article is going to press, peace prevails at the parish. Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek is in charge of the rectory. Services at St. Hedwig Church will be resumed tomorrow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
