<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-23">Feb. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Arrival of Reverend Paul Rhode</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-02-23">Feb. 23, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ARRIVAL OF REVEREND PAUL RHODE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About five years after the church had been built, [St. Michael Archangel] Parish gradually began to grow. Reverend [Adolph]Nowicki left St. Michael's [Church] and was succeeded by the young, newly-ordained Reverend [Paul] Rhode. He was very young, and it was said of him. that he looked like an 18-year-old youth full of spirit and enthusiasm. He worked in such a manner that he made his parish one of the best and most widely known of the Polish parishes. He was undoubtedly helped in his work by many splendid men, like John Chemma, who distinguished himself by his service and who died in 1900. Three years later another worthy citizen, Francis Przybylinski, followed him. This deprived the parish of two zealous workers.</p>
   <p>In 1905 Jan Lange came to the parish as vicar, but left eight months later.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, despite many changes, the parish continued to grow, until the <pb facs="5423968_10_0081.jpg" n="2"/>need for a new church arose. Through the efforts of Reverend Rhode work was begun on an imposing church in 1906. Three years later, while the new church was still in the process of construction, a great honor befell this parish. Its rector [Paul Rhode] was elevated to the bishopric, henceforth bearing the title of "First Polish Bishop in America." The church was completed in the same year, and was solemnly consecrated on June 23, [1909].</p>
   <p>In 1910 one of the former pupils of this parish, Reverend John Grembowicz, was ordained. Two years later Reverend Vincent Nowicki was also called upon to serve in the Lord's vineyard. In 1912 the newly-ordained Reverend Francis Walczak came to our parish and still continues to be one of the most energetic workers that our parish has ever had or will have. A year later, on Easter Monday, Reverend Francis Kozlowski was ordained. That the parish turns out fine young men is demonstrated by the fact that Reverend Kozlowski, although very young, has already been given a parish.</p>
   <p>And so for many years everything increased in God's bounty and blessing, until <pb facs="5423968_10_0082.jpg" n="3"/>the sad news reached us that Bishop [Paul Rhode] had been appointed to the See at Green Bay, Wisconsin, and would have to leave us. Sincere sadness and regret descended upon us on receipt of this news, because everyone was happy under the tenderly watchful eye of our shepherd, and it was difficult to reconcile oneself with the thought of parting. But, as the bishop himself said, it is God's will. Therefore on September 2, 1915, our Bishop left this parish after 18 years of caring for the souls of the people here, and another change occurred. Reverend John Lange came to take the Bishop's place, but this time as rector, and Reverend Felix Prange came with him. Later Reverend Bolinski and Reverend Francis Mazur came and, together with Reverend Walczak, continue to help the present rector in his parish work.</p>
   <p>Shortly before the bishop's departure other changes occurred. Through the death of Otyllia Chemma, the parish lost one of its most pious and exemplary women, and the Sodality lost one of its best superiors.</p>
   <p>The following year Mary Gorzelmanna, another well-known parishioner who had <pb facs="5423968_10_0083.jpg" n="4"/>done much for the good of the parish and the Sodality, died.</p>
   <p>This concludes the inspiring history of the twenty-five years of existence of St. Michael Archangel's Parish. And thus we today, together with the few remaining founders of this parish, reach back with our thoughts to the parish's beginnings, as twenty-five years hence our children will talk and write about us. Just as we today are informing the world about the deeds of our fathers and mothers, they will record our activities. May our deeds in retrospect be shown to be as praiseworthy as those of the founders of this parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
