<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-12">May 12, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Catholic Congress in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-12">May 12, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH CATHOLIC CONGRESS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today we can reassure all our readers that the Polish Catholic Congress, in spite of adverse gossip and insinuations, is on its way to a successful realization.</p>
   <p>The Buffalo committee, as can be seen from the appeals it has published in our newspaper, is working energetically.</p>
   <p>Societies and parishes in an increasing number are signifying their decision to take part in this congress. </p>
   <p>Finally, our West, which heretofore had done little about this matter, according to information from private sources, in the next few days will begin working in a manner befitting the importance of the occasion. We cannot divulge particulars regarding this movement at this time. In a few days, however, all the particulars will be published.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0493.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To the best of our knowledge everybody is in the best of spirits.</p>
   <p>The Polish Clergy understands the importance of the Polish Catholic Congress and will not want to spoil, on account of minor misunderstandings or personal grievances, an action so important for the general good.</p>
   <p>We are certain of this.</p>
   <p>We wish to note also that the date originally chosen for the congress may eventually be changed. It depends on many practical reasons. Information about this and all other matters pertaining to the congress will be published for the information of all Polish Catholics in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
