<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. 16. No.161.
<date when="1905-07-12">July 12, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Convent of the "Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0274.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. 16. No.161.
<date when="1905-07-12">July 12, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Convent of the "Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>July 6th, 1905, is marked particularly, for the meeting of the "Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth". This was the 20th anniversary of the arrival of Sister Superior Marie M. F.Siedliski, founder of this order. In the year 1885 she had forsaken her work at the parishes of St.Adalbert and St.Josaphat of which she was a member of the committee responsible for their founding, to organize this a home for the "Sisters of Holy Family of Nazareth". In a short time new Sisters joined this order; the sphere of work and activity expanded so greatly that today the Sisters of this order have twenty parishes in their fold and teach over 17,000 children not only the regular parochial school program, but teach them also the love of Church and Fatherland who strengthened with this spirit become a joy and comfort to their parents and country.</p>
   <p>Archbishop J.E.Symon blessed this day by conducting a Mass and offering Holy Communion and blessings upon these Sisters for their wonderful gathering and the recollection of their undying work to fulfill this great mission.</p>
   <p>In his beautiful speech he praised this great day, as a day of celebration for the faithful work of the founder of this order Sister Superior M.F.Siedliski <pb facs="5423968_10_0275.jpg" n="2"/>whom he had known many years before she had organized and founded this Order of Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth. He bestowed upon the Sisters his blessing for a speedy and profitable development.</p>
   <p>After finishing his speech of praise he gave over 150 holy pictures to the Sisters as a remembrance of this great occasion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
