<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 28,
<date when="1912-07-10">July 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Truth and Falsehood</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 28,
<date when="1912-07-10">July 10, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">TRUTH AND FALSEHOOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What Catholicism is to free thinking, such is truth in comparison with falsehood.</p>
   <p>What truth is to falsehood, so a Catholic is in comparison to a non-believer. Every free thinker is at the same time a non-believer, just as every liar is a pharisee and a hypocritical person. The man who is bold enough to take faith away from another, becomes a murderer and criminal. Just as light disperses darkness, so truth makes a falsehood worthless or contemptible, as the night is the opposite to day so a lying person is opposite to a rightful person.</p>
   <p>It is easier to avoid a foe lying in wait for your fortune, liberty and life than a false person, because that one pretends to be a sweet person, your friend, he entices, decoys, hugs you and kiss you, but in his heart he has hidden treachery and in his soul he is hiding a falsehood. On the other hand, a person who loves truth sometime suffers because he does not know how to lie and does not want to lie, rather <pb facs="5423968_10_0138.jpg" n="2"/>he wishes to act honorably and in a dignified manner, doing the proper thing always and everywhere.</p>
   <p>There are people who, as it is said, are always walking around with a sweet look. A sweet smile on his face, warm words on his lips, gives many promises and imagines a brother and friend, until you finally convince yourself in a short while that all this was only pretended, and the one whom you thought wished you best, somewhere else acted to your detriment. The one who praised you before your eyes, when out of sight blackened you, ridiculed you and talked about you. The one that praised your national principles and your outlook in regard to the enemies of the fatherland, in another place works against you.</p>
   <p>Oh! These are sad things, nevertheless true. What is worse is that the influence of falsehood is not only bad at the present time, but it also acts worse on the future. A hypocritical and false person lies to me and to you, to himself and to the nation. Is it any wonder that that person later on loses his faith, conceals his emotions and is afraid to be sincere, open? Oh! Today the people say, now the world is bad, today <pb facs="5423968_10_0139.jpg" n="3"/>a child does not trust its own father, the mother does not believe the child, the people do not trust anybody, and nobody believes in the sincerity of the people.</p>
   <p>Who is at fault? If we would never go the way of falsehood but that of truth, then we would have the great power of the virtue and courage of condemning all hypocritical persons.</p>
   <p>Also, more than once it seems, through courtesy, hospitality or delicacy, we assent to this one or promise to that one, we are unable to repel from ourselves people that are hypocritical and we permit this ignominious fault to grow and enlarge itself. The only remedy for this is the truth. The one who acts at all times honorably, avoids evil, and seeks the good, the one who honorably offers his hand and repels from himself a traitor and liar, that one is loved and respected by honorable people. But is there very many of this kind in our midst? Falsehood and hypocricy have unfortunately so rooted themselves among us that little children oftimes know how to delude and lie, and we looking upon this do not wring out hands with despair and do not call out with fear, What will become of this, instead we claim, The world is such at this time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0140.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Oh no! The world is not false.</p>
   <p>Because the world is a genuine truth in which neither trees nor mountains, herds nor flowers but people have evil hearts, and it is they who drive the truth away from their lives. Truth is the most beautiful virtue. It brings harmony and love, trust and honesty; it can make us the strongest nation spiritually.</p>
   <p>Then, let us put aside falsehood and hypocrisy; Let us behave the way good Chrstians should behave and then we will not allow ourselves to be led off the straight forward path on to the dark road of hatred and anger, rather looking in the glorious rays of truth, we will find success in honesty.</p>
   <p>Let us cast aside those free thinking illusions which only bring us shame and disgrace and let us hold on to the traditions of our forefathers and let us be like they were, good Polish Catholics, and the truth will liberate us from this misfortune.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
