<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-18">June 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Poles Give Proof of Loyalty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-06-18">June 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLES GIVE PROOF OF LOYALTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>And again the Poles have given eloquent proof of their patriotism! The parade staged day before yesterday, which moved down Milwaukee Avenue, Randolph, La Salle, and State Streets to the general recruiting headquarters at 526 South State Street, was successful and imposing in every respect, thanks to the participation of the Polish women.</p>
   <p>Those who saw the parade will probably have its main attraction permanently impressed upon their memories--a living American flag formed by members of the Polish Girls' Aid for Girls Society, well known for its patriotic work.</p>
   <p>People of other nationalities marvelled at Polonia's attachment to American traditions and the ideals of this country. Downtown, Americans could be heard to make such remarks as, "How patriotic these Poles are!" and so on, while everywhere storms of applause greeted the living flag and the volunteers who will leave for the training camp at Jefferson Barracks, Missouri.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1390.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The gathering point for the participants in the parade was the Polish Roman Catholic Union building, Milwaukee Avenue and Augusta Street. The parade order was as follows: two mounted policemen; the Kipkowski Brothers' orchestra; the St. Mary of the Angels Parish Scouts, led by F. C. Kukowinski of the Boy Scouts of America and his assistant, H. Roszkowski; representatives of all of the Polish organizations; the American flag, carried by Private John Nowak, with Privates Andrew Bialon and Peter Wostyn as guards; the living flag, formed by the Polish Girls' Aid for Girls Society, led by Miss E. Napieralski, followed by the recruits, numbering over a hundred men, who left for Jefferson Barracks the same evening.</p>
   <p>[List of volunteers who carried placards with inscriptions omitted by translator.]</p>
   <p>Among the citizens who participated in the parade were: John Konopa, Peter Rostenkowski, president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, Judge <pb facs="5423968_10_1391.jpg" n="3"/>Edmund K. Jarecki, Casimir Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance, Stanislaus Orpiszewski, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, K. Wiechecki, A. Dziegielewski, Teofil T. Weyna, B. Mindak, Stanislaus Kuflewski, Leon C. Nyka, A. Bisek, Joseph Niemiec, Albert Menkicki, general vice-president of the Polish Alma Mater, W. Konopa, S. C. Cyzio, Walter Wieckowski, Joseph Karwowski, W. Konecki, A. Swiadowski, Vincent Wosciekowski, W. Lysakowski, Anthony Skowronski, Albert Wolski, L. Kowalski, John Jachimowski, Michael Rudnicki, J. Antecki, A. Skibinski, S. Stemin, Marion Sowinski of Gary, Indiana, S. Pitera, M. Kudlick, C. Kaletta, J. Kielinski, A. Bona, F. Skupniewicz, K. O. Hajdukiewicz, J. Sarem, F. Niec, J. Salamonski, J. Bogac, W. Gawrys, L. Marcinowski, M. Tronicki, G. Noruk, L. Lachowicz, M. Drozdowicz, W. Wolak, D. Kaminski, J. Gierczyk, J. Iwanik, Mrs. M. Milewski and Mrs. M. Sakowski, of the women's division of the Polish National Alliance, Mrs. Mary Osuch and F. Czaja, members of the Polish Roman Catholic Union board of directors, Bertha Roda, Mrs. Julia Wisniewski, Mrs. K. Dylewski, Wanda Rajchez, Mrs. S. C. Szwec, Mrs. R. Kleczewski, Mrs. F. Olinski, Mrs. Sophie Blachowski, Emily Szlag, Helen Kilar, and Elizabeth Swiatkowski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1392.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Names of the members of the Girls' Aid for Girls Society who participated in forming the living flag will appear in tomorrow's issue, as will further details of this unusual feature.</p>
   <p>In the evening, a dance was held at the Polish Women's Alliance building in honor of the Girls' Aid for Girls Society in recognition of its work. A selected company danced to the strains of Professor Krotochwil's orchestra, and generally enjoyed itself until late at night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
