<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-14">Apr. 13, 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Fiftieth Anniverisary of the Order of the Resurrection Fathers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1191</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1191.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-14">Apr. 13, 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIFTIETH ANNIVERISARY OF THE ORDER OF THE RESURRECTION FATHERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The reign of Miecislaus brought about the birth and growth of the last pure Polish monastic Order, and never in our later past centuries of historical events was there given a thought to the idea that another Order would be organized. Today, we the children of our forefathers have seen another Order come to life under the skilled guidance of Fathers Kajsiewicz and Semenenko. Even though shortly after this Order came into being many more clerical institutions of this type were formed, at present we have more convents than monasteries.</p>
   <p>Never before did a Polish ecclesiastical Order give any thought to the difficult task of sending missionaries out among people of another faith. No consideration was given to the finding of recruits willing to sacrifice their lives as pioneers of the Catholic religion. The founding of the <pb facs="5423968_10_1192.jpg" n="2"/>Order of the Resurrection Fathers by Fathers Kajsiewicz and Semenenko gave impetus to this missionary work in other countries. After the followers of the originators reformed some parts of Bulgaria, they directed their activities to the training of priests for this work and sent many of them across the seas to the United States and Canada to reform the Poles, Slovaks, and Germans. They not only came to America to preach their theological doctrines, but also organized parishes and built churches.</p>
   <p>Literature and teachings of the Church that remained dormant during the eighteenth and the first half of the present certury began to awaken and take on new life. Soon the eloquence of the Church, under the skill of Father O. Kajsiewicz, entered into a golden epoch.</p>
   <p>In spite of many hardships and hindrances, the flower of Catholicism in our country had its drooping petals revived, and today it is blossoming more than ever before.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1193.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The other scattered religious factions naturally were not asleep. As soon as the Catholic missionaries began to emigrate to other countries to preach their doctrines to their co-nationals abroad, the opposing Orders sent out their disciples with orders to beat the Catholics to their destinations. Each time they succeeded, propaganda was spread against the Catholic missionaries. Father Kajsiewica and his followers had to combat this slandering movement more than any member of an Order of this kind.</p>
   <p>This deeply interesting information has been taken from Experiences and Memoirs pp. 206-207, a book written by H. S. Tarnowski.</p>
   <p>We could not think of a better introduction to this article, in which we wish to honor the fiftieth anniversary of the Order of the Resurrection Fathers, whose jubilee will be celebrated on April 21.</p>
   <p>Perhaps we will not be able to give a full description of the accomplishments, hardships, and persecutions during the fifty years of work of this <pb facs="5423968_10_1194.jpg" n="4"/>new Polish monastic family on the fields of religion and nationalism. We know that the native papers abroad will do a better job. Tarnowski, who is a great admirer of this Polish order, is the best authority on the subject. His prolific pen is unmatched.</p>
   <p>The divine providence of God has been carefully watching the Church with maternal solicitude. The vigilance is constant and the religious and moral standards of the people have always been protected.</p>
   <p>The Insurrection of November (1830) having failed, the flower of the younger Polish generation gave vent to wandering and many emigrated to France. This migratory group had its own great providential mission, and from it arose not only a regeneration of national spirit through the work and accomplishments of our great geniuses, but also a regeneration of religious spirit.</p>
   <p>From France all the degenerate came into Poland. Disbelief, looseness of morals, effeminacy of character, and a spirit of insubordination and <pb facs="5423968_10_1195.jpg" n="5"/>revolution poured into the country. This was to the advantage of France, and conditions took on a good turn, progress began to be felt, and the spirit of religion sprouted rapidly. Many joined the ecclesiastical Order to work for the Church and the people. The Providence of God had an important role in this spiritual revival. Out of the small endeavors of the scattered groups, the heavenly light made possible the creation of great things.</p>
   <p>Several young men, because of the defeat of the national uprising in Poland, were forced to seek shelter on French soil. They built a small colony on the outskirts of Paris and began to rehabilitate their religious spirit. Soon their work reached other Polish emigrants, and later spread to all the Polish people.</p>
   <p>In this religious group was Bohdan Janski, the first spiritual initiator of religious belief among the emigrant groups, who took into his fold a number of young men, instilled them with his pious teachings and revived <pb facs="5423968_10_1196.jpg" n="6"/>their hearts and souls. This handful of religious-minded persons began their first monastic life and prepared themselves for the regeneration of religious feeling among the emigrant groups. It was here that the early pioneers of the Resurrection Order, Semenenko, Kajsiewica, Hube, and others were quartered and instructed.</p>
   <p>The life to which these devout young mem devoted themselves was extremely mortifying, penurious, and exacting. Besides many hardships they were exposed to hunger and isolation. It was only after subjecting themselves to this vigorous routine that they became qualified to become full-fledged priests. One can read about their pathetic existence in The History of the Founding of the Resurrection Order, of which Father P. Smolikowski, C. R., Father Kajsiewicz, B. Zaleski, and the late Father H. Kajsiewicz are contributing authors.</p>
   <p>Providence guided these apostles of the emigrants through the hard road of experience. Everything great and destined to last for centuries must come out hardened from this school in order to withstand the shortcomings <pb facs="5423968_10_1197.jpg" n="7"/>of the world. Bohdan Janski did not live to fulfill his vows to the Order; premature death claimed him before he could complete his work.</p>
   <p>After a number of years of theological study in France and in Rome, Father Hieronim Kajsiewicz and Father Peter Semenenko were ordained by Monsignor della Porta. Three days later, Father Hieronim said his first Mass beside the grave of St. Hieronim, his patron saint, at the Basilica of Santa Maria Maggiore.</p>
   <p>A month later, Father Kajsiewicz wrote a letter to his friends Joseph Zaleski and Bohdan Janski. His pious letter reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Dear Friends: What is the Holy Sacrifice? Already I have performed thirty Masses and a yet I have not comprehended its significance. I pray to God and beg Him to give me the strength to never lose faith (as it often happens) during my execution of the divine services. O it is a dreadful, dreadful mystery for the Most Holy and even the seraphs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1198.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Then what of me, the poor sinner that I am? O, it is in a strange, strange way that God is forgetting about me, for He is avenging Himself for my sins by a kiss of love from His divine lips. O, my Lord, Jesus Christ, is familiar with our land and knows how to clothe and feed us so that we forget about ourselves, only to emulate his life and teachings."</p>
   <p>The foundation of the new monastery originated with Fathers H. Kajsiewicz and P. Semenenko. Soon after, the building was erected. True, it was small, but the indomitable spirit imbedded there has been and enduring.</p>
   <p>Sunday, January 9, 1842, four more Polish missionaries were consecrated. On the following day, after performing their first Mass at the grave of St. Peter, they joined the ranks of the new Order. A number of young men attached themselves to the Order as laic brothers and assisted in the duties of the new missionary home.</p>
   <p>As yet they were not bound by any ties of the monastic Order. Strong will, the urge to sacrifice themselves and become of service to God and <pb facs="5423968_10_1199.jpg" n="9"/>the people kept this early group together in their holy pursuits. Although at that time each individual acted under his own orders, all led a harmonious monastic life. Everyone carried out orders in every detail. A definite routine was established and followed in the performance of the daily duties.</p>
   <p>In the meantime the thought of taking all the vows of the Church became stronger in every member, including the laity. Soon after, those who did not meet the requirements of priesthood become students at nearby theological seminaries. Six years after the completion of the monastery in Paris, under the leadership and command of Father Semenenko, definite rules, regulations, and requisites were set up.</p>
   <p>The entire organization agreed to hold a series of conferences during the next Lenten period. Every member indulged in prayer and fast, each asking the Almighty for help, grace and enlightenment in so grave a cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1200.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>At the last consultation held on Holy Saturday, April 20, 1842, the question of a name for this newly formed Order became an important issue. The members were deadlocked on a decision; the debate was carried far into the night. The dawn of another day struck a vital chord in Father Kajsiewicz's mind. The thought that this new day was Easter Sunday made him utter the following inspired words: "Brothers, why should we struggle so hard for a name for our small monastic order. God is offering it to us. Today is the Resurrection of Our Lord. Let this small order be called the Order of the Resurrection Fathers."</p>
   <p>This suggestion was agreeable to everyone. They also resolved to go to the St. Sebastian's Catacombs at daybreak to take the monastic vows. Permission was received from Cardinal Micara. He sent them to the catacombs with the following words: "Go there and learn the principles that are so essential and necessary to all of you."</p>
   <p>The words of the Cardinal were prophetic. For many years the catacombs have been used by persecuted religious people. It was here that solitude <pb facs="5423968_10_1201.jpg" n="11"/>and comfort was sought and found by the oppressed; it was here that the strong foundations for the future were moulded. Today, these early principles hold true. Many nationalistic groups find fortitude from the tribulations of the outside world.</p>
   <p>"On Easter Sunday," write Father Kajsiewicz, "the entire group repaired to St. Sebastian's catacombs. For many reasons we did not wish to make known our pilgrimage. As we entered the chapel of the catacombs, we anticipated to find the place empty. To our utter surprise, we found a multitude of local worshippers attending Mass. All of us fell to our knees and prayed to God to help us in our cause. Before five minutes had elapsed, the Mass was ended and the faithful began to depart. Soon the chapel was without a living soul.</p>
   <p>"The Superior, Father Semenenko, was the first to fulfill the ritual of Holy Mass. He was the first one to take the vows and partake of the Blessed Sacrament. His brethren followed. At the conclusion of these services, Father Kajsiewicz conducted a Mass of Thanksgiving.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1202.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>"On the return to our home, we were light of heart and thankful for the uninterrupted fulfillment of the sacred vows."</p>
   <p>This is the story of the origin of the Polish Order of the Resurrection Fathers. During its fifty years of existence, this monastic Order has undergone many excruciating experiences; however, its spirit has remained undaunted. On April 21, the Order will celebrate its half century mark with colorful ceremony.</p>
   <p>For five decades this Polish Order has been working in the Lord's vineyard for the benefit of the Polish people living on both hemispheres. Its work has been not only for the people but for the Church as well.</p>
   <p>The accomplishments recorded are great. No other Order can duplicate this feat in so short a time. The fruits of these efforts are spread throughout many lands. No other Order has undergone during its first fifty years of religious work so much persecution, calumny, and defamation as the Order of the Resurrection Fathers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1203.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>We are not going to point out these sad incidents, especially the persecution of the Polish people. We do not wish to disturb the peace of the late apostolic fathers responsible for this Order. The persecution and calumny experienced by them was their greatest service to God; the fruit of their work was evidence enough of their fulfillment of the vows of the Order.</p>
   <p>It is only under intense heat that gold in its raw stage becomes purified in the crucible; virtue becomes tempered under a constant barrage of adversity, the bearing of which with patience and fortitude is the pillar of future greatness and glory.</p>
   <p>St. Ignacio Loyola, with tears in his eyes, spoke the following words on his deathbed to his brethren: "Remember, when the world will stop persecuting you, your end is near."</p>
   <p>These are memorable words. We can rest assured that this Polish Order used them as its slogan; it realized that the future of its work has been made more certain by these philosophical words.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1204.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>In spite of all adversities, we can share the happiness of considering the record of this organization, for in its fifty years more great men came out of this Order than from any other. Fathers Kajsiewicz, Semenenko, Jolowicki, Hube, Kalinka, and Pawlicki were no common persons; each one was a genius in his own right; all were virtuous, pious, and self-sacrificing for the Church and the people. Polish history will engrave their names in gold in the annals of the Church and the people, annals which will serve as a symbol of apostolic performance to the cultured world. Their accomplishments will be a beautiful inheritance to our future generations. The golden-lipped Kajsiewicz; this truly modern Skarda, will be a model of sublime priesthood; Jalowicki and Hube will be examples of asceticism and spiritualism; Semenenko and Pawlicki will remain masters of Catholic philosophy; Kalinka, the master of historical literature.</p>
   <p>Let us offer on April 21, the day of the fiftieth anniversary of the Order of the Resurrection Fathers, humble thanks to God, Who amidst our century <pb facs="5423968_10_1205.jpg" n="15"/>of servitude has inspired some of our great men to be the pride of our nation, and beg Him for continued favors towards our Polish monastic order.</p>
   <p>[Skarga, Father Peter (true name Paweski), writer and preacher, was born in Grojcu and educated at the Academy of Warsaw. He died in 1612, after devoting many years to the writing of religious books and sermons.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
