<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-09">Apr. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Volunteers for Polish Army Leave for Training Camp</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-09">Apr. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">VOLUNTEERS FOR POLISH ARMY LEAVE FOR TRAINING CAMP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than eighty volunteers for the Polish Army gathered yesterday morning at about ten o'clock in front of Recruiting Center II at Milwaukee Avenue and Augusta Street, ready to depart for the Kosciusko Training Camp, Niagaraon-the-Lake, Canada. At 9:30 A.M., the Citizens' Committee of St. Hedwig's Parish and Sergeant Miller, of the recruiting station in that community, met and marched to the main recruiting station, accompanied by a military band. At ten o'clock, Recruiting Officer A. Wolski gave the order to march, and the procession moved on to St. Stanislaus Kostka Church. The parade was headed by the Polish and American flags and a military band. Then came representatives of the Polish Army and of the press, the Citizens' Committee, and about a hundred recruits. The line of march was down Milwaukee Avenue to Noble Street and thence to the Church. Throngs of people waited in front of the Church to bid farewell to these soldiers who are going to fight in the holy cause of a free, independent, and united Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1373.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Shortly after their arrival at the Church, the Reverend F. Dembinski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church, assisted by the Reverends Francis Repinski and Leon Jasinski, celebrated solemn High Mass. The Reverend W. Zapala, rector of St. Stanislaus College and chaplain of the Polish Army in France, delivered a sermon that drew tears from many eyes.</p>
   <p>During the services, the parish choir, under the direction of A. Kwasigroch, local organist, sang very beautifully. Solo numbers were sung by Mrs. Nering, Mrs. A. Kowalski, Mrs. T. Stepczynski, Mrs. A. J. Kwasigroch, and Mrs. J. Blachowski; also by W. Barwig, Victor Czonstka, John Kondziorski, F. Wengierski, Thomas Blachowski, P. Kipkowski, and Anthony Barwig. A violin solo was played by W. Kipkowski. At the conclusion of the services the audience joined in singing "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland), after which the volunteers and invited guests attended a dinner at the Parish hall.</p>
   <p>After the volunteers and invited guests had taken their places at the tables, the Reverend Dembinski requested everyone to rise while he said a prayer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1374.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the course of the dinner, the gathering was entertained by a quartet consisting of Kondziorski, W. Barwig, Czonstka, and A. Barwig.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the dinner, W. Szrojda, a member of the Citizens' Committee, called upon Father Dembinski to be toastmaster, after he himself had bidden farewell to the volunteers in a few short words. After a short but patriotic address by Father Dembinski, the following persons spoke: P. Mazurkiewicz, Peter Rostenkowski, the Reverend Jasinski, Miss E. Napieralski, secretary general of the Polish Women's Alliance, and I. Wroblewski, secretary general of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. The last speaker was A. Wolski, recruiting officer for Center II of the Polish Army in France. He warned the soldiers to be careful not to bring disgrace upon the Polish uniform and the Polish name.</p>
   <p>The dinner was prepared and served by the women of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, who, as good Polish women, are lending every effort to satisfy everybody, and especially to see that the volunteers have enough to eat so that they will not be hungry on their journey to the Camp. In addition, the volunteers were given <pb facs="5423968_10_1375.jpg" n="4"/>food to take with them and $1.25 expense money each.</p>
   <p>Procession to Railroad Station</p>
   <p>After leaving the parish hall, the parade was formed again, led by the military band. It marched down Noble Street to Division Street, then to Milwaukee, to Noble, to Superior, to Chicago, to Marshfield, to Division, to Ashland, to Brigham, and to Wood Street and St. Mary of the Angels Church, where streetcars awaited the marchers. The volunteers and their guests rode to Randolph and Canal Streets, where the procession again formed, this time with three mounted policemen at its head. To the music of the military band, it moved down Randolph Street to State Street, then to Madison, to LaSalle, to Jackson, to Dearborn, and down Dearborn Street, to the railroad station. Onr volunteers were enthusiastically applauded by the crowds that lined the streets. The Americans, seeing the rather frequent parades of the Polish Army sending off its volunteers to the training Camp, are becoming convinced that the Poles are not sleeping and they are anxious to fight the enemy of mankind for the democracy of the world <pb facs="5423968_10_1376.jpg" n="5"/>and for the freedom of our beloved Poland. They have an even greater respect for us, however, because they are convinced that we are good patriots and that we understand the importance of the present time.</p>
   <p>The train left the station at 5:45 P.M., carrying our brave boys to the training Camp, whence, after they have received their training, they will hasten to France to fight our age-old enemies, the Germans. Throngs of people waved farewell to the boys as they departed with faith in a better future, believing that they will soon be victorious and will find themselves on the soil of a free, independent, and united Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
