<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I, No. 38,
<date when="1897-08-15">August 15, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Tenth Anniversary of the Society of St. Mary</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. I, No. 38,
<date when="1897-08-15">August 15, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Tenth Anniversary of the Society Of St. Mary</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, after Vespers about 4 P.M., was held a beautiful tenth anniversary program of the Society of St. Mary before a large gathering, in the beautifully decorated hall of St. Stanislau Kostka at Bradley and Noble Sts.</p>
   <p>President of the Society, Jacob Tomaszewski opened the program with a short talk and called upon the presiding officer of the gathering, Rev. Father Vicent Barzynski.</p>
   <p>Rev. Barzynski heartily congratulated the society on its anniversary and wished there would be many more such occasions and called upon the secretary of the gathering the Editor of Narod Polski, Mr. Korbaczewski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0355.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Leon Szopinski, Editor "Gazety Katolickiej", Catholic Newspaper member of the Society, gave a beautiful talk about the principles and views of the society.</p>
   <p>Then Mrs. Klarkowska and Miss Kopa sang an appropriate song "Serce Polska" (Heart of Poland) with the piano accompaniment of Father Serafino Cosimi.</p>
   <p>The main part of the program was a talk by Father Joseph Gieburowski on the subject "St. Mary," who said that St. Mary is leading and will lead the Polish race to success. He pointed out how the Poles had a great regard for St. Mary in their hearts and lips, in their their accomplishments. Rev. Father Gieburowski also read the writing of John Kazmiera, who gave the Kingdom of Poland over to St. Mary so that she could become the Queen of Poland.</p>
   <p>He also spoke of the wonderful deeds of St. Mary in helping the great sons of Poland in which Adam Mickiewicz, the poet, gave St. Mary great praise in "Pana Thaddeusza." He congratulated the society on the name it had and hoped that it would grow and prosper not only materially but morally, that it would be a <pb facs="5423968_10_0356.jpg" n="3"/>guiding star for the Parish of St. Stanislau Kostka and hoped it would attain its silver anniversary and that upon that occasion he would like to have the luck to be present. At the finish of this talk the applause was great. The above mentioned ladies then sang "Ave Maria."-</p>
   <p>Then spoke one of the oldest members, Walter Pyterek; In warm words he said he was proud that he was a member of the society, that holds such an honorable position in the affairs of the parish.</p>
   <p>He urged all Poles to become members of this society. St. Mary looks after the trials and tribulations of the society and will continue to look after it so that all members may benefit from the good work accomplished.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Klarkowski's daughter with the accompaniment of Father Cosimo sang "Swieta Lucjo"(Santa Lucia) in which the school children also sang, in Polish and Latin.</p>
   <p>The gathering ended with a talk by Rev. Father Barzynski. He called attention to <pb facs="5423968_10_0357.jpg" n="4"/>the gathering that a mass meeting would be held Tuesday to drawing up resolutions protesting the doings of the Sheriff of Luzerne County, Pa. in murdering a number of innocent victims and injuring many in a strike. There were many Polish victims and it was in their interest that the meeting was held. It closed with the audience singing "Boze Cos' Polshie." (God save Poland)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
