<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-26">Feb. 26, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Protest [Against "Independents" by Societies in Bridgeport]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-02-26">Feb. 26, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST [AGAINST "INDEPENDENTS" BY SOCIETIES IN BRIDGEPORT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago - February 21, 1897.</p>
   <p>We, the undersigned, citizens of the United States and presidents of Polish Roman Catholic Societies of St. Mary of Perpetual Help Parish of Bridgeport, a community of Chicago, unanimously agreed at a meeting held on February 14 to protest against the activities of the excommunicated schismatics who consider themselves "independent" Catholics and confuse our people.</p>
   <p>We admonish all our brothers to avoid the schismatic doctrines being spread by dissenters from the Roman Catholic Church, by fallen priests and other jugglers of the faith; for these are the ones who cover our people with shame on the eyes of the civilized world.</p>
   <p>You should remember, dear brothers, that the holding of the Holy Mass and the <pb facs="5423968_10_0418.jpg" n="2"/>imparting of the blessed Sacraments by excommunicated priests and those separated from the Roman Catholic Church are sacrilegious acts. It would, therefore, be more wholesome to discontinue such religious practices than to commit a mortal sin and sacrilege by attending such ceremonies.</p>
   <p>We admonish you in order that you may avoid committing this terrible sin. In this way you will not permit yourselves to be diverted from the faith of your fathers by fallen priests who call themselves "independents". Anger induces us to call them, not schismatics, but the pain in our hearts, for as we look upon their acts we are convinced that these fallen priests wish to lead our honest people away from the path of righteousness. By calling themselves "Catholics" they are condemning themselves in this free country. Everyone is aware of the fact that whoever is not in accord with the Holy See and opposes the powers of the bishops, which have been handed down to them by Jesus Christ, ceases to be a Catholic. Such dishonest priests as Kozlowski, Plucinski, Jakimowicz, and other charlatans, do not adhere to the orders of <pb facs="5423968_10_0419.jpg" n="3"/>their bishops; consequently they are not in unity with the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>Let it be known to you, dear brothers, that the Czars of Russia strove for many years to set up a Catholic church, independent of the Holy See and of the bishops appointed by Rome. In this attempt the Muscovites murdered many of our bishops on the Siberian steppes, and opened an archbishopric at Petersburg where the major patriarch, appointed by the Czar and not by the Pope, could more easily disunite the Catholics from Rome. The Catholic bishops were ferbidden by the Czars even to communicate with the Vatican, and only those bishops whose letters were accepted by the Czar's ministers could write to the Pope.</p>
   <p>Our Polish people accepted the dank prisons of Siberia and even death rather than the renunciation of their Roman Catholic religion.</p>
   <p>That which the Czars failed to do by persecuting followers of the Roman <pb facs="5423968_10_0420.jpg" n="4"/>Catholic faith, such priests as Kozlowski, Plucinski, Jakimowicz, and others are trying to accomplish in America. What, therefore, are these independent haranguers if they are not spreaders of the schism attempted by the Czars? What are they, if they are not ringleaders of dissension and murderers of brotherly unity? They are the betrayers of their own brothers. They are the evil spies and menials of the Czars who strove in vain to accomplish that which the Independents are attempting to accomplish today.</p>
   <p>The undersigned wish to make it known that in the event any of the members of our Roman Catholic societies discontinue their connection with the Roman Catholic Church to become associated with the schismatic "Independent Church," as stated by the constitutions of the societies, they lose all rights as members, including death benefits to their families, since their connections with the "Independents" make them non-Catholics. On the other hand, dear brothers, if you value your honor and national feeling, and if the light of the true faith has not been extinguished in your hearts, avoid contact with the heretics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0421.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Andrew Lipinski, president of St. John Cantius Society; Max Wojtalewicz, president of St. Stephen Martyr Society; Carol Einlenfeld, president of St. Francis Society; Francis Olszewski, president of St. Paul Uhlans Society; Valentine Derdzinski, president of St. Mary of Perpetual Help Society; Joseph Pawelczyk, president of St. Joseph Society; Ignace Wierzelski, president of St. Adalbert Society; Stephen Lipinski, president of St. Cecilia Society; Casimir Klukaszewski, president of St. Stanislaus Kostka Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
