<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 13,
<date when="1905-01-17">Jan. 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Answer to Youngsters at St. Stanislaus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 13,
<date when="1905-01-17">Jan. 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">ANSWER TO YOUNGSTERS AT ST. STANISLAUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For a long time the youngster of St. Stanislaus Parish have been working earnestly to reorganize a large company of cadets. A company of cadets has been an organization at St. Stanislaus for many years, but for the past few years the list has fallen from over two hundred cadets to about forty. The reasons why the cadet companies fell so low in membership are: They did not have a suitable hall where they could drill. This company of cadets did not have enough uniforms and equipment because the society was financially weak. At the present time they have a suitable hall to drill at, and the cadets have almost $200 in the treasury, besides having bought an American flag, equipment, uniforms, etc.</p>
   <p>This society of cadets has for its members a sick benefit of $1.25 a week, and in the case of death, the cadets act as pallbearers.</p>
   <p>The initiation fee is fifty cents. Dues are fifteen cents a month, and there are no additional fees of any kind. Drills are held every Friday.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1475.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Youngsters wishing to join can do so by coming to the hall on Friday, Jan. 20. All the societies of Saint Stanislaus are cordially invited. The societies are St. Casimir, St. Aloysius, Young Brotherhood of St. Joseph, and the first and second groups of cadets.</p>
   <p>All youngsters, not belonging to any society of cadets, or Polish groups, and who have reached the age of sixteen or more, and those who were members and resigned because of financial difficulties or through some misunderstanding, are cordially invited to attend the meeting. Also all Polish citizens intrusted in work of this kind are asked to be present and hear the views and aims of prominent Polish speakers.</p>
   <p>Admission free.</p>
   <p>The Committee: P. Kucharski, F. Lamkowski,</p>
   <p>A. Tworek, L. Ulatowski, A. Bukowski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
