<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-18">Mar. 18, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">St. Hedwig Church Closed Anew</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0893</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0893.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-18">Mar. 18, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ST. HEDWIG CHURCH CLOSED ANEW</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Once again sad news reaches us from St. Hedwig Church.</p>
   <p>The church, which was open last Thursday and Friday, was closed again by the archbishop because of the disturbances which took place on the second day of the opening.</p>
   <p>Last Friday Reverend Sedlaczek was present at the parish meeting and enthusiastically urged the opposition to come to terms, to come to agreement with their brothers, and to return to the road of righteousness. He informed the assemblage that he would do his best to bring these things about.</p>
   <p>This speech, however, did not create the slightest impression, nor did it bring any results. It is apparent that in the future it will be necessary for the priest to make person-to-person contact within the parish to get results.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0894.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In view of the disturbances of last Friday, the archbishop of Chicago has decided to take definite steps of action. Late that Friday evening Reverend Sedlaczek received a note from the archbishop requesting that services cease Saturday morning at the parish of St. Hedwig. This request was fulfilled.</p>
   <p>On Saturday, Reverend E. Sedlaczek called upon the archbishop and was informed that the church must remain closed because of the prevailing misunderstanding. Services did not take place yesterday (Sunday) or Saturday.</p>
   <p>The opposition sent the papal delegate, Monsignor Satolli, a telegram last Saturday. That afternoon the following reply was received:</p>
   <p>"Washington, D. C., March 16.</p>
   <p>"To the committee of St. Hedwig Parish,</p>
   <p>"1000 North Hoyne Avenue: 3:30 P. M.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0895.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Proceed as faithful Christians, and continue to obey the archbishop, who is your rightful Sovereign and understands the needs of your parish.</p>
   <p>"Monsignor Satolli"</p>
   <p>The opposing faction held a meeting last Saturday evening at Dziewior's Hall. A great deal was said, and many proposals were suggested, but nothing was adopted. Evidently the reply from the papal delegate created a lasting impression upon the opposition.</p>
   <p>It is becoming more and more apparent that a peaceful and satisfactory settlement must be affected. Yesterday--Sunday--no disturbance occurred about the church. A Republican meeting and parade, however, took place that afternoon. It is rumored that the Republican agitation relative to the coming election is being worked together with the agitation of the opposition in connection with the affairs of the parish.</p>
   <p>At three o'clock yesterday afternoon, a fire broke out in one of the vacant <pb facs="5423968_10_0896.jpg" n="4"/>lots on Elston Avenue, and created a feeling of alarm. The fire was started by a spark from a passing train. When it was put out order was restored.</p>
   <p>Reverend Sedlaczek left the parish last Saturday and returned to St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish; however, he will not stop paying visits to the parish, nor will he stop giving spiritual assistance.</p>
   <p>In view of the closing of the church it is doubtful whether the parish will be opened soon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
