<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-04-29">Apr. 29. 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Patriots Take Citizenship Papers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-04-29">Apr. 29. 1914</date>.
<title level="a">PATRIOTS TAKE CITIZENSHIP PAPERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two-hundred Poles and Slovaks Soaking Naturalization, Declare for Army Service.</p>
   <p>Last night more than two-hundred Poles and Slovaks taking out citizenship papers, demonstrated their patriotism at the office of the Clerk of the Circuit Court in the County Building.</p>
   <p>Every man declared himself ready to enlist for service with the United States, in Mexico. Most of the applicants said they sought their first papers to be eligible for military service. Several of those in the crowd had served their conscription term in the German or Russian army. Others had left the old country to escape military service. "I would not fight for Russia, but I am going to enlist here to help fight the Mexicans", one man said in Polish.</p>
   <p>Concerned About Family.</p>
   <p>"I want to enlist now", another man said: but will the government take care of my wife and children?"</p>
   <p>The Poles came from the School of Citizenship at 1455 W. Division St. They were <pb facs="5423968_10_1422.jpg" n="2"/>led by Stephen L. Kolanowski, editor and instructor in the school. Joseph Pokora, President of the Slovak-American Citizens and Political Club, brought in a crowd of fifty of his countrymen.</p>
   <p>The crowd kept clerks, Morris Marx and Walter Pietras, busy for three hours making out the papers. Each man paid $1.50 of which $1.00 goes to the federal government. After the papers were made out, the men lined up for the administration of the oath of allegiance.</p>
   <p>No Anarchists Present.</p>
   <p>"All those who are anarchists will raise their right hand", Clerk Marx shouted, as he walked up and down the line, scrutinizing the faces of the men. A few of the crowd misunderstood the question and raised their hands. Kolanowski quickly came to their rescue with a stern command. The result satisfied the clerk.</p>
   <p>"How many of you believe in having more than one wife?" Shouts of laughter followed this question.</p>
   <p>"How many of you would be willing to serve in the American Army, if you were <pb facs="5423968_10_1423.jpg" n="3"/>called upon in case of war with Mexico?"</p>
   <p>Every man raised his right hand.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
