<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 188,
<date when="1908-08-11">Aug. 11, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Address to His Excellency the Most Rev. Bishop P. Rhode</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 188,
<date when="1908-08-11">Aug. 11, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ADDRESS TO HIS EXCELLENCY THE MOST REV. BISHOP P. RHODE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the parish of St. Joseph we received the following article:</p>
   <p>In the name of St. Joseph's Parish from Town of Lake we the undersigned feel that we owe our heartiest happiness to you beloved Bishop and Sufragan; we pay tribute and our best wishes from believers of the Catholic Church, sons and daughters of the above mentioned parish.</p>
   <p>After a long expectation we were rewarded with a great triumph on the 29th of July, which was written in golden letters in our annals and in the hearts of every Polish man and woman.</p>
   <p>Our longing after a long expectation were fulfilled a plea for a polish Bishop as leader and pastor was the happiest moment for all of us. Let us be allowed to show the public that the Poles can be on the same level with other nationalities in regard to the Roman-Catholic churches.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are wishing you the best of everything; may Beloved God grant you success in your work and undertaking act as a follower in the footsteps of Jesus Christ, teach his words and teachings, act as a judge and govern the Polish people in our city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>We are promising you Father of the Catholic churches, that every order of yours will be fulfilled because we are your children.</p>
   <p>We must offer our thanks to the Almighty God that he answered our prayers; To you Bishop Rhode who has undertaken great responsibilities in his work as the head of Chicago's archdiocese and in behalf of all the people we wish you long years of life, health and satisfaction and may God be your guardian. We Polish people will continue praying that you may have success and continue aiding and helping Polish people in their hour of need, offer consolation also help the young priest so that they may follow in your footsteps.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0201.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These are the wishes from the parish of St. Joseph's with the utmost sincerity for His Excellency.</p>
   <p>The congregation cannot express their true feeling in words, but their hearts are filled with the greatest joy and happiness.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anthony Rusch, Michael Kowalski, Sigmund Schmidt, Roman J. Kowalewski and Jacob Kiepura.</p>
   <p>The above mentioned are responsible for this article being printed. They are the committee members at St. Joseph's parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
