<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XII, No. 25,
<date when="1918-06-20">June 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The First American Hero from South Chicago to Fall in France Is a South Chicago Pole</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XII, No. 25,
<date when="1918-06-20">June 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST AMERICAN HERO FROM SOUTH CHICAGO TO FALL IN FRANCE IS A SOUTH CHICAGO POLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first American soldier from South Chicago to give his life as a hero while fighting under the Starry Banner, defending civilization and humanity, is our South Chicago Pole by the name of Wladyslaw Stelmaszek. Our hero was born in Chicago on the 6th day of January, 1891, and died on the battlefield of France on June 11, 1918.</p>
   <p>Wladyslaw Stelmaszek lived with his mother Michalina Stelmaszek before enlisting in the United States Army. His mother lives at 8347 Mackinaw Avenue. He volunteered into the U. S. Army on the 14th day of June, 1917, and was sent to the training camp in the South. He landed in France last winter and served with the 18th Field Artillery until his death.</p>
   <p>In the first part of the year he was on the Western Front in France. On Friday the 18th day of June there was a telegraphic report that <pb facs="5423968_10_1371.jpg" n="2"/>our here took an active part in a battle in which he was seriously wounded. Later on there was another official report from Washington stating that he was wounded on the 7th day of June and died on the 11th day of the same month in the field hospital, four days after receiving wounds at the front.</p>
   <p>Receiving the official reports his old mother went first to her oldest son, Jan, who lives at 83rd and Burley Avenue. He left four brothers.</p>
   <p>As far as we know his remains will be buried in France, among other heroes who fought and died for a good cause. Our here fought not only for America and France; he also fought for Poland, the land of his father and mother, he fought against our eternal enemy, the Prussians.</p>
   <p>Honor to him, let his soul rest in place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
