<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>. Vol. XVII, No. 22,
<date when="1913-05-28">May 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">God and Fatherland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>. Vol. XVII, No. 22,
<date when="1913-05-28">May 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">GOD AND FATHERLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under such a title we place a handful of notes, collected from a talk by His Excellency Rev. Bishop Paul P. Rhode.</p>
   <p>This talk was rendered by our prince of the church at the convention of the Polish Alma Mater, held last week at Chicago, in St. Hedwig's Parish.</p>
   <p>From the times when St. Adalbert, Dabrowka, wife of Miecislaus, first king of Poland, brought the grain of God's truth, Poland was always a country of God. However, in this country there was a sanctuary for others who professed another religion, and in spite of this Poland did not cease to be Polish, said the Reverend Bishop.</p>
   <p>It ought to be this way everywhere, wherever a group of our children are instituting a family hearth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0132.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That is the way it was at the beginning in America. In time, however, in Europe as well as here, when our society began to be imbibed with undesired acids, relations began to spoil.</p>
   <p>Every true Pole and Catholic always should remember that he has as much business in an outside non-Polish and non-Catholic organization as a Jew has in a Catholic organization.</p>
   <p>Let the Poles who confess the faith of Moses have their own Poland and their own organizations of Moses.</p>
   <p>Let the Poles Socialists have their own Socialist Poland and their own organizations.</p>
   <p>Let the Poles unbelievers have their own Poland without God, and their own organizations.</p>
   <p>And we, Polish Catholics, faithfully loving our holy church, the faith <pb facs="5423968_10_0133.jpg" n="3"/>of our forefathers, let us have our Polish Catholic organizations, the watchword of which is "God and Fatherland."</p>
   <p>The mixing of Polish Catholics with outside elements in order to unite with them into one hearth of a permanent organization will not prove beneficial to us. It happened, although it never should have happened. Polish Catholics, with harm to their own faith and with no benefit to their nationality, have found themselves here and there, and are being found to this day in the ranks of those who are foes to the traditions of our forefathers, which demand that we here in America, above all hold on to the motto: "God and Fatherland."</p>
   <p>Should we Catholics allow the Socialists to show us the way? Shall people with a spirit strange to ours denounce us afterwards as traitors?</p>
   <p>You ought to be the real kind of Catholics; undegenerated sons, the <pb facs="5423968_10_0134.jpg" n="4"/>descendants of those who faithfully worked for God and Fatherland, united and not divided. If that which is of Polish origin will remain in America, it will only be on the strong foundation of the Holy Faith. A handful of those who, outside the faith, seemingly wish to work for the cause of nationality, often use to excess patriotic watchwords in their anti-religious aims.</p>
   <p>I believe in the host of youth born here and brought up in our schools and who, knowing our church and our priests, will not yield to the influence of wicked people.</p>
   <p>I believe in the youth emerging out of our institutions over here. I believe in those who, with their spirit, have not run away from their Alma Mater, and have not sold away the watchwords of their fathers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
