<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-30">Apr. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">From the Polish Recruiting Office</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-04-30">Apr. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE POLISH RECRUITING OFFICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More and more Poles are joining Uncle Sam's Army, coming in masses to the only Polish recruiting bureau, which is in the Polish Roman Catholic Union building, where Mr. J. S. Konopa and Mr. J. F. Skibinski are the recruiting officers.</p>
   <p>Forty volunteers enlisted, on Saturday and forty-four on Sunday. So far 343 men have applied for enlistment. Of the 300 which were registered only 7 applications were rejected after the medical examinations. This constitutes an unusually low percentage of rejections.</p>
   <p>Yesterday pamphlets in Polish were distributed in front of the churches, encouraging men to join the army. In these pamphlets the following appeal was made to the Poles as well as to others:</p>
   <p>"Poles! America calls us! Let us prove our patriotism! Let us prove our <pb facs="5423968_10_1409.jpg" n="2"/>loyalty and attachment! Let us give proof of our gratitude! Let us prove that we are the descendents of a brave and noble people! Let us remember that America demands an independent Poland! Let us enlist in the United States Army!</p>
   <p>"Polish recruiting station,</p>
   <p>"984 Milwaukee Avenue, corner of August Street."</p>
   <p>There was unusual activity at the recruiting station yesterday. Our women from the Women's Department [of the Polish National Alliance], headed by Mrs. M. Sakowski and daughter, were at the station, pinning flowers on the volunteers and encouraging the men to join the army. Among the ladies we noticed Mrs. W. Chodzinski and daughter, Mrs. J. Baranowski, Mrs. J. Sykta, Mrs. H. Pawlik, and others.</p>
   <p>The volunteers who enlisted recently held a parade Sunday afternoon.....The Boy Scouts of Avondale marched at the head of the parade. The recruits were <pb facs="5423968_10_1410.jpg" n="3"/>led by Mr. Z. Wisniewski.</p>
   <p>On Tuesday the new recruits will leave for Jefferson Park, near St. Louis, where all the Poles are kept together in the barraks. It is promised that a separate regiment will be formed for them, if enough men volunteer. Tuesday morning a Mass will be said at Holy Trinity Church for those leaving for the army. It is expected that by tomorrow the number of men leaving will increase to at least one hundred and fifty.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow afternoon the volunteers will parade downtown. This parade will be more spectacular than previous ones. The parade, preceded by a band, will be led by over a hundred Polish Scouts. These will be followed by the volunteers marching in ranks, with signs, through the main streets of the Loop. Then the boys will go to the railroad station and entrain for Jefferson Park.</p>
   <p>Regiment II, Company G, of the National Guard has opened its recruiting office at Milwaukee Avenue and Paulina Street. This office, however, is not attracting <pb facs="5423968_10_1411.jpg" n="4"/>nearly the number of men that the recruiting station of the regular army at the Polish Roman Catholic Union building is drawing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
