<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-12">Nov. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">After the "Blessing"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0719</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0719.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-12">Nov. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">AFTER THE "BLESSING"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "blessing" of the new schismatic temple by the fallen priest Kolaszewski, who was excommunicated from the Roman Catholic Church by the Pope, belongs to the past.</p>
   <p>This sacrilegious ceremony was performed last Sunday before an inquisitive and gaping crowd.</p>
   <p>It is with regret that we make note of the fact that besides the fallen group from St. Hedwig Parish, two societies of the Polish National Alliance and a portion of a Polish military organization took part in this farce.</p>
   <p>This served as an excuse for the schismatics to publicize that societies from <pb facs="5423968_10_0720.jpg" n="2"/>all Polish parishes of Chicago took part in the parade held prior to the "blessing" ceremony.</p>
   <p>It readily can be said that this is only one of the many lies that have been broadcast through one medium or another.</p>
   <p>We wish to declare:</p>
   <p>That no Polish Roman Catholic society connected with any of the Polish Roman Catholic parishes of Chicago took part in this schismatic comedy;</p>
   <p>That no righteous Roman Catholic priest was present during the "blessing" ceremonies of this scandalous temple.</p>
   <p>That on righteous Polish Roman Catholic parish of Chicago sympathizes with the fallen priest of his associates.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0721.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those who desire evidence in this respect are referred to an article of protest sent in by the Holy Trinity Parish and published in yesterday's issue of the Dziennik Chicagoski [translator's note: see article "Holy Trinity Church Protests Against Independent Church Movement" published in the Dziennik Chicagoski on November 11,<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>]. The Holy Trinity parishioners protested against the allegation that sympathy was expressed secretly for the independent church movement.</p>
   <p>As a consequence, the Sunday "blessing" actually burned against the schismatics who attempted to make this affair a triumphant event. Through this affair they have demonstrated their insignificance and weakness. It turned out to be a subject of laughter for the crowd.</p>
   <p>The befuddled group, perhaps, should be convinced that no bishop will consent to take part in the services held in the temple of the independents; that only those priests who have fallen from the true fold and who have been condemned by the bishop, or those individuals who consider themselves priests will take part <pb facs="5423968_10_0722.jpg" n="4"/>in the services; that no Polish Roman Catholic priest and no righteous Roman Catholic parish sympathizes with the charlatans--the false prophets who wish to undermine the true faith and lead the people from the path of salvation and God.</p>
   <p>This should be sufficient to the befuddled people; it should open their eyes and lead them along the right road.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
