<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-11">May 11, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Society Opposes Plea Made by Independent Church Group for Help</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-11">May 11, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIETY OPPOSES PLEA MADE BY INDEPENDENT CHURCH GROUP FOR HELP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some kind of independent church committee [not connected with the Holy See] at 20th Street and Ashland Avenue sent an appeal for help to the St. Adalbert Bishop and Martyr Society Number One of St. Adalbert's parish. The members of this organization returned the following reply:</p>
   <p>"Our former brothers! You ask us for financial assistance for your newly formed "parish," which you call the Miraculous Virgin of Czestochowa.</p>
   <p>"We had not had the opportunity to find out whether a new Roman Catholic parish was being organized in St. Adalbert's community. Upon investigation we discovered that not even the Bishop of Chicago knows of such plans. Did you approach the chancery to request permission to organize a new parish? Did the Bishop promise to send you a Roman Catholic Priest? It would be advisable to make application to the Bishop first and then to approach us for assistance. As long as this is not done, we are compelled to consider your independent <pb facs="5423968_10_0379.jpg" n="2"/>temple a creation of Lucifer [Satan as identified with the rebel archangel before his fall], for your preachers serve him in order to sidetrack the people to the road that leads to hell. How dare you, blaspheme the Miraculous Virgin of Czestochowa? Are you of the opinion that she will be the patron of Poles who bring shame to the Polish name in America?</p>
   <p>Do not use the names of Mary and the saints in vain with your sacrilegious ceremonies without thought of being punished. We have nothing in common with you. Our patron, St. Adalbert, guards us from joining condemned cliques in our parish as well as throughout Chicago. It is permissible for us to pray for you; that is the only help we can offer. It is hoped that God will not exclude you from his protection for your abuse of the name of the Miraculous Virgin of Czestochowa.</p>
   <p>Lawrence Formanek, secretary,</p>
   <p>of St. Adalbert Bishop and Martyr Society</p>
   <p>Number One </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
