<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-12">May 12, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Catholic Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0494</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0494.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-12">May 12, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH CATHOLIC CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A copy of the following letter has been sent by the main committee of the Polish Catholic Congress to all Polish societies:</p>
   <p>"To all Polish parochial societies in America: A few weeks ago we sent an appeal to all societies, inviting them to participate in the discussions at the Polish Catholic Congress and to send their delegates to it. Many societies have not as yet answered this appeal because-- we believe--they think there is plenty of time to take care of this matter." However those who understand the difficult problems to be solved and how much trouble, care, and effort is necessary to make the proper arrangements for such a congress, will realize that there is no time to waste. Everything has to be properly planned, arrangements must be made, letters must be exchanged between the Polish priests, societies, and prominent Poles in America, and an understanding with the Polish Catholics in the old country must be arrived at. All this consumes a lot of <pb facs="5423968_10_0495.jpg" n="2"/>time. If the congress is to be a success, everything must be in readiness--the list of delegates must be completed, the program arranged, and some time in advance an approximate idea as to the number of delegates participating must be known, what matters are most vital for discussion, and what matters must be decided.</p>
   <p>"The calling of the Polish Catholic Congress is in reality more troublesome than calling a simple convention of any large organization, because for a convention a call is issued to the societies of the organization, while in calling a congress such as this it is necessary to contact large organizations, societies belonging to it, and societies that do not belong to any organization, as well as many prominent individuals. Arrangements for a convention are all carefully prepared in advance, while, in calling a congress, everything must be organized, various proposals must be considered, the program must be properly arranged, and many other matters and preparations must be made.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0496.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"We don't write this to praise our own labors, but simply for the purpose of convincing all the societies that there is no time to lose, that now is the time to announce participation in the congress.</p>
   <p>"We also wish to announce once again that all Polish societies whose members are of the Roman Catholic faith are entitled to one delegate for each one hundred members, and societies numbering loss than one hundred members, even the small societies, may also send a delegate to the congress.</p>
   <p>"We therefore beg the presidents and secretaries of all Polish Catholic societies to submit this proposition to their members at the earliest possible moment, discuss the prepositions they would wish to submit and elect delegates to the Polish Catholic Congress.</p>
   <p>"With true brotherly greetings,</p>
   <p>Reverend John Pitass, president,</p>
   <p>S. Slisz, secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0497.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"P. S. Please address all correspondence to S. Slisz, 227 Lovejoy Street, Buffalo, New York."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
