<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-28">Mar. 28, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Another "Show" by the "Independents" in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-28">Mar. 28, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER "SHOW" BY THE "INDEPENDENTS" IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tomorrow another sacrilege, another humbug, more mockery of the true faith will be enacted by the "Independent" charlatans to befuddle further the poor people who broke away from the St. Hedwig Parish over a year ago.</p>
   <p>Those excommunicated priests are promising us that tomorrow they will stage the "Blessing of Bells" in the "Independent Parish of All Saints".</p>
   <p>What will this gathering really be? Everybody knows that it will be nothing but a show and a sacrilege.</p>
   <p>The excommunicated priests, self-styled prelates, the charlatans in violet robes, have no authority to perform any rites prescribed by the Roman Catholic Church, and all their assurances that they are in perfect accord with the Roman Catholic Church are deliberate falsehoods, as we are all well aware.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0523.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are not writing these words to tell the befuddled sheep of these "Independent" charlatans anything new, but once again to try to bring them to their senses. Let them not stay mired in the mud and set these additional bad examples; for, even though they are deceived, they will answer to God for their misguided sins.</p>
   <p>A hundred times worse is the responsibility of the guilty leaders. These include all those that knowingly lead these poor people from the path of righteousness. With the charlatans and prelates in violet robes, those papers that lie to the people are included. Those papers deserve the most severe condemnation for their actions.</p>
   <p>This condemnation is applied particularly to the local Dziennik Polski (Polish News) which, after publishing a great number of notices containing the lies of the "Independent" schism, yesterday again published a perverse, misleading, and false article urging the people to take part in this hideous and sacrilegious "show".....Such an article plainly marks this paper as deliberately dishonest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
