<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 282,
<date when="1906-12-10">Dec. 10, 1906</date><title level="a">Attention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 282,
<date when="1906-12-10">Dec. 10, 1906</date><title level="a">ATTENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois, Dec. 3, 1906</p>
   <p>Most. Rev. Seb. B. Messner, D. D.</p>
   <p>Archbishop of Milwaukee</p>
   <p>2224 Chestnut Street</p>
   <p>Milwaukee. Wis.</p>
   <p>Most Reverend Archbishop:</p>
   <p>We recently received the volume of the Historya Polska w Ameryce by S. Wencesaus Kruszka. This volume bears the usual Nihil Obstat by the Reverend Ant. Wisniewski, O. F. M., censor, and the Imprimatur by Your Grace, and, in addition to this, on page 279 is a Nota Bene of the Rev. W. Kruszka, that your Grace gave him for this volume, a special Imprimatur. The imprimatur of volume IX is hereby gladly given.</p>
   <p>Although it is quite impossible to understand how all this work could have received Nihil obstat and an imprimatur, yet the Nihil obstat and the imprimatur of volume IX is an evidence that the censor is a very poor <pb facs="5423968_10_0239.jpg" n="2"/>moralist, and a public proof that he is a very poor scholar, unable to discriminate what is fit for publication. His Nihil obstat would give the impression that he does not remember what he studied of the De judicio temeraric, de detractione, de contumelia, and de violatione secreti.</p>
   <p>Volume IX is a compilation of sentences extracted from different letters, written at different times, by different Fathers, to their Superior General and Rome, are adorned with malicious annotations by the Rev. W.Kruszka. Although the sentences may be true copies of those in the different letters, yet they contain private, and some ways secret, information concerning only the private affairs of members of the congregation of the Resurrection, a religious community, - therefore the publication of these sentences is a public criminal libel against the Fathers of the Resurrection.</p>
   <p>As far as we are informed, the late Superior General, Very Reverend P. Smolikowski upon request, permitted the Rev. V. Krvszka to use our archives for some study, but he never gave him permission to copy and publish any of the private letters in the archives of our congregation. According to the assertion of Very Rev. P. Smolikowski, the Rev. V. Kruszka abused <pb facs="5423968_10_0240.jpg" n="3"/>his confidence, fraudulently copied, stole and published entirely private and secret letters, and, therefore, although he obtained Nihil obstat and Imprimatur, he is guilty of public criminal libel - but more guilty is the censor, who gave the Nihil obstat and involted the Imprimatur of Your Grace.</p>
   <p>We lay this matter before Your Grace with the request, and the hope, that you will do something to remove this stain upon our character as a community, and as individuals, and also to assure us that you did not gladly subscribe to a malicious attack on priests, who hold you in the highest esteem.</p>
   <p>With the deepest reverence and the assurance of our good will, I am your Grace's most humble servant,</p>
   <p>Rev. Francis Gordon, C. R.</p>
   <p>II</p>
   <p>(An answer to his letter)</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0241.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Milwaukee, Wis., Dec. 5, 1906</p>
   <p>Rev. Francis Gordon</p>
   <p>Rector of St. Stanislaus</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Reverend and Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>Your letter of yesterday is a most painful surprise to me. Allow me to state that when I gave the Imprimatur for Vol. IX of the Rev.V. Kawszka's Historya Polska W Ameryce, I had not the slightest knowledge of its contents but had to rely absolutely on the judgment of the appointed censor, the Rev. P. Antonius Wisniewski, O. F. M., of Green Bay, just as with all previous volumes. He had given the Nihil obstat and I had, in consequence, to grant the Imprimatur. This shows at the same time how ridiculous it is on the part of the Rev. Kruszka to attack any special meaning to the phrase in my letter that the Imprimatur was gladly given. This was a mere formality of very common politeness, exactly the same as when you say that you are to do another a favor. But my "gladly" had absolutely no reference to the contents of the volume, of which I know nothing whatever. The Rev. Krusska tries to give the term "gladly" used by me, the meaning of endorsing anything at all in his volume. I must condemn such an endeavour as a most dishonest <pb facs="5423968_10_0242.jpg" n="5"/>and contemptible trick.</p>
   <p>Permit me to state further that I would not have allowed the publication of that volume, if I had had any knowledge of the flagrant abuse of private letters and information with which you charge the author. The more I appreciate the good which your community of the Resurrectionist Fathers is doing among the Catholic Polish people of our country, so deeply do I regret that my name should have been connected, even in the most unsuspecting manner, with anything derogatory to the high reputation of your order.</p>
   <p>I hope you will give this letter the widest publicity,</p>
   <p>S. G. Messmer, Archbishop</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
