<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 267,
<date when="1908-11-13">Nov. 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Catholic Congress of Missionaries</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Lithuanian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 267,
<date when="1908-11-13">Nov. 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH CATHOLIC CONGRESS OF MISSIONARIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are preparing ourselves for the first Polish Catholic congress of missionaries, which will begin next Sunday, Nov. 15. The program is completed and pamphlets with the complete outline of this Congress and the names of those on the central committee were distributed among the various parishes. They can also be obtained at the Rookery located at 217 La Salle St., where the committee bureau is located.</p>
   <p>We give a brief outline of this program: Sunday, Nov. 15, at 10:30 A. M., a great procession of prelates and priests will parade from Cathedral College to the Holy Name Cathedral. They will be escorted by 300 members of the four highest ranks of the "Knights of Columba" in full dress uniforms.</p>
   <p>At 12 o'clock a pontifical high mass will take place in the Holy Name Cathedral, performed by Rev. Father Diomede Falconia, the apostolic <pb facs="5423968_10_0183.jpg" n="2"/>delegate from Washington, who is also a special delegate of the Pope at this congress, assisted by Archbishop James H. Blink of New York, who will chant the sermon.</p>
   <p>At 1:30 in the afternoon a banquet will be held in the hall adjoining the Cathedral, issued by Chicago's Archbishop, J. E. Quigley, in behalf of his prelate guests.</p>
   <p>At 4:30 in the afternoon, Mr. J. F. Smietanka, C. F. Petikowski, and Frank A. Kwasigroch spoke as guests of honor at this banquet.</p>
   <p>To the reception committee, headed by Bishop Muldoon, belong 95 members, and among them is Mr. Michael Swientkowski.</p>
   <p>At 7:30 in the evening, Vespers and apostle blessings will be performed by Rev. Father Diomede Falconia at the Cathedral.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0184.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During this day, Sunday, Nov. 15th, many Polish churches in Chicago will hold special services to commemorate this great Polish Catholic congress of missionaries. The churches are as follows:</p>
   <p>Sunday afternoon at St. Josephus parish, Bishop Rhode will officiate the Holy Sacrament duties, Confirmation, Divine services. He will bless the parishioners and offer a few kind words to these faithful believers.</p>
   <p>At 7:30 in the evening at St. Anna's parish, Missionary G. Legris, D. D., from Bourbonnais, Ill., will officiate at the Divine services, Vespers, and bless the congregation.</p>
   <p>At 7:30 in the evening at Holy Trinity parish Most Rev. Father James Schwebach, D. D., Bishop from La Crosse, Wis., will officiate at the Vespers and offer Divine services to the congregation.</p>
   <p>At 7:30 in the evening at St. Adelbert's parish the Most Rev. Father, John F. Cunningham, D. D., Bishop from Condordia, Kas., will also officiate at the Vespers and offer Divine services to the congregation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0185.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>At 7:30 P. M. at St. Mary's parish, the Divine services and Vespers will be officiated by the Most Rev. Father John Stariha, D. D., Bishop from Lead, South Dakota.</p>
   <p>Monday two sessions will be held to commemorate this celebration. At 9 o' clock in the morning the people will gather at the corner of Michigan Avenue and 16th street and accompanied by the Polish Veterans, will parade down Michigan Avenue to the Armory, where Divine services will be performed. At 2 o'clock in the afternoon, the Ladies' Catholic League will have a banquet to honor all the prelates, bishops and priests taking an active part in this celebration.</p>
   <p>Tuesday Nov. 17th two sessions of this congress will be held, one at 9:30 in the morning, the other at 3 in the afternoon. Bishop Rhode will officiate at the morning session.</p>
   <p>In the evening of this day, which is to be a special evening for the Poles and Lithuanians, pontifical vespers will be conducted in all <pb facs="5423968_10_0186.jpg" n="5"/>Polish and Lithuanian churches in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In the oldest Polish Catholic church, St. Stanislaus, the pontifical Divine services will be performed by the apostle delegate Rev. Father Diomede Falconia. The sermon will be read in Polish.</p>
   <p>On Wednesday, Nov. 18th, two sessions will be held, the first at 9:30 in the morning; the second at 2 o'clock in the afternoon. At the morning session Missionary Piotrowski will speak on "Unity Among Catholics."</p>
   <p>In the evening at 8 o'clock the celebrated congress will finally come to a close. Admission will be by tickets only.</p>
   <p>Many committees of this congress will be headed by Poles and they will make up the largest number of people present.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0187.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The president of the arrangement committee is Bishop Rhode. Besides him there are 44 members in this committee. Among them are Rev. Father John Kosinski, C. R.; Most Rev. Father Alexander Skrypko; Most Rev. Father M. Krawczunas; Mr. Ludwig Pinderski, Dr.; W. A. Gorny; Stanley Ratajaczak, Edward Javecki and John Nerring. The secretary of all important sessions will be Anthony Czarnecki.</p>
   <p>The transportation committee consists of 41 members. Among the higher officials are Rev. Father Nawrocki, Most Rev. Father Edward Stefanowicz, Mr. Stanley Kwiatkowski, and Edward Szajkowski.</p>
   <p>The directors' committee in charge of officers and programs consists of 22 members, among them are Mr. John F. Smulski, Joseph Niestopinski, Stanley Szwajkart Dr., William Klarkowski, K. Susralski, Phillip M. Ksicki, Anthony Promiski, Joseph Buszkiewicz, Nicholas Budzban, Teofil Gordon, Michael Pejza, and John H. Kowalski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0188.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The committee in charge of distributing tickets consists of 39 members, among them Mr. J. Jozwiakowski, John E. Wieklinski, Dr. Alexander Pietrzykowski and Paul Drzymalski.</p>
   <p>The press committee consists of 5 members, one from each of Chicago's Polish daily newspapers. Representative of the Dziennik Chicagoski is Mr. Carl H. Wachtel. Mr. Adam Block, a co-worker of Mr. Wachtel, is a member of the general press committee.</p>
   <p>To the committee of speakers and celebrities of congress belong 15 members, among them Rev. Father Andrew Spetz, C. R., and Most Rev. Father F. M. Wojtalewicz.</p>
   <p>The musical committee consists of 6 members, including Most Rev. Father K. Gronkowski.</p>
   <p>The committee for convention programs lists 6 members, including Most Rev. Father Casmir Sztuczko.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0189.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>We also have a ladies' committee in charge of the Catholic Women's League, but in this committee no Polish women hold office.</p>
   <p>According to the above mentioned program of this Catholic congress, it should interest all Poles and Lithuanians of Catholic belief at the present time, and should make them very anxious to await the forthcoming Polish Catholic congress of missionaries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
