<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-23">Jan. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Delegation in Washington</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-01-23">Jan. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH DELEGATION IN WASHINGTON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Representatives of various organizations, Polish as well as those of other nationalities, appeared on January 22, 1915 before the President of the United States to protest against the immigration bill which contains a provision directed against [the admission of] illiterates.</p>
   <p>The hearings were held publicly and lasted for approximately three hours. Supporters and opponents of the bill were both well represented. Each side was given an hour and a half in which to present its arguments.</p>
   <p>The opposition group was headed by Mr. Burke Cockran, of New York, and the faction supporting the bill by Mr. Frank Morrison, secretary of the American Federation of Labor. Among the Poles who spoke were Mr. Adam S. Gregorowicz, representing the Polish National Alliance; Miss Emilie Napieralski, delegated by the Polish Women's Alliance, and Reverend John Sobieszczyk, who spoke in behalf of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. In all, there were about five <pb facs="5423968_10_1681.jpg" n="2"/>hundred delegates from both sides, but only a few of the more prominent spoke. Congressmen Sabath, of Chicago, and Goldfogle, of Boston, argued against the bill.</p>
   <p>The Polish delegates spoke the longest and the most convincingly. They asserted that the adoption of the bill would not only constitute a grave abuse of the cardinal principles of this Republic but would also bring great harm to thousands of sincere and diligent workers. They showed that illiterate workingmen are superior to educated scoundrels, drunkards, and cheats. These arguments created a lasting impression upon those present.</p>
   <p>In addition to Frank Harrison, other speakers in favor of the bill were Mr. William Clark, of Chicago, representing the conductors, firemen, and railroad engineers' union; Mr. J. H. Patten, representing a farmers' organization; Professor H. P. Fairchild, of Yale University; and Professor E. A. Ross, of Princeton University. In general, those favoring the bill claimed they represented some 245,000 members of various organizations, religious and patriotic <pb facs="5423968_10_1682.jpg" n="3"/>(?), in New York and New Jersey.</p>
   <p>In addition to the Polish delegates and Congressmen Sabath and Goldfogle, other speakers against the bill were Miss Grace Abbott of Chicago, a social worker; Oswald Garrison Villard; Charles Edward Russell, a Socialist of New York; and Robert Wagner, of New York.</p>
   <p>All the supporters of the bill argued that the flow of immigrants not only lowers the wages of the workers born here but also deprives them of work. They contended that the American worker cannot live on the wages accepted by foreign workers, that illiterates cause an increase in crime, etc. The professors contended that if our ports were closed to the illiterates, the Europeans would become more interested in Europe. They concluded that humanity in general would benefit by such a restriction [of immigration].</p>
   <p>Mr. Patten, the farmers' representative, went so far as to assert that the <pb facs="5423968_10_1683.jpg" n="4"/>opponents of this bill wanted to Russianize America. This absurd contention of the chauvinist was reprehended by President Wilson, who forbade him to make any more statements of this kind.</p>
   <p>Mr. O. G. Villard, an opponent of the bill, showed statistically that people born here who know how to read and write commit a greater percentage of crime in the United States than the illiterate immigrants. Mr. Edward Russell stated that by denying entry to illiterates the United States would cease to be a free nation and a refuge for unjustly persecuted political transgressors. Mr. Robert T. Wagner said that although the population of New York is composed of eighty per cent aliens or children born of foreign parents, the percentage of illiterates there is low and the city prospers excellently thanks to the work of these foreigners.</p>
   <p>Finally, when both sides exhausted the time allowed for presenting their arguments, the President announced that he would give due thought to the bill.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1684.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>He has until January 28 [to consider his decision]. If by that time he has not decided whether to sign or veto the bill, it will automatically become law.</p>
   <p>It is, however, expected that the President will take a definite stand on this matter and veto the bill, in view of the fact that he has threatened to do so on many occasions.</p>
   <p>The supporters of the bill in Congress are certain of victory despite the presidential veto. Those who do not share the opinion of the proponents of the bill are equally confident that if the bill is vetoed, its advocates will not succeed in gaining the necessary majority to overrule the President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
