<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-01-24">Jan. 24, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Partiotic Society Organized at Saint John Cantius Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1024</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1024.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-01-24">Jan. 24, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">PARTIOTIC SOCIETY ORGANIZED AT SAINT JOHN CANTIUS PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have been asked to publish the following announcement in the Dziennik Chicagoski:</p>
   <p>On January 22, the Poles of John Cantius parish held a meeting for the purpose of organizing in their parish a new Polish society, entitled Polska Organizacja Patryotyczna (Polish Patriotic Organization) or Servants of the Queen of Poland [Society]. The gathering was unexpectedly large. The Polish young folks, especially, proved that they desire to serve the Queen of Poland and the motherland; their interest proving that in the new John Cantius parish there are many hearts beating for the motherland.</p>
   <p>Reverend Florian Matuszewski, the founder of the organization, opened the meeting with a prayer, explaining to the audience that the purpose of the organization <pb facs="5423968_10_1025.jpg" n="2"/>is to serve the Queen of Poland, the Holy Virgin Mary. The public listened attentively, the words of the speaker touching their hearts. Full of enthusiasm at the words of the speaker, the parishioners decided to form the organization, proceeding immediately to the election of a board of directors, for which the following members of the parish were elected: Reverend Florian Matuszewski, leader and spiritual adviser; Francis Kwasinski, president; Francis Cliniecki, vice-president; Anthony Chlabowski, secretary; Francis Klaczynski, treasurer; Anthony Jasinski and Francis Osuch, directors; and Matthew Gorecki, chairman.</p>
   <p>Every person joining this organization must pay one dollar initiation fee and ten cents monthly dues. According to a decision made at this meeting, the new organization will co-operate with the Polish Patriotic Organization of St. Stanislaus Kostka parish.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held this Sunday, January 28, 6 P. M., at the St. John <pb facs="5423968_10_1026.jpg" n="3"/>Cantius parish school hall, Carpenter and Front Streets. Those who desire to join this organization should come to this meeting. So far thirty persons have joined.</p>
   <p>Anthony Chabowski,</p>
   <p>76 Cornelia Street,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
