<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-12-17">Dec. 17, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Forty-Hour Devotion Services in St. Mary of Perpetual Help Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0973</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0973.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-12-17">Dec. 17, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">FORTY-HOUR DEVOTION SERVICES IN ST. MARY OF PERPETUAL HELP PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Forty-Hour devotion services began in St. Mary of Perpetual Help Parish December 11 and continued until December 13. High Mass was celebrated at 10 P.M., and the sermon was delivered by Reverend Gutkowski of Detroit. Vespers were celebrated in the evening at 7 o'clock.</p>
   <p>The concluding sermon was given by Reverend Kozlowski of Manistee, Michigan.</p>
   <p>During the three days, the church was constantly visited by parishioners and visitors from other parishes. Over thirty-five hundred persons went to confession and partook of the Blessed Sacrament. This is sufficient evidence that the parishioners heeded the call of their good pastor.</p>
   <p>The following priests came to the assistance of our local clergy: Reverend Gutkowski of Detroit, Michigan, Reverend Matkowski of Bay City, Michigan, <pb facs="5423968_10_0974.jpg" n="2"/>Reverend Skory of Gaylord, Michigan, Reverend Lipinski of Saginaw, Michigan, Reverend Kozlowski of Manistee, Michigan, Reverend Szukalski of Milwaukee, Wisconsin, Reverend Balczewicz of Chicago, Illinois, Reverends Koblynski and Wojtalewicz of Hammond, Indiana, Reverends Tyszka and Brodowicz of LaSalle, Illinois, Reverends Lange, Laczynski, Sztuczko, Truszynski, Sedlaczek, and Matuszewski of Chicago, Illinois, and Reverend Kolesinski of Terre Coupee (sic).</p>
   <p>Sincere thanks are expressed for the kind help and co-operation of the clergy and parishioners.</p>
   <p>A Parishioner</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
