<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 31,
<date when="1904-02-06">Feb. 6, 1904</date><title level="a">"From Michigan City, Indiana."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>Polish</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item><item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 31,
<date when="1904-02-06">Feb. 6, 1904</date><title level="a">"From Michigan City, Indiana."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Michigan we have about 20,000 inhabitants, of this number we have about 400 Polish families.</p>
   <p>The Polish people have a Catholic church, St. Stanislaus, with Rev. Father E. WROBEL as pastor; and the Catholic school has an attendance of 200 children, which shows that the Polish people are doing nicely with so few people.</p>
   <p>Rev. Father E. WROBEL is at the head of all great Polish movements, such as church affairs, bazaars, picnics, club organizations and many others. The people place their faith in their pastor, because he is working solely for the good of the Polish welfare.</p>
   <p>Some of the work of Rev. Father WROBEL is as follows: - (He organized these)</p>
   <p>1. Society of St. Hedwig, group No. 24 of the Roman Catholic Religion was organized in 1899, has 75 members, and 200 dollars in the bank.</p>
   <p>2. Society of St. Casimir, was organized May 20, 1892, has 166 members and 900 dollars in the bank.</p>
   <p>3. Society of St. Stanislaus was organized in 1891, has 80 members, and $600.00 in the bank.</p>
   <p>Besides these mentioned above there are a few groups of ladies and young men's societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0291.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To show their appreciation for the Rev. Father's good work, the Polish people bought a new furnace for $600.00 to be used to heat the church.</p>
   <p>In the neighborhood near this church of St. Stanislaus, the Felician Sisters of La Fayette, Indiana, made collections, to build a Polish hospital at the cost of $50,000, when completed will be be named St. Anthony's Hospital.</p>
   <p>We also have a 24-piece orchestra all Polish musicians, living near St. Stanislaus, this also shows that the Polish people are a hard working, and ambitious group.</p>
   <p>We the Polish people are trying to get a Polish pharmacist, a lawyer, a doctor, and an interpreter to move into our neighborhood, for the Polish people who do not as yet speak good English, and do not understand the English language. The committee in charge of this is: Mr. John ZIETARA and Mr. Peter SZWAZ.</p>
   <p>There is plenty of work here, and many Poles seeking employment can find it in the new Michigan City railroad yards or in the candy factories, where many Poles are working.</p>
   <p>The children are being taught the English language as well as their own native tongue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
