<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 17,
<date when="1916-04-26">April 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Scouting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XX, No. 17,
<date when="1916-04-26">April 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SCOUTING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Started by the Polish National Council, (P. N. C.), the idea of Polish scouting is getting slowly but steadily more popular among lovers of scouting.</p>
   <p>The Scout Commission, composed of scout instructors from Chicago and Milwaukee, elected an executive committee consisting of the president, vice-president, secretary, cashier and general scoutmaster, whose duty is to propagate the idea of scouting among the school youth.</p>
   <p>We are asking for cooperation and support from the pastors.</p>
   <p>In all matters connected with scouting, please ask for and address letters to the secretary of the commission: Polish Boy Scouts Council, 984-6 Milwaukee Avenue, Chicago.</p>
   <p>Regular monthly assessments for funds should be sent to the cashier, W. Follmer, 8742 Exchange Avenue, South Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1457.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To carry over the plans of the scouting commission we need financial support, so we are asking all good scouting friends for their help.</p>
   <p>His Excellency Wojtalewicz, pastor of the Immaculate of St. Mary, at the meeting of the P. N. C., promised to pay us a $50 monthly fee for the above funds.</p>
   <p>We are grateful to him for such a lavish gift. We are asking others to act likewise.</p>
   <p>The commission of scouting will hold an outing and camping expedition of all Polish scout troops from Chicago and suburbs. Mr. A. Malkowski, general scoutmaster of Polish scouts in Europe, is in the United States at present and has promised us he will be there.</p>
   <p>If there are plenty of funds the course for instructors headed by Mr. A. Malkowski will begin in May or June.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1458.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Scouting in America is developing with the greatest rapidity in all states, on account of rich and influential people who like a good system of bringing up the youth. We are sure that in a short time it will be in the schools, that is why we Polish youth should join and organize scout troops.</p>
   <p>Pastor T. Langfort.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
