<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-26">May 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Pole Admitted to West Point</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-26">May 26, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">POLE ADMITTED TO WEST POINT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not easy to become a cadet at the West Point Military Academy, because of the limited number of young men each state can recommend, and because of the high qualifications required of each applicant for entrance.</p>
   <p>Many an American young man would like to enter West Point. How much effort is often exerted by such young men, how many parents would like to see their sons in West Point uniforms--all in vain! It is as difficult for a great many young men to get into West Point, despite greatest efforts, as it is to draw a whole garment through the eye of a needle.</p>
   <p>Henry Szymanski, son of a well-known and respected citizen living at 858 North Wood Street, Chicago, was a fortunate young man to be admitted to West Point through the efforts of Casimir Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance, and on the recommendation of Congressman Gallagher.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1400.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Henry Szymanski was born on July 4, 1898. He received his early education at Holy Trinity parochial school, Chicago, and the Polish National Alliance Academy in Cambridge Springs, Pennsylvania. He later attended Northwestern University with a view to becoming a lawyer.</p>
   <p>He had an uncommon liking for military training of any kind, and he always linked physical training with mental, proof of which is the fact that he excelled in his studies. Those who know him more intimately say that he is of fine and noble character, as a good Pole should be.</p>
   <p>Henry will enter West Point during the first half of June. We believe that he will conduct himself in such a manner as to enable Chicago's Polonia to be proud of him.</p>
   <p>We wish him success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
