<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-21">Apr. 21, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">From St. Adalbert Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-04-21">Apr. 21, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">FROM ST. ADALBERT PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of presidents and marshals of all the societies of St. Adalbert Parish was held at the parish hall Sunday, April 18. The Reverend John Radziejewski, pastor of St. Adalbert Church, opened the meeting and explained its purpose. It was his wish that all the society officials arrive at some understanding as to how they would participate in the observation, on Thursday, April 22, and Friday, April 23, of the nine hundredth anniversary of the death of St. Adalbert. The pastor explained that solemn Vespers will be celebrated Thursday evening and solemn Mass will be sung the following day. Vespers will also take place Friday afternoon, and he urged all church societies to attend in full regalia, if possible. The two-day tributory services, he said, will be concluded with the celebration of the solemn "Completa," Friday evening, at 7:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>F. Wachowski was called upon to preside as chairman, F. Czerwinski as assistant chairman, and Leon J. Schultz as recording secretary. A motion <pb facs="5423968_10_0402.jpg" n="2"/>was made that the societies stage a procession through the streets of the neighborhood. It was agreed that all societies are to meet at 1 P.M., at the St. Adalbert Parish Hall, 16th and Paulina Streets, from where the parade will start. The course of the parade will be as follows: Paulina Street to 17th Street, 17th Street to Ashland Avenue, Ashland Avenue to 18th Street, 18th Street to Wood Street, Wood Street to 17th Street, and 17th Street to the church for Vesper Services.</p>
   <p>The chief marshals of this affair, who were chosen by election, are F. Kirshenstein, Marion Knutkowski, and Joseph Chodyniak.</p>
   <p>A celebration in honor of St. Adalbert, together with a May Day exercise [an event marking the anniversary of the Polish Constitution of the Third of May], will take place on May 2. A special committee was assigned to prepare plans for this coming event.</p>
   <p>Among the societies to take part in the parade are:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0403.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>St. Adalbert B. and M. [Bishop and Martyr] Society</p>
   <p>Holy Name Society</p>
   <p>Holy Name of Mary Society</p>
   <p>St. Casimir Knights' Society</p>
   <p>St. Adalbert No. I Society</p>
   <p>St. Dominik Brotherhood</p>
   <p>St. Dominik Archbrotherhood of the Rosary</p>
   <p>Holy Family Brotherhood</p>
   <p>Sacred Heart of Jesus Society</p>
   <p>Sacred Heart of Our Lady of Sorrows Society</p>
   <p>St. Adalbert Foresters</p>
   <p>St. Michael Archangel Foresters</p>
   <p>St. Florian Cracuses Society</p>
   <p>King Zygmunt Society</p>
   <p>St. Martin Hussars' Society</p>
   <p>Pulaski Volunteers</p>
   <p>August Kordecki Society</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0404.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Pulaski Volunteers, "K and C" (sic)</p>
   <p>St. Stanislaus Kostka Young Men's Society</p>
   <p>St. Cecilia Singers' Society</p>
   <p>The above societies have already agreed to take part in the celebration. All others wishing to participate are requested to be present Friday at 1 P.M. at the St. Adalbert Parish School Hall, 16th and Paulina Streets. It is desired that all societies and members take part.</p>
   <p>Leon J. Schultz</p>
   <p>Secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
