<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 15,
<date when="1921-11-14">Nov. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">About the Cradle of Polish Settlements; Remodeling of St. Stanislaus Kostka's Auditorium</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 15,
<date when="1921-11-14">Nov. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE CRADLE OF POLISH SETTLEMENTS; REMODELING OF ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA'S AUDITORIUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The cradle of Chicago's Polish settlements is the parish of Saint Stanislaus Kostka.</p>
   <p>In 1917, Saint Stanislaus'parish celebrated the 50th year of its existence. The majority of the old Polish settlers, who were forced to leave their mother land and make their homes across the sea, selected this piece of land near Noble St. for their domiciles. From here, just like children leaving the home of their parents, they wandered forth to other places and established new Polish settlements. Saint Stanislaus' settlement is the cradle and mother of other Polish settlements.</p>
   <p>The parish buildings occupy a large square. Saint Stanislaus church is located on one side of the block. The rectory is located in the rear of the church building. On the other side there is the large St. Stanislaus Auditorium and School buildings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0040.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The entire church property presents a magnificent appearance. It is a great Polish Roman-Catholic fortress, protecting our people against moral disease.</p>
   <p>The entrance is located at Noble and Bradley Avenues. The hallway is wide and light. The auditorium itself is very beautifully redecorated. The most prominent is the stage and its curtains. There are two curtains: the first is the steel curtain with the view of Wawel, the other is a cloth curtain with beautiful scenery painted by the Polish artist L. H. Boruski.</p>
   <p>Let us have a good look at this scenery. Below the scenery there is an inscription reading, Cud nad wisla (The miracle on the Vistula). The scenery is composed of two parts: upper and lower. The middle of the lower scenery represents Father Skorupka falling down mortally wounded by a Russian bullet. On his right side, General Haller, on foot, with a sword in his hand, giving a command to attack. Near these two important persons, our soldier holds a Russian by the throat, convincing him <pb facs="5423968_10_0041.jpg" n="3"/>that here is not Matushka Russia (Mother Russia). A little farther the scenery represents two boys: one kneeling, the other resting a gun on his shoulder, aiming at the Russians. Still farther the scene represents the retreating Russian army in disorder. The upper scene represents a company of Polish hussars in the act of attacking, near them a Napoleonic legion, then Kosciuszko, Glowacki and other Polish patriots. There is also a picture of the Holy Virgin. This scene is very beautiful and artistic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
