<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-06">Jan. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">From a Mass Meeting under the Watchword "The Return to Poland in Groups"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-06">Jan. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FROM A MASS MEETING UNDER THE WATCHWORD "THE RETURN TO POLAND IN GROUPS"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Monday afternoon a meeting was held in the auditorium of the Polish Women's Alliance Building to discuss the question of mass re-emigration to Poland.</p>
   <p>The spacious auditorium was completely filled, and many were forced to stand for lack of seats. For more than two hours and a half everybody listened attentively to several speakers. The program of the meeting was very skillfully arranged. At the beginning one of the speakers described the geographic and economic position of Poland, making use of the most recent map. He showed that Poland was a rich country of great possibilities, where there was room enough not only for those living there already but also for all the emigrants now living outside the boundaries of the homeland. He urged that we should return home without delay and go there to work with intelligence, according to a previously <pb facs="5423968_10_1633.jpg" n="2"/>well-thought-out plan.</p>
   <p>He showed how silly it was to work so hard here for ever-decreasing wages or even to be without employment, while over there, in our native land, one can do useful and well-planned work.</p>
   <p>The next speaker, in sincere, warm, and enthusiastic words, proved to those present that now is the best time to go back, since before long all the most important places in Poland will have been taken by foreigners, who in ever-increasing numbers are entering Poland, seeing there a splendid opportunity for themselves. He proved conclusively that one should return to his native land not only to promote his own interests but from a sense of civic duty as well. Return we must, not singly, but in groups, and in groups of which every single individual is well informed as to the purpose of his return and the future work he is to do.</p>
   <p>The next speaker discussed the plan of mass return to Poland and the project <pb facs="5423968_10_1634.jpg" n="3"/>of group work. The speaker indicated that Poles who have the intention of returning home are forming an organization, the "Community," of which the object is to gather all the energetic, alert, and enterprising people desiring to re-emigrate and to form of them one large group whose departure from America and the beginning of whose new life in Poland would follow a well-formed plan for the whole group.</p>
   <p>The aim of this organization is not the promotion of individual profit but the creation of mutual aid and co-operation among its membership. The founding of this organization is not for the purpose of conducting business here in America but of doing business in Poland.</p>
   <p>The organization is based on the sound proposition that each member shall conduct an enterprise in Poland individually with his own capital, while the organization will aid in establishing commercial or industrial enterprises by the wholesale buying of merchandise and the distribution of it among separate units and by supplying information and instruction in <pb facs="5423968_10_1635.jpg" n="4"/>organizing and conducting individual business units.</p>
   <p>Another meeting with the same purpose in view was held on the South Side, where the hall was equally well packed. This fact shows the great interest of our people in re-emigration in groups according to a well-organized plan. Those who attended even demanded that such meetings be held more frequently in order that they might become better acquainted with one another and have an opportunity to exchange views and discuss their ideas on this question. It was decided, therefore, to hold such meetings in different sections of the city.</p>
   <p>From the great interest in this question shown everywhere one is justified is supposing that the great majority are in favor of our plan. Similar movements and the same enthusiasm are shown in many Polish communities all over America, for the members of the "Community" are already at work everywhere in America increasing the family of emigrants returning to Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
