<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-18">Dec. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Will He Veto It?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1639</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1639.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-12-18">Dec. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WILL HE VETO IT?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Burnett Immigration Bill, with its already famous "literacy test clause" for immigrants, was passed recently by the United States Senate. This bill was passed by the lower house of Congress at the last session; evidently the all-powerful "Madame Politics" and fear of the elections kept its promoters from forcing it through the Senate [at that time].</p>
   <p>Now that the elections are over and the Senators no longer need reckon with public opinion, the anti-immigration bill was passed by a large majority. If the House of Representatives approves of certain amendments made to the bill by the Senate, it will then proceed to the White House, to the president, who will either sign it or veto it.</p>
   <p>The major concern is, What will President Wilson do? We know that President <pb facs="5423968_10_1640.jpg" n="2"/>Wilson has already vetoed this bill once before, taking a definite stand against any laws which would make literacy tests compulsory for incoming immigrants. This stand brought him a great deal of popularity not only among the great masses of immigrants, but also among those long settled here, because in many cases their forefathers were illiterate immigrants to this country.</p>
   <p>If we raise our voice against this bill today, it is not because we fear for the fate of our brethren who will come here when the war is over, because it is more likely that Poles from America will return to their native land than that these from Europe will come here; we are concerned with the injustice and the unfairness of the law as compared with the broad concept of freedom symbolized by the Statue of Liberty on the Atlantic coast.</p>
   <p>It is not in the best interests of this country, our adopted motherland, to exclude strong and healthy people, and to take away their chance for a better life simply because they were not taught to read in their native <pb facs="5423968_10_1641.jpg" n="3"/>land, or perhaps because they were not permitted to read as much as forty words in any language. It is not their fault, but the fault of the government under which they lived. It is the government of a country that must always be held responsible for the illiteracy of its people.</p>
   <p>It is too bad that our enlightened lawmakers, such as Burnett and others, cannot understand this, and push through anti-immigration bills with the enthusiasm and zeal worthy of a much better cause.</p>
   <p>We believe, however, that the President of the United States will not share their opinion. We believe that he will veto the bill again, and thus show the world that all of the lawmakers of the United States are not short-sighted bigots who cannot see beyond their own personal interests. If the Congress of the United States tries to pass the bill over the President's veto, and if it succeeds, there is only one--rather sad--opinion that we can hold of those who voted for and passed the bill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
