<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-06-19">June 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Consecration of a Polish Church in Cragin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1074</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1074.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-06-19">June 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">CONSECRATION OF A POLISH CHURCH IN CRAGIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The consecration of the recently completed St. Stanislaus B. M. (Bishop and Martys) Church was a solemn occasion for the new Polish colony in Cragin yesterday. This colony has a promising future before it. Situated on the Northwest Side, just within the boundaries of the city(twenty odd minutes by the train from the Loop), not far from factory and business districts, it has attracted quite a large number of Poles--and will continue to attract them. Besides the Poles already settled there, a great many more own lots on which they intend to build homes. Yesterday's consecration of the church was due entirely to the efforts of the Poles living in Cragin.</p>
   <p>The little church, whose patron is St. Stanislaus B. M., is a frame building with a foundation and steeple of brick. The cost of its construction was ten thousand dollars. Its interior is almost completely furnished. There is a beautiful altar to St. Stanislaus, and bells have been presented to the church by one of the landowners of Cragin. The organ is a gift of Walter Wleklinski of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1075.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The solemn ceremonies of consecration began yesterday at eleven o'clock in the morning. Throngs of visitors from Chicago were present. The following societies from St. Stanislaus Kostka parish came In Corpoke by train: The society of St. Stanislaus B. M. the Society of King Ladislaus under the patronage of Jesus Christ, society of John Sobieski III, and others. Among the uniformed societies present were: the cadets of St. Stanislaus, the Queen's Guards, and the Uhlans of the Holy Virgin of Czestochowa. Representatives were sent by the Societies of St. Michael Archangel, St. Hedwig, and St. Joseph (the last mentioned is from St. Hedwig's parish). The societies marched to the church in a parade to the accompaniment of three bands. Mr. Michael Sergott led the parade on horseback.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Dowling officiated at the consecration ceremonies and addressed the gathering in English. He lauded Polish adherence to the Catholic faith, urging continued devotion to God. The Reverend Vincent Barzynski spoke next in Polish. Among other Polish priests present, was the Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek.....</p>
   <p>A pastor has not yet been assigned to St. Stanislaus B. M. Church, but in the <pb facs="5423968_10_1076.jpg" n="3"/>course of the next few days, a priest will be designated to take up the service of God in this new temple.</p>
   <p>The beautiful weather contributed greatly to the success of this solemn ceremony</p>
   <p>[Note: The ceremony was postponed twice on account of rain]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
