<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 210,
<date when="1908-09-08">Sept. 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">From the Parliament of Polish Unions in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 210,
<date when="1908-09-08">Sept. 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PARLIAMENT OF POLISH UNIONS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The parliament of the Polish Unions in America is in session at the St. Adelbert's parish hall, from which we will receive an accurate report.</p>
   <p>Homes in the neighborhood of St. Adelbert's are beautifully decorated. At 8:30 in the morning, societies from the Parish of St. Casimir (two lady's and two men's groups), with a delegation, marched to the parish of St. Adelbert, where the divine services took place. At the wishes of His Excellency, Bishop Rhode could not take part in the street parades because of important matters coming at the last moment, detaining him.</p>
   <p>Bishop Rhode arrived about 10 o'clock in Mr. Kwiarkowski's car, accompanied by Rev. Fathers Wojtalewicz, John Lange and A. Szpotanski; at 10:30 the Episcopal divine services began. Honorary deacons were Rev. Father Wojtalewicz and Rev. Father Szpotanski; assisting Bishop Rhode at the divine mass were Rev. Father Felix Feldsheim and Rev. Father Zachola; in charge of this ceremony were Rev. Father Lange, Rev. Father Ostrowski, and Rev. Father Truszynski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the church were gathered about 200 delegates from various Polish unions and many priests. The gospel was read by Rev. Father Prelate Dominick Meyer, who for many years was chaplain of the Polish unions in America; also the first Most Rev. Father and pastor of St. Adelbert.</p>
   <p>Before the delegates and priests entered the church the mandate committee was chosen.</p>
   <p>The afternoon program began at 1 o'clock amid a beautiful display of flowers and the singing of hymns and songs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
