<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-26">Nov. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">News from St. Casimir's Parish</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Local News)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-11-26">Nov. 26, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM ST. CASIMIR'S PARISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Local News)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A religious rite of confirmation was conducted at St. Casimir's Parish on Sunday, November 20, 1910. Children and adults not as yet confirmed were to receive this sacrament. Ignoring completely the parishioners' requests for a Polish bishop, the reverend pastor invited an Irish archbishop, the Right Reverend Quigley, to conduct the ceremony. This attitude of the reverend pastor created a general feeling of dissatisfaction among the parishioners. Consequently they acted entirely indifferent to the Irish Catholic dignitary. Neither the religious nor the national societies came out to welcome the archbishop, as is the custom; only a small handful of people loyal to the reverend pastor welcomed the distinguished ecclesiastical official. Many adults failed to appear to be confirmed, having no wish to receive this sacrament from the hands of a person of another nationality. There were many vacancies in the church, because a large number of children also stayed away; and, when the archbishop commenced to talk to the congregation in the English language, <pb facs="5423968_10_0171.jpg" n="2"/>half of those present left the church. This religious ceremony was a total failure because of the anger of the parishioners. Such tactics on the part of the pastor can cause a break in this parish--an occurance that should be avoided. We have enough dissensions as it is among our heavily oppressed people. The maxim taught by the clergy, "He who is a Catholic is also a Pole, and he who is not a Catholic is not a Pole," seems to have lost its effect. This was proved by the behavior of the Polish Catholics in the presence of the Irish Catholic dignitary. In this instance we find that nationalistic feelings have taken an upper hand even over religious feelings. The Poles have indicated clearly that they are staunch Poles and that they want everything to be Polish--even in a church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
