<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-11">Mar. 11, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">St. Casimir Young Men's Society Stages Special Anniversary Program</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-03-11">Mar. 11, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ST. CASIMIR YOUNG MEN'S SOCIETY STAGES SPECIAL ANNIVERSARY PROGRAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special anniversary program was staged by the St. Casimir Young Men's Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish yesterday afternoon at 4 o'clock in the parish school hall. This program was given to terminate a year of work in the benevolent and patriotic field. The hall was filled to capacity by the Polish youth of the parish.</p>
   <p>A picture of the patron saint, consecrated yesterday during special services apropos of the occasion at St. Stanislaus Kostka Church, was on display during the affair. The portrait was painted by the well-known Polish artist, Thaddeus Zukotynski.</p>
   <p>The program was officially opened by John Nering, president of the St. Casimir Young Men's Society, who called upon Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek, chaplain of the <pb facs="5423968_10_1516.jpg" n="2"/>Society, to act as chairman; Vincent Jozwiakowski was appointed recording secretary.</p>
   <p>The program, rich in variety, was as follows:</p>
   <p>St. Cecilia Men's Choir opened the program with the song "Trzysta Lat Przeszlo" (Three Hundred Years Have Passed). Then the choir sang "Z Ojczyzny Mej Wagnany" (Exiled from My Fatherland) and "Serce Lasze" (Polish Heart). The audience received these national songs with unstinted applause. Credit should be given to Andrew Kwasigroch for his fine direction. J. Kondziorski sang a beautiful Polish solo which captivated the audience.</p>
   <p>Declamations were executed with great feeling by A. Klafta, A. Frank, J. Anderszat, and Julian Szczepanski.</p>
   <p>The program was given added color by the amateur mandolin orchestra, composed of members of the local post office. This group offered their services free of charge; they were invited by F. Kwasigroch, superintendent of the Milwaukee Avenue Post Office.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1517.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Henry Nagiel, who spoke on "Youth--That Is Our Future," was the initial speaker of the program. He pointed out the importance of Polish youth and described the duties it is to perform. He urged it to elevate, enlighten and moralize itself; to make a sincere effort toward truth, good and justice; to protect its ideals; and to follow the road that leads toward the culmination of Christian morals and truth. Mr. Nagiel especially urged the Polish-American youth to retain its Polish culture, to be fond of work for the Polish cause, and to maintain the high standards and ideals which were handed down to us by our fathers.</p>
   <p>Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, who was a part of the audience, was requested to make a speech. He directed his words, warm and sincere, toward the Polish youth in the hall. He told this youth that its primary aim is to safeguard its virtue and religion, and through faith to find various means of work for the Polish cause. The pastor pointed out St. Casimir as a model after which Polish youth should always pattern itself, <pb facs="5423968_10_1518.jpg" n="4"/>if it wishes to be respected by God and its fellowmen.</p>
   <p>The next guest to take the speaker's stand, by invitation, was Peter Kiolbassa, who expressed sincere wishes for the continuation of the good work and growth of the St. Casimir Young Men's Society. He urged the youth to live honorably, and to remember religious, family and citizenship duties, as well as national ones. Mr. Kiolbassa stated that the present day Polish youth is fortunate as compared to the youth of the times of the early Polish settlers; for they have schools, churches, libraries, and societies at their disposal. He urged it to take advantage of all these opportunities.</p>
   <p>All the speakers were received with enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>The occasion was closed by Reverend Sedlaczek, chaplain of the Society, after which the Polish national hymn "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland) was sung by the Polish youth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1519.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>A word must be said about the beautiful painting of the patron saint of the Society, created by Mr. Zukotynski. It is indeed such a fine piece of art work--one that our Poles of Chicago can take pride in. The portrait is a true representation of St. Casimir; angels with emblems of the faith fill the background. In the corner of the picture is found the coat of arms of Poland and Lithuania. The coloring is unusually beautiful and realistic. Its worth is recognized not only by lovers of art, but also by the average person.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
