<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-16">Mar. 16, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Conclusion of the Mission in St. Hedwig's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-16">Mar. 16, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">CONCLUSION OF THE MISSION IN ST. HEDWIG'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since last Thursday our missionary, Father Szulak, has been assisted by the Reverend Father Matuszek of St. Louis, Missouri, a priest serving God among the Poles in America since 1864. Both of them are Jesuit priests, and are among the oldest of our immigrant clergymen. They alternated in preaching the sermons during this mission.</p>
   <p>The closer it was to the end of the mission, the greater was the crush of the faithful in the Church, and the larger was the attendance of visiting priests.</p>
   <p>The first Mass, at four o'clock yesterday morning, was offered by Reverend Szulak. The second Mass, at seven o'clock in the morning, was offered by Reverend Matuszek. At both of these Masses the members of various parochial societies received Holy Communion. At eight o'clock in the morning the pastor, Reverend John Piechowski celebrated the first Mass, and then Reverend Matuszek <pb facs="5423968_10_0550.jpg" n="2"/>preached the first sermon.</p>
   <p>After the next Mass, offered by Reverend Dr. Biela, a High Mass was celebrated by the Reverend S. Turski. Father Szulak then preached the words of Christ.</p>
   <p>In the afternoon the ceremonial vespers were celebrated by Reverend Dr. Biela, and Reverend Matuszek preached the sermon. In the evening the Rosary was recited by the Very Reverend Simon Kobrzynski, the superior father of the Resurrectionist Congregation, and the last mission sermon was preached by Reverend Szulak.</p>
   <p>Great crowds of the faithful filled the church, the aisles, and the stairways, or stood on the street if unable to get into the Church.</p>
   <p>In an impressive spiritual array, the crowds assisted during the ceremony of blessing the Mission Cross, to which certain indulgences are attached. All of <pb facs="5423968_10_0551.jpg" n="3"/>the priests visiting the parish at the time also took part in these unusual ceremonies, which were performed by the Reverend Szulak, who then bestowed the Apostolic Blessing on the faithful, and concluded with the Benediction of the Blessed Sacrament.</p>
   <p>The singing of "To Deum Laudamus" (We Praise Thee, O Lord) by the entire assembly ended the mission in the St. Hedwig Church.</p>
   <p>Those taking part in yesterday's ceremonies, besides the two local priests, Reverend John Piechowski and Reverend Dr. Biela, were the two Jesuit priests, Reverend Szulak and Reverend Matuszek, Very Reverend Simon Kobrzynski, Reverend Theophil Szypkowski, Reverend Joseph Gieburowski, Reverend Casimir Furman, Reverend Truszynski, and Reverend B. Nowakowski, all of Chicago, and Reverend S. Turski of Bay City, Michigan.</p>
   <p>Twenty priests, all Poles, took part in this mission.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0552.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Reverend Father Szulak left Chicago this morning to labor in Michigan. Reverend Father Matuszek is leaving tonight for the same place. Both he and Reverend Turski expect to visit their brother clergymen and some other friends in the neighborhood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
