<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-18">Nov. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Reply to Article of Clergyman from New England</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Voice of the People)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-18">Nov. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REPLY TO ARTICLE OF CLERGYMAN FROM NEW ENGLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Voice of the People)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I have read in Dziennik Zwiazkowy, of which I am a constant reader, the article by the reverend from New England, in the issue of October 28, 1911, and since this article has antagonized me, I hope that I too may be granted the privilege of having a few words published in the same column.</p>
   <p>The clergyman from New England attacked us for being dissatisfied with the parochial schools, and declared that we should be grateful to the Polish clergy for the work that it is shouldering--upholding the Polish language in a foreign land, and trying to keep our Polish children from losing their national identity.</p>
   <p>This is all very well. But thank Heaven our Polish people can see a little <pb facs="5423968_10_0153.jpg" n="2"/>beyond this, and know what the truth of the matter is. Indeed, how could any sane person allow the wool to be pulled over his eyes in this manner? If there were no Poles here in America, then, certainly, there would be no Polish clergy here either! And when it comes to the matter of the Polish language, a large proportion of the Polish clergy shows no interest in it, with the exception of only a few priests who are true Poles, who feel Polish blood coursing through their veins, and who help parents in educating their children in the mother tongue. This work, however, is very difficult. Children today in ordinary speech use English almost exclusively, even in speaking to their parents. The parents, if they forbid the use of English at home, do so because they do not understand it.</p>
   <p>The clergy does not alone bear the burden of Polish nationalism or Polish welfare. We carry all of it on our own backs--Polish welfare, our future, and the future of our children, and in addition we must also bear the burden of the clergy, to the point of developing humps.</p>
   <p>History tells us that in the days of its freedom, priests were the defenders <pb facs="5423968_10_0154.jpg" n="3"/>of Poland. We can see how well they defended her. The same thing would happen in America were it not for our great organization, the Polish National Alliance. This champion of Polish nationalism stands guard over all Poles, and works for the good of Poland and of her children here in America. Many of our brothers shed bitter tears; often they would be happy just to see the shadow of their homeland, to hear the sound of the bells of its little village churches. Come, brother, to us; admit that you are a Pole; join the Polish National Alliance, which God blesses because we are His children and do His will.</p>
   <p>I, therefore, proclaim, in the name of Polish nationalism: Polish people, open your eyes, awake! Join the ranks of the Polish National Alliance, because only in this organization lies the national good of Poland, because only the Alliance can truly dry the tears of those who weep and need help. Why should not you, our brother, benefit from and help stand guard over your own blood, your own country, and the Alliance here in America? When we feel that we are all Poles, why do we not all gather beneath the banner of the Polish <pb facs="5423968_10_0155.jpg" n="4"/>National Alliance, as our forefathers once gathered under the Polish banner during the reign of King Jagiello, when they rose like one man and ousted the Knights of the Cross? When they raised our Polish flag in battle, the very earth shook beneath the Polish and Lithuanian soldiers, and our forefathers completely annihilated their vicious enemies.</p>
   <p>Brother Poles, let us rise like one man beneath the banner of this great organization, the Polish National Alliance! Let us show the world our solidarity, our numerical superiority, our union under the motto, "Love for the mother country"! If we do this, we will have good schools and good financial institutions, and as we march together in a concerted mass, everyone will have to take notice of us!</p>
   <p>(Signed) A Member of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
