<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 17,
<date when="1917-04-25">April 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Recruiting Station in Polish Roman-Catholic Union Home</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1412</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1412.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 17,
<date when="1917-04-25">April 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RECRUITING STATION IN POLISH ROMAN-CATHOLIC UNION HOME</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>War! War!</p>
   <p>War in defense of human rights, in the name of liberty, in the name of the people.</p>
   <p>War!</p>
   <p>And the Star Spangled Banner is our banner.</p>
   <p>And our Polish Roman-Catholic Union is not only Catholic, but also patriotic, which always and everywhere manifested those dearest emotions and is still manifesting them.</p>
   <p>The time now has come for the greatest trial. And what is happening?</p>
   <p>In the home of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union, atop which wave Polish and American flags, a recruiting station opened up, at the end of the past week.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1413.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the large store which was formerly occupied by the Polonia Clothing Company. At present the Polish-American youth is beginning to give proof that they love the free United States, that its Star Spangled Banner is our banner.</p>
   <p>This recruiting station in the Union Home has been opened in the very center of a district most thickly populated by the Poles, on the Northwest Side of Chicago, where are situated the headquarters of our large organizations, the editorial offices of our newspapers and higher institutions of learning.</p>
   <p>Captain Kenney, the chief recruiting officer in Chicago for the regular United States Army, has fixed the location in the Union Home, 984 Milwaukee Avenue, as a new station, set up exclusively for the Poles in Chicago, and the general secretary has been named the manager.</p>
   <p>The location, as is confirmed by the main Polish newspapers, is ideal in all respects, as the building is at one of the main business arteries in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1414.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The recruiting station, fronting two streets, Milwaukee and Augusta, is quite large. Captain Kenney stated that a better recruiting station could not be found anywhere.</p>
   <p>Captain Kenney has ordered the manager of the station to organize a personnel which will take a few days. All Poles who apply to Captain Kenney for any kind of recruiting information, will be referred to the station manager.</p>
   <p>Addressing all Poles in Chicago, and especially the young men who desire to follow in the footsteps of Kosciuszko and Pulaski and offer their services on the altar of their adopted country, which has given them shelter, freedom and a chance to earn a living, and quite often to become prominent, it is only proper to appeal to them, it is desirous that they join the army through this Polish recruiting station, by which they will render a service to their nationality.</p>
   <p>We should mention here that all type of information will be given at this station as to any branch of the army service, the infantry, cavalry, or artillery in the regular army, information will also be given in regard <pb facs="5423968_10_1415.jpg" n="4"/>to the officers, reserve camps, etc.</p>
   <p>The station will be opened each day up to a late hour.</p>
   <p>And so, Poles, rouse your spirits! Let's harden our strength, let's not be cowards!</p>
   <p>Because the Star Spangled Banner is our banner!</p>
   <p>The war of the United States, our new fatherland, with Germany has already broken out.</p>
   <p>The government calls upon all loyal and good citizens to arms.</p>
   <p>From all directions young men are gathering under the Star Spangled Banner. Poles in other cities, good citizens of this country, are organizing Kosciuszko corps, who will fight for the safety and the rights of America.</p>
   <p>Follow countrymen! Are we to remain in the rear, behind others? Are we to <pb facs="5423968_10_1416.jpg" n="5"/>wait until this country compels us to join the ranks of the army?</p>
   <p>No! Our duty is to protect safety and the rights of this country, this adopted Fatherland of ours. We appeal to all of you to enlist under the American flag. We call the attention of all Polish young men, call at the office in the Union Home, and they will receive all necessary information.</p>
   <p>Do not wait until the Germans and others foes of the United States come to your very homes and dishonor your mothers and daughters, and lead off your aged fathers, burn up your homes and rob you of your property. He who is young, who is healthy, let him join the ranks.</p>
   <p>Let us revive among us the tradition of Kosciuszko and Pulaski, who fought for the freedom of this country.</p>
   <p>Now is the time to join the army. Do not wait and do not say, "Let the others go first." Your country calls, it is time to go and defend our new Fatherland.</p>
   <p>Long live the United States of America!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
