<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-12">Aug. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Independent Church Consecrated Without Services of a Bishop</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0809</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0809.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-12">Aug. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">INDEPENDENT CHURCH CONSECRATED WITHOUT SERVICES OF A BISHOP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, Sunday, will stand out as a memorable day for the residents of the St. Hedwig Parish community.</p>
   <p>The consecration of a schismatic [independent] building [church] was to have taken place and a bishop was to officiate in the services. But there was no bishop!</p>
   <p>The adherents of the ex-Reverend Kozlowski decorated their homes with banners and flags and one of the streets displayed a large sign with the following words: "Welcome Your Eminence, the Bishop, For Coming to Bless the Church of All Saints."</p>
   <p>In truth "his eminence" (a cook from Green Bay by the name of Vilatte) <pb facs="5423968_10_0810.jpg" n="2"/>and Kozlowski and his followers received a set back because of the "bishop's" failure to be on the scene. Instead, Kozlowski blessed the building himself and said from the pulpit that this was sufficient. "His Eminence" will arrive when the church has been fully completed.</p>
   <p>This is how this comedy was performed.</p>
   <p>Truth dictates that we mention that among the flags which decorated the homes we saw a Mussulman flag with a half moon, a Muscovite flag and another, apparently very old, which we could not recognize.</p>
   <p>But this is of lesser import. The fact remains that the ex-priest, Kozlowski, has befuddled a certain portion of our poor people to such an extent that they are going along with him--directly to hell, for they have fallen for his lies.</p>
   <p>These lies and subterfuges, which the schismatic leaders tried to explain, <pb facs="5423968_10_0811.jpg" n="3"/>especially the absence of the bishop, are undergoing various naive changes. A child could not believe such lies in a similar matter.</p>
   <p>It has been said that on the eve of the blessing ceremony a telegram was received by Kozlowski from the Pope with authorization for the "consecration".</p>
   <p>Others seem to have quietly spread the idea that a letter was received from Cardinal Ledachowski.</p>
   <p>Still others (prior to the consecration) openly stated that a bishop from Cleveland (?) will officiate at the services.</p>
   <p>It must be understood that no bishop arrived on the scene.</p>
   <p>The Roman Catholic bishop of Cleveland is the Most Reverend Horstman and <pb facs="5423968_10_0812.jpg" n="4"/>his assistant is the Reverend Boff. Both have and are energetically working against Kozlowski's schismatic influences in Cleveland. It would be illogical for a normal thinking individual to assume that these two priests would favor this schismatic step in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Consequently there was no mythical "bishop" present.</p>
   <p>To explain his absence new lies were fabricated: The "bishop" was kidnapped! That is true....He was to have arrived at some parish--and was ready. But it was here that someone reached him and paid him off with a bag of gold. The "bishop" left and everything was over.</p>
   <p>This was repeated as an absolute truth by some of the schismatics at St. Hedwig Parish, especially by those who had a few drinks the night before. And this from full-grown individuals. Such spread of nonsense has been unheard <pb facs="5423968_10_0813.jpg" n="5"/>of. Perhaps the devil himself must have taken away their power of thought.</p>
   <p>We wish to make it known that the parishioners from the right, of St. Hedwig Church,held a mass meeting at the parish school hall. The attendance was so large that all standing room was occupied.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by the Reverend J. Piechowski, C.R., pastor of St. Hedwig Church, with a prayer. Besides the pastor who spoke, the following gave short addresses: Messrs. Armknecht, S. Zahajkiewicz, Fruzyna, and S. Bieszki. The aim of all speakers was to convince the audience in the belief of the Roman Catholic religion. All speeches were filled with deep respect for the Christian faith. No derogatory statements were made about the schismatics. It only was said that some of our brothers had strayed from the righteous path to the joy of the devil. All speeches were received with loud acclaim.</p>
   <p>The audience left with a deeper inward feeling about its religious beliefs <pb facs="5423968_10_0814.jpg" n="6"/>and with full hope for the future.</p>
   <p>We wish to add that the happenings of yesterday brought this result:</p>
   <p>Many of Kozlowski's adherents, because of yesterday's comical rites, have finally seen through all this deceit and have decided to mend their ways. It has become evident to them that their leaders are charlatans. In a short while all will be of the same conviction.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's incident should help to lift the veil from the people's eyes. If only God would will this!....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
