<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-24">Feb. 24, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Some News from St. Hedwig Parish</title><title level="a" type="sub">by a Parishioner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0594</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0594.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-24">Feb. 24, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">SOME NEWS FROM ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">by A Parishioner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the members of the various societies in St. Hedwig parish, the necessity for unity of action has long been evident. This has been discussed in various ways. Some suggested organizing a local association, others expressed a willingness to join one of the larger death benefit organization. Our pastor decided to call a meeting yesterday, after vesper services, and members of all the local societies attended. All the officers of the general administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union also were present.</p>
   <p>After an appropriate speech by the pastor, Reverend John Piechowski, and the saying of prayer, Mr. Charles Armknecht was chosen chairman, and Mr. Michael Wachowski secretary.</p>
   <p>Then followed a debate, in which Mr. Clemens Belinski, the president, and Mr. <pb facs="5423968_10_0595.jpg" n="2"/>Jedrzejek, the treasurer, of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, spoke on one side; Mr. F. Sobieszcyk and Mr. C. Armknecht spoke on the opposing side. The speakers stressed the necessity of joining some organization, one of which is opening its gates wide for agitators who are endeavoring to overthrow our faith, and for the expatriation of our countrymen; the other guards our dearest treasures, religion and nationality, and at the same time dries the tears of orphans and widows in the case of death of the husbands and fathers.</p>
   <p>Catholics and Poles will do best, in the speakers' opinion, by joining the oldest Polish Catholic organization, to which a great number of our Polish priests belong; it is left to the decision of those present, to which organization the St. Hedwig parish societies will belong.</p>
   <p>When the time came for voting, all present arose from their seats and decisively announced that they wished to join the Polish Roman Catholic Union of America, under the protection of the Sacred Heart of Jesus.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0596.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I am also pleased to announce that our young women's society exists not merely for show. A week ago it gave a sum of money for the Kosciusko monument, and yesterday contributed fifty dollars for a library for girls in our parish. Such generosity for so noble a cause is eloquent proof that our Polish women understand on what foundation true patriotism is built. The daughters of such Polish women will never be lost to our religion and our nation.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Chicagoski has already mentioned the mission which is to be held in our parish. I understand that the mission will commence on Sunday, March 8. It will strengthen the ties binding us to the Catholic church, and those attacking it will lose their influence. The eyes of sober, thinking people are opening wide. They are beginning to realize the necessity for spiritual supervision.....</p>
   <p>All this is happening quietly, without publicity. We hope that the coming mission will do us all some good, and especially that it will please St. Hedwig, <pb facs="5423968_10_0597.jpg" n="4"/>our patron saint, who never will stop in her prayers for the conversion of our poor, misguided brethren.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
