<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-10">May 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Timely Topics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-05-10">May 10, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TIMELY TOPICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's Chicago Evening Post gave a prominent place to an article telling the Americans to bow their heads before the young Polish and Czech men who are enlisting willingly in Uncle Sam's Army.</p>
   <p>Excerpts from this article are as follows:</p>
   <p>"Including the number being sent today, 637 Polish boys have been sent to the regular army during the past week from one recruiting station on Milwaukee Avenue, according to last night's records.</p>
   <p>"In our selfish interpretation of the matter, we have sent these Polish boys out to fight for America as Americans; and so they are.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1402.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"But besides this, the Poles keep before their eyes the vision of a free Poland, the ideal for which brave Polish men have always been willing to die since the time the criminal divisions tore their country out of their hands and gave it to three Emperors as a savory tidbit.</p>
   <p>"The Poles are enlisting in the American Army because by fighting for America they are also fighting for Poland."</p>
   <p>In writing further about the Czechs, who are also enlisting willingly in the Army, and of the part that the Czechs will play some day in history, the Evening Post's editorial concludes with the following words:</p>
   <p>"It is America's good fortune that by fighting for the freedom of all nations, she draws the young men of all the oppressed nations which have found a haven on her shores.</p>
   <p>"This is the reason why Chicago surpasses New York and New England in the <pb facs="5423968_10_1403.jpg" n="3"/>number of men recruited daily for the American Army. Those Chicago citizens who left behind them the plains of Poland or the hills of Czechoslavakia are eager to fight with double enthusiasm. They fight not for one country but for two. They fight not only for America, but for the freedom of the world.</p>
   <p>"Let us give them the recognition they deserve, cries the Evening Post. Let us take our hats off to the Poles and Czechs of Chicago. Let us not deceive ourselves into thinking that Americanism in Chicago is of a higher standard than the patriotism in New York or Boston; but Chicago certainly has a better recruiting record."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
