<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-05">Dec. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish-American Veterans Andthe Bonus Question</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-05">Dec. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH-AMERICAN VETERANS ANDTHE BONUS QUESTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A year from today the question of a bonus for all ex-soldiers who served in the United States Army during the World War will be decided in Springfield, Illinois.</p>
   <p>One thing is certain and this is that all veterans, especially Polish-Americans, could put the bonus money into good use. A favorable decision depends upon the attitude of the ex-soldiers. In order to assure victory, work must be started today in this direction. Surely everyone will sacrifice a little time in order to get a few hundred dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1350.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to make this a possibility the Polish-American veterans are opening a drive for new members. This is being done in order to divide the work for the bonus campaign. The organization is fully determined to do its utmost to get the bonus for its "boys." There are several thousand Polish-American veterans in the state who could accomplish a great deal if they were organized. Success in this drive would be no miracle. The joined forces of such a large group could win any campaign.</p>
   <p>Therefore, in order to be certain of a bonus next year, join the forces of the Polish-American Veteran Organization. Remember, in union there is strength!</p>
   <p>It is certain that if a membership of several thousand of these Polish <pb facs="5423968_10_1351.jpg" n="3"/>youths, who are not afraid to work and fight for their rights, is reached, success will be inevitable.</p>
   <p>All veterans should bear in mind the fact that if they won the War, then it certainly should be easy to duplicate another in our fight for the bonus. After all, this money was promised and there is no reason why it should not be given out. All Poles, both men and women, who served in any branch of the United States Army are eligible and should become members.</p>
   <p>Further information can be obtained by writing to or calling in person on B. F. Kalisz, organizer of the P. -A.V.O., 1656 W. Chicago Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
