<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><date when="1923">1923</date><title>Memorial of the 25th Jubilee of the Parish of St. John Cantius</title> By Rev. Stanislaw Siatka and Rev. Felix Ladon.
<title level="a">Preface</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1315</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1315.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><date when="1923">1923</date><title>Memorial of the 25th Jubilee of the Parish of St. John Cantius</title> By Rev. Stanislaw Siatka and Rev. Felix Ladon.
<title level="a">PREFACE</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the parish of St. John Cantius is one of the youngest, yet, thanks to its prosperous development, it is regarded as one of the biggest, and the best maintained Polish parishes in the United States.</p>
   <p>The start, as always, was rather hard, but owing to the devotion of the parishioners and unfailing work of the organizer, Rev. Jan Kasprzycki, and other priests who came after him, we have overcome the difficulties, and today all of us look with pride upon the fruits of our devotion and work, our parish, which is well known not only here in Chicago, but all over America, and even in the old country, in Galicia.</p>
   <p>Here we give the history of our parish according to its chronicles and narrations of those who know and remember the beginning of the parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1316.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The history of our immigration in the free land of Washington reveals the great vitality of the Polish people and its sense for organized life; thereby denying the conviction of our inability to respect our superiors.</p>
   <p>Of course, if our superiors are despotic, when they do not want to do anything but rule, then our Polish nature, which is through and through democratic, resents and the collision is inevitable. A Pole never was and never will be a slave, because he loves freedom and is able to govern himself quite as well as individuals of other nationalities.</p>
   <p>The best evidence of it is our organized religious and national life.</p>
   <p>The St. Stanislaus Kostka parish is the mother of all parishes on the northwest side of Chicago. This parish, which in the beginning had consisted of only twenty-five Polish parishioners, grew so rapidly that in a short time it set up two separate parishes, St. Josephus' and St. Hedwig's, not counting the Holy Trinity parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1317.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It seemed that after establishing the new parishes, the St. Stanislaus Kostka parish would be able to take care of itself and that its church and school would be spacious enough for many years to come.</p>
   <p>But it turned out to the contrary. The parish did not diminish at all. It rather proved the necessity of a new church and school. And in 1892 first steps were taken to organize a new parish in the neighborhood known as "Polish Patch."</p>
   <p>Next year the ground of the new church and school, at the corner of Front and North Carpenter streets, was purchased for a total sum of $75,000. The cost of the buildings was set at $130,000.</p>
   <p>As soon as all legal formalities of the purchase were arranged, work on the new buildings started under the supervision of the newly appointed first pastor of the parish, Rev. Jan Kasprzycki.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1318.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Within one year the lower part of the church was completed, so that it could serve as a temporary place of worship. Yet, the further development of events at that time, stagnation in industry and unemployment, retarded the final completion of the buildings, and it was not until 5 years later that the church was finally finished.</p>
   <p>The St. John Cantius church was consecrated on Sunday, December 11, 1898. The ceremony attracted such a big crowd that all the streets around the church were impassable.</p>
   <p>Archbishop Feehan, after consecrating the church, addressed the parishioners, emphasizing their generosity and devotion, which enabled to erect that magnificent house of God.</p>
   <p>Members of the St. John Cantius parish can be proud of the fruits of their efforts, because our church is one of the most beautiful not only <pb facs="5423968_10_1319.jpg" n="5"/>in Chicago, but all over America.</p>
   <p>The exterior of the church makes an extraordinary impression. The interior, built in Romanesque style, is bright, full of light, and has perfect acoustics. Five beautiful altars and an organ with a clear tone add to the resplendency of our church.</p>
   <p>Of course, at the beginning the interior of the church was rather poor. But owing to the zeal of its pastors and the continuous generosity of the parishioners, the shrine gradually became the most impressive one.</p>
   <p>The pastors, under whose leadership the church was beautified, were Rev. E. Sedlaczek and Rev. S. Rogalski. Particularly, the latter took pains in bringing the church and the parish to its most developed state.</p>
   <p>During Rev. Rogalski's pastorship the interior of the church was painted, and two years later a clock was set on the church tower.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1320.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>All that, the painting, the clock and some additional work on the premises, cost $8,500. The next pastor, Rev. J. Kosinski, established a ventilation plant and electric light. And so the St. John Cantius church became not only the most beautiful, but also the most hygienic church in Chicago.</p>
   <p>School: One of the most important things in a parish is the school, where the young generation is fostered and reared. For us, Poles, the parochial school is specially important, because in that school children receive not only a religious but also a national education.</p>
   <p>If the third generation of our immigration in Chicago still speaks Polish, the credit for it should be given to the parochial schools. The first organizers of Polish parishes in America, the Resurrection Fathers, were quite aware of the mission of the parochial school; and that was why they were so infinitely concerned over the establishment of schools. Before they ever built a church, a school had to be set up, where children could assemble for classes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1321.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The same principle prevailed when first steps were taken to establish the parish of St. John Cantius.</p>
   <p>Even before the lower part of the church was completed, Rev. J. Kasprzycki altered one of the buildings, which had been purchased previously, and set up there the St. John Cantius School.</p>
   <p>The immediate enrollment for the school amounted to 150 children.</p>
   <p>In 1894 two houses, at the corner of North Carpenter and Chicago Avenue, were altered to accommodate the ever growing number of pupils, which at that time amounted already to 1,000 children. Fifteen sister-teachers were in charge of the pupils. The classrooms were not sufficiently hygienic nor comfortable, and upon Rev. Rogalski's suggestion the parishioners decided to raise funds for the erection of a new school building.</p>
   <p>In the spring of 1903 the conerstone was laid, and on December 27, 1903, the 10th anniversary of the establishment of the parish, the new school building was completed and regular classes began.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1322.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The school building is very impressive. It consists of thirty comfortable and hygienic classrooms, in which over 2,000 children receive their primary education, under the protection and supervision of thirty teaching sisters. The principal of the school for many years was Sister M. Oswaldyna, who, through her education, long practice and tact, contributed very much to the development of the school. The Board of Education of the City of Chicago granted our school all the prerogatives of a public school.</p>
   <p>The House for Sister-Teachers and further improvements in the parish buildings: The sister-teachers' lodgings were quite inadequate. They lived in two dilapidated houses, in very uncomfortable and unhealthy condition. Because of that situation, and in order not to mortgage the parish, it was decided to delay the erection of a separate building for the teachers, and instead purchase a neighboring house on Fry Street, in which the sisters could be temporarily accommodated.</p>
   <p>In 1914 Rev. Kosinski signed a contract for repainting of the interior <pb facs="5423968_10_1323.jpg" n="9"/>of the church, but did not live to see it done. His successor, Rev. Wincenty Rapacz, took care of all the improvements and alterations that were indispensable to insure the parish buildings against possible damages. The cost of the interior decoration amounted to $11,000.</p>
   <p>On March 4, 1915, Rev. Stanislaw Siatka, a newly appointed pastor, arrived, and immediately took general charge of the parish. His assistants were Rev. W. Rapacz, Rev. W. Filipski, Rev. J. Prechowski, and Rev. W. Kuniecik.</p>
   <p>In 1916, after necessary improvements in the heating plant and some alterations about the church buildings, steps were taken to erect the long awaited and the most indispensable building: the house for sister-teachers. Four lots were purchased for $19,000, and on July 17, 1916, the building of the house started. The work was completed next year, and on August 5, 1917, the sister-teachers were accommodated in the new, spacious building.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1324.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>It would not be an exaggeration if we said that there is no other parish in America, where the sister-teachers enjoy such comfortable and hygienic accommodations.</p>
   <p>The basement of the house consists of a kitchen, pantry, refrigerator and a refectory. The heating plant and the laundry are in a separate part of the basement. The first floor is occupied entirely by offices, guest rooms and a recreational hall for the sisters.</p>
   <p>Apartments and a seamstress' working room comprise the second floor. On the third floor there is a big hall for study, a chapel and some more apartments. Every sister has a separate room. The cost of this building amounted to $75,000.</p>
   <p>Other activities of our parish: The constant and unusual growth of the St. John Cantius parish proves its great vitality. There are twelve confraternities and fifty other lodges under the church's leadership.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1325.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Besides, there exist a charitable organization and other women's clubs.</p>
   <p>The guides of the parish, our pastors, have taken pains in preserving and lifting the religious and patriotic spirit of their parishioners. Another factor which contributed very much to the development of St. John Cantius parish was the harmony, prevailing among the parishioners. Our parish is one of those Polish parishes in America, where not even the slightest controversy has ever arisen. Thereby confirming our conviction that we, Poles, possess a good sense for organized life.</p>
   <p>The St. John Cantius parish took part in the activities with regard to our fatherland, Poland. At the beginning of the World War our people was the first one to start collecting money for our unfortunate brothers, afflicted with the horrors of war. Then, when the Polish National Council in America was established, our parish was not behind in calling upon the Polish population here to unite for the benefit of our oppressed <pb facs="5423968_10_1326.jpg" n="12"/>fatherland, but quite vigorously supported the Polish cause.</p>
   <p>And when the organizing of the Polish army in America began, our parishioners took active part in it and contributed generously to the Polish National Fund.</p>
   <p>Besides the work for Poland, our parishioners manifested their devotion to our adopted fatherland. We were the first on the list of subscribers for the United States Liberty Bonds, and we provided both the American and the Polish armies with a great number of volunteers.</p>
   <p>We may certainly be proud of all we have accomplished during this period of time.</p>
   <p>Rules for the parishioners: Every parishioner should rent a pew in the church for himself and his family, for which he is to pay in advance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1327.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>If someone is so poor that he cannot pay for the pew, he should see the pastor, who will arrange a place for him without any charge.</p>
   <p>Everybody willing to join the parish ought to register, buy a membership book, and, according to his income, contribute to the parish expenditures.</p>
   <p>The price of the membership book is $5. Every parishioner is obliged to pay a $5 yearly share and contribute to the extra collections.</p>
   <p>Whoever attempts to elude these collections, or to foment others against them, should remember that he cannot expect any service or help on the part of the church and the parish.</p>
   <p>But if someone, because of misery or sickness, cannot share in the contributions, then he ought to submit his situation to the pastor, who will temporarily or even entirely exempt him from his duties.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
