<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 18,
<date when="1917-05-02">May 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Early History of Poles in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXI, No. 18,
<date when="1917-05-02">May 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">EARLY HISTORY OF POLES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Very interesting are the annals from the chronicle of one of the oldest Polish parishes in America, and namely St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish in Chicago; this chronicle can be a typical history of our beginnings in this country, an example of how almost all our settlements, parishes and colonies arose and were formed; these annals start from the year 1850 and they sound literally as follows:</p>
   <p>1850. The first permanent Polish settler in Chicago, in the neighborhood where St. Stanislaus parish is located, was Anthony Smarzewski (Scherman), who came to Chicago in the year 1850 and became the founder of the first Polish settlement in this city. At that time this neighborhood was a desolate, muddy area, connected with the city of Chicago by a road called "Plank Road," the present Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>1864. Slowly new arrivals began to flow into this colony and in the year 1864 the settlement numbered about 30 Polish families, who organized <pb facs="5423968_10_0070.jpg" n="2"/>here the first brotherhood aid society under the name of St. Stanislaus Kostka. The founders of this society were Anthony Scherman, Peter Kiolbassa, John Niemczewski, John Arkuszewski, and Paul Kurr. This society nevertheless fell. Through the efforts of Peter Kiolbassa there came to Chicago in February 1864, Reverend Leopold Moczgeba, so as to hear Easter confession of the Poles settled here; he was the first Polish priest in Chicago.</p>
   <p>1866. Just as soon as the settlement increased with new arrivals, there was brought to life the fallen Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka, which also became the first permanent union of Polish life in Chicago. The constitution and by-laws of this society were voted upon and adopted on June 1, 1866. This constitution was printed in Paris, France. The first officers of this society were Peter Kiolbassa,,president; Marcel Ziomkowski, secretary; Lawrence Stas, Joseph Oziewior, Thomas Nowicki, Anthony Bok and Anthony Matysiak made up the board of directors.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0071.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>1867. After the St. Stanislaus Kostka Society became constitutionalized then began the new work of organization. Work was begun on the establishment of a Polish parish and in this aim four lots were purchased at the corner of Noble and Bradley so as to build upon them a Polish church. These lots were bought for $1,700. The settlement at that time numbered 150 families.</p>
   <p>1869. After the plans were prepared by architect Petruszak, the construction of the first Polish church in Chicago named St. Stanislaus Kostka began in September. The church was of frame construction, 40 feet wide and 85 feet long. The first story, 12 feet high, intended for class rooms and an assembly hall for societies. The second story 22 feet high, intended for the church; the height of the steeple with the cross reached 85 feet. The cost of construction amounted to the sum of $6,885. The first pastor was the Rev. Joseph Juszkiewicz. There were 17 baptisms in 1869 and 6 marriages. The parish at that time numbered 235 families.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0072.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>1870. After a six-month pastorship, fatigued with work, difficulties and age, the Rev. Joseph Juszkiewicz retired, and his place was taken by Rev. Adolph Bakanowski. The parish at that time numbered 500 families. There were 64 baptisms and 30 marriages.</p>
   <p>1871. In the year 1871 the Rev. Hieronim Kajsiewicz, general superior of the Order of Resurrectionist Fathers in Rome, visited Chicago, In that year, on June 18th, the consecration ceremonies of the church took place, which were fulfilled by the Rev. Bishop Foley. Five priests took part in the consecration. Eleven mounted marshals and eight societies numbering 2,200 persons took part in the parade. After holy mass, 300 persons received confirmation. The parish numbered about 600 families. The pastor was Rev. Adolph Bakanowski. During that year, in February, the Society of St. Joseph was organized. During the course of that year the pastor was assisted in his work by the Rev. Julius Wolf, the Rev. John Wollowski, and the Rev. Vincent Barzynski. In the year 1871 there were 174 baptisms, 39 marriages and 3 funerals. In the year 1871, during the night of the 7th to the 8th of October, a horrible fire broke out in Chicago, which <pb facs="5423968_10_0073.jpg" n="5"/>destroyed over 18,000 buildings, with a loss of about 300 million dollars. From among the Poles nine lost their property on account of the fire and for a certain time some of them were forced to live in the school below the church.</p>
   <p>1872. After the ill-fated fire a new life began in Chicago, work was plentiful and for that reason the influx of the laborer was very numerous. So many Poles arrived that the Polish church already presented itself too small and during the summer of that year, at a parochial gathering, it was reflected upon what to do, whether to enlarge the church or build another in some other place. The whole affair was carried on between the Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka and the Society of St. Joseph. The result of the discussion was the building of the Holy Trinity Church. Twenty-one acres of land were purchased during that year for the first Polish-Bohemian cemetery in Niles, at Plant Road, the purchase price was $5,500. The pastor was the Rev. Adolph Bakanowski, and the assistant pastor Rev. Peter Kranc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0074.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In this year there were 328 baptisms, 49 marriages and one funeral.</p>
   <p>1873. The Rev. A. Bakanowski left Chicago for Rome on May 29, 1873, and the Rev. John Wollowski was in Charge of the Parish from May 29 to Sept. 15, on Sept. 15th the Rev. Felix Zwiardowski took over charge of the parish as pastor, the Rev. Charles Lanc assisted him in his work. In that year there were 466 baptisms and 74 marriages.</p>
   <p>1874. The Rev. Felix Zwiardowski, not being able to stand the Chicago climate on account of his health, was compelled to return to Texas. After him from July until September 18th, the parish was managed by the Rev. Simon Wieczorek. On September 18th the Rev. Vincent Michael Barzynski was appointed pastor. In that year the first rectory was built at a cost of $1,500. On February 2nd, the sisters of Notre Dame from Milwaukee, Wis., took charge of the school. In the beginning three nuns, and namely Sister Rogeria, Sister Melaria and one postulate (novice). About 150 children attended the school. That fall the number of children increased to 350. In the middle of October a convention was <pb facs="5423968_10_0075.jpg" n="7"/>held in St. Stanislaus Parish, in which twelve priests and many delegates from different Polish parishes took part, in the aim of organizing the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>Here we cut short our annals from the chronicle of the St. Stanislaus Parish, because the last mention in it regarding the organizing of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union moves us into the history of Polish-American organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
