<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-17">Jan. 17, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Disturbance at St. Hedwig Parish</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0955</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0955.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-17">Jan. 17, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">DISTURBANCE AT ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is with extreme pain that we lift the pen to write about a very grievous matter which, unfortunately, brings shame and great damage to a large portion of our Polish people in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We refer to the disturbance and misunderstanding which has been prevalent for some time at St. Hedwig Parish.</p>
   <p>The affair is all the more delicate because the storm that caused the split was created by a Polish priest who, considering his station in life, ought to be a champion of peace among the people, for he is duty bound to set an example among them, to lead them on the road of righteousness, toward salvation, truth and harmony. This priest, this sower of dissention among the people, is Reverend Anthony Kozlowski, who came to America about a year ago and who has been acting <pb facs="5423968_10_0956.jpg" n="2"/>as an assistant at St. Hedwig Parish. This clergyman--now suspended from performing his duties of an assistant, and by the order of the Archbishop left in a state of irregularitatis and deprived of the right to perform the obligations of priesthood--has spun the web of intrigue which has caused this unpleasant agitation at the parish and may result in much unpleasantness for some parishioners.</p>
   <p>Nothing has been mentioned about this condition, because it was felt to be a most unpleasant subject. It has not been touched, because it was hoped that the perpetrators would abandon their evil plans and that as a consequence the matter would quiet down and disappear of its own accord. But when this anticipation was not realized, when the instigators began per fas et nefas (through right and wrong) to press this affair forward, when they did not hesitate to resort to unlawful action and violence, while the righteous parishioners were compelled to seek the protection of the law against this attack, continued silence about it would be unjustified. Therefore we are forced to bring to light the facts in this unpleasant situation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0957.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The facts that present themselves are as follows:</p>
   <p>As is well known, Reverend Joseph Barzynski has been pastor of St. Hedwig Parish for some time. Reverend Barzynski, a secular priest, has commonly been approved by his parishioners, be they members of the Polish National Alliance or the Polish Roman Catholic Union, because his management has been intelligent and efficient, and he has never given his parishioners cause to object to his actions.</p>
   <p>Last year Reverend J. Barzynski added the newly-arrived Reverend A. Kozlowski to his parish. From the very beginning this priest began to disregard his proper duties. After four months--according to present indications--he wove an unbecoming intrigue, directed at removing the present pastor of St. Hedwig Parish and filling the vacancy himself. This plot was carried out secretly. The young assistant went from home to home to provoke the Polish parishioners against the pastor by whispering unfounded stories--and in this way the new assistant slowly built his own "party."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0958.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We all know how credulous our people are; therefore this evil whispering campaign reached an indulgent ear here and there.</p>
   <p>It is interesting to note that this plan against Reverend Barzynski was based upon unestablished claims, the most notable being that the pastor occasionally handled himself too clownishly among the parishioners. We need not comment on this lie, but the plotters at any rate overlooked the fact that under the guise of the clown there beats a heart of gold....It is an established truth that Reverend Barzynski has always wished his parishioners well, that he heartily loved them and in return was loved by them.</p>
   <p>Reverend A. Kozlowski and his cohorts began to gather names on some kind of petition. To a large extent the parishioners, ignorant of the facts, were informed by this clique that the petition was an appeal to have Reverend Kozlowski retained as assistant at St. Hedwig Parish. In reality, it was a petition asking the removal of Reverend J. Barzynski as pastor. This action was dishonest and subject to punishment. Through this procedure hundreds of misinformed <pb facs="5423968_10_0959.jpg" n="5"/>people, mostly newcomers and those unfamiliar with the affair, signed the petition. Many who did not belong to the parish also signed.</p>
   <p>The petition was placed before the Archbishop at the Chicago Diocese. The outcome was obvious. The Archbishop was convinced that the entire matter was an unworthy scheme, and, since no facts were presented to substantiate the claims, denied the leaders of this instigation their demands, and immediately recommended that Reverend Kozlowski, the originator of the plot, who had not as yet been accepted by the diocese, be forbidden to execute his duties as a clergyman in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Reverend Anthony Kozlowski conducted himself ostensibly in line with the Archbishop's edict. He withdrew from the parish and even announced repeatedly that he was leaving Chicago. In reality, he lives with one of his adherents in the parish--and is carrying on his original plans. Secret meetings and conciliabulums have been conducted for several weeks; schemes and acts of violence have been attempted and carried out.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0960.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The aim of the plotters was to create misunderstanding and general disorder. In part, their plans were successful. A point was reached where actual violence occurred. The agitators tried to force the pastor to attend their meeting, but this proved unsuccessful, Then last Sunday they would not permit the services to go on at the church. In the face of this a majority of the parishioners were compelled to look to the law for protection against the small unruly clique. Under the protection of the police services were resumed. Warrants for the arrest of six of the perpetrators of the acts of violence were issued and executed.</p>
   <p>These are the facts of the sad state of affairs at St. Hedwig Parish. The question new arises, what is to happen to the arrested instigators? What is to be the future outcome? This is something that we wish to touch upon.</p>
   <p>By their actions, the culprits have jeopardized their salvation and have assured themselves spiritual punishment. But this is not all. They have also exposed themselves to the civil laws of this country by their disturbance of the peace. Blinded, pushed by unscrupulous plotters, they go forward, unaware of the fate <pb facs="5423968_10_0961.jpg" n="7"/>that is awaiting them. One does not attend the services of the church with the intention of stirring up revolt through agitation and violence. Revolt against the law of the church is revolt against God, under whose authority the church was founded. Such revolts have occurred in the church, but they never shook its foundations. The guilty ones in question are following the road that leads to the loss of their souls.</p>
   <p>It is had to become a part of this evil movement. When such things occur, the laws of the country are generally broken. The guilty suffer the fullest penalties of the law for creating violence, disturbing the peace, and violating the freedom of the individual. In this respect the penalty will be felt by the accused and their families as well.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, we ought to be concerned about our national honor, the honor of the Poles in the presence of other nationalistic groups. News of this incident has reached the local English-language press and is spread out in its columns. This is a blot on our prestige--disgrace in ours.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0962.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Should we carry such dishonor upon our shoulders at a time when we are commemorating the one hundredth anniversary of the partition of Poland? Is it worthy for us to go through with the plans for such a sorrowful anniversary when an attempt is made against the church and our nationality?</p>
   <p>With tears in our eyes we call upon our strayed brothers to collect themselves. Let them spurn the evil whisperings of the plotters. Let them follow the path that is becoming to true-spirited Poles and Catholics.....And God will shower them with His blessings--and all of them will be grateful. If they should pursue the opposite road, if they should continue to thrive on their mistakes, then a very sad future awaits them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
