<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-06-12">June 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Growth of St. Mary's Parish</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-06-12">June 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GROWTH OF ST. MARY'S PARISH</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large number of people residing in Chicago perhaps never had an opportunity to pass through the Polish settlement which is located in the vicinity of Thirty-second and Laurel streets. The improvements which have been made there within the last six years are surprising. Some years ago a stranger passing through this neighborhood would have observed a small frame church, which was located on Springer Avenue. Around this little church there were several cottages, which could be counted from a distance. Another sight was the vast prairies and cabbage fields, which surrounded this vicinity for miles. The appearance was something similar to that of a western village in the spring time. The roads or streets were impassable. There were no sewers there at that time. Street car facilities were beyond reach, and some of the people who settled in that neighborhood in those early days were under the impression that it would take years before this location would be built up.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1151.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But the Polish people had a different opinion; and when the neighborhood began to grow, they commenced to organize a church. An entire block was purchased, bounded by Thirty-second, Laurel, and Musprat streets, and Springer Avenue. Subsequently this block was subdivided into lots. A Sufficient number were retained for a church and school house, and the rest of the lots were sold mostly to Polish settlers.</p>
   <p>The Polish people who settled here at that time were mostly of the laboring class, but they were industious, energetic, and faithful; and those who saved their money from their hard work soon bought lots and built themselves homes. Later the Poles purchased a small frame church and moved it on the church property and a school house was built.</p>
   <p>It is to the Rev. John Zilla that much of the success of the parish is due. When he took charge of it in October, 1886, there was no money in the treasury, and there was a debt of over $1,500 on the church building, besides nearly $5,000 more on the lots. He managed to raise enough money by collections, however; to clear the obligation, and then set about improving the church property.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1152.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He first raised a loan of $10,000, with the permission of the Archbishop of his diocese, to build a new rectory, and then as the frame church grew too small to hold the growing congregation, he decided to build a new one which should accommodate all the Polish people in the neighborhood. The Rev. John Zilla worked hard to accomplish his undertaking, and there was need for hard work, for the cost of the building was $200,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
