<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-08-10">Aug. 10, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Our Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-08-10">Aug. 10, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some of the Catholic as well as all of the liberal papers have stated in their editorials that only four newspapers are actively supporting the Polish Catholic Congress, and about forty Polish American papers are opposed to it.</p>
   <p>This may be so, but we can truthfully say that these four newspapers express the opinion of all the Polish Catholics in the United States, have the greatest circulation, possess much greater influence, and are considered more important by the Poles in America than ten times as many other publications which have very meager circulation.</p>
   <p>The mere fact that of the three daily newspapers published in the United States, the two most influential and with the largest circulations are supporting the Polish Catholic Congress, is sufficient proof that many more voices are <pb facs="5423968_10_0442.jpg" n="2"/>in favor of the Congress, and not against it. And of the weekly papers, Wiara i Ojczyzna (Faith and Fatherland), the official organ of the largest Catholic organization in America, and with the greatest circulation, and the Gazeta Katolicka (Catholic Gazette), also one of the most influential, best edited, and oldest papers in the United States, are also according the Congress a hearty support.</p>
   <p>Certainly, in comparison, the various "rags" of a few hundred circulation are not to be taken seriously.</p>
   <p>Only the Zgoda, the official organ of the Polish National Alliance, can be considered a serious adversary. It does influence a great number of people because of its large circulation.</p>
   <p>But this "patriotic" Zgoda, which claims to be neutral and wishes to exert its influence on all the Poles in the United States, has taken a strange stand. On the one hand the Polish Catholic clergy to whom we owe the fact <pb facs="5423968_10_0443.jpg" n="3"/>that we have remained Poles, following the examples of those great Polish heroes Kordecki, Mieczyslaw, Jagiello, and Jobieski, hold the cross high and cry out to their people on this American soil: "In this sign you will conquer!" On the other hand the Jews (note the last issue of Nowe Zycie [New Life], whose editor is the Jew Korngold) are shouting in the most vicious language for us to turn away from the priests. They hurl the most scandalous accusations at them and hold them and hold them responsible for all kinds of crimes. Then there is the organ of the Polish National Alliance, the organ of the "patriots who love their Fatherland above everything else," a paper which claims it is Polish, patriotic, honest, and sincere, yet in every issue it urges its readers to turn away from the clergy and follow the road to which the Jews and anarchists point.</p>
   <p>You Polish people have your choice; our Catholic clergy and our Catholic press point to the cross at the top of our national flag; the Jews and the liberal party becken you in their direction; in the center, supposedly neutral, the patriotic Zgoda cries out that patriotism demands that you go where Jewry <pb facs="5423968_10_0444.jpg" n="4"/>and anarchism lead; it complains that the clergy values the flag of religion too highly.</p>
   <p>Choose then, which brand of patriotism is most convincing!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
