<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-15">Nov. 15, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Kolaszewski and Kaminski Arrested</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0700</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0700.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-11-15">Nov. 15, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">KOLASZEWSKI AND KAMINSKI ARRESTED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As is well known, the two apostates, Kolaszewski of Cleveland and Kaminski of Omaha, or from God knows where, came to Chicago to disturb the peace of the Poles, to agitate and incite brother against brother, to sow scandal and cast slander and, in other words, to provoke anarchy. It is apparent, however, that the law did not let this pass without taking some action.</p>
   <p>Just as a means was found to combat the anarchists who tried to arouse one class against another, so a method was found to check those lordlings who hastily tried to bring about a disturbance of social peace, create friction amid the Poles, and even cause bloody battles.</p>
   <p>That a remedy for this type of propaganda can be found is set forth by the following facts: One of the local citizens, Isadore Komorowski, was present at the infamous and scandalous "agitation" meeting in St. Adalbert Parish [held at Pulaski Hall on November 12.]</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0701.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When he heard loathsome and abominable reflections cast upon the Roman Catholic clergy of Chicago he realized that the aim of the gathering was the disturbance of the peace and the creation of misunderstandings. It was then that Mr. Komorowski decided to take action against these strangers from Cleveland and Omaha--these intruders and disturbers of the peace.</p>
   <p>On the following day he had a warrant issued for the arrest of Kolaszewski and Kaminski charging them with disturbing the public peace.</p>
   <p>Judge M. A. LaBuy issued the warrant against these disturbers of the peace, and officers Zwierzynski and Laskowski made the arrest on November 13, at 5 P.M. at the home of their companion, Kozlowski, the excommunicated priest.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the arrest, a peregrination about town was started by the friends of the arrested men to find a judge who would accept a bond for their release. It was not until 8 P.M. that a judge, Judge Blum, was found who would release them under bond. As soon as this was done the entire clique repaired to Town of Lake to preside at another "agitation" meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0702.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This affair, of course,did not fare so well. Yesterday at 1 P. M., after a preliminary hearing in Judge LaBuy's court, the case was postponed until November 21. The arrested men remained under bond.</p>
   <p>The law in the case is very simple, and it will be difficult to gainsay it before a competent judge. Moreover, common sense and logic teaches us that some kind of action should be taken to put an end to these disturbances of the peace.....The law should protect us from the activities of such individuals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
