<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 85,
<date when="1922-04-11">April 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Important for Ex-Soldiers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 85,
<date when="1922-04-11">April 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT FOR EX-SOLDIERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reason that a vast number of Poles, former soldiers in the American Army, who have participated in the World War, don't belong to any organizations is because of unreliable information or lack of encouragement. So being the first organizer and present director of the Polish American Veterans' Organization, I wish to express myself in a few words.</p>
   <p>Many of us are ex-soldiers in the various ranks, with minds wandering about a new life after fulfilling the duties toward our adopted country, in defense of civilization, and with full measures for our abandoned Fatherland, groaning in chains, Poland.</p>
   <p>I admit that every one of you experienced this. Today we already know that a person stands and supports himself by his moral strength; that no acknowledgment guards us, if we don't get down to work! It is <pb facs="5423968_10_1342.jpg" n="2"/>convincing that we shall be as we have created ourselves, but not as people wish to make of us. Let us always remember that we were soldiers in one of the greatest wars in the world. This reason alone should separate us from others, because of our services and gallantry under the standard of Uncle Sam. All foreigners were struck with admiration toward our perseverance. We are not referred to as "damned Polacks" any more because they were convinced that in us exists strength and energy. In organization we can't be harmed.</p>
   <p>Friends, the Polish-American Veterans' Organization is the only Polish organization in America. It has no concern with any military or other organizations.</p>
   <p>Honor!</p>
   <p>Leon T. Walkowicz</p>
   <p>Ex-Soldier.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
