<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-09-02">Sept. 2, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Suitable Quota for Both Mexico and Canada</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1613</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1613.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-09-02">Sept. 2, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title><title level="a" type="sub">A SUITABLE QUOTA FOR BOTH MEXICO AND CANADA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time the Department of Labor at Washington has been actively engaged in establishing ways and means of applying European immigration quota laws to Mexico and Canada. The American press however, is not supporting this project as vehemently as it did the limitation of European immigration. One Texas newspapers states that this law would do great injury to both industry and agriculture in the Southwest. Publications near the Canadian border claim it would be an insult to our Canadian neighbors; other publications farther removed from either of the borders are strongly in favor of applying the restriction of immigration to both our neighbors. If the controversy arises over Mexico, writes The Kansas City Star, then the situation is as follows: There are at present in the United States 800,000 Mexicans. In one of the past years, the emigrants to this country from Mexico numbered 68,000, as to the number smuggled in, no one knows.</p>
   <p>The Dallas News differs from others in the Southwest. It says that it would be both a comedy and a tragedy if the number of Mexican immigrants were equal to the quota allowed the English, Irish, Swedish, Danish, and Italian countries.</p>
   <p>The opinion of the Pittsburg Sun is, that the smuggling of Mexicans into the United States has grown to such alarming proportions that the coming Congress will find it <pb facs="5423968_10_1614.jpg" n="2"/>"If a quota were allotted Mexico," says the Milwaukee Journal. "Instead of 68,000 Mexicans, only 1600 would be permitted to enter this country." Probably the states in the Northwest would rid themselves of the cheap laborer, but legally, as yet, they cannot dispose of this curse. The rest of the country would, without protest, be glad to restrict European immigration of cheap labor. And the states in the Southwest should take the same course against Mexican cheap labor. In reply to this; The Post Dispatch from Houston Texas says: "The Southwestern States will fight any such proposed project, because the elimination of the source of cheap Labor would bring about the ruination of many citizens, the farmers in particular. With the mass movement of the Negro to the East and North, the exclusion of Mexican cheap labor would prove a grave danger. Therefore, such movements should not be promoted. Further, restriction of Mexican immigration would cost the United States millions of dollars."</p>
   <p>If Congress, according to The Rocky Mountain News of Denver, closes the doors to Mexican immigration, they will have a harder nut to crack, than they did when they set a quota on European and Asiatic immigration. The St. Louis Globe-Democrat warns that setting a quota on the labor supply, under present circumstances, might eventually lead to a complete breakdown of the quota system. The greatest difficulty in this matter, according to the opinion of The Brooklyn Eagle and The Manchester Union, lies in the fact that if a quota is established for Mexico, then a quota for Canada also must be established.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1615.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, there is a great difference between a Mexican and a Canadian, the former settle in communities populated with their own kind, and are not assimilable, on the other hand, Canadians do not differ from us, therefore, make good citizens. From the North is voiced the indignation of The Helena Independent. They write: "If any friction between the United States and Canada be brought about within the next 100 years, it will be because our bureaucrats are not on a solid footing. They are looking around for a new territory of conquest."</p>
   <p>The Commissioner of immigration, Hull, will endeavor to establish an immigration barrier between the United States and Canada. There is as much logic for such action, as there would be in the establishment of an immigration barrier between the States of Maine and New Hampshire, or any other state. Evidently the hundred percent Nordics, who were so anxious to restrict European immigration, are now confronted with an even greater problem, and instead of Italians and Poles, they have a influx of Mexicans, whose standard of living is much lower than that of the European, besides their being of an unassimilable nature. The southwest is being flooded with Mexicans. The Negro is moving East. You can almost visualize how this Nordic America will look in the future with immigration doors closed to Europeans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
