<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-11">May 11, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Effects of Schism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence from St. Hedwig's Parish)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0380</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0380.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-05-11">May 11, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">EFFECTS OF SCHISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence from St. Hedwig's Parish)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday's [May 9] bloody brawl opposite St. Hedwig's Church, covered by the Dziennik Chicagoski yesterday, was started by young, ardent hoodlums, adherents of the schismatic movement [reference to the independent church that was opened in the vicinity of St. Hedwig's].</p>
   <p>Six drunken hoodlums of the independent faction, armed with a gun, knives, and razors, pounced upon a crowd of young and old parishioners of St. Hedwig's Church who were engaged in a peaceful discourse. Two young men of this orderly crowd were knifed, and by the intervention of God one of the attackers was wounded by the gunshot of one of his allies.</p>
   <p>A reporter from one of the local American newspapers [covered the fight], and it is apparent that he was either one of the independents or one who was bought <pb facs="5423968_10_0381.jpg" n="2"/>out, for a false report of the incident appeared the following day in the Chicago Chronicle. Not only was St. Hedwig's parish discredited, but the Poles of Chicago were made a laughingstock.</p>
   <p>The blame of all the misunderstanding in this parish falls upon the loathsome schismatic clique. It is well known to every one what kind of peace and unity prevailed here formerly; how one respected the other, how [the parishioners] loved one another--it was all pleasant to look at. But since the appearance of the ringleader of the schism [reference to the fallen priest, A. Kozlowski], who has influenced a group of people to fall away from the Roman Catholic Church, everything has changed.</p>
   <p>The prevalent conditions of other schismatic communities have sowed and bred hatred and discord against every individual who is true to God and the Roman Catholic Church. And this hatred is vented without respect for relationship, for brother, father, or stranger, all are treated alike if they are not of [the schismatics].</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0382.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is the gist of the matter. Schism means splitting, severing, or separation. Its first signs are ruin, discord, the severing of brotherly ties, and the loss of the spirit of love and unity. In its stead it sows in people's hearts hatred, misunderstanding, quarrelsomeness, etc.</p>
   <p>Further, this schism spreads on all sides demoralization, wild abandonment of morals, and utter baseness, especially among the youth.</p>
   <p>Since the start of the schism in this once peaceful community one innocent and honest individual of St. Hedwig's Church has been killed by the wild independent horde. Several attacks like that of last Sunday have been made against innocent parishioners, and many of them have been hurt....How much damage have they done....how many unjust demonstrations have been made against the clergy and the parishioners....how many names have been called, and condemnations made, not only of the authorities of the Church but of all true Catholics, it is impossible to say. Whenever they get an opportunity, they cause untold misery to the innocent. At times a number of the old settlers have had to sell their homes <pb facs="5423968_10_0383.jpg" n="4"/>and move to another section of the city.</p>
   <p>Why comment upon all this? The answer is simple. "The flock is like the shepherd, and the stable like the groom," is an old adage.</p>
   <p>So with these people, poor and crude, who hear nothing in their independent temple but blasphemy, lies, slander, etc. They see nothing but shameful scandal seething every where, especially among their own preachers, who are known for their various dishonorable affairs....</p>
   <p>Nothing gets into their hands except the schismatic rags passed out by the independent schismatic preachers. Each issue is filled with hatred and scorn and is read in back streets and saloons.</p>
   <p>In this schism rests the seed of corruption, and the blame should be attached to it for Sunday's fight and for the defamation of the Polish name. This schism is the moral gangrene which corrupts our people, especially our youth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0384.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>An end should be brought to it; the head of this Hydra should be lopped off, and only then will harmony and unity prevail among our people.</p>
   <p>But before this can be accomplished, it must be stated that there must be no repatition of last Sunday's bloody brawl, for there is no place for such disorder among our people. It seems that the same individuals are always guilty of the same crime.</p>
   <p>It is anticipated that the court will deal out proper justice, and that afterwards the police will keep an eye on them until their zeal for battle has cooled.</p>
   <p>At the present time these hoodlums are behind bars and are awaiting trial.</p>
   <p>J. Braha, a member of St. Hedwig's Church</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
