<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-10-23">Oct. 23, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Tamillo, Chrestowski, and Company, Founders of the Polish Independent Church, Are in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0985</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0985.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-10-23">Oct. 23, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">TAMILLO, CHRESTOWSKI, AND COMPANY, FOUNDERS OF THE POLISH INDEPENDENT CHURCH, ARE IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following is the text of a letter we received for publication, and which we mentioned in our first article on the Independent Church. "Similis simili gaudet, that is, 'Like takes pleasure in like.' We know that if one will see something, one will find it.</p>
   <p>"Tamillo, from Saint Hedwig Parish, the sage who some time ago tried to show his great wisdom by making such public statements as 'Moses created God,' etc., has decided to become the founder of a 'wild' church in Chicago to be known as the Polish Independent Church.</p>
   <p>"We Poles recognize only one Holy Apostolic Roman Catholic Church, but this Tamillo, who is evidently a religious maniac, would like to have a church after his own fancy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0986.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"As soon as Tamillo found out that there was a fallen Polish priest who could be bribed, he invited Reverend Kolaszewski--the self-styled priest excommunicated by the Catholic Church, who creates monstrosities called Independent Churches to come to Chicago, or rather to Avondale, for the purpose of establishing a church dependent on Tamillo but independent of the authority recognized by Christ and the Holy Ghost.</p>
   <p>"Kolasewski,who has decided to make not only as living but also a good business out of his dishonest work, accepted the proposition of this maniac and brought with him to Chicago the notorious blasphemer Chrostowski, editor of Jutrzenka (Morning Star) and another false priest by the name of Radziszewski. All these apostles, fortified with the power of an evil spirit--that is, with lies, slander, sacrilege, and blasphemies--are now in our Polish settlement in the Avondale district, all set to wage war against the Holy Ghost.</p>
   <p>"Having no decency, either Christian or of any other kind, they would like <pb facs="5423968_10_0987.jpg" n="3"/>to take advantage of the imprudent and ignorant in Godly things and, through Tamillo, lead them into the mire into which they themselves have fallen. Their aim is to lead their followers so far from the right path that they will lose sight of the light of Faith and fail to hear the voice of conscience--all of which calls for church penalties, anathema, and eternal damnation.</p>
   <p>"It is important to know that, because his conduct was unworthy of a priest, this unfortunate man, this Kolaszewski, after being admonished and corrected time and again, was finally deprived by church authorities of his office of pastor of a Polish parish in Cleveland, Ohio.</p>
   <p>"Now that he is attacking impudently the apostalic unity of the Roman Catholic Church, not only his bishop but also other bishops and archbishops, and even the apostolic delegate, consider him a perverted schismatic, and excommunicated blasphemer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0988.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"His boast before the American masses that he broke away from the Holy Father, that he is founding a church completely independent of the Holy See, makes him an open apostate, inasmuch as in this manner he places his infallibility above the infallibility of the Pope, and prefers to obey some kind of Protestant vagabond and call him his bishop rather than obeying the authority of the Vicar of Christ, the visible head of the Holy Roman Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>"Kolaszewski has renounced the sacramental oath he made to the Holy Church in the presence of a bishop, from whose hands he received the Sacrament of the Holy Orders. Today this man guilty of perjury, sacrilege and apostasy, dares announce himself as the founder of a Polish Church.</p>
   <p>"We know how Luther founded the German [Lutheran] Church. We know that the Russian czars founded the Muscovite [Russian Orthodox] Church through a corrupt clergy and by brutal force. We know the reason why the adulterer <pb facs="5423968_10_0989.jpg" n="5"/>Henry VIII founded the Church of England. But up to now we have never heard anything to the effect that a Polish Church has ever existed, with the exception, of course, of that of the maniac Tamillo, who is probably trying to imitate Bismarck. Depending upon Lucifer, he and the Apostate Kolaszewski are striving to bring disgrace upon the Polish nation. With misleading phrases they endeavor to coax our people away from the true faith, leaving them in the trackless path of perdition.</p>
   <p>"The Pharisees crucified the Son of God because, instead of Jewish synagogues, He established the universal or Catholic Church. Likewise the Polish Pharisees blaspheme against the holy Catholic Church whenever the latter refuses to satisfy their whims.</p>
   <p>"We are not surprised when one who proclaims publicly that 'Moses created God' affiliate himself with Kolaszewaki, Christowski, and the like. What hurts and makes us sad is, that some of our countrymen are afflicted with <pb facs="5423968_10_0990.jpg" n="6"/>this disease.</p>
   <p>"We should recall the words of Saint Paul to the first Christians, that even if an angel would descend from heaven and proclaim different teachings than those taught by the Apostles, one should not believe him, for God's truth and revelation cannot be changed.</p>
   <p>"Every Christian should know that even a Roman Catholic bishop has no right to establish a parish in another diocese without the permission of the bishop of that diocese; neither has he any right to perform any church function. If he violates these regulations, he will be punished by the church authorities, and such functions as he may have performed are voided by the Church. By what authority, then, have mentally deficient, blasphemous, and slanderous people excommunicated by the Church the right to organize a parish without the permission of a bishop?</p>
   <p>"In view of all this, we warn all our countrymen not to associate with this unfortunate priest, who was openly and publicly excommunicated by the Church, <pb facs="5423968_10_0991.jpg" n="7"/>as else they would expose themselves to Church penalties, and anathema--both of which lead to temporal and eternal punishment.</p>
   <p>"A Catholic Priest from Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
