<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-05-22">May 22, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[Opposition to Immigration Bill Grows]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-05-22">May 22, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">[OPPOSITION TO IMMIGRATION BILL GROWS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A protest meeting was opened by Joseph Kawczynski, who explained the purpose of the gathering. The secretary, Mr. Joseph Slezak, introduced the first speaker, Mr. Kmieciak, director of the Polish National Alliance. He interpreted every thing that is being attempted against the Poles by federal authorities in Washington. His lengthy speech explaining what should be done to prevent the passage of the Dillingham and Burnett bill, won a loud burst of applause.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was John J. Slomski, a very active and popular steamship agent in St. Ann's community, who in a convincing manner explained how authorities treat the immigrant upon his arrival, and how, for the past several years, they tried to prevent immigration of Poles to this country.</p>
   <p>The following resolution was accepted unanimously: We, American citizens of Polish extraction, protest against the Dillingham, Burnett and Roets revised immigration bill, which by wicked means is trying to prevent the immigration of <pb facs="5423968_10_1749.jpg" n="2"/>of Poles in the United States. We Poles should, because of the fact that our great heroes, Kosciuszko and Pulaski, fought for America's freedom and independence, have unrestrained admission to this country.</p>
   <p>Whereas, the Poles are a useful people to the growth and expansion of this country, for they may be found farming, mining, at the anvil in foundries; and at other hard and dangerous work.</p>
   <p>Whereas, the Poles are willing and capable workers, and their unity is evidenced by the churches, schools and large organizations, such as the Polish National Alliance, the Polish Roman Catholic Union and many others.</p>
   <p>Whereas, our brothers upon landing are subjected to wrongful treatment, we demand better treatment and care for our future immigrants, and we further demand the withdrawal of the Dillinger and Burnett bill by our representatives in <pb facs="5423968_10_1750.jpg" n="3"/>Washington.</p>
   <p>Resolution committee:</p>
   <p>John Szot</p>
   <p>Thomas Czerwiec</p>
   <p>Anna Borowicz</p>
   <p>John Slomski</p>
   <p>Joseph Slezak</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
