<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-12-20">Dec. 20, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">St. Casimir Young Men's Society Adopts New Measures at Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1523</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1523.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-12-20">Dec. 20, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">ST. CASIMIR YOUNG MEN'S SOCIETY ADOPTS NEW MEASURES AT ANNUAL MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several new measures were adopted by the members of the St. Casimir Young Men's Society at the annual meeting held December 18 at the St. Stanislaus Kostka school hall.</p>
   <p>It was agreed to have a painting made of St. Casimir at the expense of the society, and donate it to the presbytery of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church. Since the famous Polish artist, Thaddeus Zukotynski, is to arrive soon in Chicago from Europe, it was decided to engage him to do the famous historical painting, as well as a larger canvas for the society, which will be hung in the place of meeting.</p>
   <p>It was also agreed that the society would arrange programs for the Polish League. These programs, which will be free to the public, will serve for the <pb facs="5423968_10_1524.jpg" n="2"/>purpose of educating the audience in the various fields of Polish culture.</p>
   <p>Fifteen dollars was turned over to the Educational Department of the Polish League to help raise funds for new libraries.</p>
   <p>Ten dollars was set aside for the new church which is being built in Avondale, St. Hyacinth Parish.</p>
   <p>Another step forward was taken when it was agreed to form a Polish Falcon group of forty members.</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected to office for the next year: John Nering, president; Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek, chaplain; Joseph Grabowiecki, vice-president; August Klafta, recording secretary; Theophilus Gordon, financial secretary; Francis A. Kwasigroch, treasurer; and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1525.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At present the society numbers 214 members.</p>
   <p>Vincent J. Jozwiakowski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
