<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-17">Sept. 17, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">In Defense of Reverend Pyplatz and St. Joseph Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0789</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0789.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-09-17">Sept. 17, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">IN DEFENSE OF REVEREND PYPLATZ AND ST. JOSEPH PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(We have received the following article for publication:)</p>
   <p>Chicago, September 14, 1895.</p>
   <p>Dear Editor: Perhaps hell itself has poured out its ire during the past few days so that the respectable name of our pastor and all peace-loving parishioners have been defiled by the surreptitious stories that have been conveyed to the reading public through the medium of the local American press. This campaign of lies has been going on for some time.</p>
   <p>In order to put an end to this situation once and for all, the pastor, Reverend M. Pyplatz, called a meeting of the parishioners on Sunday, September 8. An addition to the board of trustees was made and the enlarged staff immediately set out to take inventory of the parish's financial status.</p>
   <p>The undersigned members tackled the books energetically and fulfilled their <pb facs="5423968_10_0790.jpg" n="2"/>obligations to the letter. The findings are as follows:</p>
   <p>He who claims that the Reverend Pyplatz has mishandled some of the church funds is a prevaricator. Every penny, both income and expenses, was accounted for in the books, and the receipts for every expense item corresponded to the records in the books.</p>
   <p>He who asserts that the pastor has furnished the rectory luxuriously is a liar. This committee has inspected the rooms of the rectory and found that they were furnished with no better furniture than the home of a worker of moderate circumstances.</p>
   <p>He who maintains that the pastor has unlawfully made payments to the servants from the parish treasury is a liar. The pastor has a perfect right to make such payments, according to the diocesan report which bears the seal of the Archbishop of Chicago. A caption in this report is entitled "Household Expenses."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0791.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the annual statement made by Reverend Pyplatz's predecessor the following statement is made: Household expenses for 1892, $357.01, and for 1893, $570. If in a previous year $570 was paid out for household expenses, then why is there a controversy over the expenses of the past year when they only amounted to $346.50?</p>
   <p>He who alleges that the use of church apparatus was abused is a prevaricator. In the annual report there is an article that lists "Material and Equipment Purchased." Receipts account for everything that has been bought. They were inspected and estimated by this body. The conclusion was that purchase of the material was essential.</p>
   <p>He who claims that the organist received and disposed money of the parish without control is a prevaricator. Mr. Kucharczyk has never acted independently, and we know him to be a trustworthy person.</p>
   <p>Those who contend that a large proportion of the parishioners have broken away from the St. Joseph Church are liars. Not one individual in our parish <pb facs="5423968_10_0792.jpg" n="4"/>has cause to make an accusation against his pastor; they were made, perhaps, by those who for many years disdained Jesus Christ, and for many years never saw the inside of a church, and by those who never gave a cent towards the support of the Church.</p>
   <p>He who claims that the organist has wheedled money from the Polish workers for the building of the new church is a liar. Joseph Rus and the contractor are the best witnesses in this matter.</p>
   <p>He who claims that the pastor has charged the parish $127.52 for whitewashing the church and purchasing two lamps is a liar. This work specifically belongs to the maintenance of the church and those that do not attend the services at the St. Joseph church do not know anything about such matters.</p>
   <p>This statement would go on indefinitely if we were to enumerate all the lies that have been cast about in our parish. Suffice it to say that these storytellers are people who thrive on lying--for it is their sustenance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0793.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The more dastardly lies have been exposed and presented for the general public to judge. Let the opinion of the honest sons of Poland pass its judgement. The sowers of these lies have brought infamy to our parish, rent many brotherly hearts, and they should be despised by every Pole and adjudged by the justice of God.</p>
   <p>Other Polish papers are requested to reprint this article.</p>
   <p>[Signed]:</p>
   <p>Andrew Ciudaj, Anthony Rus, Andrew Skonieczaj, Joseph</p>
   <p>Jankowski, Joseph Rusch, John Wiza, Michael Andrzejewski,</p>
   <p>Anthony Rossman and Stanislaus Goniakowski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
