<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-18">Feb. 18, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to the Parishioners of St. Hedwig Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0922</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0922.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-18">Feb. 18, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO THE PARISHIONERS OF ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The undersigned, a staunch and upright parish committee, recognized by the Archbishop of Chicago, are concerned about the recent humiliating events that took place in the St. Hedwig Parish and feel obligated, as Christians, as Poles, and as the original founders of the parish, to make an appeal to all their brethren, asking them to support the movement leading to the restoration of order [in the parish] and to the prompt opening of our church and school.</p>
   <p>This will only be possible if we succeed in convincing the Archbishop of the Chicago diocese that the dissension in St. Hedwig Parish has been completely eradicated, that harmony has been restored, that the temporarily duped parishioners are strongly in favor of returning to the path of righteousness, the path of respect for the will of the Bishop, and finally, that such shameful incidents will never occur again.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0923.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to convince the Archbishop and thus make possible the opening of the church and school as soon as possible, the undersigned committee have prepared a petition to the Archbishop, which has been signed by several hundred parishioners who sincerely desire to see order restored. The greater the number of signatures obtained, the sooner will the doors of our church be open.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we, the undersigned, appeal to all good-spirited people of the parish who desire harmony and unity instead of dissension and disunity, and who wish to have the church opened soon, to come to the home of any one of the undersigned and sign the petition, signifying that they agree with the will of the Bishop and that they sincerely desire to have the school and church opened.</p>
   <p>To err is human and many of us have made mistakes, but to continue in this state is sinful. Let us remember this. Let us bear in mind the damage <pb facs="5423968_10_0924.jpg" n="3"/>that is being done to our souls when we continue in our stubbornness. Let us cast off our errors once and for all.</p>
   <p>We urge everyone of the parishioners of St. Hedwig Parish, all Catholics and Poles of good will, to act, not for personal gain, but in the name of the good of all, for the salvation of all our souls.</p>
   <p>Brothers in Christ,</p>
   <p>Andrew Glwoczewski, president of the committee</p>
   <p>Anthony Barczynski, secretary of the committee</p>
   <p>Joseph Jablonski. Julius Recki, Francis Klafeta, Francis Kielichowski, Boleslaus Hofman, Francis Jaktorowski, John Konczykowski, John Szczepanski, Francis Sobieszczyk, Stanislaus Frazyna. [Translator's note: Addresses omitted in translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
