<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-22">June 22, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Newly Appointed Pastor of St. Hedwig Parish Makes an Appeal to the Parishioners</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0839</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0839.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-22">June 22, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">NEWLY APPOINTED PASTOR OF ST. HEDWIG PARISH MAKES AN APPEAL TO THE PARISHIONERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A short notice about the opening of the Church and the change of pastors in St. Hedwig Parish was given yesterday. Further details about the change have been received.</p>
   <p>First of all, we are authorized to announce that the change of pastors in St. Hedwig Parish was made at the request of Reverend Eugene Sedlaczek, who was of the opinion that perhaps it was because of him that some of the dissension had been aroused. He announced this to the church authorities, expressing hope that they were in accordance with his request. Reverend Sedlaczek said that his only wish was to see the glory of God prevail in the parish.</p>
   <p>Archbishop Feehan was the first to consent to the request.</p>
   <p>Reverend John Piechowski, rector of St. Stanislaus Kostka College and pastor of <pb facs="5423968_10_0840.jpg" n="2"/>St. Hyacinth Parish, well known to the Poles of Chicago, was appointed the new pastor. We trust that the new duties placed upon his shoulders will be willingly carried out.</p>
   <p>Below we give the new pastor's announcement to the parishioners of St. Hedwig Parish, informing them of his new assignment and of tomorrow's opening of the Church:</p>
   <p>"To the parishioners of St. Hedwig Parish:</p>
   <p>"Brothers in Christ:</p>
   <p>"The unpleasant disputes which have been continuous during the past month in St. Hedwig Parish are arousing a deep feeling of sorrow in the hearts of every Catholic and every Pole.</p>
   <p>"Disloyal persons have created lamentable discords in the parish, as a result of which the church has been closed for a considerable length of time, depriving <pb facs="5423968_10_0841.jpg" n="3"/>the pious parishioners of spiritual succor.</p>
   <p>"At last the limits of this privation have been reached. Archbishop Feehan, acknowledging the good will of the majority of the parishioners, consented to open St. Hedwig Church. In addition, the injunction issued against the opening of the church has been lifted by the civil court.</p>
   <p>"The court gave a stern warning to the dissenters not to create any further trouble in the event the church were to be opened, under severe penalty of the law.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, tomorrow, June 23, at 10 A. M., by order of the Archbishop of Chicago, St. Hedwig Church will be opened by Reverend Muldoon, chancellor of the Archbishop, and solemn services will be read.</p>
   <p>"Called at the present time to take over the duties of pastor of St. Hedwig Parish by order of Archbishop Feehan, and loyal to my magistery, I have begun the work <pb facs="5423968_10_0842.jpg" n="4"/>for the good of your souls, with love to all without exception, and am prepared to dedicate my services to you, because I have hope that God will bless my work.</p>
   <p>"It is high time that peace return once more to the discord-rent parish and that the glory to God be re-established in order that the people recognize their wrongs and stop sinning.</p>
   <p>"I extend a sincere invitation to all members of St. Hedwig Parish and to those from neighboring Polish churches to take part in the official reopening of the church tomorrow.</p>
   <p>"Further, I beseech all those who feel guilty for their part in the dissension to comply with the desires of the church authorities, to come to peace terms, to repent their sins, and to return to the road of righteousness. The Church of God is like a mother who constantly protects and takes to her fold all those who are compassionate, but castigates sternly and justly those children who are disloyal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0843.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Those who have been sowing dissension amid your ranks have realized that they are in no position to break St. Peter's foundation or overcome the Church of God. What is more, they have even been severely reprimanded by the civil court.</p>
   <p>"Once again I call upon all to act in harmony with the church, and for the good of your souls I desire to see the peace of God prevail at St. Hedwig Parish.</p>
   <p>"Your Servant in Christ,</p>
   <p>"Reverend John Piechowski, C. R."</p>
   <p>As is seen from this announcement, the new pastor speaks to the parishioners in behalf of peace, with authority and good will.</p>
   <p>His words ought to be felt in every faithful heart. Now there is no more need for delusion at the parish. The Archbishop has condemned the dissenters. They have no recourse before them. If they wish to be true to the church they must abide by the logical reasonings of the civil court, as well as by the laws of the church.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0844.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We are fully familiar with the energy, as well as with the peaceful and loving nature, of the new pastor of St. Hedwig Parish. We firmly believe that in his new parish he will be able to bring about the complete settlement of the differences.</p>
   <p>We wish this new pastor all the success in the world in bringing about harmony in his parish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
