<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-14">June 14, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Radziszewski, Former "Independent" Priest, Is Penitent</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0863</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0863.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-06-14">June 14, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">RADZISZEWSKI, FORMER "INDEPENDENT" PRIEST, IS PENITENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Well known for his scandalous activities among the people in Cleveland, Baltimore, Chicago, and other cities, Reverend Joseph Radziszewski, who has turned "independent" (many articles about him have appeared in Dziennik Chicagoski) has reformed and desires to return to the fold. Through the influence of several local priests, he has agreed to repent and return to the path of righteousness. Reverend Radziszewski has expressed sincere sorrow for his sins and whatever scandals he has created.</p>
   <p>In order to give the penitent a means to fulfill his desire to reform, funds were given him so that he might have money to reach Rome. He was also given a letter to Cardinal Ledachowski, with the request that the cardinal suggest a form of penance and a way to a better life.</p>
   <p>Reverend J. Radziszewski left for New York yesterday where he will board a vessel for Rome. Before departing, he left a signed statement in the <pb facs="5423968_10_0864.jpg" n="2"/>hands of a person who is held in high esteem by the Polish people. It was his last wish that it be published in the Polish press.</p>
   <p>This statement (the original is in our possession) is printed below. It reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>June 13, 1895.</p>
   <p>"To the Polish brethren of America:</p>
   <p>"Leaving today for Rome to do penance, I publicly wish to beg forgiveness of all my Polish compatriots for my scandalous actions, that is, for influencing them to join the "independent church."</p>
   <p>"My downfall was very heavy, but God gave me hope and strength to lift myself from this mire. I deeply regret that I have permitted myself to be temporarily <pb facs="5423968_10_0865.jpg" n="3"/>persuaded to join the ranks of those who were of ill will and faithless. I have a firm hope that they, in their prayer to God and the Blessed Virgin for help, will follow my example and will, if only in part, right their previous wrongs.</p>
   <p>"Follow me, therefore, Reverends Kozlowski and Kolaszewski.</p>
   <p>"Enough offensive work has been started by us. Our conversion will once again bring about unity and brotherly love in those parishes to which we have brought scandal.</p>
   <p>"Let us not create any more shame for our brothers here and in Poland. Let us not do any more wrongs against the Mother of the Holy Church, and the Mother will welcome our return to her fold once again.</p>
   <p>"Once again I beg forgiveness of all and remain,</p>
   <p>Your Brother in Christ,</p>
   <p>Reverend J. C. Radziszewski"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0866.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Additions to this statement are superfluous. It speaks for itself. The Polish press at large is kindly requested to reprint this statement of the ex-schismatic Radziszewski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
