<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-24">Feb. 24, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">St. Hedwig Parish and the Polish Roman Catholic Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0591</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0591.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-02-24">Feb. 24, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">ST. HEDWIG PARISH AND THE POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the pitiless fight declared on the Polish Roman Catholic Union, under the protection of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, by the enemies of Catholicism and opponents of unity, and in spite of the damnable conspiracy hatched in Milwaukee against this oldest Polish Catholic organization in America, the Polish Roman Catholic Union is being revived and is growing.</p>
   <p>The void created in the ranks of the Polish Roman Catholic Union in Milwaukee is filling up, and soon it will not be recognizable.</p>
   <p>We have, in the last few days, mentioned that new members and new societies are joining the Polish Roman Catholic Union. Now we wish to announce a new departure which is highly effective.</p>
   <p>At a meeting held yesterday, the societies of St. Hedwig Parish in Chicago <pb facs="5423968_10_0592.jpg" n="2"/>decided, as one man, to join the Polish Roman Catholic Union, and to fight under its banner, on which is written "Bog I Ojczyzna" (God and Country).</p>
   <p>This is a highly significant occurrence.</p>
   <p>In this parish, where the greatest storm was raging,and in whose bosom was born that infamous "independent" schism--in this same parish, in a few months there has settled (thanks to the sincere efforts of the reverend priests) such peace and understanding that this parish, as one person, has decided to increase the membership of the largest and most important Polish Catholic organization in America--and simultaneously, by joining this great Catholic movement, it strengthens its own members spiritually.</p>
   <p>All honor to the priests and their work; hail to the people who understood so well the necessity of unity with the true church and co-operation with their brethren!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0593.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This news, so pleasant to our ears, speaks well not only for the Poles in St. Hedwig Parish, but also for our old, honored Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>It proves that the Polish Roman Catholic Union will withstand all dishonest attacks, that it will go forward without harm, as it has heretofore. Waves of inciters, scoundrels, and blinded hoodlums have rolled high against this Catholic and Polish edifice, but have broken against it ignominiously....The cross, rising on the ramparts of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, has repulsed them. National solidarity is ever strengthening these ramparts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
