<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-20">Aug. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[The Polish Priests and National Affairs]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-20">Aug. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[THE POLISH PRIESTS AND NATIONAL AFFAIRS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As long as the representatives of the clergy persist in demanding that religion should never be forgotten in national affairs, as long as they do not acknowledge [the rights of] any Pole unless he is an active Catholic, and, lastly, as long as the liberal or progressive party leaders are interested only in drawing away the public from the influence of the priests, by arousing and disseminating distrust and hatred toward the clergy in order eventually to deprive the people completely of faith and "free them from narrow-minded prejudices," so long will the leaders of both parties be unable, under any circumstances, to come to a mutual understanding, since their principles and viewpoints are diametrically opposite. Certain factions do not differ so much in their viewpoints that a concord could not be effected between them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1112.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>completely separated from affairs of the Church and that the priests be deprived of any influence on national affairs. Since the apparent dissatisfaction toward this faction's present administration is growing with each day, and since the majority of its rank and file still has reverence for some members of the clergy and as yet is not deprived of the Catholic fundamentals, an eventual understanding between these two factions is not an improbability.</p>
   <p>The internal feuds and disunity within both camps complicate such an understanding. Another factor tending to complicate matters is the highly unpleasant and exhausting partisanship arising now and then over trifles, a partisanship which seems always to manifest itself in personal attacks, deceit, and slander.</p>
   <p>Among the clergy there are also factions that, being in utter ignorance, help spread discord, not to mention those who, from personal motives--because <pb facs="5423968_10_1113.jpg" n="3"/>they were not successful in securing a certain parish they desired--are ready to sacrifice the public interest. There are a few who declared a schism and actually fell away from the Catholic Church, and there are others who gave bad examples with their own private lives. These unworthy clergymen have harmed immensely--and still are harming--the entire conservative faction. With their conduct, they are placing a mighty weapon in the hands of the liberals, who, incidentally, never fail to make good use of scandal, spreading and publishing anything that may besmirch the clergy as a whole. Besides, there are among the clergy many who are deserving of profound respect and reverence, merited by their good work among the immigrants here, but who, aside from their high education and religiousness, and a patriotic distinction, are somewhat too prejudiced and--if we may say so for lack of other words--too radical in their own sphere. These regard everything in the camp of their opponents as evil, and refuse to hear of any mutual understanding or retreat.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1114.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the liberal camp, made up of a variety of elements, there is also dissension, which increased when the priests were forced to leave the camp because of certain resolutions. Besides the anti-Catholic directors of this camp, there come into its circle more and more agitators, outcasts, anarchists, and other people of socialistic beliefs. The rank and file is dissatisfied with the administration, with the reception of these unpleasant detachments, as well as with the outside assistance of anarchists or atheists, but it does not know how to defend itself or how to refuse this unwelcome help.</p>
   <p>Among the clergy who direct the affairs of the conservative camp are the very distinguished Fathers of the Resurrectionist Congregation, who, at the request and through the efforts of the Saint Stanislaus Kostka parishioners, came and took charge of the greatest parish in the United States, perhaps, as some claim, the greatest parish in the world. The parishioners of the Saint Stanislaus Kostka parish invited the Resurrectionists to take over the control <pb facs="5423968_10_1115.jpg" n="5"/>of their parish, and it seemed that at least against these Resurrectionists no one could step forth with any kind of inculpation. The liberals, however, promptly directed a series of violent attacks against them, especially, against their principal representative, the pastor of the parish. Any infraction, or whatever the liberals found objectionable in the conservative camp, was attributed to this one person. Various pretenses were utilized in an effort to slander him; if these proved unsuccessful, his foes did not hesitate to employ the most vulgar forms of defamation and calumny. To make matters worse, some of the unworthy members of the clergy, envious of the prestige gained by this clergyman, joined the ranks of these attackers and began a vulgar polemic. When peaceful answers were not effective, when the weight of facts was ridiculed, and when virulence had increased [beyond endurance], a great indignation arose in the conservative camp. Those who did not understand these peaceful answers were dealt with in a more adequate manner, with a certain violence. Then was born the famous though shortly <pb facs="5423968_10_1116.jpg" n="6"/>lived newspaper, Kropidlo (Aspergillus), and since then the nickname of "Clerical Sprinklers" has been applied to the representatives of the conservative camp, who reciprocated by calling all the members of the opposing camp, Masons.</p>
   <p>The fight drags on--in alternating periods of violence and calm. The only difference now is that some of the priests who were forced to leave the liberal camp will not, because of pride or prospects, enter the conservative camp. They, secretly or under pseudonyms, carry on this combat against the Resurrectionist Fathers, fortifying certain newspapers with ugly articles. In reality, the arguments usually arise over trifles, having no connection with the basic issues. For this reason, the altercation appears very complicated to outsiders.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, we should like to reply to the Kuryer of Milwaukee, in regard to its insinuation that the Dziennik Chicagoski "claims nonpartisanship".</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1117.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>In the very beginning, as well as later during the discussion, Dziennik [Chicagoski] declared its sympathy for the conservative camp. This newspaper recognizes the great merits of the clergy as well as the unworthy conduct of the liberal intelligentsia. However, since this newspaper is not the organ of any party--clerical or otherwise--or of any one certain individual, it has endeavored to present the situation from an impartial aspect. Consequently, this newspaper, under the circumstances, as any newspaper conducted by reasoning people, is convinced that, to the camp which condemns it, it must appear partial. But since this camp does not concede any rights of the party they defend, since its members keep their eyes closed to the faults of their party, and since they praise anything that appears good to them in their camp, it is no wonder that Dziennik Chicagoski certainly appears partial in the eyes of so prejudiced a group.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
