<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-12">Feb. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Letter of the Apostolic Delegate Relative to the Agitation at St. Hedwig Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0930</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0930.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-02-12">Feb. 12, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">LETTER OF THE APOSTOLIC DELEGATE RELATIVE TO THE AGITATION AT ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The instigators intent on disrupting the harmony in St. Hedwig Parish have from the very beginning told lies to the parishioners, and they are still telling them. These lies have been spread in order to get the people to oppose the local ecclesiastical powers, whose head is the Apostolic Delegate, Monsignor Sattoli, of Washington [D. C.].</p>
   <p>Such prevarications are often tactfully made by wranglers within the parish. The people readily believe them because the leaders occasionally send letters of protest to the Apostolic Delegates, and sometimes they even send delegations.</p>
   <p>In order to convince the duped parishioners as to how the representative of the Pope looks upon the various agitations and uprisings in St. Hedwig Parish, a letter from Monsignor Satolli to one of the leaders of the opposition, which was sent immediately after the affray of February 3, is published below.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0931.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The letter, written in English, is found in the archives of the Bishop of Chicago, and reads as follows:</p>
   <p>Apostolic Delegate of United States of America</p>
   <p>Washington, February 8, 1895</p>
   <p>No. 1305 (In reply refer to this number)</p>
   <p>Peter P. Bloch</p>
   <p>254 Webster Avenue</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Dear Sir: I am grieved more than I can tell you at the scandalous performance which took place in the church of St. Hedwig last Sunday. It is too bad that your people cannot control themselves sufficiently at least to respect the sanctity of the House of God, and the celebration of the Divine Liturgy. You <pb facs="5423968_10_0932.jpg" n="3"/>must understand that the government of the diocese and the right of removing or changing pastors and other priests belongs to the bishop. If the parishioners have any valid reason for objecting to the priests assigned to them, they should present those reasons to the bishop, and he is bound to give them his careful consideration. When he has done so, the people are bound, if they wish to remain good Catholics, to abide by his decision. I beg you and the others who are discontented with the priests you have to be patient, and I assure you that proper consideration will be given to the matter, and such provision made as will secure peace and harmony. It is to be hoped that there will never be a repetition of the scandal of last Sunday.</p>
   <p>Faithfully Yours in Christ,</p>
   <p>Francis Archbishop Sattoli</p>
   <p>Apostolic Delegate</p>
   <p>Comment on this letter is superfluous. The Apostolic Delegate's letter plainly condemns the various agitations and hostile acts against the church government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0933.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>From the contents of the letter it is apparent that Archbishop Satolli was not informed about the horrible and bloody rioting in St. Hedwig Parish on Friday, February 8. It is plainly evident how much more severe the letter to follow from the representative of the Pope in America will be.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
