<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-08-05">Aug. 5, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Incorrigibles</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0451</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0451.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-08-05">Aug. 5, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">INCORRIGIBLES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We return once again to the article written by Mr. Maryanski in the Goniec Wielkopolski (paper published in Poland).</p>
   <p>In the introduction to the article the Goniec Wielkopolski states that the Polish Catholic Congress unreasonably tends to push into oblivion those whom it should attract and correct.</p>
   <p>Correct! Attract to it! The statement shows how little the Goniec Wielkopolski knows of our conditions. The suggestion it makes is but a dream.</p>
   <p>Those whom we should attract and correct would become angry at the mere thought, that they need to be corrected. Never could they be attracted who, in their opinion, are an example of the most enlightened, the most patriotic, <pb facs="5423968_10_0452.jpg" n="2"/>and the greatest Poles in America; who wish to reform and correct everybody to their own way of thinking, and who accept the notion, that religion should have nothing in common with patriotism, and will never relinquish it.</p>
   <p>The Polish Catholic Congress has many important aims and will initiate many great and beneficial moves.</p>
   <p>The Congress will not put aside anyone who wishes to labor and co-operate in a spirit of good will in the field of enlightenment; and it surely will not decide that anybody belonging to this or that organization dare not participate in the great work to be done.</p>
   <p>It must, however, condemn those who have systematically interfered with this work for many years and especially so in recent years. It must point out by whom and with what kind of sermons the people are being confused and led to the evil and dangerous path of destruction. It must show that such things have happened and how they have happened. Being forced clearly to expose all this, <pb facs="5423968_10_0453.jpg" n="3"/>the Congress cannot accept the co-operation of those who, by spreading demoralization, have insisted on being leaders and teachers of the people. Permitting them to mutual discussion would mean to nullify the aims of the Congress, and instead of peaceful, beneficial, and necessary debates, there would result quarrels, disorder, and confusion.</p>
   <p>These enemies of religion are incorrigible and will not be pacified; they have shown this too often in the past.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
