<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1908-04-18">April 18, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Fire in St. Vincent's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0220</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0220.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1908-04-18">April 18, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">FIRE IN ST. VINCENT'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish church in flames. A fire started in back of the main church altar at about 3:15 in the afternoon. The fire was first noticed by Mr. Anthony Kaczmarek, a clerk in a drug store who notified the fire department. The fire continued from the alter to the ceiling, then to the loft. The smoke was coming in big clouds through the steeples and windows. When the fire department arrived, they first cut holes in the roof to let the smoke escape, so they could enter the church. Four fire departments were engaged in fighting the fire in this wooden structure. The small altars and the pews were covered with canvas to protect them from the fire and damage.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0221.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The flames were so great around the main altars that the firemen could not get close enough to save some of the sacramental ornaments, but all the banners representing church societies were safely carried out. By this time thirty policemen were keeping the curious people a safe distance from the church, thousands of people were watching the fire.</p>
   <p>At last the firemen were able to pour water into the church, but to no avail, because the main altar was completely burned. It cost $2,000. The main supporting beams of the roof were completely burned, and the fire marshal and the building inspecting commissioner demanded that temporary beams placed on jacks be used to keep the roof from caving in and bring more damage.</p>
   <p>This church was built by Polish people about seven years ago; the insurance company is at present estimating the amount of damages.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0222.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The rector of this parish is Rev. Father Lex. assisted by Rev. Father Krupka.</p>
   <p>The casualty was a fireman of company four, who was out and bruised about the head by falling timber. The injured man, Mr. Koschmiter, was given first aid by Mr. Glosza, a druggist.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
