<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 23,
<date when="1907-01-28">Jan. 28, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">At St. Adelberts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 23,
<date when="1907-01-28">Jan. 28, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">AT ST. ADELBERTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday at 2:45 o'clock, members of the St. Anne Society, group 30 P. N. A., gathered in the Pulaski Hall, from where they all went to the St. Adelbert's church for vespers. After vespers the blessing of flags took place; this ceremony was performed by Rev. Father L. Zuchola. There were thirty god-mothers and god-fathers, persons from the parish. After the blessing of the flags, Rev. Father Zuchola gave us a wonderful sermon. He reminded and warned the Polish mothers that in raising their little loved ones, they should follow the example of St. Anne, also adding, to send their young ones to Polish Catholic schools where they shall educate themselves in a patriotic and religious spirit. He also advised the people to join a society, such as St. Anne Organization, group 30 Z. P. A. (P. N. A. Polish National Alliance).</p>
   <p>During the wonderful playing of a march on the organ, the society marched out of the church, under the leadership of the White Eagle and the Central <pb facs="5423968_10_0229.jpg" n="2"/>Polish Women Society with their flags, and went to Pulaski Hall. Here the committee presented the flags to its president, Miss Stephany Chmielinska, who in a short speech encouraged our Polish women to work and strive for the good of everyone in general, and to pay good attention to the education of their children and last but not least, to join and familiarize themselves with such organizations and groups as, for example, St. Anne Society.</p>
   <p>After the conclusion of the speech by president S. Chmielinska, A. Lasko and A. Okon handed the president two pretty scarfs; Miss A. Neuman, a gold pin; Miss A. Schneider, a chest; Miss M. Labudzka offered a brilliant sceptre; the St. Helen Society gave her a golden nail. Other assistants presented her with two laurel wreaths.</p>
   <p>We must also note that the society's flags were given by our president Miss S. Chmielinska. These banners had on one side the image of St. Anne, <pb facs="5423968_10_0230.jpg" n="3"/>all handwork, and on the reverse side the picture of the White Eagle, and below it was inscribed: "God Redeem Poland." Miss Jos. Okoniewska, at the end of the flag ceremony, rendered a wonderful declamation, proper for the festivity.</p>
   <p>Later there was dancing that lasted till late hours of the night. Over a hundred and fifty couples were present. The hall was magnificently decorated and the playing of the orchestra of our J. Nagle added splendor to the occasion.</p>
   <p>This Society of St. Anne, Group 30 P. N. A., was organized May 20, 1903. At present it is adding ninety members. It has over $550 cash on hand in its treasury.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
