<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish-American Veterans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1345</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1345.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-28">Jan. 28, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH-AMERICAN VETERANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish-American veterans of the United States Army have announced a mass meeting of war veterans who live in the Avondale district and its vicinity to be held at 2:30 o'clock in the afternoon, February 12, in Central Hall, 3600 Wolfram Street.</p>
   <p>We ask all veterans to come to this meeting, whether or not they are members of the Polish American Veterans' Association, because the purpose of the meeting is to promote the welfare of all veterans. In the Avondale district a great many veterans live who are not yet members of the Veterans' Association, and they do not have their own Post in this district. This meeting will elect the officers of the Post and will choose as its name that which is agreed upon by the majority of those present.</p>
   <p>Veterans! Come to this meeting, take an active part, and demand recognition of your rights: Give an hour of your time to this serious and all-important <pb facs="5423968_10_1346.jpg" n="2"/>business. Let Poles demand that they be treated on an equality with others, and their demands will then be granted in the City Hall and everywhere else. Do we Polish veterans lack the courage to demand the rights for which we fought, shed our blood, and suffered indescribable hardships and privations?</p>
   <p>Veterans! Uphold your self-respect and your honor as soldiers! Unite with those who suffered with you, shoulder to shoulder, your fellow veterans!</p>
   <p>At this meeting, as soon as the staff of the Post has been elected, each veteran's application for the State bonus will be filled out. Every veteran who intends to join the Veterans' Association should bring with him his Army discharge papers necessary in filling out applications for the bonus.</p>
   <p>Veterans, let our work prove that a good soldier is also a good citizen, a true buddy, a veteran!</p>
   <p>All in unity after the war!</p>
   <p>B.F. Kalisz, general organizer</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
