<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-11">Jan. 11, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">From St. Hedwig's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-11">Jan. 11, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">FROM ST. HEDWIG'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local Przewodnik Mlodziezy (Youth's Guide) published a very interesting letter about the situation in St. Hedwig Parish, parts of which we gladly reprint:</p>
   <p>"Everything in our old parish (St. Hedwig) church is as pretty as a picture. The altars are repainted, renewed, repaired, and shining as never before. And how beautiful are the services! What wonderful sermons do our priests preach from the pulpit! What a spirit of Christian love do they inspire in our hearts!</p>
   <p>"Why, everyone must agree that we have never showed such love for one another as now. One is not jealous of the other, we love each other as brothers--and it agrees with us, especially in our societies, which vie with one another to work hand in hand with our pastor and to praise God--all for our own benefit.</p>
   <p>"For what benefit? Well, you see, I refer to the children. What happened to our school children? These rascals are studying like nobody's business. They <pb facs="5423968_10_0665.jpg" n="2"/>know more than some of their parents, and in addition they are so modest, so peaceful, so God-fearing, that the souls of their fathers and mothers are overflowing with joy.</p>
   <p>"Just let anyone try to tell me that our parish is not Polish. Don't you remember our national celebrations? Here was no parrot-like recitation. Everyone spoke with feeling, and those youngsters of ours--the girls and boys--recited, sang, and played various musical instruments, so that our hearts were thrilled and I didn't know whether to cry or laugh with joy.</p>
   <p>"All of this demands work and supervision, but our priests find time for everything. That is why members of the various committees work with them so freely; the Sisters labor like ants; new societies, choirs, orchestras, theatrical groups, patriotic clubs, women's clubs, etc., are growing like mushrooms after a rain and survive.</p>
   <p>"Finally, our pastor has established a library, purchased a lot of books, and <pb facs="5423968_10_0666.jpg" n="3"/>created more bother for himself. Crowds swarm to the rectory, crowding in and borrowing books as if the place belonged to them, as if the pastor had nothing else to do but be a servant of his parishioners.</p>
   <p>"He really is a servant, a brother, a teacher, a friend and a father to all of us. Everybody loves him, both old and young, and St. Hedwig, the patron saint of Poland and of our own church, is rejoicing in heaven, observing how our Polish people, with their Polish pastor, comprise one great multitude of faithful Catholics.</p>
   <p>A Parishioner."</p>
   <p>As can be seen, conditions in the St. Hedwig Parish are beautifully settled.Thank God.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
