<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-05-24">May 24, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Immigrants and Crime</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1740</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1740.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1912-05-24">May 24, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">IMMIGRANTS AND CRIME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American chauvinists feel that no interpretation will appease their antagonism against immigrants from other countries, although they themselves are grandchildren or great-grandchildren of immigrants. They contend that most crimes are committed by new arrivals from other parts of the world. However these are bare statements without the support of evidence, and were caught at random by the chauvinistic press which presented them as positive and irrefutable facts. Meanwhile, cold but honest statistics show something different. Statistics, playing no part in politics or chauvinism, present the facts as they really are. From these facts we learn that the alien is not as bad, as proclaimed by chauvinists and their press, and that the greater percentage of crimes committed falls to Americans instead of aliens, even in cities where the number of immigrants is equal to that of Americans. At a protest meeting held in the Auditorium against the anti-immigration bill, Judge Edwin E. Brown, of the Appellate Court, reviewed police records to compare the number of law violations committed by the different nationalities, and we learned from the records of the Guardianship Court that in March there were <pb facs="5423968_10_1741.jpg" n="2"/>seventy-four arrests for various violations. Of these, sixty-two were men and twelve women. This figure represented the following nationalities: fifty-one Americans, one Canadian, seven Germans, one Irish, one Norwegian, six Italians, three Poles, two Austrians, one Bohemian, and one Englishman. These facts prove that the aliens are not as bad as they are painted, but that these violations and scandals are committed mostly by Americans. Records of other courts will show similar conditions, but the American press with its silence covers up many violations committee by Americans; many of the crimes committed by natives are unloaded upon the shoulders of immigrants, while the others receive only slight mention as does some insignificant occurrence of the world. The fact must be taken into consideration that to a city like Chicago, outcasts of society flock from all over the world.</p>
   <p>Judge Brown, an impartial person, knows present conditions best, for every day he passes judgement in a large number of cases. He submitted a true statement and advised the American chauvinists to reform Americans, because they violate more laws than the new arrivals from Europe and other parts of the world. If an honest survey were conducted, one would find more crimes committed by Americans than by the foreign born.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
