<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Thaddeus Kosciuszko</title>", <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. IV, No. 6,
<date when="1926-02">February 1926</date>, P. 1.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1590</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1590.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Anonymous - "<title level="a">Thaddeus Kosciuszko</title>", <title>Chicago Society News</title> (Monthly), Vol. IV, No. 6,
<date when="1926-02">February 1926</date>, P. 1.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the heroes that we honor in the month of February we find Thaddeus Kosciuszko, the Polish Patriot, who fought in the American Revolution and whose name has gone down in the annals of the history of the United States and of his nativecountry as the brave defender of Liberty.</p>
   <p>February 12 will mark the one hundred and eightieth anniversary of his birth. Kosciuszko was born in Mereszezowezyzna near Novogrudek of an ancient but impoverished Lithuanian family. He attended the Military Academy in Warsaw and completed his education at Versailles after which he returned to Poland receiving the appointment of Captain of the Polish Army.</p>
   <p>The Hero of Saratoga</p>
   <p>Upon his arrival in the United States in 1777 he received letters of recommendation from Benjamin Franklin which obtained for him a Colonel's Commission in the American army. Kosciuszko was attached to General Gates' army which was operating in northern New York. It was here that the victorius Saratoga battle was fought and the excellent strategic position taken by the American Army at Bemis Heights was largely <pb facs="5423968_10_1591.jpg" n="2"/>planned by Kosciuszko. He was later appointed Chief Engineer and was engaged in constructing fortifications at West Point. After this he was Adjustant to General Washington. In 1780 he served under General Greene in the South and participated in the famous battle of Cowpens in which a handful of Americans annihilated an army of eleven hundred British.</p>
   <p>Returns to Europe</p>
   <p>Kosciuszko was landed for his assistance to the United States and at the close of the war he received the thanks of Congress with the brevet of Major General.</p>
   <p>He returned to Poland in 1786 and became the Commander of Chief of the Polish Army fighting the combined attack of the powers that had determined the division of Poland. He was successful at Raclawice but at the battle of Maciejowice Kosciuszko fell, covered with wounds uttering the sadly prophetic words: "This is the end of poland". To this fall the Poet Campbell refers in his couplet:--</p>
   <p>"Hope for a season bade the earth farewell.</p>
   <p>And Freedom shrieked when Kosciuszko fell.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1592.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After the downfall of Poland, Kosciuszko lived quietly in France revisiting the United States in 1787 at which time he received a pension and a grant of land from Congress.</p>
   <p>Dies in Switzerland in 1817</p>
   <p>In 1798 Kosciuszko again returned to Europe on a mission from the U. S. Congress to France and contributed toward bringing about an understanding between France and the United States. The month of April 1814 found Kosciuszko once more engaged in trying to secure a free constitution for Poland but his efforts were without avail.</p>
   <p>Kosciuszko's death was occasioned by a fall from his horse on October 15, 1817 at Solothurn, Switzerland. In 1818 his body was removed to the Cathedral in Cracow to lie side by side with that of John Sobieski. A cairn built up of soil brought together by his admirers stands upon a hill in the suburbs of Cracow which commands a view of the city, the Vistula, and the distant mountains.</p>
   <p>Kosciuszko is the author of "The Maneuvers of Horse Artillery", "A Description of the Campaign of 1782", and Volume XVI of Raczynski's "Sketch of Poles in Poland".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
