<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-11">June 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Holy Trinity Parish Jubilee</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-06-11">June 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HOLY TRINITY PARISH JUBILEE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In yesterday's issue of Dziennik Zwiazkowy, we printed a short item on the celebration by the parish of the twenty-fifth anniversary of the opening of Holy Trinity Church by Cardinal Satolli. We did not describe this celebration in detail, for it is well known that, on such an occasion, solemn High Mass is said, and there are sermons and other church ceremonies with which we are all familiar. Such an occasion usually closes with a reception or so-called banquet for guests and sympathizers, where speeches are made on the subject at hand.</p>
   <p>It makes no difference who attended this celebration and who did not, for we are concerned here not so much with the persons who were present as with the fact that last Sunday the Holy Trinity Parish celebrated a great <pb facs="5423968_10_0051.jpg" n="2"/>triumph over ill will and human prejudice, faults which can be found even in the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>The history of this parish is well known to all of us, for we know of its struggles for existence resulting from the fact that most of its members were members of the Polish National Alliance, whom certain church circles "deigned" to call Masons, heretics, and God knows what else when they would not submit to the jurisdiction of certain individuals who thought that even the Church could not exist without them.</p>
   <p>But let that matter rest. It happened a long time ago, and we do not want to raise irritable points here; it is not our purpose to describe the history of the parish in this article. It is enough to say that Holy Trinity Church has actually been the "church militant," since it fought for truth against the intrigues and prejudices of individuals and triumphed in the end because it followed the precept so widely spread by <pb facs="5423968_10_0052.jpg" n="3"/>Jesus Christ, "Love thy neighbor as thyself". For this reason, Holy Trinity Parish is an example to all other parishes, and with just dignity and joy it is celebrating the twenty-fifth anniversary of the opening of a once small, poor church that has grown to impressive size, gathering about it a great many members of the Polish National Alliance (whose motto is, "God with us and we with God") in the name of truth and justice, which virtues are recognized by heaven itself. And so there was great joy on Sunday that the truth and justice upon which Christ's teachings are based have triumphed. There were services in Holy Trinity Church, as is usual on such occasions, and throngs of people prayed to the Lord of Host and thanked Him that truth had prevailed, for God Himself blesses and supports the righteous.</p>
   <p>Holy Trinity Parish is regarded everywhere as the "Polish National Alliance Parish" because its members are nearly all members of that organization, and it was these people who participated in throngs in this rare church <pb facs="5423968_10_0053.jpg" n="4"/>ceremony. The entire Central Administration of the Polish National Alliance attended the Mass, celebrating not only the church occasion but the national ideal which today permeates all strata of our society.</p>
   <p>After all, Holy Trinity Church was reopened as a result of the efforts of Alliance members under the leadership of Francis H. Jablonski, former editor-in-chief of Dziennik Zwiazkowy and one-time president of the Polish National Alliance, who, together with Grajczyk, still living today, journeyed to Rome and explained the situation properly, as a result of which the Pope authorized Cardinal Satolli to reopen the church; this was done twenty-five years ago. Thus the Alliance members accomplished their purpose, and they can be proud of the fact that their parish is in splendid condition today, the second largest Polish parish, we believe, in the United States. Thanks are also due to its pastor, the Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, who, as a capable leader, conducts the parish affairs in exemplary fashion and has successfully weathered all storms. Today he <pb facs="5423968_10_0054.jpg" n="5"/>can enjoy the fruits of his labor, and he is filled with gratitude toward those who helped him during the most trying times.</p>
   <p>The most important feature of the jubilee celebration last Sunday was the banquet, at which important addresses were delivered. Many sincere and truthful words were spoken. About five hundred persons were present--not merely to eat their fill and return to their homes but to hear the history of the parish from the speakers' lips and to learn of its early struggles. There were not only Polish speakers, who knew the history of the parish, but there were also non-Poles, who gave the Poles credit for having upheld and developed their parish, one of the most exemplary parishes in America, in harmony and solidarity.</p>
   <p>Among the speakers was Casimir Zychlinski, president of the Polish National Alliance, who is well acquainted with the history of the parish from its very beginning. He said that the Polish National Alliance and Holy Trinity <pb facs="5423968_10_0055.jpg" n="6"/>Parish are members of one family, for both were persecuted at the same time; both fought and both were victorious. It is no wonder that his words were greatly applauded and that the gathering honored the Polish National Alliance by rising to its feet.</p>
   <p>It would be difficult for us to quote the words of each individual speaker, for behind them all was the same spirit, the same good will. The words of Zychlinski were echoed by Father Sztuczko, who in his turn said that, during the most critical times, Alliance members stood firmly at his side....and that he regards the Polish National Alliance as the foremost leader of the Polish element here, deserving of the highest recognitions and greatest support, since it never forsakes either God or Country.</p>
   <p>Holy Trinity Parish, to which belong about forty P. N. A. groups, has our best wishes that it attain a golden anniversary and live to see a free, independent, and united Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
