<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 11,
<date when="1907-01-14">Jan. 14, 1907</date><title level="a">Attention!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 11,
<date when="1907-01-14">Jan. 14, 1907</date><title level="a">ATTENTION!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The voice of God shall spread all over the world... to every nation... to teach lessons in getting rid of murders, robbers, diseases in general, insanity and accidents... how to open jails ... free prisoners.. and convert jails into churches for the new generation.</p>
   <p>In every school, all over the world, children must be taught reverence for God and His Ten Commandments... and their catechism.</p>
   <p>My dear children, brothers and sisters... God is asking you to learn and obey his commandments and all the catechism... to use it as a guide through your entire life... every step of the way until death, to save you from the penalties of sin and crime.</p>
   <p>Then, and not before, will the jails be turned to churches for the benefit of our new generations.</p>
   <p>Why should we not be satisfied to live peacefully in such a beautiful <pb facs="5423968_10_0234.jpg" n="2"/>world, when God has created everything for us? Even the tiny bee works for us collecting pollen to make honey for our enjoyment and benefit. Why do we rob each other? Why do we kill each other? Why are we filled with jealousy, envy, greed, and all forms of diseases, including insanity, in this world? It is merely because we forget to follow the commandments of God and the teachings of Jesus Christ.</p>
   <p>We are, each and everyone, merely human beings; but we must receive that power into our mind and heart, and keep it there forever. Then we will be able to love each other, replacing the present conditions with a spirit of peace.</p>
   <p>The death knell will then be sounded on the present conditions of murdering, stealing, robbing, diseases in general (including insanity), and accidents; in fact, all that contributes towards any form of unhappiness. Then jails shall become places of worship as well as asylums where - as human beings prayer and thanks may be offered to God.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
