<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-14">Jan. 14, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Societies in St. Adalbert Parish Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0660</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0660.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-14">Jan. 14, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIETIES IN ST. ADALBERT PARISH PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time past, St. Adalbert Parish has been the scene of unpleasant activities on the part of certain individuals who are continually trying to antagonize and split our ranks by creating quarrels and disputes.</p>
   <p>The attacks have been primarily directed against the president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union under the protection of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, Attorney Clemens J. Bielinski, because he is a brave defender of the organization he heads, and because he defends our religion and our church. These attacks have culminated in an incoherent protest against Mr. Bielinski, as published in the local liberal papers, and signed by a few individuals from St. Adalbert Parish.</p>
   <p>These protests have exhausted the patience of our societies and the Polish citizens of our parish.</p>
   <p>A meeting of various societies of St. Adalbert Parish was held Sunday, <pb facs="5423968_10_0661.jpg" n="2"/>January 12, in the parish school hall, for the purpose of considering this matter. The meeting was opened by Reverend John Radziejewski. Mr. F. Czerwinski presided and Mr. J. Pacholski acted as secretary. Many of those present took part in the discussion, severely condemning the attacks on Mr. Bielinski.</p>
   <p>As a result resolutions were adopted which condemned these vilifiers in the proper manner.</p>
   <p>These resolutions, due to lack of space, will be published tomorrow, but here we wish to mention that they were adopted by representatives of the following societies from St. Adalbert Parish: St. Adalbert's, Soldiers of St. Casimir, Holy Name of Jesus, Brotherhood of St. Dominic, St. Stanislaus, Our Lady of Sorrows, Most Sacred Name of Jesus, Holy Family, Archbrotherhood of St. Dominic, Reverend August Kordecki, St. Adalbert No. 1, "Krakus" of St. Florian (a military group), Hussars of St. Martin, and St. John The Baptist.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
