<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-29">May 29, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Second Agency of Polish League Opened in St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-29">May 29, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND AGENCY OF POLISH LEAGUE OPENED IN ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A second agency at the Polish League was opened by the St. Joseph Young Men's Society of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish. There are hopes that much will be achieved by this young group.</p>
   <p>This marks the twenty-eighth agency which has been opened during the short existence of the Polish League. This latest group has, above all, the aim of upholding the principles of the League; it also wishes to be in close harmony with the first agency of this parish and also with the third, which is being proposed.</p>
   <p>The members of this new agency, comprised of the youngest group, held a meeting Sunday, May 26, at 2:30 P.M. Reverend Vincent Barzynski, pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka Church and general secretary of the Polish League was present. Fifty-four new members joined, making ninety-six in all that have joined since the beginning of this organization early this month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1514.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The fees for the first forty-two members, twelve cents each, were paid from the treasury of the St. Joseph Young Men's Society for the entire year. [It is not stipulated whether this fee of twelve cents is per month or per year.] This withdrawal will be refunded through the process of a tax on all members of the Society. Two cents per month for two months was donated toward the Polish National Fund of the Polish League for the next fifty-four members.</p>
   <p>The officers of this agency are: S. Sambrowski, 221 Cleaver Street, superior; Francis Michalek, 555 Holt Avenue, secretary; and Valentine Roszkowiak, 131 Cleaver Street, collector. In view of the youth of the members it was decided to appoint Reverend Barzynski as chaplain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
