<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-16">Dec. 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Bells of Holy Trinity Parish Blessed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0686</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0686.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-16">Dec. 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">BELLS OF HOLY TRINITY PARISH BLESSED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(The following article was received by the Dziennik Chicagoski for publication.)</p>
   <p>Yesterday at 3 P. M. the Reverend A. Morrisey, president of Notre Dame University, South Bend, Indiana, with the assistance of the Reverend F. Byrgier, A. Schott, chaplain of St. Elizabeth's Hospital, the Reverend E. Raczynski, C. S. C., and the Reverend Casimir Sztuczko, pastor of Holy Trinity Church, opened the ceremonies for the blessing of the two new bells of Holy Trinity Church.</p>
   <p>The larger bell, weighing one thousand three hundred pounds, was named after St. Casimir, and the other, weighing six hundred and seventy pounds, was named after St. Florian.</p>
   <p>After the consecration ceremony, the Reverend Morrisey delivered an address in <pb facs="5423968_10_0687.jpg" n="2"/>English. He lauded the people for their ardent belief and support of the faith and urged everyone to continue to adhere to the religion of their ancestors. The visiting priest concluded by saying that a good Catholic will always make a true patriot.</p>
   <p>He was followed by the Reverend Byrgier, who expressed his hopes that the tolling bells would remind the congregation to offer prayer for the souls of the dead. "The sound of the bells", he said, "should also remind you that death is awaiting you; therefore, you should live piously so that you may have a happy end."</p>
   <p>The following societies took part in this event: St. Joseph Society, Holy Cross Society, St. Florian Society, Holy Trinity Parish Singers' Society, and the Polish Cadets of Holy Trinity Parish. The Polish Uhlans Society of St. Stanislaus Kostko Parish also participated.</p>
   <p>The following national groups also took part: Kosciusko Society, Young Business <pb facs="5423968_10_0688.jpg" n="3"/>Men's Society, Boleslas Chrobry Society, Cabinet Makers' and Carpenters' Society, Pulaski Guard, King Miecislas I Society, St. Casimir Jagello Society, Polish Krakuses Society, Polonia Society, John Kochanowski I Society, and Gmina Polska (Polish Commune) Society.</p>
   <p>Among the individuals that took part in the blessing ceremony were: J. Scherman, M. Majewski, S. Slominski, A. Groenwald, T. Nalepinski, J. Kowalski, J. Wojtalewicz, M. Wojtalewicz, P. Binkowski, F. Sergott, and J. Marcinkiewicz.</p>
   <p>The Wanda Society also took part.</p>
   <p>Sincere thanks are extended to all those that took part in this event.</p>
   <p>The Holy Trinity Parish Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
