<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 34,
<date when="1912-08-21">Aug. 21, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">About Polish Youth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 34,
<date when="1912-08-21">Aug. 21, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT POLISH YOUTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish youth is being denationalized. Everybody agrees to this, seeking means and ways of prevention, of which the main ones are Polish societies, societies of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>In such societies the Polish youth, who now find themselves in a critical position, ought to group themselves. The entire hope of the church and the nation rests in the Christian way of bringing up the youth. If the Polish youth will join with Polish societies, we can hope that they will grow up to become outstanding citizens and Catholics. In what sort of difficult position does our youth find themselves at the present time? This is easily detected by the way the different rival organizations are enticing unto themselves our Polish youth. On the one hand they are attracting them through entertainments or outings which they arrange free of charge. but they do not know how to get along without our money.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1464.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On the other hand they are calling them to the standard which has a watch-word: Away with faith and nationality! The parents should not permit their children to join such societies. Because Polish youth ought to have other places, other societies and other entertainment. They ought to group in Polish societies! The Polish youth ought to educate and endeavor to learn in their younger days to carry themselves is a dignified manner, respectably and properly, so that in later years they would not repeat the accusation: I have wasted my life! And to God I must give a reckoning! It pains us mostly that the youth roams the streets at late hours of the night or hangs around in taverns and there poisons its healthy mind with alcoholic drinks, which becomes unpleasant to every decent person.</p>
   <p>It is high time to elevate the spirit and to save that which is about to parish. Therefore, we should stand up against such habits and try to get our youth to join Polish societies, societies of the Roman-Catholic Union where, under the guardianship of more enlightened and <pb facs="5423968_10_1465.jpg" n="3"/>good people they can avoid despoilment and become defenders of the holy faith and the Polish nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
