<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-01-10">Jan. 10, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Important to All Poles</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-01-10">Jan. 10, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT TO ALL POLES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A bill is to be submitted to congress to promote chauvinism. A Chicago delegation of The Council for the Protection of Foreign Born is convoking representatives of union and non-union organizations, to discuss the preparations for negotiating an attack of this bill in congress, which, if passed, will compel all foreign born to register, be photographed and fingerprinted, by an authorized official. The procedure and treatment of the foreign element will be very similar to the treatment accorded criminals, detained at the detective bureau.</p>
   <p>The conference will be held Tuesday, at Machinists Hall, 113 So. Ashland Ave., at 8:P.M. All labor organizations are invited to send representatives to participate. We must oppose three bills of the foregoing nature, introduced by congressmen Aswell, Johnson, and Holiday. One of which proposes to make it possible that the Department of Labor deport aliens. This will place those of us who are of Polish birth, at the mercy of officials, who in most cases discriminate against the foreign element. Mr. Orlowski, Secretary of the organization maintains that the originators of this bill assume and take for granted that people of foreign element have forgotten about these issues, and that they may be submitted before congress without difficulty. It is, therefore, essential that we remind them, that the foreign element is fully aware of threats against their security, also of the source, therefore, they are preparing to attack chauvinism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1618.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These bills are not in line with clean Americanism. In the opinion of the Secretary of Labor, it is said that the registration of foreigners is not compulsory. This bill greatly jeopardizes the labor organization, if passed, it would be possible to deport any alien during a strike, particularly those who participate in picketing.</p>
   <p>The aforementioned bills were condemned in two conventions of the American Federation of Labor, one in Kansas City, the other in Detroit, Michigan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
