<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-11-12">Nov. 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting in Behalf of the Polish Youth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-11-12">Nov. 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING IN BEHALF OF THE POLISH YOUTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A group of Polish parents met yesterday at Bradley Street Hall for the purpose of organizing their sons, who are leaving school.</p>
   <p>Several hundred Polish fathers, with sons thirteen years old and older, were present.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Reverend Vincent Barzynski, who told the parents that something has to be done for our young, growing generation, that it may not waste its time idly, that it may not lose faith, morality, and love for the country; that on the contrary, it may grow mentally and become successful. Up to now we have had our youth organizations, but these organizations have been without supervision by and participations of older persons, and as a result their work has been useless. This defect in our youth organizations must be remedied by the creation of special committees composed of older persons, <pb facs="5423968_10_1527.jpg" n="2"/>mature enough to protect and lead our young people along the right path.</p>
   <p>The audience accepted this plan with approval. Some of the parents asked for the floor and expressed their opinions.</p>
   <p>Finally, a plan was adopted to organize a youth society under the name Sodalis Marianus, or Saint Mary Sodality, after the fashion of the old religious society of the same name in Poland, to which knights used to belong.</p>
   <p>The purpose of this society will be to protect our youth, to strengthen it in faith and morality, to enlighten it, to help it complete its education by attending evening and Sunday courses, gymnastic exercises, drilling, etc.</p>
   <p>This plan met with general approval. A special committee will prepare a suitable constitution, after the announcement of which another meeting will be called.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
