<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-08">Feb. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Roman Catholic Union Installs New Officers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-08">Feb. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION INSTALLS NEW OFFICERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting [at which the Union's new officers were installed] was begun with a prayer led by the Reverend B. R. Celichowski. Members of both the old and the new administrations were present.</p>
   <p>The former president of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, P. Rostenkowski, delivered a short address in which he expressed his hopes for the Union's continued growth, pledging his aid and support at all times. He then turned over the gavel to N. L. Piotrowski, the new president.</p>
   <p>After formally accepting the office, Piotrowski made a short speech in which he thanked the organization for the honor it had conferred upon him. He promised to work and sacrifice for the good of the Union, and said that he would do his best, so that in the report of his activities at the next convention he would be able to say that the Union had doubled its membership.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0065.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Speeches were also made by Reverends Celichowski, Wojtalewicz, and Gorski, and by the vice-president, Dr. Smykowski. All were pleased that affairs had taken such a good turn, and that the old administration had retired voluntarily; they expressed hopes that peace and harmony would again reign within the Union for the good of the organization.</p>
   <p>The new administration received a great many congratulatory letters and telegrams, and many flowers.</p>
   <p>At eight o'clock in the evening, all of the members of the new administration gathered at the headquarters of the Polish Press Club, on Pierce Avenue with a few invited guests, to celebrate their first day as duly installed officers of the Polish Roman Catholic Union. More than forty persons were present at the banquet, at which John Czekala presided as toastmaster.</p>
   <p>The first speaker was Dr. Smykowski, who had to leave the banquet after receiving a telegram calling him to a conference in Buffalo. As he left, Piotrowski <pb facs="5423968_10_0066.jpg" n="3"/>asked him to assure the people in his part of the country that the Polish Roman Catholic Union was supporting the Polish Army in France with all its energy. Other speakers were Stanislaus Marciniak of Buffalo, Reverend Wojtalewicz of South Chicago, Mr. Singer of St. Paul, Reverend Robakowski of Posen, Illinois, ex-Director Starzyk of Chicopee, Massachusetts, Reverend Wilamowski of Floral Park, New York, Mr. Jurczak of Wheeling, West Virginia, Mr. Kosko of Passaic, New Jersey, and finally, John F. Smulski, who arrived at the hall in company of Thaddeus Wronski.</p>
   <p>In greeting the Union's new administration and expressing his best wishes for a fruitful term of office, Smulski laid emphasis first of all on the fact that the Union belongs not only to its members but to Polonia as a whole; that the new administration is responsible not only to the organization but to the entire people; that the new administration ought to recognize this fact and seek to be of service not only to the organization but to the Polish nation. Smulski commended the Union for its twenty-five-cent assessment, voted at the last convention, and urged the members of the organization to pay it willingly, <pb facs="5423968_10_0067.jpg" n="4"/>for Poland's great hour is at hand, and anyone who is not willing to contribute does not deserve to be a Pole. Finally, Smulski expressed a few words of greeting from Paderewski, who, because of fatigue after attending the Polish Clergymen's Convention, was unable to be present.</p>
   <p>Other speakers following Smulski were Mr. Blaszko of Pennsylvania, ex-Director Mrs. Czaja, Director Zielinski of Holyoke, Massachusetts, and Editor Stefanowicz. The chairman also called upon Thaddeus Wronski who told the gathering in a few words that in his last tour with his military band he had worked to encourage volunteers for the Polish army. Henceforth, however, he said, he would strive to raise money for the Polish cause. Other speakers following him were Mr. Twarogowski from Ohio, the retiring editor of Narod [Nation], Francis Barc, ex-Director Pionke, Mr. Chubinski of Indiana Harbor, Indiana, the secretary of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, Setmajer, and finally, the Union's new syndic, J. J. Jankowski. As the last speaker of the evening, the toastmaster called upon Piotrowski, who spoke earnestly to the gathering, defining his own position and <pb facs="5423968_10_0068.jpg" n="5"/>pointing out the task facing every loyal Union member.</p>
   <p>A collection for the relief of war victims in Poland, taken up on the initiative of Jankowski, netted fifty-two dollars.</p>
   <p>Before the singing of "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland), Toastmaster Czekala thanked the officers of the Polish Press Club for allowing the Union to use its quarters, and expressed his great joy that the Poles of Chicago can boast of such a club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
