<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 3,
<date when="1899-01-19">Jan. 19, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Is This Permitted?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0315</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0315.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 3,
<date when="1899-01-19">Jan. 19, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">IS THIS PERMITTED?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I must give the readers of Zgoda the true facts about some thing that happened to me, about the had behavior of our Catholic priests.</p>
   <p>Rev. Father E., of St. Stanislans parish come to my home a few weeks age for the yearly church collection. As I was showing him my parish book from the Holy Trinity parish, I said: "I can't donate money for the upkeep of two parishes." The Rev. Father left and later told some people that I throw him out of my home.</p>
   <p>This incident occurred to me on December 25 of last year: I was invited by a lady to escort her and her baby to participate in a Catholic church rite (the churching of a woman), I knelt down to give praise to God when Father S... came from the sacristy and said: "Get out, go to Holy Trinity."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0316.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I ask of you, should priests act this way and insult people in church? These are the priests that force Catholic people to join the Independent Catholic Church; the Catholic priests call these people Coxeyites (members of Coxey's army), but this is not the people's fault, but the priest's. If we did not have priests like Rev. Father S... we would have peace and love among us Poles.</p>
   <p>Another priest, Father P..., came for a collection to my daughter, who owns a store, and when he did not receive any money because she does not approve of giving for the support of two parishes, Father P... visited other business people and told them lies about my daughter and warned people belonging to St. Stanislaus parish not to trade in this store. Is this permitted?</p>
   <p>Doesn't Rev. Father P... know that on grounds of slander he can be sued in court for damaging and ruining her business unrightfully? This is not the work and teachings of Jesus Christ.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0317.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Why must the priest be so rude and make trouble? They can be nice and lovable if they would only stay within the bounds and obligations of the Catholic religion and the Bible.</p>
   <p>This eventually leads to bitterness, hard feelings and misunderstandings. Can't we do our part and not permit such scandals?</p>
   <p>R. Centella.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
