<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-04">Apr. 4, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[News from St. Adalbert's Parish]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-04">Apr. 4, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">[NEWS FROM ST. ADALBERT'S PARISH]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We received for publication the following letter from a member of St. Adalbert's parish:</p>
   <p>"It is a long time since Dziennik [Chicagoski] wrote last about our parish. Indeed, we live and work peacefully, but at Easter time at least our activities could be mentioned.</p>
   <p>"St. Adalbert's parish, on the Southwest Side, is progressing. Our beautiful new rectory is already completed, and our large new parochial school, with twelve spacious classrooms, is nearing completion. The new school building is a necessity, for until now our children have all been crowded in the small basement of the church. We hope that the children will occupy the new quarters after their summer vacation.</p>
   <p>"From the time when our parish became unified, life here has proceeded more easily. Everyone is everybody else's friend, and there seems to be much more <pb facs="5423968_10_1084.jpg" n="2"/>mutual love and respect among our parishioners.</p>
   <p>"We have a great many church societies. In all, there are twenty-three male societies, five of which are military. [These "military" societies are church organizations, the members of which wear uniforms while at patriotic exercises and parades. In some cases the members are veterans of Polish wars]. We arranged a procession, which started at five o'clock in the morning, on Easter Sunday. The weather was so beautiful and the air so still that, although we circled the church three times, not one candle was extinguished. All our societies contributed to the beautiful music that was heard in the church. In general, all our church societies deserve praise for their generosity whenever contributions of money are necessary.</p>
   <p>"On April 23, we will celebrate the day of our patron saint, St. Adalbert. On May 23, children will receive first communion from the Archbishop. In three months, three banners--given to the societies by our pastor himself to replace those that were lost--will be blessed during a special ceremony. Then, of <pb facs="5423968_10_1085.jpg" n="3"/>course, the new parochial school will be dedicated. One of the bishops has said that a school is the heart of a parish.</p>
   <p>"During the coming year, there will be many special ceremonies, as for instance, when our beloved pastor, Father Radziejewski, celebrates his twenty-fifth anniversary of priesthood. St. Adalbert's has not yet seen such an occasion. Thus, in a few words, you have all of our parish news."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
