<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-24">May 24, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Independent Church Planned for the Vicinity of St. Hedwig Parish</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0871</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0871.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-05-24">May 24, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">INDEPENDENT CHURCH PLANNED FOR THE VICINITY OF ST. HEDWIG PARISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has happened! A very and story comes from St. Hedwig Parish. We have learned from the English papers that two meetings were held this week by the opposition group of St. Hedwig Church and it was agreed to break away from the church--and travel on the road of schism. It was also agreed to form an "independent parish" and erect a church, which will be patterned after the Catholic church.</p>
   <p>At the present time we will not divulge any further particulars nor the names of the proponents of this shameful affair, for we have hopes that all those connected with this will collect themselves and realize where they are heading. We wish only to point out that a Polish priest, unfortunately, is mixed up in this revolt. This Catholic priest, [Reverend Joseph Radziszewski,] is the <pb facs="5423968_10_0872.jpg" n="2"/>same one who has started all the trouble at St. Hedwig Parish. His plotting and innocence was covered in previous issues--he claimed that he was not working against the wishes of the bishop. Today he has been appointed pastor of this "independent parish"; he also informed the bishop and the Pope of this revolt.</p>
   <p>This is painful to say the least. We have great hope that this shameful matter will not have further results, that the befuddled people will awaken at the eleventh hour--and will not complete this scandalous project which will bring them the condemnation of the church, as well as the ruin of their souls.</p>
   <p>To those who wish to be duped into the "independent church" we wish to refer to a letter from Cardinal Ledachowski to Joseph Deranek of Cleveland, which was published Monday, May 21. [Translator's note: This is erroneous; it was published Saturday, May 19.] The letter reveals that the so-called "independent" churches and parishes are not Catholic parishes and churches, but "flocks of heretics"; that the priests revolting against powers of the church, and condemned <pb facs="5423968_10_0873.jpg" n="3"/>by the bishop (a fate which undoubtedly will face the "independent" priest at St. Hedwig Parish) do not belong to the Catholic church; and, that such behavior by a priest against religious ceremonies is sacrilegious.</p>
   <p>For the benefit of those who are thinking of following this path, we wish to inform them that they are heading toward perpetual damnation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
