<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-19">Dec. 19, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Roman Catholic Union in Good Financial Position</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-12-19">Dec. 19, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ROMAN CATHOLIC UNION IN GOOD FINANCIAL POSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last issue of the Wiara i Ojczyzna (Faith and the Fatherland) a comprehensive statement of the new administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union (under the guidance of the Sacred Heart of Jesus) was published, covering the quarter from September 1 to December 1, 1895, the first quarter after the South Bend Convention.</p>
   <p>It is gratifying to note, according to the facts and figures cited in the report, that the Union stands on a firm financial footing, contrary to the rumors, false reports, lies, etc., spread by the opposition. Despite the fact that the Milwaukee group was taken off the books, the membership of the Polish Roman Catholic Union is growing steadily. Before the next quarter passes the number of new members will far exceed that of the expelled Milwaukee faction.</p>
   <p>In general the Union stands on a firm foundation. It is immune to any discord <pb facs="5423968_10_0681.jpg" n="2"/>or dissention, such as the Milwaukee faction tried to stir up. The future may be looked forward to with the greatest calm. The figures given in the report are the best proof.</p>
   <p>Let us look at the number of old and new members. According to the report, they are as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Old members as of September 1,</cell>
     <cell>8,782</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>New members as of December 1,</cell>
     <cell>419</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>9,201</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Number of deaths during first quarter</cell>
     <cell>22</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Number taken off books</cell>
     <cell>1,219</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total number dropped</cell>
     <cell>1,241</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Total number of members as of December 1</cell>
     <cell>7,900(sic)</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>These figures indicate that despite the loss of the 1,219 Milwaukee members, one third of this number or 419 were added, thus cutting down the loss considerably.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0682.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the present time the Polish Roman Catholic Union has almost 8,000 members on its books. This makes it the largest Polish organization in America.</p>
   <p>The following societies joined the Union during the past quarter: St. Joseph Society of Schenectady, New York; Sacred Heart Society of Dorr, Allegan County, Michigan; St. Adalbert Society of Berea, Ohio; St. Michael Archangel Society of Alden, Pennsylvania; St. Joseph Society of Chicago; and the Holy Name of Mary Society of Peru, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Out of the above seven societies, six are from out of town. This again indicates that the Polish Roman Catholic Union is not merely a local organization. The opposition cannot refute these figures.</p>
   <p>On the other hand it can be said that Chicago could play a greater part in this organization and undoubtedly it will in time. But this does not mean that it is going to interfere with the out-of-town members. On the contrary, all will be treated with equal consideration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0683.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As to the financial status of the Union, according to the report of the quarter, it is as follows:</p>
   <p>INCOME</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>As of the month of September</cell>
     <cell>$4,526.80</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>As of the month of October</cell>
     <cell>6,700.46</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>As of the month of November</cell>
     <cell>6,501.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance on hand September 1, 1895</cell>
     <cell>4,050.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$21,778.86</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>EXPENSES</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Total paid out in September</cell>
     <cell>$7,416.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total paid out in October</cell>
     <cell>5,689.95</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total paid out in November</cell>
     <cell>6,974.31</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Grand Total</cell>
     <cell>$20,080.36</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0684.jpg" n="5"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Income</cell>
     <cell>$21,778.86</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Expenses</cell>
     <cell>20,080.36</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance on hand December 1,1895</cell>
     <cell>$ 1,698.50</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>These figures definitely indicate that the Polish Roman Catholic Union is by no means on the verge of bankruptcy, and at the present time it has a surplus in its treasury. Out of the $20,080 listed under expenses, $18,300 were paid out in death benefits.</p>
   <p>In other words the Union is resting on a sound foundation. Despite the assertions made by the opposition and the expelled members from Milwaukee, the treasury has a surplus. Its officers and staff are working energetically to improve the standing of the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>The officers of the Union made reference to the misleading articles written about their organization by its enemies at the last meeting. A resolution was unanimously passed to make a reply to all such attacks and to have it published for the information of the public. This resolution is being drawn <pb facs="5423968_10_0685.jpg" n="6"/>up by B. Klarkowski.</p>
   <p>The publication of this resolution will be a very good and timely step, and should once and for all seal the lips of the opposition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
