<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-02-02">Feb. 2, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Activities</title><title level="a" type="sub">From St. John Cantius Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1022</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1022.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-02-02">Feb. 2, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ACTIVITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">From St. John Cantius Parish</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have received the following report for publication:</p>
   <p>Although our church is not quite finished, the people attend all its services with great pleasure.</p>
   <p>Yesterday being the day of the Purification of the Blessed Virgin (a candle day), there were church services in the afternoon, and the main altar was beautifully decorated. Many Polish young ladies, dressed in white, occupied the front pews and the whole front nave. One of these young ladies, surrounded by a group of little girls, also dressed in white and holding flowers in their hands, held the banner of the Virgin of the Immaculate Conception.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1023.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As part of the ceremony of blessing the banner of the Holy Rosary Society, Reverend Vincent Barzynski and Reverend J. Kasprzycki, our pastor, appeared before the altar, the former intoning "Veni, Creator," accompanied by the choir. This formality over, the prelate blessed the banner. Father Barzynski then preached a sermon, interesting and full of spiritual nourishment, in which he said to the young ladies under his supervision that he was entrusting them to our pastor, assuring them that they would have good care. He told the young ladies that meekness, modesty, humility, and obedience to their parents are maidenly virtues.</p>
   <p>His sermon over, Father Barzynski celebrated vespers, after which he blessed the people with the Blessed Sacrament.</p>
   <p>All who were present felt that they received spiritual help. Honor to our clergy!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
