<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XX, No. 27,
<date when="1901-07-04">July 4, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">To Polish Parishes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>, Vol. XX, No. 27,
<date when="1901-07-04">July 4, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TO POLISH PARISHES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reverend Fathers and Dear Fellow Citizens:</p>
   <p>About thirty years ago Polish immigrants began coming to this country in great numbers, and at the present day they represent here a population of several millions.</p>
   <p>At the beginning the Poles organized independent societies; then they organized Polish parishes, and later united into bigger and stronger organizations. There exist hundreds of other independent societies that were supported in the earlier days, but today the united organizations, having the majority of the Polish people as their members, are controlling the greatest percentage of all organizations' finances.</p>
   <p>The newspapers of former days referred to the Poles as individuals, <pb facs="5423968_10_0302.jpg" n="2"/>because they worked and carried on business as individuals; but today they refer to the American Poles as a class of people. The Poles are recognized as a hard working, striving and persistent nationality in America. The credit for this recognition of the Poles is due mainly to our Catholic priests and some individuals who worked with the priests in this respect.</p>
   <p>Every day we are more and more convinced that we can exist as a prosperous nationality in Chicago, but at the same time that we prosper we build up hatred among other nationalities who are planning continuously to cause hard feeling amidst ourselves and attempt to keep us Poles from uniting as one nationality and from working in harmony. Many times attempts have been made to stop teaching of the Polish language in parochial schools; also to have the gospel read in Latin or in the Irish language during mass in the Polish churches. At this point <pb facs="5423968_10_0303.jpg" n="3"/>the Polish priests aroused the Polish people to the fact that if we don't put a stop to all these slander and false accusations, the Polish language will soon be extinct.</p>
   <p>The Polish newspapers took an active part in this affair and supported all the movements of the Polish Catholic churches. A meeting was held at the St. Stanislaus parish hall, where the Polish people with the aid of the Polish priests, made resolutions and took steps to stop all this propaganda about the Polish language. The priests also sent letters to the Pope, asking that he be kind enough to ask the priests of other nationalities to end their bitterness and hard feelings toward the Poles.</p>
   <p>The Polish people can see for themselves that the Polish priests are the backbone of our language and nationality, and deserve the full support of every true blooded Pole.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0304.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Some of the resolutions passed are:</p>
   <p>1. To place the Polish clergy on a level with the clergy of other nationalities in Chicago.</p>
   <p>2. To put a stop to the slandering and criticizing of the Polish language by priests, bishops and other members of the Roman-Catholic clergy.</p>
   <p>3. Schooling and its reforming.</p>
   <p>4. All Polish people should take an active part in local, church and political affairs.</p>
   <p>5. Promote and support Polish business enterprises and join the Polish Businessmen Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0305.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Raise funds for all great Polish movements. The members of this committee are: Rev. Father John Pitass, president; Stanley Slisz, secretary; Rev. Father Thomas Flaczek, Rev. Father F. Kasprzak, W. A. Truszkowski, W. Jacolik, M. Wojchiechowski, Joseph Milewezyk, Joseph F. Antozak, and Joseph Slisz.</p>
   <p>Send all your suggestions and complaints to Father Jan Pitass, or Stanley Slisz, in care of St. Stanislaus, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
