<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-08">Aug. 8, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">Tenth Anniversary Celebration of St. Cecelia Society in Chicago, Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1119</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1119.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-08-08">Aug. 8, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Tenth Anniversary Celebration of St. Cecelia Society in Chicago, Illinois</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the St. Cecelia Society celebrated its tenth anniversary. The program comprised two parts: first, to commemorate the memories of its foundation and development, and second, a performance of two gay comedies.</p>
   <p>At the opening of the program Mr. John Czekala, the president of the Society, invited the director of the parish choir, Mr. Andrew Kwasigroch, to act as chairman. Thereupon, Mr. Kwasigroch briefly outlined to the audience the rise of St. Cecelia Society out of the Lute Society, which had been in existence for four years prior to the founding of St. Cecelia. And because it progressed so marvelously, it is today the support of the parish choir.</p>
   <p>The chairman summoned Mr. Walter Barwig as secretary, who delivered the main address. He brought out the worthy purposes of the Society, mentioning the <pb facs="5423968_10_1120.jpg" n="2"/>various important matters concerning the preservation of the national spirit among us, and the question of schools and libraries.</p>
   <p>The Reverend W. Barzynski spoke in sincere words at the conclusion of the first part of the program. The speeches were intermingled with songs by the male choir of the Society.</p>
   <p>The second part of the program followed with a performance of two elegant comedies, "Pity the Mustache" and "Nightingale". Both comedies were a great success and the crowd had a merry time. Miss Lottie Chlebowska proved in both comedies that our amateur stage is still adorned with grace, worthy of succeeding the much mourned performers, Mrs. Andrew Kwasigroch, Mrs. Francis Kwasigroch, and other well-known amateurs. The sympathetic "Amelia" and the pleasing "Nightingale" of last night, found indeed a valiant friend in Miss R. Zukowski, who was the exquisite "Dorothy". The part of "Mr. Anzelm" in the first comedy, was played by Mr. Szczesny Zahajkiewicz, who performed his role very efficiently, enhancing the entire play. Mr. Kondziorski, for whom the part in the first comedy was not necessarily appropriate, since he is a serious-minded <pb facs="5423968_10_1121.jpg" n="3"/>individual, made a remarkable lord in "Nightingale". Mr. John Czekala as usual, held the crowd in perpetual laughter, with his remarks and characteristic motions. Indeed, all had a jolly time, except for the long intermissions between plays, when some of the audience began showing signs of impatience. However, the delay was justified by the fact that the amateurs had to have time to change their make up.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
