<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-31">Aug. 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Edmund F. Sosnowski Enlists in United States Navy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-08-31">Aug. 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">EDMUND F. SOSNOWSKI ENLISTS IN UNITED STATES NAVY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Edmund F. Sosnowski, president of the Polish-American Athletic Club has enlisted in the United States Navy and is awaiting his call. With his entrance into active service the Club adds another star to its list. The Polish-American Athletic Club now has thirty-six prominent athletes doing active service in the battle between democracy and autocracy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sosnowski joined the Club in 1915, and from the very beginning he has taken part in all branches of sport. In 1916 and 1917 he held the Club championship in tennis. In 1918 he attempted to gain the same honors but was defeated by Stanley Mazur. In this contest for the championship Sosnowski gained second place. He has frequently participated in track meets and for two successive years was recognized as one of the outstanding basketball players of his time.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1363.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polish-American Athletic Club has been in a very critical position during the last two years. Because of the excellent management of Mr. Sosnowski, however, the Club has finally emerged from its embarassing position. At present it is recognized as one of the leading athletic clubs of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sosnowski has the honor and the distinction of being the first member of the Club to join the United States Navy. He has been a fighter at all times, and now he wants to demonstrate to all that he fears no one, especially not a Hun. It is for this reason that he has selected for himself a very difficult task.</p>
   <p>All Poles wish Mr. Sosnowski good fortune. May God in heaven protect him and all those who have gone to fight in defense of a just and honorable cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
