<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 30,
<date when="1915-07-28">July 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Address</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 30,
<date when="1915-07-28">July 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ADDRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Apostolic Delegate in Washington X. John Bonzano, D. D.</p>
   <p>Your excellency:</p>
   <p>Availing themselves of the sojourn of Your Excellency in this city, the delegation of the Polish citizens of Chicago is paying you a visit, in these days of genuine sorrow caused by the demise of our never-to-be forgotten archbishop, the Most Rev. James Quigley, and at the same time greet you with hearts sympathetic and truly Polish, and as such, inflexibly attached to our Holy Faith.</p>
   <p>Upon this occasion we desire to state that the Polish citizens of the United States know you, honor and love you, and shall ever remember the great favors conferred upon them; your gracious sympathy bestowed upon us, as well as all the kindly acts you have rendered our brethren.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0107.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We, the Polish community of the United States, shall, always be grateful to you, for it sees in you, and hopes you shall continue to be the most eminent guardian and advocate and supporter of our religious interests.</p>
   <p>And at this moment which finds you sojourning in our city, at this hour of grief consequent upon the death of the late archpaster and steward of our diocese, we learn that a singular honor has befallen our Polish community, namely, he who was the late archbishop's right hand, his chosen collaborator and excellent assistant, the Right Reverend Paul Rhode, D. D. is to be transposed from his office to that of bishop of the diocese of Green Bay.</p>
   <p>It is indeed a great favor and honor that has befallen the Polish Catholics of America and our Polish community lacks words to express its gratitude to the Holy Father for this signal mark of this paternal solicitude for the interest of our Holy Faith among us.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0108.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We wish to state that without exception the entire Polish Catholic community is overjoyed because the honor has befallen Bishop Rhode, whose work has endeared him to all classes of our people. Through his efforts and his work among us a spirit of harmony and peace hitherto unknown prevails among us. Our Catholic organizations have been strengthened in their salutary influence on our community; our reverend clergy have been united to common action in all matters affecting the welfare of our Polish Catholic population.</p>
   <p>Owing to his efforts, also much has been done to raise the standard of our parish schools, and a more lively interest is being taken in the training of our young generation growing up in America. In general our devotion to the Holy Mother Church has taken new life. Yet, while acknowledging our great debt to our Holy Father for the favor which He has so benignly conferred upon us, and while thanking him with all our heart for it, we cannot as loyal children of God's Holy Church, permit the occasion to pass without voicing at the same time our fear <pb facs="5423968_10_0109.jpg" n="4"/>that here in Chicago, deprived of the care of a bishop from among our own race, who would know us intimately, the interest of our holy religion may suffer.</p>
   <p>We number about 350,000 faithful and devoted Catholics and our number is continually growing. Our churches and other institutions are increasing in number. We have about 140 Polish priests, 45 parishes and about 35,000 children in our schools.</p>
   <p>In general, our religious interests are becoming so complex and important from the standpoint of our present and future growth that we feel in conscience bound to humbly pray your Excellency to remember us in a special manner and we earnestly beseech your Excellency that we be not left without care and guidance of a bishop of our nationality, who will understand our needs and aspirations.</p>
   <p>We thank your Excellency from the bottom of our hearts for the extra-ordinary marks of sympathy which you have already shown to the Polish <pb facs="5423968_10_0110.jpg" n="5"/>Catholics in the United States, and we earnestly hope that our prayer may truly be understood by Your Excellency and may be granted in so far as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
