<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-10">Nov. 10, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Young Polish Lawyer Honored</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-10">Nov. 10, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG POLISH LAWYER HONORED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today the Poles gained another public office, one of the most important in the Government of the United States. A young Polish attorney, who was born in Chicago and educated in Polish schools, was appointed to a high office which no Pole has until now had the opportunity to hold.</p>
   <p>This fortunate young man is Attorney Peter P. Mindak, who was appointed United States Assistant Attorney for the northern district of Illinois, with official residence in Chicago, by Attorney General George W. Wicker-sham, with the approval of President Taft. He is the first Pole to be appointed as an attorney in the Department of Justice.</p>
   <p>This high office was granted to a Pole at the request of James H. Wilkerson, District Attorney for the Government of the United States, who is at the head of the Department of Justice in Chicago. Mr. Wilkerson, a sincere friend of the Poles, immediately after receiving his own appointment a <pb facs="5423968_10_1425.jpg" n="2"/>month ago decided to press his superiors in Washington to appoint a Pole to the important post of United States Assistant Attorney. For many years Mr. Wilkerson has been the friend of Election Commissioner Anthony Czarnecki, and through Mr. Czarnecki he has become acquainted with, and a friend of, the Poles. Before he attained his present post, Mr. Wilkerson promised his associate, Mr. Czarnecki, that as soon as he received his appointment he would begin action to secure the appointment of a Polish lawyer as his assistant. Election Commissioner Czarnecki took up this matter as soon as Mr. Wilkerson took office, and today a wire from Washington established the fact that the request had been granted. Mr. Wilkerson, in requesting a Polish attorney as his assistant, was strongly supported by Attorney General Wickersham. It must be emphasized that President Taft, to whom this matter was referred, also sincerely endorsed the selection of a Pole for this important post.</p>
   <p>Attorney Peter Mindak lives with his mother and sisters at 1243 North Robey Street, and has his office in the Prospect Building, at Division Street and <pb facs="5423968_10_1426.jpg" n="3"/>Ashland Avenue. He was employed for eight years as a clerk in the main Post Office, and during this time he not only performed his duties, and supported his mother, but he furthered his education by studying law in his spare time. A year and a half age he completed his law studies at the John Marshall Law School and passed his bar examination. He pursued his endeavors to educate himself so quietly that not until his graduation did even his most intimate friends know of his studies. Attorney Mindak is a member of Polish, as well as American, organizations.....</p>
   <p>This year is an especially memorable one for Chicago Poles in politics. Not only have the Poles obtained more municipal posts, through the present mayor, but they have also obtained posts never before held by Poles. For instance, for the first time a Pole, in the person of Attorney Ludwig Pinderski, is an assistant in the office of the State's Attorney. For the first time a Polish woman, Mrs. Rose Kwasigroch, is a member of the Commission for Charitable Institutions. And today we find another of our countrymen, Attorney Peter Mindak, in the post of United States <pb facs="5423968_10_1427.jpg" n="4"/>Assistant Attorney.</p>
   <p>Attorney Mindak announces that he will be at the service of any of his compatriots who desire legal advice every evening (except Sundays and holidays) from 7 P. M. to 9 P. M. in the Prospect Building, at Ashland Avenue and Division Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
