<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-07">Jan. 7, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of a New Cross at St. John Cantius Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0963</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0963.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-01-07">Jan. 7, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF A NEW CROSS AT ST. JOHN CANTIUS PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dedication ceremonies of a new cross were held yesterday afternoon at 3:30 at St. John Cantius Parish. The costly cross was obtained by the St. Cyril and Methodius Society, which is affiliated with the Polish Roman Catholic Union.</p>
   <p>All the societies of St. John Cantius Parish made efforts to collect money for a cross at the parish fair sometime ago; the St. Cyril and Methodius Society was the most successful. Success came easily to this organization, because at that time it was the only one connected with the Polish Roman Catholic Union. This is concrete evidence that, those who join a large group working in one spirit for a common cause are always successful, because there is greater moral support and more energy and spirit.</p>
   <p>Prior to the consecration ceremony, a procession was held in which the cross, beautifully decorated with ferns and flowers, was displayed and <pb facs="5423968_10_0964.jpg" n="2"/>later brought before the central altar of the church.</p>
   <p>Reverend F. Matuszewski delivered a sermon appropriate to the occasion. It was based on the following theory: Since the Christians once, confident in the words which were given them from above, "In hoc signo vinces" (By this sign [the Cross] thou shalt conquer), under the standard of the cross at their head defeated the enemy, the preacher realized that the cross is the only power, the only bond, the only joiner which binds the people, as if with one long chain. As a result of this, it is necessary for all of us to unite as one, and work in one spirit toward the love of Christ; etc.</p>
   <p>After the sermon the dedication ceremonies began officially. Reverend John Kasprzycki, pastor of St. John Cantius Parish, officiated. The church choir sang the beautiful "Veni Jesu."</p>
   <p>At the close of the ceremony the cross was placed at the designated place in the processional, after which everyone came to kiss the cross, according <pb facs="5423968_10_0965.jpg" n="3"/>to custom. There were so many of the devout parishioners present that it took three hours for all to perform the holy ritual.</p>
   <p>Credit and thanks should be extended to all the church societies of St. John Cantius Parish (except St. Ladislaus Society), especially St. Cyril and Methodius Society, St. Joseph Society, and the cadets of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish for participating. Thanks should also be given all the parishioners, parish priests and guests for their co-operation.</p>
   <p>Peter Bocian,</p>
   <p>Secretary of St. Cyril and Methodius Society</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
