<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-07-22">July 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Polish National Alliance Attacked by Polish Clergy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-07-22">July 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE ATTACKED BY POLISH CLERGY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Vicious attacks on the Polish National Alliance by some Polish clerical newspapers, prove that a handful of wicked individuals, false servants of Christ unworthy of wearing clerical robes or Roman collars, feel that they are losing ground on account of the awakening of the public. The realization that they are isolating themselves from Polish public life, disturbs their mental and moral equilibrium to a point where they are using the tactics employed by people who have nothing in common with ethics, morality, Christian love, or Polish idealism.</p>
   <p>No person with a sane mind and some education, let alone a Pole and especially a priest, whose duty is to teach his flock Christian love as was taught by our Great Master the Lord Christ, would abuse his fellow men the way it is being done by the "reverent" publishers of the clerical newspapers Gazeta Bostonski, Wielkopolanin, and Polonia. These libelous newspapers are so repulsive that even the most reactionary and unscrupulous journalist would be ashamed of them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0166.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>With whom are these blundering cassocked knights fighting? Whom are they slandering and libeling? They are slandering their own fellow men who have grouped under the national colors to spread enlightenment among our people. How degraded the soul of people who attack the good national workers! "By their fruits ye shall know them," say the Scriptures. Their work alone has revealed to our people the true nature of these priests of a false god, and that is why many are turning away from these pharisees, hypocrites and impostors. On the other hand, our people as a rule hold in great respect those priests who are good and patriotic.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance is a lay organization; it does not interfere with clerical organizations. Not being interested in religion at all, it does not meddle in the individual religious activity of a member, provided, of course, that such practice is such as not to interfere with others.</p>
   <p>The priest inside the church and the Polish National Alliance outside of it, have a duty in common, namely, to lead and guide the Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0167.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our clergy will never draw the people to themselves by slander, libel, and attacks on national institutions. The members of the Polish National Alliance are good church members and respect the clergy when they are patriotic and honest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
