<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-20">Apr. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">International Movement of Catholicism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III C (German)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-20">Apr. 20, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">INTERNATIONAL MOVEMENT OF CATHOLICISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The social question or problem is international because it concerns all peoples. The importance of social relations is more evident each day throughout the world.</p>
   <p>An industrialist not desiring to tempt bankruptcy, caters to the every will of his employees. As a human being and a Christian, he has this right. The same applies to every nation individually. However, no matter how hard a government tries to meet the demands of the workers, it cannot attain the goal essential to the masses of workers in our present industrial age.</p>
   <p>The only thing that a nation can do is to start a strong general social reform, a reform that may be adopted unanimously by all other governments.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1183.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This same thought is harbored in the heart of every worker, whose endeavors and desires have taken on an international tenor.</p>
   <p>Their international plotting will not be of any benefit to the people, nor will the international alliance of capitalists evolve anything of value. There is only one institution in the world that can bring about a gradual and firm change in international relations, and this is the Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>The Catholic Church is truly international because it is universal and instituted for all countries, peoples, and times. It has the key to the hearts of all its children the world over; its teachings and writings find their way to millions of followers. No form of government, institution, customs, and habits interferes in its mission for civilization.</p>
   <p>Because of this, it is easy for the Church, through a wise direction of the peoples's minds and actions, to lead its followers to a gradual but <pb facs="5423968_10_1184.jpg" n="3"/>continual and favorable improvement of the unbearable social conditions of modern times.</p>
   <p>Its standard in proceedings and principles is the same as that of Christ, the King of the social order, who in His heavenly teachings left efficacious measures for healing various social weaknesses.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the principles of Christ have been sadly mutilated. Godless liberalism, because of its alleged wisdom, wants to arrange the affairs of the world. As a result, there is chaos in understanding, digression in thought, and injustice and delinquency in actions.</p>
   <p>However, the people, warned today of the terrible future fire of subversion which socialism and anarchism is fanning in their decadent hearts, are turning their eyes in the direction of the Catholic Church and recognizing it pure fatherly guidance.</p>
   <p>The Catholic Church constantly points out blunders, clears up doubtfulness, <pb facs="5423968_10_1185.jpg" n="4"/>confirms the truth, and passes out sound literature intended for the gradual regeneration of society.</p>
   <p>We see a great and definite step in this direction in the profoundly inspired Encyclical of Leo XIII, especially that part of it dealing with the condition of the working class.</p>
   <p>The Encyclical of Leo XIII as concerns the condition of the working class, is a sublime treatment of the universal social question; it is a splendid social program of vast proportions, and it could not have been otherwise.</p>
   <p>The details of so vast a program could not have been adopted because the Pope in this respect would have to set a standard for all branches of activity of each individual nationality and delve into the smallest detail of their social life. But it does include great and lucid principles out of which can be derived practical suggestions and regulations for every situation, for every nationality.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1186.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This Catholic social movement is advantageous to the peacefulness and happiness of the people. It can be seen in operation in our times, for example, at every popular Catholic Congress taking place in America and abroad. The French, Germans, Italians, and Poles, especially the Germans in America, give their own congresses a special manifestation of their faith, including a beautiful demonstration of the close attachment to the Apostolic See, the immovable rock. The social question directed by pure Catholic influence, therefore, flows freely, apparently towards expansion.</p>
   <p>But we Poles in America participate in separate councils, national and Catholic. We argue and abuse ourselves. Everyone, even those who by practice and life injure the Church, proclaims verbally that he respects the Church and its doctrines, but when it come to the question of staging a general Polish Catholic congress, where we as Poles could demonstrate before the eyes of the world the faith of our fathers and our attachment to the Holy See, no one mentions it, no one thinks of it, and perhaps no <pb facs="5423968_10_1187.jpg" n="6"/>one will ever give it any consideration.</p>
   <p>Our feelings, thoughts, and actions spread out to all sides. The Liberty League and pan-pagan congresses hold more interest for us than a Catholic congress. We are losing ourselves in a shroud of trifles of some kind of nationalistic praise, forgetting about a major movement from which flows salvation and temporal praise.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
