<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-07-03">July 3, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Polish League Lays Stone</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-07-03">July 3, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH LEAGUE LAYS STONE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The corner stone of St. Mary's Polish Catholic Church at Hawthorn was laid yesterday, by Archbishop Symon, the Polish legate. He was assisted by a number of priests among whom were Rev. S. Navrodski, from St. Louis, as deacon and Rev. C. Gronkoski of Milwaukee, who acted as assistant deacon. Nine Polish organizations, including two women's societies and 150 girls from the Polish parish school, participated in the celebration.</p>
   <p>Rev. B. Czajkowski, pastor of the church, was the master of ceremonies.</p>
   <p>George Commerford, president of Cicero, a platoon of police and the St. Aloysius Cadet band led the parade through the streets. The St. Casimir court of Foresters, St. George's Roman Catholic society, St. Stanislaus order, St. Mary's Knights, Ladies' Sadality of St. Mary's Knights, St. Anthony's society, the St. Florians, Star Freedom club, the Ladies' Society of Agatha and the Polish parish school formed the procession.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0277.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Archbishop was met by the paraders at Fifty-second avenue and Thirtieth street. Surrounded by the school children dressed in white and bearing bouquets, he was escorted to the rector on Linden street near Thirty-first, where M. Kozlewski, captain of St. Mary's Knights, delivered an address of welcome.</p>
   <p>The Archbishop was introduced by Rev. B. Czajkowski. He blessed the site and the rising edifice. All the ceremonies and services were conducted in the Polish language.</p>
   <p>The new church will be two stories high. It will be constructed of stone and brick and will cost $55,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
