<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-07">Apr. 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Church Societies Meet to Discuss Kosciusko Manifestation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_1009</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-27">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1009.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-07">Apr. 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH CHURCH SOCIETIES MEET TO DISCUSS KOSCIUSKO MANIFESTATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The church societies of St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish held a meeting last night at Bradley Street Hall to discuss the Kosciusko manifestation.</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by J. Tomaszewski, who called on T. Krolik to act as secretary, Then, the names of the societies which had sent their representatives for the first time were registered.</p>
   <p>The following societies from St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish were represented at this meeting: St. Joseph Benevolent Society, St. Valentine Society No. 1, St. Hedwig Society, and St. Michael Archangel Society.</p>
   <p>Also represented were three military societies, namely, Knights of St. Martin, Uhlans, and Guard of the Queen of Poland.</p>
   <p>Besides these, there were also representatives from the following Polish societies:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_1010.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From St. Hedwig Parish: St. Mary of Scapular Society, Second Company of Knights of Krakus, Sacred Heart Society, St. Hedwig Society, and Holy Cross Society.</p>
   <p>From St. John Cantius Parish: St. John Cantius Society, St. Cyril and Methodius Society, and St. Peter and Paul Society.</p>
   <p>The president explained to the participants that every member would be assessed fifteen cents. Then the meeting was adjourned until next Friday, that is, until April 13. Until that date, every society must send in its report stating whether it will take active part in the manifestation.</p>
   <p>Jacob Tomaszewski, president;</p>
   <p>Albert Jendrzejek, cashier;</p>
   <p>Thomas Krolik, secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
