<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-27">Mar. 27, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Commitee Arranging the Polish Catholic Congress Gets Busy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-27">Mar. 27, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">COMMITEE ARRANGING THE POLISH CATHOLIC CONGRESS GETS BUSY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committee selected in Detroit to make arrangements for the Polish Catholic Congress has already started to work.</p>
   <p>We have received a copy of an appeal prepared by this committee and signed by Reverend Deacon Pitass, president, and Mr. Stanislaus Slisz, secretary, both of Buffalo.</p>
   <p>This appeal is addressed to the Polish societies in America, and will be sent to them all, without exception. The appeal explains the necessity for a Polish Catholic Congress in the following words:</p>
   <p>"Evil has grown to such tremendous proportions lately, that something must be done to stop it from spreading further. Disbelief, immorality, and evil conditions are growing worse; perverse persons are creating disturbances in our Polish parishes; societies are being organized to wage war on the Catholic <pb facs="5423968_10_0525.jpg" n="2"/>church; the "Independent Church," a schismatic movement, is raising its ugly head among us. To put it briefly, these conditions are very serious. Shall we remain indifferent? No, to do so would be a crime. We must stand ready to fight and repel the attacks of our enemies, who want to steal our dearest possessions, our Holy Faith, and our national existence. For this purpose a Congress is being called, at which Polish priests, representatives of Polish parishes, and Polish Catholic societies will discuss remedies and the means by which these evils shall be eradicated."</p>
   <p>Further on the appeal gives a synopsis of the motions passed in Detroit. (These have already been published in the Dziennik Chicagoski.) It also states that all societies are being invited to take part in the Polish Catholic Congress.</p>
   <p>No doubt all societies will receive a copy of this invitation, so we will not publish it. We merely wish to mention that answers to this invitation should be addressed to S. Slisz, 227 Lovejoy Street, Buffalo, New York.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0526.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>So the first step has been made. A meeting will probably be held soon, or more correctly a gathering of the committee arranging this Congress. (If we are permitted, we wish to propose that this gathering take place either in Toledo or Cleveland.) At this meeting the committee will make the final arrangements for holding the Congress, and it will decide on: a method of determining the selection of delegates, the date of the Congress, the work to be assigned the various committees.</p>
   <p>Thus the work has started, and it will continue, so as to insure success for this worthy enterprise. We wish them all success!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
