<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-21">Sept. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Consecration of New Church at St. Adalbert's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-09-21">Sept. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CONSECRATION OF NEW CHURCH AT ST. ADALBERT'S PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday St. Adalbert's Parish presented an unusually festive appearance, because it was an unusual day in the history of this district. Early in the morning crowds began to gather in the streets. Here groups of St. Adalbert's parishioners collected and over there a group of people from some other parish gathered to discuss the new church. All houses in the district were decorated. The street was full of Polish flags, festoons, and garlands. St. Adalbert's was celebrating.</p>
   <p>"You can see that there is a good husbandman here. How different this parish looks from ours" said one of the men standing in a group discussing the celebration which was about to begin.</p>
   <p>"It is through the efforts of Reverend Gronkowski that the church was built. Reverend Gronkowski looks after everything, and administers his parish like a good and capable husbandman. Therefore it is clear that on the day of the <pb facs="5423968_10_0119.jpg" n="2"/>consecration of the new church many more people will gather, to show by their presence that they appreciate a good and honorable chaplain."</p>
   <p>Now the societies are arriving in groups. Let us look at those marching dressed in their festive clothes. They are marching under the leadership of the grand marshal, Bernard L. Maciejewski, assisted by adjutants, Mr. John Przeworski, Marion Knutkowski, and Mr. Dubiela. There are four divisions composed of the following: [Translator's note: Here a section of the paper has been torn out and destroyed.]</p>
   <p>As was expected, there was not room enough in the church for all of the people who came. Everyone of course wanted to see the highest church dignitaries and everyone wanted to hear the inspiring words uttered on the occasion of the consecration of the new church. Everyone wanted with all his heart to squeeze in as close as he could. but the church was not large enough to hold all of those who came. Within the church, although it was terribly crowded, order prevailed. A few minutes after 10 A. M. Archbishop Quigley consecrated the new church under <pb facs="5423968_10_0120.jpg" n="3"/>the blessing of St. Adalbert. Then the pontifical mass was celebrated by His Eminence the Apostolic Delegate, Giovanni Bonzano, in the presence of all the church dignitaries and the great crowd of people.</p>
   <p>After the ceremonies in the church, the societies formed with their banners a line which extended from the church to the rectory, making a guard of honor for the clergymen returning to the rectory from the church.</p>
   <p>The people of St. Adalbert's Parish welcomed the various military and civilian organizations with truly old-fashioned Polish hospitality. The faces of all of the participants reflected true contentment and joy. The parishioners of St. Adalbert's were happy, and well they might be. The erection of a church is not the work of one day, but the result of long and hard labor. Yesterday these efforts were rewarded--a magnificent church stood with its tall spires reaching up toward the sky, a church for the glory of God and service to the parishioners of St. Adalbert's. The guest were happy, too, because the happiness of Reverend <pb facs="5423968_10_0121.jpg" n="4"/>Gronkowski's parishioners was their happiness as well.</p>
   <p>Reverend Gronkowski, this exemplary parish priest, experienced great joy no doubt, at having accomplished this great task. His parishioners owe this magnificent church to his skillful and praiseworthy administration. [Translators note: The rest of this article has been destroyed.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
