<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 52,
<date when="1921-10-11">Oct. 11, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Personal Profits from Religion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0044</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0044.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXV, No. 52,
<date when="1921-10-11">Oct. 11, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">PERSONAL PROFITS FROM RELIGION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The people who are trying to take religion away from their fellow men are doing them a great injustice, because they are depriving them of the only consolation and the very existence of life.</p>
   <p>We can easily prove this without referring to religious dogmas or theological truths. We can prove this by simple everyday examples from life.</p>
   <p>In the first place we must take for granted that a thinking man must have some kind of faith; he must have a theory about the beginning of the world, which he can neither comprehend nor investigate. If there is a cause for every understandable incident, then there also must be a cause for the whole universe and everything that we see. There must have been and there must be some power which caused the existence of the universe, and formed the laws controlling the life and death of that universe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0045.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We call this power God, the Creator of all things.</p>
   <p>The desire to know God Who manifests Himself through His works, helps man to learn the laws of life and nature of all creatures. Whoever understands these laws will profit in everyday life and be happy.</p>
   <p>Religion tells us that God is good and just, that He rewards good and punishes evil; that we should love our neighbor as ourselves, that we should do no harm to anyone and finally that God rewards good deeds in this and the next life. The promise about the forgivingness of sins and happiness in life hereafter alone, makes us contented. It removes the fear of death and makes life easier. In other words, the belief in future happiness makes the last days of our life pleasant.</p>
   <p>The belief in what our Christian religion teaches gives to a man some higher ideal and that alone is a great happiness.</p>
   <p>The good deeds alone are a reward for man. Everyone of you must have <pb facs="5423968_10_0046.jpg" n="3"/>experienced a sort of inner satisfaction after every noble deed and felt aversion after harming some one. All great deeds have religious causes. Self-sacrifice produced civilization and keeps it going. If we deprive a man of idealism we will change a happy and contented man into a being who hates himself and others, ready to harm his fellow-man or commit suicide.</p>
   <p>If we take into consideration the happiness of man on earth and if we view from the same point the work of anti-religious elements, we must admit that everyone who opposes religion causes his fellowmen a great harm.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
