<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>,
<date when="1907-05-20">May 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">How Churches Are Built</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0226</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0226.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>,
<date when="1907-05-20">May 20, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">HOW CHURCHES ARE BUILT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago police are looking for Father Vincent Lagan, a well known deceiver and swindler, who having collected $6,000 for the erection of a new church, disappeared with the money, together with Miss Sophia Korda and his viear, Father Boleslaw Baligrodzki, well known amongst the Polonia of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The people have contributed their last cent, donating a sum of $6,000 for the revelry of these soul healers.</p>
   <p>This incident recalls many other swindles of this kind.</p>
   <p>Not so long ago a Catholic pastor of a Polish parish in St. Louis, left for Europe with a woman, and thousands of dollars belonging to the parishioners.</p>
   <p>In Chicago, about four years ago, two very active swindlers were arrested, who were collecting from workers in the Town of Lake, for the purpose of <pb facs="5423968_10_0227.jpg" n="2"/>erecting some kind of church in Galicia. One of them whose name was Stephen, after leaving jail found so much delight in working for the soul and as redeemer of the people, that he became a priest for three whole months.</p>
   <p>No one can forget also the constant collections of Father Pociehowski for various aims.</p>
   <p>The workers of Pittsburg also, well remember the Polish bank that was established by Father Tomaszewski, and can't forget the money they lost in it.</p>
   <p>And so we go on, endlessly, with the poor Polish people being swindled, robbed and kept in the dark as to who swindles or breaks them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
