<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-11">Mar. 11, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Intrigues in St. Casimir Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0568</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0568.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-03-11">Mar. 11, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">INTRIGUES IN ST. CASIMIR PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(We have received the following correspondence with a request that it be published in the Dziennik Chicagoski.)</p>
   <p>From the very beginning perfect order and peace have reigned in our Parish, under the guidance of our pastor, Reverend Albert Furman. However, some people inimical to us have recently been spreading reports to the effect that some of our parishioners are not satisfied with our pastor. To make matters worse, signatures were being solicited for a petition to be sent to the Archbishop attacking our pastor.</p>
   <p>To ascertain how much truth there was in these reports, a group of parishioners called on the pastor and requested him to call a parochial meeting, so that they could find out who was responsible for the reports that discord existed among the parishioners and that it was caused by dissatisfaction with the management of our pastor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0569.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This meeting was held on Sunday, March 1, in the school hall, and the parishioners filled the hall. After the purpose of the meeting was explained, every body was in a state of expectancy and watched to see who the dissatisfied agitators were. But, thank God, not one appeared.</p>
   <p>It was evident that every one of us was heart and soul with the pastor, and to prove it, everybody demanded that the signatures of all those present be affixed to a declaration of confidence, and that the declaration with the signatures be sent to the Archbishop. By this action we hope we have put an end to these scoundrelly intrigues.</p>
   <p>The committee which took care of this matter then called another meeting. This second meeting took place on Wednesday, March 4, on the holiday of our patron saint, St. Casimir. The parishioners appeared at the meeting as one man. A petition affirming our respect and our confidence in the pastor was read in the English and Polish languages, and it was decided unanimously to send the petition to the Archbishop. The following were selected as a committee for <pb facs="5423968_10_0570.jpg" n="3"/>this purpose: Mr. W. J. Pijanowski, Mr. Joseph Zajeski, and Mr. Andrew Belinski. This committee then called on Mr. Joseph Kozlowski, a notary, before whom they swore that everything embodied in the petition was right and just, and that they were authorized by the entire parish to present it to the bishop.</p>
   <p>Finally for the third time this committee called a meeting, which was held on Sunday March 8. At this meeting the committee gave a complete report of their visit to the Archbishop.</p>
   <p>The report is as follows:</p>
   <p>The Archbishop received the committee cordially, and, after accepting the petition and reading it, said:</p>
   <p>"I am happy, my children, that you came to me with this matter, because such committees are rare. Thank God, that you come with praise for your pastor and <pb facs="5423968_10_0571.jpg" n="4"/>not with complaints."</p>
   <p>He assured us that to this day he had not received any bad news about our parish or about our pastor, the Reverend Furman. Finally the Archbishop added: "You did well, my children, that you brought this to my attention; in the future I will know what to do."</p>
   <p>Our Archbishop received the delegation cordially, as our fathers would do; he inquired about many other matters in our parish, and these were thoroughly explained by the committee.</p>
   <p>After talking over various matters of the parish for almost an hour, the committee left the Archbishop's palatial residence, satisfied and happy</p>
   <p>The parishioners gathered at this meeting raised a happy, loud cry of, "Long live Reverend Albert Furman! Long live St. Casimir Parish! May the parishioners always work together in peace and brotherly love!"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0572.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And, undoubtedly, such will be the case.</p>
   <p>We sincerely love and respect our pastor, for he is our loving shepherd. This should satisfy those who would like to disturb the peace and brotherhood in which we live. The agitators' intrigues did not succeed--and we hope they never will.</p>
   <p>John Grzegorzewski, secretary,</p>
   <p>1064 South Albany Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
