<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-17">Jan. 17, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Forty-Hour Devotion in St. John Cantius Parish</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_10_0643</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0643.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-17">Jan. 17, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">FORTY-HOUR DEVOTION IN ST. JOHN CANTIUS PARISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Forty-Hour Devotion was celebrated in St. John Cantius Parish from the fourteenth to the sixteenth of January.</p>
   <p>The services were begun and concluded by Right Reverend Father Simon Kobrzynski, head of the Chicago home of the Resurrectionist Fathers.</p>
   <p>It is worthy of note that very many of the faithful approached the Holy Sacraments. The priests worked in the confessionals from morning till night in order to satisfy the demands of the faithful.</p>
   <p>Many out-of-town priests came over to help the local priests. They deserve the greatest credit for their sincere and conscientious labor, and I wish to thank them most heartily.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_10_0644.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following participated in the services: Father Simon Kobrzynski, C. R. (Resurrection Congregation), offered the Holy Mass on Tuesday morning and concluded services on Thursday; Reverend Francis Gurowski from South Chicago officiated at High Mass on Tuesday, at which Reverend P. Rhode preached the sermon; Reverend H. Truszynski from Holy Trinity Parish preached the sermon Tuesday evening; Reverend John Kruszynski, C. R., celebrated High Mass on Wednesday; Reverend John Obyrtacz preached the sermon Wednesday morning, and Reverend A. Lipinski of Saginaw, Michigan, preached the sermon on Wednesday evening; Reverend John Radziejewski celebrated High Mass on Thursday morning, at which Reverend John Gieburowski, C. R., of Avondale, preached the sermon; Reverend Biela, C. R., of St. Hedwig's, preached the concluding sermon.</p>
   <p>The following priests were also present: Reverend Adolph Nowicki; from South Chicago; Reverend D. Mayer, from St. Paul, Minnesota; Reverend R. Guzowski, from St. Paul; Reverend Vincent Rapacz, C. R., Reverend Eugene Seolaczek, C. R., Reverend Francis Breitkopf, C. R., Reverend Theophil Szypkowski, C. R., Reverend John Barzynski, from St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish, and Reverend <pb facs="5423968_10_0645.jpg" n="3"/>John Piechowski from St. Hedwig Parish.</p>
   <p>The devotional services, attended by so many priests, were grand. The church was continually filled with the faithful. The brotherhoods and the children were present every day to give homage to the All Highest.</p>
   <p>All the ceremonies created a fine impression, and we hope they will bring lasting benefits to the participants.</p>
   <p>We have, mainly, to thank the reverend priests, who so gladly rushed to help us, and to whom I once more wish to extend my sincerest thanks in the name of the Parish.</p>
   <p>Reverend John Kasprzycki, C. R., pastor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
