<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1932-01-25">Jan. 25, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Report 550,000 Jews Being Supported by Chicago Jewish Ccharities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0423</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0423.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1932-01-25">Jan. 25, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT 550,000 JEWS BEING SUPPORTED BY CHICAGO JEWISH CCHARITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 32nd annual meeting of the Chicago Jewish Charities took place yesterday evening at the Standard Club.</p>
   <p>Close to one thousand guests were present to hear the reports about the general sad plight of the city's needy, as well as the terrible situation of the tens of thousand of Jewish families. The attending guests also learned from the reports that the Jewish Charities are in a "tight fix" and have a big deficit this year.</p>
   <p>Together with the hundreds of individuals present, there were also a considerable number of representatives of various organizations. Mr. Leo Wormser was Chairman of the evening. Mr. Sol Klein, acting president, requested the audience to stand up in honor of the memory of the late honorary president, Julius Rosenwald, who for the past thirty years was an executive member of the Jewish Charities. The audience respectfully rose and remained standing for several minutes.</p>
   <p>The speakers of the evening were: Sol Klein, acting president of the Jewish Charities; James H. Becker, treasurer; Samuel Goldsmith, executive <pb facs="5423972_7_0424.jpg" n="2"/>member of the Jewish Charities; and Samuel Insull Jr. who was a guest speaker.</p>
   <p>Treasurer Becker pointed out in his report that the Jewish Charities spent $1,501,727 in 1931. The Charities have a deficit this year amounting to $128,106.11.</p>
   <p>Mr Goldsmith, in his report, told about the statistics of the Illinois Department of Labor, which statistics show that there are 650,000 unemployed in Chicago. That means that 125,000 families are now dependent upon relief. Figuring proportionately, according to the Jewish population of Chicago, 50,000 Jews receive relief from the Jewish Charities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
