<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-04-06">April 6, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Flood Relief Committee Organized, Sexds Out Relief Message.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1711</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1711.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-04-06">April 6, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">FLOOD RELIEF COMMITTEE ORGANIZED, SEXDS OUT RELIEF MESSAGE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To Chicago Jewry:</p>
   <p>The great misfortune, which occurred in the districts around the Ohio River has caused a great loss in property and in human lives, and the result is that thousands of families are left without the necessary means of life. The misfortune is a national one. And the American nation has rendered, and is rendering all possible aid to alleviate the misfortune.</p>
   <p>As Jews, we are highly pleased to see how many of us were the first to respond to the cries of the unfortunate, and among the hundreds of thousands dollars that were raised a great part was contributed by the Jews. It is only natural that the "sons of compassion" should be the first to respond to such a relief cry.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1712.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is also pleasing for us to observe that in this great misfortune the American nation showed that it does not know any difference between man and man. In the distribution of relief there was no difference between Jew and non-Jew.....</p>
   <p>It is the unfortunate case, however, that Jews suffer twice as much. They suffer as people and they suffer as Jews. And when the General Relief Committee tendered assistance to every Jewish family, they could not help them as Jews..</p>
   <p>The Jews suffer as Jews on account of the forthcoming Passover. We can not ask the general committee to provide the unfortunate families with matzo; it isn't reasonable to think that the Red Cross will distribute sacramental wine for the Passover services. Jews can accept from Gentiles neither fish nor meat for the holidays and it remains for the afflicted Jews dwelling on the banks of the Ohio River to go hungry.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1713.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>together with their wives and children, during the week of the Jews' greatest holiday of freedom - Passover.</p>
   <p>The Jews of Dayton, Ohio were the first to apply for relief and the Federation, in behalf of Chicago Jewry, responded as Jews should - "We Will Help."</p>
   <p>In order to help them, as we should, we urge everyone to submit his contribution large or small, as soon as possible. Do not forget that there are only two weeks until Passover. The need is so great and the time is so short. Help immediately!</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1714.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>All contributions should be submitted to the treasurer, Mr. Samuel Phillipson, of the Flood Relief Committee of the Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities, 12th Street and Newberry Avenue, or to the office of the Jewish Courier.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
