<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-20">Apr. 20, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Meditations of the Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-20">Apr. 20, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MEDITATIONS OF THE DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Charities have made up a budget for an average family of six. It comes to one hundred and ten dollars and eighty-five cents a month. It is certainly exact in its attempt to be so. Nevertheless it exhibits but a poor conception of the social and economic problem it considers. It lists a series of expenditures which in their very expression proclaim their ludicrousness, as for instance, rent $18, food $14.35, spending money $4, all on a monthly basis. A social agency should be the last to propose such an impossible program. It is a charity dole, which by no means can provide an independent living standard.</p>
   <p>Baseball, a national American sport, has made its seasonal bow to the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0588.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The English newspapers devote a great deal of space to the pastime, as if it were a major business to American life. So in fact it is with much of the population of this country. We believe, however, one may be even a hundred per cent American, of one remarks that the interest taken in the sport is altogether out of proportion to its value. A healthy body, we have long since well learnt, is as essential as a healthy mind, at least. But baseball does not serve the physical welfare of any of the fans, but only of such as play it, and of those really only the ones such as play it in moderation. We venture to say that few people outside of the youth of this country and that of one sex only take a real active interest in the play. Most of those who attend baseball games or read the progress of different clubs, and the writer of these musings admits his personal weakness in at least the latter respect, get little or nothing out of their interest. Undoubtedly there is some recreational value in the viewing of the game but we think all such value to be a minimum for the time expended on the sport. A recreational value of a much healthier or a higher kind spiritually is attained by an interest in other forms of recreation, <pb facs="5423972_7_0589.jpg" n="3"/>such as the theatre, rowing, hiking, and the like. Perhaps we are mistaken and if there be some extreme Jewish fan among our readers, we hope we may hear from him or her on that score.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
