<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-11">Feb. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Keren Hayesod Is the Only Fund to Build Palestine, Says Dr. Thon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-11">Feb. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">KEREN HAYESOD IS THE ONLY FUND TO BUILD PALESTINE, SAYS DR. THON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Red Room of the Hotel La Salle was crowded yesterday afternoon with Chicago Jews who have contributed to the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization]. In the words of Dr. Joshua Thon, the Keren Hayesod is "the only fund which will build Palestine". The Chicago Jews came to hear a report by the Keren Hayesod officials as to what has become and what will become of all the money that is being raised for the rebuilding of our country. Those who came were not disappointed. On the contrary, they expressed their satisfaction with the collections made and with the disbursement of the money.</p>
   <p>Max Shulman, chairman of the Chicago Keren Hayesod Committee, opened the meeting. Before reading his report, he asked Leonard J. Grossman to read a resolution expressing sorrow at the death of ex-President Wilson.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0505.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Cantor Greenberg chanted the "Prayer for the Dead," after the resolution was read. The audience arose and with bowed heads listened to a brief speech by Max Shulman about Wilson, the friend of the Jews.</p>
   <p>Dr. Joshua Thon was the guest of honor at the meeting. Dr. Thon, who is a senator in the Polish Parliament and a leader of the Polish Jews, came to America in the interests of the Keren Hayesod and of the Jewish schools in Poland. Dr. Thon, in an excellent speech, urged the audience to continue the work for the Keren Hayesod, "which will rebuild the Land of Israel because there is no Land without Israel just as there is no Israel without Land". The speech of the leader of Polish Jewry aroused great enthusiasm among those present.</p>
   <p>Professor Heinrich Levy, director of the National Jewish Library in Palestine, drew a rich and beautiful picture of Jewish life in Palestine, where a healthy Jewish generation is growing, healthy in spirit and in body.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0506.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Shulman then began to read his report, which was brief but meaty and impressive. His report did not leave the slightest doubt in the minds of those who heard him that their contributions to the Keren Hayesod are used for noble purposes and for practical work in Palestine. Shulman reported that $4,300,000 has been collected in cash since the Keren Hayesod was founded, and that sixty-three per cent of that sum came from America. Chicago has contributed the following sums of money:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1921</cell>
     <cell>$ 52,116.62</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1922</cell>
     <cell>113,211.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>1923</cell>
     <cell>152,080.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$317,407.62</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Chicago's bureau also conducted Keren Hayesod campaigns in Minneapolis, St. Paul, Milwaukee, Omaha, and Sioux City.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0507.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The main office of the Keren Hayesod in London has received $4,300,000. Of this amount, the London office spent the following sums of money for the purposes listed below:</p>
   <p>Twenty-three per cent, or $937,297.67 was spent for agricultural purposes. This sum includes the help extended to the halutzim, whom the Keren Hayesod settled on the land.</p>
   <p>Twenty-one per cent, or $799,416.89, was spent on schools and other educational institutions. Hebrew is taught in all those schools; 131 educational institutions are maintained, and 504 teachers instruct 12,456 children.</p>
   <p>Slightly over fourteen per cent, or $529,947.20, went to the Immigration Bureau. This money was used to help 35,000 Jewish immigrants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0508.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>About $294,767.50 has been spent on hospitals and other sanitary aid. The Keren Hayesod now maintains seventeen hospitals. It has given free medical aid to fifty thousand patients.</p>
   <p>The Keren Hayesod also has a Central Mortgage Bank, which helps small businessmen and workers.</p>
   <p>The Rutenberg project is a success, thanks to the Keren Hayesod which has invested a quarter of a million dollars in it.</p>
   <p>The expenses of the Keren Hayesod are the smallest that any organization can possibly have. Only five per cent is spent for administrative purposes, and the remaining ninety-five per cent is spent in Palestine for the above-mentioned purposes.</p>
   <p>Mr. Shulman's report was accepted unanimously and he was thanked warmly for <pb facs="5423972_7_0509.jpg" n="6"/>the clarity of his report.</p>
   <p>Plans for the Keren Hayesod activity for 1924 were discussed after Mr. Shulman finished his report. Chicago's quota is three hundred thousand dollars, which amount those present at the meeting pledged themselves to raise. The 1924 Keren Hayesod campaign will begin on the last day of Passover, April 27, and will last for two weeks.</p>
   <p>Harry A. Lipsky then greeted the meeting in the name of the Zionist organization. Mr. Lipsky is the president of the Middle Western Zionist organization. After his speech, the nominations committee, consisting of Sam Ginsburg, B. Hackner, and B. Sloan, brought in the following nominations for Keren Hayesod officials, all of whom were unanimously elected: Max Shulman, chairman; Rabbi J. L. Gordon, vice-chairman; Rabbi Saul Silber, vice-chairman; Samuel Ginsburg, vice-chairman; Samuel Philipson, treasurer; B. L. Sloan, financial secretary; Barnet Hodes, recording secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0510.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The following were elected to the Board of Directors: Dr. A. J. Agronat, Meyer Abrams, Philip Altshul, M. Ben-Ami, Rabbi A. Cohen, Mrs. J. Eisenstein, Moe B. Levin, Alex Eisenstein, Sam Epstein, Martin Fox, Rabbi Leon Fram, Mrs. L. Gelpspan, I. Halpern, D. Hepner, Rabbi L. Lassen, J. Linenthal, Rabbi B. Margolin, George J. Marrock, Benjamin J. Morris. Dr. George K. Rosenzweig, Mrs. Benjamin Davis, Charles Rubens, B. Ruekberg, M. Stein, Lester Toloff, J. Weil, Leo Behrstok, I. Shor, B. J. Bronstein, L. S. Hubsman, Alex Markles, C. Mishkin, Jacob Siegel, Sam Steiner, Nathan Alexander, Nathan Miller, J. Fox, Dr. Walder, M. A. Henock, H. Kaplitz, Mrs. Bertha Reod, Sam Zelikowitz, A. Krilof, E. Newman, M. Skolnik, Rabbi Philip Lang, Rabbi Felix Mendelson, Harry Morris, Mayer Gitlich, Judge J. Shulman, Paul Risman, Fred Bernstein, Jacob Landon, Jacob J. Arvey, Jacob Levin, Sam L. Antonow, Rabbi Goldman, Benjamin Leitman, Fleishman, Fink, Morris Augustus, Sam Rosenthal, W. Durshlag, M. Golub, M. S. Sloan, Morris Geller, A. R. Mahrv, Joseph Smith, David Gorchakoff, Jack Galant.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0511.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The finance committee is composed of E. Hackner, Emil Braude, and B. A. Antonow.</p>
   <p>The executive committee is composed of B. Bregner, Charles Bierman, Max Konheim, I. A. Lassers, Leonard J. Grossman, T. Fisher, Rabbi H. Harrison, Bernard Horwich, Dr. S. M. Melamed, H. Steinberg, J. Miller, Dr. Jacob Sonderling, M. P. Ginsburg, Sam Dushkin, John Risman, Harry Lipsky, A. S. Roe, Fred Berenson, L. Karogatsky, S. Natenberg, Mandel Shor, Julius Savit, M. Zevin, I. L. Feingold, Dr. Shoerson, and L. Enturner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
