<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-15">Mar. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Special Relief</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0634</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0634.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-15">Mar. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">SPECIAL RELIEF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The heads of the synagogues of Chicago have decided at their last meeting to appeal for the war sufferers in Eastern Europe on the last day of Passover. They did it at the request of Mr. B. Horwich, the chairman of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee, a branch of the Central Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>It is, of course, true that the position of our people in Eastern and Central Europe has not undergone a change for the better during the last two years. In many respects the situation is much worse now than two years ago, and they are surely not yet economically independent. We must continue to help them, to help them substantially to avoid more misery, but the question is how can we do it best; that is to say, how can we raise the necessary sums needed for the continuation of our relief work in Europe. The old cry, Help the War Sufferers, <pb facs="5423972_7_0635.jpg" n="2"/>no longer finds an echo in the heart of the American Jew. He has been giving all these years for the war sufferers, and is simply tired of giving; he is, so to speak, philanthropically exhausted. We do not assert that he cannot give any more, but he is simply tired of giving. He is already [so] accustomed to the cry from the other side of the ocean that it no longer makes an impression. These are the bare facts, and the Central Relief Committee must take these facts into consideration and act accordingly.</p>
   <p>We are almost convinced that if a general relief appeal were to be issued today by the leaders of American Jewry, it would be of little effect, and even a relatively small sum of money, let us say, five million dollars, could not be raised today from the American Jews. But inasmuch as our people over there are still dependent on our help, and inasmuch as we must continue part of our relief work, some new methods of soliciting and collecting monies for relief purposes must be found, and we believe that such methods can be found and that the new methods will induce the average American Jew to continue to give money for relief purposes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0636.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We would advise our relief workers and all those who are interested in the relief work to specify the sort of work they mean to do, and to specify the purpose for which the money to be collected will be used. We have just heard that the Joint Distribution Committee is only caring for fifteen thousand war- and pogrom-orphans in Europe, but there are not less than three hundred thousand all told, and what is to become of the two hundred eighty-five thousand of the war- and pogrom-orphans who are not cared for by the Joint Distribution Committee? Are we going to leave them to their fate? Are we going to let them starve? There are also more than a half-million Jewish refugees in Central Europe, and their fate is as bitter today as it has been a year or two years ago. Some of the European governments have decided to expel them from their countries, and where are they to go? No other country would admit them. It is surely our duty to care for them and to help them as much as we can.</p>
   <p>The Central Relief Committee should concentrate all its efforts on helping these two victims of the war and the pogroms, the orphans and the refugees, and the appeal to be made in the synagogues on the last day of Passover should not be <pb facs="5423972_7_0637.jpg" n="4"/>made for the war sufferers in general, but for the orphans and the refugees. The Jewish public must be told that although the general relief work has actually come to an end, there are still some special cases to be taken care of, and that it is our duty to deal with these cases. We should not ask money for the Jewish war-sufferers in Germany, but we should make it clear in the appeals that the money is to be devoted only to caring for the orphans and the refugees. Let the speakers in the synagogues, whether they be rabbis or laymen, dwell on this point. We hope that by specifying the work to be done by the Central Relief Committee in Europe, the Orthodox Jews in America, although also tired of giving, could be induced to give more. We believe that the new name will do the miracle. The cry should go out, Help the orphans, Help the refugees. Let us not call it relief work at all. Let us call it "Orphan and Refugee Aid". The case of the poor and starving orphans was always dear to the heart of the Jews, and the case of the refugees is also near to his heart. Let us specify the purpose for which the money is to be used; let us forget about general relief or war sufferers, and we will get some money as a result of the appeals. If we were to make the appeal for the war sufferers in general, we would scarcely get anything at this time of the year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
