<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-03-01">Mar. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">New York's Bad </title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0854</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0854.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-03-01">Mar. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEW YORK'S BAD <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As was to be expected, New York Jewry has not responded to the appeal of our relief workers in behalf of our suffering people across the seas. New York's quota is five million dollars. The first onslaught has resulted in pledges and cash amounting only to one and one-half million dollars. This already includes large sums given by the Schiff and other families and all other wealthy and prominent Jews of New York. Compared with the results achieved in Chicago, the New York response makes a very poor showing. The first appeal in Chicago was responded to generously. Chicago Jewry was asked to give one and one-half million dollars, and the response to the first appeal was eleven hundred thousand dollars. The rest was solicited and collected within ten days. If New York had followed the example of Chicago, the response to the first appeal should have resulted in cash and pledges to at least three and one-half million dollars. But now that only one and one-half million dollars have been collected or pledged <pb facs="5423972_7_0855.jpg" n="2"/>within the first week, there is no reason to hope that the balance will be collected within the second week of the drive, and unless the period of the campaign is lengthened considerably, the drive in New York will be a failure, and instead of fourteen million dollars, only about eleven or ten and one-half million dollars will be raised. However, since fourteen million dollars and not eleven million dollars must be raised, it goes without saying that the relief workers will make a great effort to get the balance from the Jews outside of New York.</p>
   <p>New York Jewry could easily have raised not five, but ten million dollars, because the Jewish middle class in New York is numerous and wealthy today, and besides, there are proportionately more rich Jews in New York than there are in Chicago or Philadelphia. The impression prevails that the mass of New York Jewry have not only not responded generously to the appeal of our relief workers in behalf of our suffering people abroad, but they have not responded at all. Only the comparatively small group of Jews in New York have given their relief donations. Whether this indifference is due to a moral lethargy of the mass of <pb facs="5423972_7_0856.jpg" n="3"/>New York Jews or to other causes, has not been determined. We believe that it is more or less due to poor organization. The relief workers in Philadelphia, Chicago, Boston and Pittsburgh are better men and more able men than the relief workers in New York. The assumption that the New York leaders are the embodiment of wisdom is a wrong one. There are (sic) a set of Jewish workers and leaders in the country communities, especially in Chicago, who would do wonders in New York, because they have done wonders in Chicago and elsewhere. A Chicago gentlemen, Mr. Charles Ruben, who is chairman of Zone Number Seven, has put in more work and has shown more results than five other workers in New York, but the New York leaders and workers will not admit their inferiority and would not invite the help of men outside of New York, and this vanity of the New Yorkers is primarily responsible for the poor campaign organization in New York, and thus responsible for the failure of the New York drive. In the end New York will not give one cent more for this drive than Chicago has given, and there are five times as many Jews in New York than (sic) there are in Chicago, and the New Yorkers have no reason to be proud of such a record. We hope that in the future our relief workers will make out different quotas and will not tax <pb facs="5423972_7_0857.jpg" n="4"/>New York with five million dollars.</p>
   <p>New York has never given its quota and has never even collected its pledges. New York has done a great deal of talking and boasting, but no work. The capital of Jewish relief activities is not New York, but Chicago, and we do not see why the headquarters of all Jewish relief activities in America should not be in Chicago. We dare say that as far as distribution of the money is concerned, Chicago would also do a lot better than New York, but New York has the numbers--a million and a half Jews--and most of them are unproductive philanthropically, but they want to be considered the greatest donors and the best leaders, though they are neither.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
