<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-06-01">June 1, 1920</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0226</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0226.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1920-06-01">June 1, 1920</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today the Workmens Circle became the owners of the Douglas Park Auditorium.</p>
   <p>Last Saturday at 6 in the evening, the deal was closed. It took four hours to prepare and sign the legal documents that were turned over to the Labor Lyceum Committee of the Workmens Circle.</p>
   <p>At the negotiations the following were present: The previous owner of the Douglas Park Auditorium, Mr. J. M. Hoyt; Mr. Endzeng of the Central Bond and Mortgage Co., 208 S. La Salle St.; L. Garry, lawyer who represented the seller; Abraham Lidski, lawyer, member of branch 32, who helped put the deal through; Jessie Marks, a lawyer representing the Workmens Circle, member of branch 277, and financial secretary of the City Central Committee of the Workmens Circle. The Building Committee of the Labor Lyceum were also present.</p>
   <p>The dream of possessing a home of their own, a cultural social center, is now a reality. The Douglas Park Auditorium will soon develop into a worker <pb facs="5423972_7_0227.jpg" n="2"/>temple where the whole labor movement will find a home for the economical, political, social, cooperative and cultural activities of Jewish workers of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Starting with one small branch of a few members, the Workmens Circle has grown to an organization of 6,000 branches which are united in one powerful workers organization, with a chain of rings over the land who can put together the largest, most successful, Jewish cooperative enterprise in the world. The Workmens Circle of America has 80,000 members with a treasury of $1,300,000.00. The Workmens Circle is also an organic member of the great growing Socialist movement and helps the Socialist Party, morally and financially. The Workmens Circle helps build the cooperative movement of the workers. The Workmens Circle also helped in the relief work for the war sufferers.</p>
   <p>For information regarding the Workmens Circle, call any of the 53 branches, or the Foward, and ask for the Secretary of the District, Organization Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
