<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-19">Nov. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the Federation and Who Are its Opposers?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article Three)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1647</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1647.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-19">Nov. 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE FEDERATION AND WHO ARE ITS OPPOSERS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article Three)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The writer of this column owes an acknowledgment to the current events editor of the Courier who mentioned the civic workers by their Jewish names pointing out their derivations. The first was the well-known "Ben Ha-Ha" whose field call was "The will to work." We suggest a plan whereby these Ha-Has should organize under that very name using the field refrain as a motto and working for the welfare of those persons who must come to the institutions that are financed by the Federation.</p>
   <p>The gratitude that is due the current events columnist is not merely for the proper names he set for the workers, but also because their <pb facs="5423972_7_1648.jpg" n="2"/>opposers too, have to be given a fitting appellation. It is understood, if one party is called "Ben Ha Ha, the other must be termed "Ben Bog-Bog; if the motto of the first is "The will to work," the other's motto is "Stand Still."</p>
   <p>At first the opposers called themselves the "Has Beens," which certainly was not suitable. Primarily, "Has Been" would involve the trait of being backward. Thus, they were like the geese of Rome whose parents quacked at the proper time. But the Ben Bog Bogs did not even possess this quality. God knows, they are not to blame for becoming heads of their various charitable institutions; on the contrary, they have done everything to show how incompetent they were as civic workers. Secondly "Has Beens" is a horrible name to write or print. Should the printer <pb facs="5423972_7_1649.jpg" n="3"/>decide to omit the H and the N there would be a great turmoil, a great clamor because the truth was told. The name Ben Bog Bog was, therefore, adopted at the right time. The Chicago Jewish community should present the columnist of the Courier with a watch and chain for this suggestion.</p>
   <p>At the time the Ben Ha-Has undertook to finance the institutions, twelve, in all, their total expenses amounted to about $100,000. Establishing this amount as a goal they collected about $120,000. As the money passed from one hand to another, there finally remained only about $16,000. Many schemes were inaugurated to create the deficit. The widows' money was taken; houses were built for which there was no necessity, all because there existed a "building fund" as a source of money for daily expenses. Of all the Chicago Jewish Charitable Institutions, only the burial society, "Gimel Chessid Shell Emis," had enough business for expenses; all others, without exception, had deficits. One did not need <pb facs="5423972_7_1650.jpg" n="4"/>be a prophet to foretell that sooner or later the strings would break.</p>
   <p>The Ben Ha Ha plan was simple. Should the Federation collect the $120,000,it would not go through as many processes; going directly to the institutions. First, there would be enough to finance all the institutions, and secondly, enough money would remain to pay off the debts. Thus, instead of making new mortgages every year, the practice of reducing them would be established.</p>
   <p>This is one of the main principles on which the Bog Bogs could not agree. They, although knowing their personal limitations, believed, however, that being on the board of directors of the Federation, would make them powerful enough to give orders in all the institutions. To them it meant becoming a victor, a gross inquisitor, a sort of Russian official invested with supreme power.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1651.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Ben Ha Has had a very different idea of civic work. They sought no honors, but added their own personalities, popularity and abilities to the movement without meddling in the internal affairs of the individual institutions.</p>
   <p>The Ben Bog-Bogs were determined to use the Federation as a means of lording over everyone, but the Ben Ha Has wished only to serve for the good and welfare of charity through the Federation.</p>
   <p>This principle exacted much hard labor. The Ben Bog Bogs noting that the Ben Ha Has were much stronger and more successful in all their undertakings, sought means of weakening them by splitting their ranks.</p>
   <p>The Ben Bog Bogs, being in the majority on every board of directors, influenced their respective institutions to increase their expenditures. As soon as it was known that an institution was to be financed by the</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1652.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Federation, contracts were signed by superintendents for larger and extravagant sums. The various boards, instead of limiting expenditures voted on new costs running into thousands of dollars, stating: "Never mind, the Federation will pay." Thus, started the spree of wild money spending.</p>
   <p>This brought the cost of Chicago's Jewish Charities to $130,000.</p>
   <p>It is true that there is something to show for the money. There are half-orphans in the orphanage; the schools are first class schools; the Strangers' Haven has been swept clean; the Moimonides Hospital has opened, to the pride and joy of Chicago's Orthodox Jews; the Old Age Home has a new wing; yet, it is also true that the Ben Bog Bogs created the staggering expenditures that the Ben Ha Has were forced to finance.</p>
   <p>Besides, the Ben Bog Bogs have organized to reduce the income of the Federation. We will write about this action in a future article.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
