<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-22">Jan. 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago in Palestine</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-22">Jan. 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO IN PALESTINE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We already have in Palestine a colony called "Balfouria," to perpetuate the name of Balfour, who gave the Zionist organization a Magna Charta in Palestine. It is very likely that within a short time we will have colonies in Palestine which will bear foreign names, names of people and cities that have done something for Palestine. It was, therefore, a very good idea of the leaders of the Chicago Zionists to propose that the Chicago Jews should grant to the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist] the necessary means to establish a colony in Palestine which will be called "Chicago".</p>
   <p>The Keren Hayesod and the National Fund now have sufficient land in Palestine to settle many Halutzim. The valley of Israel is not yet colonized because the Keren Hayesod doesn't have enough money to carry <pb facs="5423972_7_0540.jpg" n="2"/>out its colonization plans. The Keren Hayesod will begin at once to execute those plans if the Chicago Jews give it a substantial sum of money for that purpose. The Keren Hayesod workers of Chicago think that it would be advisable to make an agreement with Dr. Chaim Weizmann that one-half of the Keren Hayesod monies raised in Chicago during this year's campaign should go to the regular budget, and the other half toward the establishment of a Chicago colony.</p>
   <p>We do not believe that this plan can be realized. Chicago is not a small town, it is one of the six great cities of the world. A Chicago colony in Palestine should be a large colony or the nucleus of a large colony, which can later on develop into a large settlement, perhaps a city. The Chicago Jews cannot build a village in Palestine and call it "Chicago," if they are going to build a Chicago colony in Palestine. This will sound like a bad joke. Chicago Jews must build something substantial. They must get ready to build a large colony, for which purpose a great deal of money will be <pb facs="5423972_7_0541.jpg" n="3"/>needed--at least two million dollars.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, propose the following plan: Let the Chicago Jews, through the Chicago Keren Hayesod, pledge themselves to raise the sum of two million dollars during the next four or five years. This sum of money should be spent exclusively for the building of a large colony in Palestine which will be called "Chicago". The Chicago colony should correspond in greatness to the city of Chicago in America, which means that just as Chicago is one of the greatest cities in America, so the Chicago colony in Palestine should be one of the greatest colonies in Palestine. With two million dollars, one can settle at least fifteen hundred Halutzim, which means three or five thousand people.</p>
   <p>Let the other large cities in America do the same thing. Let the Jews of all the large cities in America establish colonies in Palestine, in proportion to the greatness of their cities. The result of this activity <pb facs="5423972_7_0542.jpg" n="4"/>will be that during the next few years, thirty or forty new, large Jewish colonies will spring up in Palestine. This method will make it easier for the Keren Hayesod to raise money for constructive work, and will lay the foundation for a sound, economic Jewish development in Palestine.</p>
   <p>The monies which the Chicago Jews will give to the Keren Hayesod for the establishment of a Chicago colony, should not be a donation to the Halutzim but should represent a sinking fund which will be repaid over a period of years. We believe that during the next fifteen years, there will be raised in America not less than sixty million dollars for the Keren Hayesod, that is to say, four million dollars a year. After the fifteen years have passed, the Keren Hayesod won't have to beg for money. It will be able to withdraw the capital which it invested in Palestine during these fifteen years, and with this capital it will be able to continue building. It will be able to increase its activity after the first few years because each year it will get back a part of its capital through the sinking fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0543.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>There is also a psychological element involved in our proposal. A Chicago Jew does not give as much as he can--he gives as little as he can when he is asked to give money for Palestine. His attitude, however, would be different if one were to approach him with a plea to give money to establish a Chicago colony in Palestine, which will perpetuate the name of Chicago in Palestine. The name of Chicago is dear to him; it is the name of a city where his luck changed for the better, a city which gave him an opportunity to rise in the world. This is an approach of an intimate nature. The Chicago Jew is asked, as it were, to shoot two birds with one stone: to give money to build Palestine, which will mean to give money to perpetuate the name of a city which is near and dear to him. The task of the Keren Hayesod in Chicago will be a hundred times easier if it is able to specify for what purpose the money raised is being used. One must be capable of thinking abstractly in order to give money to a country. One does not have to think abstractly to give money for a colony--everybody can understand that. We believe that money will be given for this purpose even by <pb facs="5423972_7_0544.jpg" n="6"/>those Chicago Jews who care nothing about Zionism.</p>
   <p>A large colony is made up not only of houses and barns, but also of public institutions, religious, social, and so on. Chicago has groups of Jewish men and women who will be willing to build a synagogue, a school, a library, or a clubhouse in the Chicago colony. This will stimulate the work of the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <p>We are going to build a Chicago colony in Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
