<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-14">Mar. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A World Relief Conference Must Be Called</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-14">Mar. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A WORLD RELIEF CONFERENCE MUST BE CALLED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The tragic condition of the Jews in Eastern Europe becomes more and more acute each day. The misery and despair in Poland, Rumania, and Galicia become greater each day, and our duty to the victims of hunger and sword increases proportionately. At the present time, America is contributing the major share of the money being raised at alleviate the want and misery in Eastern Europe. But the American Jews alone cannot carry the entire burden, and the Jewish groups of Europe must participate in the relief work to a greater extent now than ever before. Up until now, the Jewish groups in Europe have not done their duty.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, imperative that the proposed Jewish world relief conference should take place immediately, because only through such a conference will the European Jews be drawn closer to the activities of the relief work and into <pb facs="5423972_7_1179.jpg" n="2"/>participation in the reconstruction work.</p>
   <p>The Jews in America, who are willing to co-operate with the Jews in Europe, are greatly interested in the World Relief Conference, and today's relief conference in Chicago must raise its voice in favor of the immediate calling of a World Relief Conference. The New York relief leaders will be unable to ignore the voices of the relief representatives from seven states.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
