<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-22">June 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Beginning of Constructive Relief</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary of Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-22">June 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE BEGINNING OF CONSTRUCTIVE RELIEF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary of Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The various representatives of the American Jewish Relief Organization, Mr. Bilicoff of New York, Mr. B. Horwich of Chicago, and probably Mr. Bogin, who spent several months in Europe investigating relief work, will soon return.</p>
   <p>Each will, of course, report what he saw and heard. Naturally, it will not be joyful news. We already know what they have to tell us--the same old tragic story. The entire Jewish population of Eastern Europe is subjected to suffering, hunger, and death. Cemeteries increase day by day in Poland, Russia, and Rumania. Only the work of grave digging goes on.</p>
   <p>Had war continued another year or two, the entire ghetto of Eastern Europe would be one great cemetery. Luckily, this is not the case, for in a few days there will be peace throughout the world. We are not immediately concerned with whether this peace is good or not, but rather [with the fact] that now we <pb facs="5423972_7_1318.jpg" n="2"/>shall be in communication with our brothers in Eastern Europe.</p>
   <p>With the seas and the roads of transportation again open, we can assuage their hunger. American Jews will be able to send ships carrying food and clothing to our brothers and sisters across the sea. This in itself is no solution since it does not secure their future which at present looks very dark. But at least we can save them from starvation.</p>
   <p>This requires immediate action, after which we must turn to the much discussed question of constructive relief.</p>
   <p>The thousands of towns and villages ruined by the War and by pogroms must be rebuilt with our aid. Until such time as Palestine possesses a great Jewish settlement, our task will be to uphold Eastern European Judaism, the religions, spiritual, and moral reservoir of our people.</p>
   <p>For this purpose we need, not tens, but hundreds of millions of dollars. Under no circumstances can we permit Eastern European Judaism to disappear, for emigration may lead to one of the worst catastrophes imaginable.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1319.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The solution of both the immediate and the constructive relief problems depends upon us American Jews opening wide our purses and giving five or ten times as much as we have already contributed. For the past several months, our relief organizations have sent about seven million dollars to the needy countries. This sum is but "a drop in the bucket". For immediate aid alone, we need at least fifty million dollars. Even this may be insufficient, for the Joint Relief Committee can send no money to Poland and Russia due to lack of funds in its treasury. Therefore, we must not only go on with the old work, but must use all our energies to collect money for the war victims; then, after having learned to give and think in greater amounts, we can take up the problem of constructive relief.</p>
   <p>It is possible that the problem of constructive relief will be solved by other financial methods than that used for immediate relief, i. e., through the National Loan or an International Loan guaranteed by rich Jews throughout the world. But one thing is certain, in either case: we must deal with huge sums of money. It is time to prepare the public so that, at the psychological moment, it will open its pockets.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1320.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We now propose a conference of all relief organizations in the country to formulate plans for the new relief program. The sooner such a congress convenes, the better it will be for all concerned. All Judaism must be prepared to assist in the struggle for existence of our people in Eastern Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
