<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-28">Feb. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Weizmann Is Coming</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0665</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0665.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-28">Feb. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">DR. WEIZMANN IS COMING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization] has officially announced that Dr. Chaim Weizmann, president of the World Zionist Organization and representative of the Jewish Bureau of the English Mandate over Palestine, will arrive in Chicago on April 15. Jews who have a well-developed sense of duty understand the significance of this announcement. Dr. Weizmann is not coming from such a distance (3,000 miles) to amuse us or to tell us of his latest experiments in chemical research [Dr. Weizmann is a chemist], but rather, he comes to remind us of our duties toward Palestine.</p>
   <p>Dr. Weizmann, who is today the recognized political leader of the Jewish people and bears the greatest responsibility for Palestine, has a right to ask: What have you Chicago Jews done for the Keren Hayesod in the <pb facs="5423972_7_0666.jpg" n="2"/>course of the past twelve months, and what do you intend to do in the future? Willingly or unwillingly, we shall have to answer that question. We cannot, under any circumstances, evade our duty because conditions make it imperative that we fulfill our obligation. If Jewish conditions were today normal, i. e., if the whole Eastern European Jewry were not as good as economically wiped out, we would then be able to say: Let the European Jews give, and if they don't give, then we'll come to the rescue.</p>
   <p>At present, we cannot use that excuse because they [Eastern European Jews] are completely impoverished and if we do not help now in the building up of Palestine, it is true that the world will not perish but the Jewish people will because the majority of our people live in countries that promise no future for the Jews.</p>
   <p>Seventeen million people cannot live forever in pogrom-ridden areas and cannot forever be dependent upon charity and cannot forever live in horror and fear.....We must not allow a feeling of despair to overwhelm <pb facs="5423972_7_0667.jpg" n="3"/>the Jewish masses. Millions of Jews in Eastern Europe are now living on hope alone. Take away their hope and they will collapse morally and physically.</p>
   <p>We cannot shirk our duty. We must help build Palestine and we must strengthen the hand of our leader. In our name, he assured the Great Powers that we would rebuild Palestine if we were only given the opportunity to do so. Morally, we have not sunk to such depths that we should retreat like cowards and withhold from our leader the aid which should be given him, and which he has a right to expect from us.</p>
   <p>Dr. Weizmann, the great Zionist leader, will arrive in Chicago on April 15. Are we prepared to receive him as he deserves, as his mission merits?</p>
   <p>If we have any self-respect, if in our soul there still remains a spark of Judaism, and if our Jewish hearts have not yet become petrified, we will not only give our great Zionist leader an enthusiastic reception, but we <pb facs="5423972_7_0668.jpg" n="4"/>will, by our action, also convince him that we stand solidly behind him, and that we will do everything to help him bear the great responsibility which he has assumed.</p>
   <p>Dr. Weizmann will arrive in Chicago on April 15. Let every Jew in Chicago do his duty. Let every Jewish organization in Chicago do its duty, because on the performance of these duties rest not only the prestige, but also the existence of our people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
