<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>, Vol. 37,
wk. of <date when="1909-07-03">July 3, 1909</date>. Page 621-622.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>, Vol. 37,
wk. of <date when="1909-07-03">July 3, 1909</date>. Page 621-622.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Summer outing camp and convalescent home for the Jewish children of the congested district of Chicago will be opened about July 15 by the Chicago Section of the Council of Jewish Women. It will be located at the village of Western Springs, near Hinsdale.</p>
   <p>A three-acre tract, with a large house has already been purchased and the work of remodeling and equipping the property will commence at once. The institution will be owned and managed by a separate corporation to be known as the Summer Outing and convalescent Home, Chicago Section, Council of Jewish Women.</p>
   <p>A rticles of incorporation were issued on June 19 by the Secretary of State. Named as the incorporation were Mesdames Moses Weinberg, Israel Cowen, Hugo Eppstein, Henry Solomon and Martin Barbe.</p>
   <p>Mrs. M.A. Weinberg, president of the Summer Work Committee, stated that the summer outing and the convalescent home will be two separate and distinct branches of the work. During the summer months the plan is to give different groups of poor Jewish children, who are sweltering in the heat and dirt of Chicago's congested district, a few days of fresh air and sunshine in the country. The house <pb facs="5423972_7_0335.jpg" n="2"/>is large enough to accommodate about 30 children at one time. During the winter the building will be used as a convalescent home with a staff of competent doctors and nurses to look after the patients. $6,000 was paid for the property as it now stands. More money will be spent to fit up the home and lay out the gardens.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Martin Barbe is the chairman, Mrs. Herman Landauer, the treasurer and Mrs. I.J. Reis, the secretary. Among the women interested are Mrs. Charles Haas, Mrs. Henry Hart, Mrs. Albert Loeb, Miss Julia Felsenthal and Mrs. Julius Kuh.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
