<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-10-18">October 18, 1911</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1911-10-18">October 18, 1911</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Hebrew Institute opens the new winter season with a great and rich program of Jewish activities.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Hebrew Institute is without a doubt one of the most useful Institutions in Chicago Jewry. It takes this method of notifying the Jewish public of the opening of the 7th annual winter season.</p>
   <p>According to Dr. Joseph Pidot, the superintendent of the Hebrew Institute, who was interviewed by a Courier reporter, the coming winter season will surpass all previous years. The Hebrew Institute is now the main spiritual center in Chicago, not only for the immigrants, but also for Americanized-Jews. They all find a certain interest in the Institute. From day to day the Institute is drawing out the enthusiasm of the Jewish public. Great preparations are being made by the different committees and with Dr. Pidot at the head, it surely looks like success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0313.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Institute officers have arranged for a series of lectures. The lecturers selected are people of great talent, personality, prominence, and International reputation. Among these are Miss Jane Adams of Hull House, W. M. French of the Chicago Art Institute, N. I. Rubins, Dr. Yaros, Professors of Universities, etc. They will speak on the subjects of Political Economy,Sociology, Science, Literature and Knowledge in general. The lectures will certainly be interesting and instructive. Price of admission 10¢. The time and place of meeting will be announced later.</p>
   <p>The Institute has arranged for an orchestra of boys and girls, who are skilled in different kinds of musical instruments. Mr. Alexander Zshokowsky, the well known violinist, will have full charge of the orchestra. All who are interested in orchestral music may make application for entry, at once, at the office of the Institute.</p>
   <p>The dancing school of the Hebrew Institute will be ready for new applications on the 21st.</p>
   <p>The Civic Bureau will have classes, especially for new immigrants, to teach them <pb facs="5423972_7_0314.jpg" n="3"/>how to become American citizens. Every immigrant no doubt understands the importance of citizenship, hence you are urged not to neglect this and to take advantage of this privilege.</p>
   <p>The people's concerts will start again next Sunday, October 29th. Last year these concerts drew large crowds, and this season, Dr. Pidot assures the public of much more interesting musical programs. With the presence of the well known and beloved violinist, Mr. Alexander Zshokowsky and the noted Thomas orchestra, we see no reason not to expect great crowds of music lovers.</p>
   <p>From time to time, we will keep you informed of the Hebrew Institute activities. At the present time we urge you to visit our Institution, and we will take great pleasure in showing you all particulars in the different departments.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
