<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-05">Apr. 5, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Frame the Yizkor in Charity, Say Chicago Rabbis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-05">Apr. 5, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FRAME THE YIZKOR IN CHARITY, SAY CHICAGO RABBIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Chicago Jews! We never thought that we would have to approach our fellow Jews, at this time, with the ancient and mournful text of the Lamentations of Jeremiah. We had all hoped that the misfortunes and woes of our brethren in the European valley of sorrow would be over by now.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, however, the stream of tears still flows. The cries of the Jewish people are still heard. In the Jewish world, the heart-breaking plea for help continues. The cries of those who are to perish from the sword and from hunger are heard! Oh, Lord of the universe, when will there come an end to these troubles?</p>
   <p>Brethren of Israel! Everyone of you is familiar to some extent with the conditions of the Jews abroad, through the private letters that you receive from relatives. It is also true that many of you support your relatives.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We envy you because you know only of the bitter conditions of your own relatives. We, however, receive a multitude of letters, in which pain and suffering are described by Jews from all parts of the world, and we hear one cry: "Jews of America! We have no relatives in America, but we are, nevertheless, Jews. Have mercy upon us. Appease our hunger; assuage our pain!"</p>
   <p>Friends! We ask that you give heed to these despairing cries from those victims of misfortune.</p>
   <p>Thousands of widows, hundreds of thousands of orphans, cripples, infirm, aged, sick, and those frustrated by despair and torture, can see only a dark future ahead of them. There is no ray of hope; only one spark of expectation sometimes penetrates the darkness--and that is, relief from America.</p>
   <p>Jews of Chicago! You should not and must not lock your hearts and close <pb facs="5423972_7_0613.jpg" n="3"/>your hands.....As long as many hands are outstretched toward you, and as long as many eyes are directed at you, you must not close the gates of compassion. Be merciful!</p>
   <p>On the last day of Passover, before Yizkor [memorial services], appeals will be made in every synagogue of Chicago for the purpose of raising money to save the refugees in various countries, to aid the Ukrainian orphans, and to make possible the existence of various institutions to which the soul of our nation is inextricably bound.</p>
   <p>In that sacred moment, when we pray for peace for the souls of our parents, as well as for the souls of our martyrs, let us frame Yizkor in charity, and thereby add consolation to the souls of the dead. In the name of charity, the Almighty will keep our families united, and will protect all of Israel.</p>
   <p>The United Rabbinate</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
