<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-14">Oct. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Preparations for the Big Drive</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0988</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0988.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-14">Oct. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARATIONS FOR THE BIG DRIVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The preparations for the big relief drive--this year fourteen million dollars must be collected--have already begun. In all heavily populated Jewish centers in America the relief workers are already busy with the organization of the machinery for the drive, teams, publicity, canvassers, etc. The representatives of the American Jewish Relief Committee are particularly busy with the great preparations for the drive, because without their initiative, energy and work, the National Relief Conference would not have taken place, and they are, naturally, interested that the undertaking should be successful.</p>
   <p>We do not doubt that the drive will be successful but we believe that this year we will have to put in greater effort than we did last year in order to reach our goal. The news of the preparations for the campaign for <pb facs="5423972_7_0989.jpg" n="2"/>fourteen million dollars came unexpectedly, and because the drive was unexpected many local relief workers were busily engaged in doing local relief work. In Chicago, since we did not anticipate the relief drive, we were preparing for a big campaign in behalf of the Mount Sinai Kosher (sic) Hospital. In Philadelphia, Boston and Pittsburgh the news about this year's relief campaign surprised many local workers and disarranged their plans for local work.</p>
   <p>Although every local social worker understands that relief for the millions of hungry, lonely and worn-out Jews in Eastern Europe is of much greater importance than local work and local charities, just the same there is some ill feeling between the local charity workers and the relief workers. Naturally, this ill feeling is not due to any personal reason, because the conflict in interests is not between various personalities but between two kinds of charity--local charity in America as opposed to relief for millions of Jews abroad. This ill feeling exists and it is the task of all the relief workers to do everything possible to overcome it, because if the relief drive <pb facs="5423972_7_0990.jpg" n="3"/>for fourteen million dollars is to be a success, it can only be possible when all the Jewish forces participate actively in this drive.</p>
   <p>Even with the participation of all the forces, the work this year will be much more difficult than it was last year because the economic situation this year is not as good as it was last year. It is, therefore, twice as necessary that unity should rule within our ranks and that we should all work for the great task--the raising of fourteen million dollars for relief.</p>
   <p>One of the most essential tasks in preparation for the drive is to create harmony between the local charity interests and the relief interests. The relief workers should confer with the local charity workers in order to come to some understanding with them. Everything must be done to set aside the ill feeling now existing between one group and the other. We believe that this ill feeling can be set aside, because every Jew in America realizes that the relief work for millions of Jews is of greater importance than the local charity work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0991.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The leaders of the relief work in Chicago, Mr. Julius Rosenwald, Mr. A. D. Becker, Major Becker, Mr. Deutch and others should not forget this preparatory work. It might be well worthwhile to call a conference of all the various groups of workers in the city, particularly the group that is so interested in the Jewish Hospital (which, surely, is a needed institution), and to talk over all the questions that are connected with the drive. Such a conference could create the unity of forces necessary for the success of the great undertaking.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
