<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-01-21">Jan. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Jews Are Opening Their Homes to the Refugees.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-01-21">Jan. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">JEWS ARE OPENING THEIR HOMES TO THE REFUGEES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Lipsky's appeal, which was published in yesterday's Courier, made a great impression on the Jews of Chicago. Every Jewish individual in Chicago, who has become familiar with the true picture of the Russian Jewish refugees who escaped the Russian Gehenna, should show his brotherly love. It is not expected of you Jews of Chicago, that you donate anything to these unfortunate refugees, for they are not of the mendicant kind. They are sons of wealthy parentage, and most of them are professional people. Home for them for a certain period of time, until suitable positions can be obtained for them, will be highly appreciated.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1525.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Jewish public immediately responded to Mr. Lipsky's appeal and Mr. Simon, the superintendent of the Hebrew Institute, has already received the names of 20 prominent Jewish citizens, who are ready to open their homes to these young Jewish refugees, who escaped from the Russian inferno and have come here to a land of freedom. Additional applications can be made at the office of Mr. Simon, which will be open all day today. Those who live too far from the office may phone Mr. Simon, Haymarket 6400, and a suitable guest will be assigned to you, according to your means, etc.</p>
   <p>Mr. Simon, before he sends out an exiled refugee to a home, is quite careful in the selection of the home. He sees that the home is suitable, so that the newcomer may feel at home in his new home, and be comfortable. An additional number of these immigrants is expected to arrive in Chicago in <pb facs="5423972_7_1526.jpg" n="3"/>the next few days, and we hope, that many more of our Jewish brethren will respond to this call for the worthy cause of receiving these intelligent young Jewish men who escaped from the Russian Gehenna. A number of good homes for these war refugees have already been secured. Employment has also been looked after for them and many of them are already at work.</p>
   <p>All refugees who arrived here in the city recently may present themselves at any time to Mr. Phillip Seaman at the Hebrew Institute, Taylor and Lyttle Streets, and a suitable home and employment will be secured immediately.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
