<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-02">Nov. 2, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Heard and Seen.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1677</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1677.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-02">Nov. 2, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">HEARD AND SEEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Federation of Orthodox Jewish Charities has come to build, not to destroy, to improve not to deface, to unite, not to scatter, and to support, not to neglect.</p>
   <p>As proof we point to the performances in the ten months of the Federation's existence. Truly sincere and honest people consider good deeds not only a debt which must be cared for but also a heartfelt responsibility, and knowing this, are very enthusiastic about such an organization. They know that a good future for the Federation means a good future for the Chicago Jewish community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1678.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not only those that are closest to the internal activities of the Federation deem this to be true, but, also the great masses feel thus, the 6,000 subscribers. A year ago, before the existence of the Federation, individual Orthodox Jewish Institutions had barely 2,000 members, all told, but now, under the Federation the 2,000 have grown to 6,000 within a year. This in itself shows which way the wind blows, in which way the great masses prefer to support the Federation.</p>
   <p>The Federation had many foes. We underline the word had, although we know well enough that these same foes are still with her, wearing the mask of friendship, claiming to be the original Federationists. The true friends are the masses of people who are in sympathy with the Federation, and who so overshadow the opposition that they must bow their heads before them, knowing that sooner or later the Federation will do away with their blackmailing and evil methods, even to the point of excluding them from the honest and decent communities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1679.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Behind their masks of friendship, as patriots of the Federation that is so dear to their hearts, these people place the blame for every error at the doors of the supervising officials. They are not even original, adhering to ancient ways and methods. They realize that the establishment of a strong constitution whose main principle is "One for all and all for one," will not furnish honorary positions for "do-nothings" or enrich a person just because he is orthodox.</p>
   <p>These enemies knew that the building of a Federation would do away with the old methods of receiving and disposing of funds without accounting for them. It would ruin their "business." Therefore their attempts to do away with such an institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1680.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They have associated themselves with all those who live off the people, who go from house to house worm their way in, and live on the bounty of a generous host, for the sake of charity; thus taking advantage of the lack of system and order. And now they have all joined to condemn the Federation.</p>
   <p>First they criticised the Federation and its Constitution, but to no avail. Now they point out the slightest faults to prove the undesirability of this institution.</p>
   <p>Again this was of no avail. The great Jewish masses felt its necessity. Then came a new howl: "The Federation is sound and good but the officials at its head are incompetent." It truly is hard to convince a public that such an accusation is false or why some men are natural leaders who are able and active in every movement. But these men did not need to convince the people. After many years of experience they have learned that every new undertaking has its enemies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1681.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>As the Federation grows in strength, these foes will one by one disappear. The good work of the officials will speak for them and pave the way, to improving the unity and support of the various institutions. All Judaism will honor and respect its laws and activities, and be proud to stand with its leaders....</p>
   <p>Ahlef.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
