<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-03-27">Mar. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">All Institutions Declare Confidence in the Federation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1557</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1557.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-03-27">Mar. 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ALL INSTITUTIONS DECLARE CONFIDENCE IN THE FEDERATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities must go on and fulfill its sacred duties for which it was founded. So it was determined last night at a regular assembly of the directors of all institutions connected with the federation, including the directors of the federation, at the Hebrew Institute.</p>
   <p>Mr. James Davis was chairman. B. Hurwitz, A. Libsen - and Rabbi Sol Silver - addressed the audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1558.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Rabbi Silver's remarks, straight from the heart, brought forth great enthusiasm, with his appeal to the directors for the unity of the federation and urged the people not to stand aside, but stay united and make the Chicago Orthodox Charities powerful.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Silver's successful speech proved effective and the assembly later answered the Rabbi's appeal by approving the resolutions he brought forth, unanimously.</p>
   <p>They are as follows:- 1. The presidents and directors of institutions connected with the federation, determined that the Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities must go on.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1559.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>2. Each of the institutions will arrange through its directors to fill the treasury of the federation, by subscriptions so that there will be sufficient money for all member institutions.</p>
   <p>3. Each institution expresses its fullest confidence in the federation's good work and gives full power to the directors to deal as their conscience dictates for the welfare of the federation, and each institution will use every opportunity to help the federation in its work.</p>
   <p>4. A committee of all the presidents of the institutions connected with the federation, shall be appointed, for the purpose of helping to carry through all conclusions reached by the federation.</p>
   <p>5. The presidents and directors of all the institutions express their condemnation of irresponsible people who spread false accusations against the federation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1560.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The meeting was closed in harmony, and it was noticed that every director present went home with new power and courage for energetic work to raise the necessary funds for the federation to continue its noble work in keeping up all orthodox institutions in a proper manner as fit for such a Jewish community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
