<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929">1929</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929">1929</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are indeed interested in all of the by-products of camping. If, in camps conducted by Jewish agencies such as ours, we can also feel that the summer camps have Jewish assets, it makes the work even more significant. Tens of thousands of Jewish boys and girls left the cities and towns during the hot summer months last year for various camps. The movement has grown so tremendously among Jewish institutions that there is now hardly any such institutions that are operating in fairly large communities where there is not included in the general program an outdoor camping program.</p>
   <p>Jewish educators are beginning to realize great possibilities that camp life holds for the directing Jewish interests for the children and deepening them. Many camps include in their program an intensive Jewish atmosphere and are providing not only Kosher food, but also special services on the Sabbath, classes for Jewish subjects, and entertainments of a Jewish nature. The opportunities for positive instruction are rather limited <pb facs="5423972_7_0155.jpg" n="2"/>since the main objective is to offer physical comfort and sport life that will tend to make children stronger, sturdier, and more fit for the work they are expected to perform during the Winter months. If, however, the positive Jewish tone is given to the activities and the leaders are actuated by the Jewish ideals and are inspired with the Jewish consciousness, much can be done in an indirect way toward creating a Jewish atmosphere in a camp and toward inspiring the children with a love and a devotion to the Jewish values and hopes. Because the children are constantly under the supervision of their counsellors, the opportunities for implanting in them high ideals of character, of Jewishness are even more plentiful than they are in the home, and more fruitful positive results because of the expert guidance of those who are in most cases not only especially trained for the work, but have a keen interest in its value. It is encouraging to see that some national bodies that are interested in education are realizing the important work that may be accomplished <pb facs="5423972_7_0156.jpg" n="3"/>in the camps and are devoting themselves to assisting camp directors in working out programs of work that should result in introducing a stronger Jewish spirit. The camp presents a wonderful opportunity in American Jewish life which must not be neglected. The influence exerted on the minds of young people in such camps often lasts for life, and it is hoped that this may become, in the course of time, an added source of strength and vitality for Jewish development in this country.</p>
   <p>In our own instance, we have cooperated with the Bureau of Jewish Education, and for a number of Summers have had in charge of our specifically Jewish activities, a counsellor who makes up a part of the staff of the Bureau of Jewish Education.</p>
   <p>The following are a few of the figures in connection with Camp Chi: 383 girls under sixteen years of age for a period of two weeks each. There was one girl under sixteen who was there for the whole summer, and two <pb facs="5423972_7_0157.jpg" n="4"/>under sixteen who were there one month each. There were 182 over sixteen of whom 107 were regulars and stayed for two weeks, and seventy-five who were there as extras, remaining a shorter period, or a total of 568 for the summer. In addition to this number, there were six girls' places that were taken by girls who stayed extra time, and four girls who were at camp prior to camp opening. There were in all five groups. The fifth group consisted mostly of High School girls who attended Summer school and it was amazing to observe how splendidly they responded to the camp routine. These girls found the two weeks at camp a real Godsend because of the fact that they were not only busy with their school work during the entire year, but included Summer work at school as well. The physical condition at camp, in spite of the lack of rain, was in every way splendid. The cabins and the washrooms were at all times immaculate. The girls prided themselves on the making of their beds.</p>
   <p>The following additions to the camp equipment were made: New tables in the dining room, making it cheerful and colorful, a new cabin for week-end <pb facs="5423972_7_0158.jpg" n="5"/>girls, and a library and nature study hall, which was made possible through a gift of sisters of Simon W. and S. J. T. Straus in honor of their sixtieth and fiftieth birthday anniversaries respectively. The week-end cabin was made possible by gift from Mrs. Walter I. Schiff, Mrs. Arthur J. Baldauf and Mrs. Ernest Greenbaum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
