<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1917-12-27">December 27, 1917</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1440</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1440.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1917-12-27">December 27, 1917</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great conference of the Peoples Relief, to organize a gigantic campaign among the Jewish working masses for the Jewish war victims, was a great success last night. The conference was opened in the West Side Auditorium. Dr. Hyman Cohen was chairman. Seventy-seven organizations were represented through one hundred and fifty-four delegates. There were delegates from large trade unions. The Workmen's Circle Branches, the Socialists branches, the Poale Zion and the Progressive and Peoples organizations.</p>
   <p>The principal speaker of the conference were B. Sugarman, manager of the Peoples Relief, who came from New York especially for this purpose. The conference determined, at its first session, to raise the sum of one hundred thousand dollars, in a period of six months, through an active and energetic campaign.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1441.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was determined to appeal to all workers to contribute one day's pay for the war victims and to demand from the business men that they give ten percent of their sales of a certain day.</p>
   <p>It was also decided that each organization should raise a certain sum of money. A larger campaign committee was appointed so as to carry on a vigorous campaign and to raise one hundred thousand dollars in six months.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
