<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-03">Feb. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">It All Depends Upon You</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-02-03">Feb. 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IT ALL DEPENDS UPON YOU</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The leaders of the Keren Hayesod work in America have every reason to be optimistic as far as the results of the Keren Hayesod movement in the minor communities are concerned. The minor communities always respond nobly and generously to every appeal made to them in behalf of our people and its major communities and especially such large communities as New York and Chicago, when neither the classes nor the masses can easily be reached, that make the work of the Keren Hayesod very difficult. Even relief workers complain about the attitude of the major Jewish communities toward our relief enterprises. Of course Chicago has given more than its quota for relief during the last relief campaign, but we should be sincere and honest enough to admit that this tremendous success of relief work in Chicago is largely due to the philanthropic genius of Mr. Julius Rosenwald. He is <pb facs="5423972_7_0891.jpg" n="2"/>just forcing his powerful philanthropic personality upon the community. In other large Jewish communities in the States where there are no Rosenwalds to inspire the masses and the classes the relief campaigns are not as successful as they are in Chicago, and New York is by no means an inspiring example as far as relief work is concerned. New York is supposed to give some five million dollars for relief and the leaders of the relief work will be satisfied if New York will give three million dollars in cash.</p>
   <p>Now, it is generally admitted that while our relief campaigns are general Jewish enterprises, our Keren Hayesod campaigns are somewhat different in nature. While every Jew in America is interested in relief work and is greatly moved by the sufferings of our people across the seas, not every Jew in America is interested in the Keren Hayesod movement and a great many of our people here, especially the radicals from left and right are opposed to the movement. The Keren Hayesod leaders are therefore confronted with a difficult and complicated task. They have to raise as much money as the leaders of relief work, but their clientelle is not of the same size and <pb facs="5423972_7_0892.jpg" n="3"/>they cannot appeal to as many people as relief workers can, and they have therefore to rely on the idealism and devotion of those interested in the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <p>It is said that Chicago has secured the success of the relief campaign in the States. One must also admit that Chicago can and must secure the success of the Keren Hayesod campaign in America. What the minor communities are doing in regard to the Keren Hayesod matters little, because they cannot raise large sums, but what Chicago is doing with regard to the Keren Hayesod means a whole lot. If Chicago will do its share, New York will have to do its share too, and needless to say that Chicago will determine the fate of the Keren Hayesod movement throughout the Middle West. Considering the conditions as they are in Chicago we are by no means too optimistic as to the outcome of the Keren Hayesod campaign in New York, for the movement is still lacking in a central figure, able to inspire the masses and the classes, and unless everyone interested in the Keren Hayesod intensifies his activity and makes great sacrifices in both time and money, the Keren Hayesod campaign <pb facs="5423972_7_0893.jpg" n="4"/>in Chicago cannot be much of a success, and if it should not be a success in Chicago, it will not be much of a success in the other cities in the Middle West either. In short, the success of the Keren Hayesod campaign in Chicago and in the Middle West depends on you, and on you only. It depends on your zeal, on your devotion and on your energy.</p>
   <p>In a month or so, Mr. Nahum Sokolow, the head of the second Zionist delegation will arrive in Chicago to lead the Keren Hayesod campaign. Mr. Sokolow will not come to you to be honored by you or to be praised by you, but to get your contribution to the Keren Hayesod and also to get your co-operation, interest and participation in the work. If you are a serious minded Jew, if you know what is at stake, if you know that Chicago can make the Keren Hayesod work in America a failure or a success, and if you know that you can contribute either to the failure or to the success of this great enterprise, you will surely try your best to do not only your duty, but more than your duty. Accomplishments of Chicago Jewry in the field of Keren Hayesod work has been poor in the recent past. A minor community like <pb facs="5423972_7_0894.jpg" n="5"/>Milwaukee has given much more money in cash for the Keren Hayesod than has Chicago, the second largest Jewish community in the world. Chicago Jewry has no reason to be proud of its achievements for the Keren Hayesod, and if it is only anxious to be on par with other communities, it has to make some serious efforts to raise ten times as much money for the Keren Hayesod as it has been raising during the last seven months. We know that this is not an easy task. There is no Julius Rosenwald behind the Keren Hayesod in Chicago. But if you and your next-door neighbor are serious minded Jews, you can make the Keren Hayesod in Chicago a success even without Rosenwald backing it. Will you do it and are you ready to do it?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
