<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Forward</title>
      <date when="1921-12-12">Dec. 12, 1921</date>
      <title level="a">"United Hebrew Trades determined to help People's Relief"</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0943</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0943.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Forward</title>
     <date when="1921-12-12">Dec. 12, 1921</date>
     <title level="a">"United Hebrew Trades determined to help People's Relief"</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The decision that the People's Relief is to remain with the Joint Distribution Committee, and to partake in the relief drive was approved by the United Hebrew Trades at a meeting today. Here is a picture of 57 Jewish orphans that Comrade Zuker, manager of the Chicago People's Relief Committee, found packed in a freight car at the railroad station in Lemberg. They were hungry, half-naked, and barefooted, and were brought from various countries to Lemberg because they were wanderers and when they were picked up most of them claimed that they had been in Galicia before, so they were packed in a freight car and sent to Lemberg. When the train arrived at the Lemberg station this one freight car was disconnected from the train and left standing at the station, where the orphans remained for 2 days without a piece of bread to eat until the people in the city heard about this. Soon many children were at the scene giving their last bite to the poor starving sisters and brothers who were caged in the filthy freight car like wild animals. On the third day these orphans were removed from the freight car and given homes in various orphan institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0944.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Who will care for the tens of thousands of orphans who are still wandering in the streets? That is the question the People's Relief Committee is asking all the Jewish workers of Chicago. Think of the destruction that come upon the Jews across the sea. Help save them, even if is the last you have. Partake in the 14 million dollar drive of which Chicago must reaise 2 million dollars. It is not enough that you also give, but see to it that your friends also contribute. It is our duty to help more than we can to save them from destruction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
