<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-13">May 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal from the Head of the Lomzsher Yisheva</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-13">May 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL FROM THE HEAD OF THE LOMZSHER YISHEVA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Rabbi Ephraim Epstein has lately received a long letter from the scholarly Rabbi Echeal Mordecai Gordon, head of the Lomzsher Yisheva. This letter brings to Chicago the first news of this school since America entered the war, and is written in German. It reads:</p>
   <p>"Very esteemed friend:</p>
   <p>"It affords me great happiness to have this opportunity to write to you. I now recall those moments of our youth when together we attended the Slobodker Yisheva and together spent our time in the world of Torah. The greatest fortunes in the world are very small compared to that happy and courageous life.</p>
   <p>"But the World War has altered everything; now I have the responsibility of upholding a holy mission, the Lomzsher Yisheva, the only one in Poland that has remained undestroyed in this war.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1350.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Unfortunately, its materialistic situation is very poor because of the impossibility to secure money from America as was done formerly, before the war. Our income has decreased considerably, while expenses have greatly increased due to present dearth or high prices. Our debts stand now at thirty thousand marks.</p>
   <p>"Another place where to get this money, I do not have. Nor can I further uphold the Yisheva. I turn therefore to you, entreating that you do something for the Lomzsher Yisheva. I believe there is much you can do. Advertise in the Jewish newspapers so that the Jewish masses may come to the assistance of the Yisheva.</p>
   <p>"I hope you will do everything possible to rescue the only Yisheva in Poland spared by the War."</p>
   <p>Rabbi Ephraim Epstein sent the letter to us, stating he has nothing to add to this illuminating letter of Rabbi Gordon. In itself, it is an <pb facs="5423972_7_1351.jpg" n="3"/>appeal to local Jews to aid the Lomzsher Yisheva in its present plight.</p>
   <p>"I am certain, said Rabbi Epstein, that local orthodox Jews will not permit the fall of this Yisheva which so miraculously escaped the fires and destructions of War."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
