<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-13">Oct. 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Bring Order into the Charities</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0992</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0992.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-13">Oct. 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">BRING ORDER INTO THE CHARITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last four weeks Chicago has been flooded with letters from Jerusalem and other cities in Palestine asking for charity. The letters are from individuals and from institutions. As far as the institutions are concerned, something is known about them--what they do and how much help they need, but as far as the individuals are concerned, we do not know anything. What is more, many letters have been received from Eastern Europe, most of them coming from theological institutions asking for help.</p>
   <p>We do not know how the Chicago Jews respond to all these appeals and letters. We imagine that these appeals are not entirely without result. Every Jew is ready to give small sums without asking why and what for. This, however, does not serve the cause of charity for the institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0993.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are many philanthropic institutions in Palestine that deserve to be supported, and there are some that should not be supported until we know more about them. We can say that all the theological seminaries in Eastern Europe deserve our help. The heads of those seminaries and their overseers are men who occupy important places in Jewish life, and most of them are well known to us. If they did not need financial help for their institutions, they would not ask us for it and we can feel sure that it is very unpleasant for them to come to us with an appeal for help. If they could have gotten along without us, they would certainly have done so.</p>
   <p>This does not mean that we have done our duty by just giving; if we are interested to that extent in the great Talmudic institutions of Eastern Europe, then our interest should express itself in a more earnest, a more decisive form. It is an insult to the seminaries and to the people who devote their entire life and energy to the study of the Torah when we show just as much interest in them as we do in any begging letter from Zofas (sic) or Jerusalem--from a doubtful institution or from a professional beggar.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0994.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We should establish in Chicago a permanent committee for foreign relief, that would not only encourage but also control the work done for the Jewish institutions in Eastern Europe and in Palestine. This committee should be held responsible for all our charities abroad and it should, therefore, see that the institutions that deserve our help should get it regularly. This can be accomplished by having a system and a [central] control. The committee should also take care that the money shall not be wasted. If an appeal from Palestine does not deserve our response, or if a missionary is not trustworthy, then the committee should investigate each case and let the people know about it.</p>
   <p>We say once more: It is the duty of the representatives of the Orthodox Jews of Chicago to institute order in our foreign relief so as to help the institutions that should be supported and to prevent the fake institutions from abusing our good nature.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
