<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-28">Oct. 28, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Weak Knees</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0981</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0981.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-28">Oct. 28, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WEAK KNEES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of the three hundred thousand Jews in Chicago the majority are orthodox, which means that they are not Reformed Jews. In America we have a different conception of orthodoxy than in Europe. When we say of a Jew in Europe that he is "strict", we mean that he is a Jew who lives according to the Shulchan-Aruch. [Translator's note: Shulchan-Aruch means "prepared table". It is the title of the systematic collection of religious laws, made by Joseph Care, a cabalist, in the sixteenth century]. When we say of a Jew in America that he is orthodox, we do not mean that he is a Shulchan-Aruch Jew, but that he is not a Reformed Jew. As far as he, personally, is concerned, the Jew may be more or less pious, but as far as society is concerned, he wants the Jewish traditions to be kept up.</p>
   <p>The orthodox Jews of Chicago, whether they are pious or not, want the Jewish <pb facs="5423972_7_0982.jpg" n="2"/>institutions, and particularly the Jewish philanthropic institutions, to be conducted in the spirit of the Jewish tradition. That is why they have the Federated Charities. The orthodox Chicago Jews worked for a long time until they put the Federated on a solid basis. The aim of the Federated is not only to do charity, but to do Jewish charity; and to do Jewish charity means that the recipient shall not be raped morally and spiritually; that he shall also have his say in religious questions. The non-Jewish charity gives scant consideration to the recipient of charity. The Jewish charity takes into consideration his conscience and his religious convictions. It gives him something not only of material value, but also something of spiritual value--it lets him live according to his religious convictions.</p>
   <p>The achievements of the Federated Charities in Chicago are the best proof that it is both an organization that is absolutely necessary, and an organization with a future. The orthodox Jews of Chicago have a right to be <pb facs="5423972_7_0983.jpg" n="3"/>proud of their Federated and the only criticism they can make of the leaders of the Federated is that they do not work on a much larger scale and are satisfied with a relatively small budget. The Federated is popular because it is doing brilliant work and it would not be difficult to develop the Federated into a first-class charity organization with an annual budget of half a million dollars. The Federated is, in any case, capable of further development because it has shown itself capable of accomplishment, and a greater degree of accomplishment will depend only upon the energy of its leaders.</p>
   <p>Now, since the Federated, by its last "drive" has proven how popular it is and how capable of achievement it is, the tendency to unite the Federated and the Associated has become so strong that both charity organizations have elected a committee of ten prominent representatives of both organizations to consider the question of amalgamation. We have learned from reliable sources that the committee of ten has already met and has started the negotiations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0984.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We do not know upon what lines the consultations evolved, but we do know what the representatives of the Federated should demand, upon what they should insist. A Jewish community, especially a Jewish community like the one in Chicago, cannot have double bookkeeping in its philanthropic life. It cannot have a charity organization with two departments, a kosher and a non-kosher department, particularly when the majority of the Jews in Chicago are orthodox. A united Jewish charity organization in Chicago can have only one department--a kosher one. If it doesn't, there won't be a Jewish charity organization in Chicago, but a charity organization that is being kept up by the Jews.</p>
   <p>The Jews give money for the Salvation Army and for other non-Jewish charities; just the same, these are general charities, not Jewish. A Jewish charity organization must conduct all its institutions in a Jewish spirit and according to Jewish law.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the Federated must say to the leaders of the Associated, which <pb facs="5423972_7_0985.jpg" n="5"/>does not conduct its institutions according to Jewish spirit and law: "If the institutions of the Associated are conducted according to Jewish law and spirit, we do not see why the two charities should not unite because a union, under such circumstances, would be only a blessing to the community. But if the Associated does not transform its institutions into Jewish institutions, we do not see how a union is possible at all because a united Jewish charity organization in Chicago cannot, under any circumstances, have 'double bookkeeping' in its Judaism."</p>
   <p>This seems to us to be the only possible and logical stand which the Federated and its representatives can take in regard to the question of amalgamation. Besides that, the representatives of the Federated should consider that if they act in any other way than the one we have indicated above, their action will not only not win the approval of those who support the Federated, but will certainly provoke the orthodox Jewish masses in Chicago and the end will be a unanimous protest [on the part] of the orthodox masses against the representatives of the Federated.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0986.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We, therefore, say once more to the representatives of the Federated Charities: No weak Knees! Have the courage to express your convictions, which are the moral foundations of the organization you represent! Either a united Kosher charity organization or the Federated remains independent and will continue to go its own way. It cannot be any other way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
