<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-11-20">November 20, 1924</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-11-20">November 20, 1924</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Workmen's Circle of Chicago, bought a piece of land for a summer home for children of its members. The colony consists of forty acres. This will be one of the finest children colonies in the country.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt in any one's mind that we needed a colony that size. Every summer we had considerable trouble to find a suitable place for the children to spend their vacation. They were always among strange people and they could not feel as carefree as children should feel under the free sky in the summer months.</p>
   <p>Now the Workmen's Circle has arranged a colony where the children will feel as they do in their own home.</p>
   <p>Tuesday night at the meeting of the City Central Committee of the Workmen's Circle, a report was submitted by a special committee that this colony which had been planned on for a long time has been purchased. The forty acres of land is in South Haven on the shore of Lake Michigan. Twenty acres of this land were set aside for a children's colony.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0179.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On this land is a large house and two smaller houses, having twenty eight rooms in all, with all conveniences and equipment for a summer home for children.</p>
   <p>The other twenty acres, will be divided into lots and sold to members only, for building summer homes. The delegates of the central committee concluded that this was the best buy ever made for a summer home for the children and members of the Workmen's Circle, and the report was approved. It was then determined that the deal be closed, the contract signed, and the sale of lots begin.</p>
   <p>The members will have to hurry to buy these lots because the number is limited.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
