<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1929-03-16">March 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Jews Are the First to Pay Their Pledge of One Million Dollars to the Joint.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1929-03-16">March 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO JEWS ARE THE FIRST TO PAY THEIR PLEDGE OF ONE MILLION DOLLARS TO THE JOINT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Jews were the first of the three largest cities in the United States who fulfilled their pledge one hundred per cent to the Jews in Europe. The total sum collected by the Joint since 1925 - for the suffering Jews in the European countries is fourteen million dollars.</p>
   <p>Chicago's quota was one million dollars and this week the last payment of 150 thousand dollars was made to Mr. David A. Brown, National Chairman of the campaign. Yesterday Mr. Brown sent a receipt for the 150 thousand dollars with a statement greeting the Jewish community of Chicago, especially the famous Jewish phanthropist, Mr. Julius Rosenwald, whose contribution was the largest, towards this fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0451.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Brown also expressed his appreciations to Mr. Jacob M. Loeb, head of the Chicago campaign committee who helped a great deal in creating this fund.</p>
   <p>In his statement, Mr. Brown claims that this is the second example that Chicago presented to the Jews in America, of devotion and sincerity to such great Jewish cause. In 1921 Chicago was the first great Jewish community to hear the cry of help from our sisters and brothers across the ocean, and were the first to pledge generously to the cause.</p>
   <p>Four years later, Mr. Brown states it was necessary to send relief again and Chicago was the first to help. "I wish to express my sincere appreciation for the excellent spirit of the Chicago Jews, and especially to the leaders of the Chicago campaign," said Mr. Brown, in his statement, such as Jacob M. Loeb - chairman of the Chicago campaign - Sol Klein - the associate chairman, also the generosity of Mr. Julius Rosenwald, whose excellent contributions have encouraged and out new life into the entire national campaign.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
