<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-04">Mar. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[Collectors for Palestine]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-04">Mar. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[COLLECTORS FOR PALESTINE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I should like to know what has happened to the committe which was organized a few months ago to supervise the collections being made for foreign institutions of charity, and to prevent fake collectors from swindling the public. At the present time, the city is swarming with conscienceless swindlers from Palestine who misappropriate the funds they collect, and thus do a great deal of harm to Palestine. When they enter a Jewish house and see a National Fund box there, they say that they are collectors for the National Fund and empty the box. When the real collector for the National Fund arrives sometime later, he is suspected of being a thief and is chased out. Sometimes these fake collectors will begin to abuse the National Fund. [Nevertheless], the ignorant Jew or Jewess will willingly surrender the National Fund box to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Palestinian agents also deliver speeches at the small synagogues. Instead of appealing for the institutions which they say they represent, they will gossip and spread malicious rumors about the National Fund, the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization], and the constructive work in Palestine. Later they visit members of the small synagogues and get as much money from them as they can.</p>
   <p>An end must be made to this scandalous state of affairs. If the rabbis and synagogue presidents cannot do it, the Zionist organization can and will. Of course, there are honest collectors who appeal for institutions which are really useful and necessary. If you want to distinguish between an honest and a fake collector, just listen closely to what he says. If he appeals for his institution only, if he can prove that he is a bona fide agent of a well-known institution, he is an honest man. If he first calumniates the National Fund, the Keren Hayesod, the halutzim, and the entire Palestine settlement, and then begins to talk about himself and his institution--he is a thief, and you know how to handle him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
