<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-02-02">Feb. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Naturalization Aid League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.7"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 7</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-02-02">Feb. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">NATURALIZATION AID LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual conference of the Naturalization Aid League took place yesterday. The league represents all the most important labor organizations of Chicago, and helps immigrants become citizens.</p>
   <p>After a hearing of the reports of the work accomplished in the past year, the assembly went on to discuss and arrange plans for the coming year, whereby the work will be carried on more energetically.</p>
   <p>It is a fact that all the large Jewish unions, The Workmen's Circle, The Socialist Alliance, and The Federation, are combined to carry on this work. This, in itself, if the best proof that the work is important and deserves the trouble and energy that people of the labor movement spend to continue with it.</p>
   <p>The delegates at this conference have shown a clear and firm position against the inferior elements and destroyers of everything that is good and beautiful in the labor movement, a number of whom tried to disturb the conference by forcing themselves in as uninvited guests to give a hand in work none of them had ever done before.</p>
   <p>But likely, the majority of the delegates knew well the work and dealings of that <pb facs="5423972_7_0371.jpg" n="2"/>element. The majority of the delegates considered the fact that the Naturalization Aid League, which until the present has carried on such brilliant work and has established a name among the widest stratums of the Chicago Jewish population, cannot afford to take risks with such important work, for which absolute unity and harmony is required of the people undertaking it by suddenly making friends with the very people whose main ambition is to break and destroy everything constructed by the labor movement.</p>
   <p>The conference believed that for the good and welfare of this organization, it would be best to keep the disturbing elements at a distance, so we can be free to proceed with the work. And so, these left wing disrupters were refused admittance and told they were not wanted.</p>
   <p>The Naturalization Aid League will continue in her important work and as in the past, will get the full support of the entire labor movement. The plans taken up at this conference for the coming year will be carried through with inspiration by these people, who find this work a pleasure. Even those few delegates who, in the spur of the moment, were in sympathy with those undesired guests, will soon realize that the transactions of the conference were for the best interests of this important work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
