<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-07">Dec. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Another Lawndale Day for the Federation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1616</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1616.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-07">Dec. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER LAWNDALE DAY FOR THE FEDERATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Lawndale Committee that has already accomplished brilliant work in securing subscribers and subscriptions for the Federation, hold meetings at the Mark's Nathan Orphan Home. This Sunday, when they again meet, they will go out into the Lawndale District to awaken the people to the noble work of charity.</p>
   <p>At the last meeting there was present the president of the Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities, Mr. B. Horvitch, who was requested to speak on the floor. He praised the committee for its good work and pointed to other parts of the city, where businessmen are organizing in Federation committees, as an example to be followed here.</p>
   <p>"In this way," Mr. Horvitch said, "it would facilitate securing for the Federation fifteen thousand yearly subscribers with an annual income from subscriptions amounting to three hundred thousand dollars." He further stated that the committee not only performs the noble work of charity but also fulfills its duty in interesting Chicago's businessmen in this noble task, which in itself is a great contribution to the <pb facs="5423972_7_1617.jpg" n="2"/>Jewish community.</p>
   <p>The Lawndale Committee to the present time has secured in subscriptions a sum of four thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The propaganda committee is at present in the full swing of its work in organizing the business and professional people into Federation Committees. Work is now being done in the following districts. From Canal St. east, Albany Ave. west, Madison St. north, and 22nd St. south. This section is densely settled with Jews. It is said that all of them are willing to do their share for the Federation, but it requires the salesmanship of an interview to explain and clarify the matter to them.</p>
   <p>For campaign purposes, of securing subscribers for the Federation in this district, a meeting was held in Attorney Max Schulman's home, where plans were formulated for the initial steps.</p>
   <p>At the last meeting of the Englewood Federation Committee, held at Mr. Max Mindus' home, 423 W. 62nd St., those assembled expressed their approval of the designated work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1618.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Also at this meeting Mr. B. Horvitch, president of the Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities, was present. He expressed his satisfaction on work done by this committee, and hoped that they would in every respect follow the example set by the Lawndale Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
