<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-03">Feb. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Hundreds Besiege Post-Office Branches with Food Parcels for Poland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-03">Feb. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">HUNDREDS BESIEGE POST-OFFICE BRANCHES WITH FOOD PARCELS FOR POLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The news, published exclusively in the Sunday Jewish Courier, that our government has established parcel-post connections with Poland and now accepts food packages for transportation, has stirred all the Jews of Chicago. Yesterday, hundreds of Jews besieged the post-office branches in the Jewish neighborhoods and waited their turn to mail parcels of food to their starving relatives and friends in Poland.</p>
   <p>The majority of them were elderly Jewish women, some with infants in their arms, and adolescent school-children. The latter were kept home by their mothers in order to give them the opportunity to do a good deed by sending a parcel of food to their starving friends. All their faces were serious. Some expressed happiness at finally being able to help their unfortunate friends; some had tears in their eyes.</p>
   <p>Many chatted together and praised the Jewish Courier as being the only Jewish paper in Chicago that is sincerely devoted to Jewish interests, and is always</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>the first and only newspaper to report everything pertaining to these interests.</p>
   <p>A reporter of the Courier who listened to the conversations discovered at the same time the contents of the food packages which the Jews are sending to their starving relatives.</p>
   <p>The majority of them contained flour, sugar, tea and canned goods. Some also sent rice, grits and even chocolate for the youngsters. Many even provided their suffering relatives in Poland with matzoth for Passover.</p>
   <p>It is also necessary to state that meat cannot be sent to Poland; but there are grounds to believe that the Government will in the near future permit its transportation, and then the American Jews will be able to send meat to their hungry friends in Poland.</p>
   <p>Many of those who sent packages did not properly follow the rules which were published in the Courier, and they were compelled to go back home to repack</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1201.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>their parcels. On the other hand many went far beyond the rules; they packed the parcels in heavy boxes tying them with heavy cord that would be strong enough to withstand a journey to the planet Mars.</p>
   <p>In order to avoid these inconveniences we repeat the rules regarding the sending of food parcels to Poland.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
