<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-04-13">Apr. 13, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Charity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-04-13">Apr. 13, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">CHARITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fifty million dollars yearly is paid out to poor and suffering families in Chicago, the Chicago Commercial Club disclosed yesterday after a thorough investigation which lasted almost two years.</p>
   <p>There are 232 charity organizations besides hospitals and the appropriations made by the city of Chicago and Cook County every year to help poor unfortunate families.</p>
   <p>The private agencies themselves paid out over eighteen million dollars last year for charity. Hospitals where poor patients are admitted free had an expense of over eight million dollars.</p>
   <p>In addition there are other charitable institutions run by the State, County, and City, which appropriate funds for charity purposes. Chicago, then, according to the report, will have spent over 50 million dollars this year <pb facs="5423972_7_0473.jpg" n="2"/>to help poor unfortunates and sick people who are compelled to resort to charity.</p>
   <p>The masses have no conception as to the extent of poverty in which tens of thousands of families find themselves while part of the Chicago population flourish in luxury and wealth to the extent that they do not know what to do with their money.</p>
   <p>At a time when a part of society bathe in milk and wine, live in sprees and diversions, become sick from dissipation and naughtiness, tens of thousands of men, women, and children suffer in want and must resort to organized charitable agencies for bread, rent, and coal for winter.</p>
   <p>When women workers ask for work in order to better their condition, - mothers who are anxious to work with their sweat and blood to support their children, the very same philanthropists, who give charity and are personally active in charitable organizations, carry on the bitter struggle of not giving them work, making every effort to suppress them, to the extent that they are forced to accept charity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0474.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is the great contradiction of our present system: wealth, luxuries, and superfluity on one side; hunger, want, and misery on the other. Yet, there are many naive persons among the poor class who say that we are living in a country and in a period where everyone is alike, and every one has the same opportunity to accumulate wealth and not be forced to resort to charity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
