<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-27">Nov. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the Federation and Who Are its Opposers?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article Eight)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-27">Nov. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE FEDERATION AND WHO ARE ITS OPPOSERS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article Eight)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We believe this is one of David Fishman's stories. The story concerns an old man who sat in a small town synagogue at the stove muttering cabalistic paraphrases. This old Nachman sat muttering in this manner for several years. No one seemed to notice him. He considered this only natural and so did everyone else.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1621.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One beautiful morning when everyone came to pray, old Nachman arose, ascended the platform and spoke aloud to the assembly:</p>
   <p>"People! Know ye, that the Messiah visited me this night in my dream giving me authority to reveal myself to you, therefore, I declare that commencing today, I am your holy man and command you to bring a "tithe," to me.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1622.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Some of the listeners shrugged their shoulders, but there soon arose many who believed Nachman to be a holy man who must be paid the greatest respect since the Messiah himself had visited him in his dream.</p>
   <p>In the audience there was a young man of ready wit who said: "You old fool"! If it were true that the Messiah wished to reveal you as a holy man why has he not come to us in our dreams? You may know you are <pb facs="5423972_7_1623.jpg" n="4"/>a holy man, but we who know it not, are the ones the Messiah should have visited and informed of your holiness. Therefore, old fool of a holy man, go to your oven until the Messiah comes to us in our dreams, then will we set you at the head of everything, crown you our holy man and give you the best or the first of our possessions."</p>
   <p>Such a melodrama is now being enacted in the Chicago Jewish Community by the opposers of the Federation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1624.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>For years they have grumbled, but no one has paid any attention to them. No one even knew they existed. They felt that the less they were known the better it would be for them.</p>
   <p>Suddenly one fine morning recently we heard them shouting that they are not senile, and not fools, but radicals, a part of the large Chicago Jewish population; people with opinions to be reckoned with. They declared we must do business with them and give them tithes, but they do not use the excuse of a Messiah. Instead they claim to have many readers; may God forgive them their sins.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1625.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It is to be expected that in the average dumb audience, there would be some who would believe like the old woman who said: "Perhaps this self-proclaimed God is also God, even if he is a senile man speaking."</p>
   <p>It is high time we answer these fools and send them back to the oven and tell them that the Messiah must appear in our dreams if they wish a tithe of hundreds of dollars. Let him reveal that you are radical instead of wanton fellows; let your sponsors come and proclaim your greatness, importance, influence, etc. But, since we know you too well we say, return to your oven. We will not give you $800 as a tithe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1626.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Among the subscribers of the Federation, we find several radicals; it is not enough to mention such personalities; as, Peter Zussman, Dr. Frankle, Dr. Kafman and others of their kind. No one would have suspected these people of conservatism, dyed in the wool orthodoxism if we had paid the Forward a tithe. If they think the Forward represents radicalism, or that it may harm or help the Federation, they as the Messiahs of radicalism, and all the subscribers of the Federation, and all the people whose opinions must be reckoned with must be the first to appear in the dream of the Federation and proclaim the Forward as a holy one entitled to a tithe of $800.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1627.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>But the Messiahs of radicalism, the Zussman's, the Frankle's, and the Kafman's know the Forward does not represent radicalism or the radical public. The best members of the Federation do not read the Forward.</p>
   <p>This is the answer to the great secret of the failure of the Forward's cries, and a sample of the Federation's opposers.</p>
   <p>Now we have seen the true reason for the existence of opposers, those senile beings who want to reveal themselves as holy ones, to receive <pb facs="5423972_7_1628.jpg" n="9"/>tithes, but who have no Messiah to champion them in the dreams of the proper persons. This is the combination of hypocrisy and sham that masquerades under the mask of radicalism and orthodoxism, crying with crocodile tears when the Federation demands to see their Messiah, if only in its dreams.</p>
   <p>Everyone knows the Federation is an organization lead by the best Jews. Everyone knows its opposers are those tithe seekers, who cannot earn a decent living. Chicago Jews, the subscribers of the Federation, are not <pb facs="5423972_7_1629.jpg" n="10"/>influenced by these tithe seekers, for they do not come in contact with them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
