<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-07">February 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Religious Rearing of Orphans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-02-07">February 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">RELIGIOUS REARING OF ORPHANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Sol Druker, superintendent of Marks Nathan Orphanage, in his annual report to the Board of Directors, paused at the clause of "religious upbringing" and said:</p>
   <p>"In addition to a kosher kitchen in an orthodox institution, I felt that our children should receive a thorough Jewish education. Daily services, conducted by the boys themselves under correct supervision, were introduced. They also officiate at Friday evening and Sabbath services in the synagogue - one acting as cantor and another as rabbi. He, who acts as rabbi, prepares the weekly sermon, which is delivered with great respect and importance. I have arranged a series of Friday night lectures where I speak to them on the great men in Jewish history.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0284.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I have invited quite frequently our rabbis to address the children. We emphasize the holidays, so that the children shall know the significance of those days by observing them properly."</p>
   <p>It is very pleasant to hear and know that the superintendent provides the children with a Jewish education in addition to a kosher kitchen and an orthodox rearing. It was recently rumored that the main object, for which the Marks Nathan Home was established, is being greatly neglected; remarks were passed that Jewish education is being neglected; that Jewish-orthodox surroundings do not prevail there; that the devotion and loyalty of the superintendent to the orphans is so great that he sacrifices their future world for this world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0285.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They, who adhered to that opinion, constantly attacked him by saying that it is impossible for a man, who personally does not approve of Kashruth, who is thorough in his views against orthodoxy, to rear and educate children as orthodox Jews. The most that can be expected is that he will make hypocrites of the children. Knowing that their support comes from orthodox Jews, they would conduct themselves in an orthodox manner, that is as long as they would be obligated to the community, and would merely pretend to hold services, and disguised as cantors and rabbis, they would mock sermons; As actors on a stage they show religious feelings because they are being paid for it.</p>
   <p>These people claim that an orphanage can, should, and must establish such Jewish surroundings so that the children will receive a natural orthodox rearing, where caricatures of cantors and rabbis will be unnecessary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0286.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But as the superintendent states in his report, the children through their own initiative have introduced daily services with their own cantor and rabbi.</p>
   <p>This proves that the surroundings there are extremely orthodox. Seeing that the superintendent and other officials of the home are engaged in prayers each morning at the services, it is only natural that the children should imitate them, and eventually they will become so ascustomed to the Jewish tradition, that it will become part of their existence, just as it is with the superintendent.</p>
   <p>Such rearing is the true Jewish-bringing-up, which Jewry wishes to see in the Marks Nathan Home, and it will please everyone to learn from Mr. Druker's report that they are getting a thorough Jewish education.</p>
   <p>The poor things need it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
