<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-01">Feb. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Do Not Hold Back the Blood Money</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1518</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1518.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-01">Feb. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">DO NOT HOLD BACK THE BLOOD MONEY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish tag day has come and gone, and the results are most gratifying. It is estimated that over $100,000 was raised on the Jewish tag day. We read in the press that many Jews have sold their jewelry at auction and turned the money over to the Jewish war sufferers' fund....Hundreds of Jewish girls stood all day on the street corners not at all minding the heavy rain and wind. They let no one pass without selling him or her a tag. Many committees made house to house canvasses where they were successful in getting monthly pledges for the fund to help their unfortunate brothers and sisters in the war-ridden countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1519.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Everything possible was done to make the Jewish tag day a success. The report of Samuel Phillipson, local representative of the Jewish relief fund, shows that $4,000 was taken in through the tag sales on the streets, and an additional amount of approximately $11,000 was collected by the National Relief Conference. This sum of money we must call "Blood-Money," because hungry ones are waiting for food, sick ones are waiting for medicine, and the dead are waiting for burial. Every dollar that reaches Russia at once brings in twofold relief, for every dollar today, can be turned into food, while the same dollar tomorrow may have to be used for a shroud instead. So to hold back this blood-money until all the moneys are collected, will cause unnecessary trouble and sometimes it will be a matter of life and death if relief should be delayed.</p>
   <p>We understand that there are still many tag boxes in the hands of Jewish women, who have not as yet turned them over to the committee. This waiting is just a case of negligence on their part, for every day's delay in sending relief to the unfortunate war victims may cause hardships....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
