<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-18">Feb. 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Too Much Charity--Too Little Tzdokoh</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0684</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0684.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-18">Feb. 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TOO MUCH CHARITY--TOO LITTLE TZDOKOH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jews have always given Tzdokoh [Hebrew word meaning righteousness or alms], but America has taught them to give charity. Tzdokoh means to give anonymously; charity is a matter of publicity. Every Jewish community has its charitable institutions, but only here in America do we make such a fuss about our charitable institutions, just as if we in America were the only Jewish group in the world that took care of its orphans and aged, of its sick and needy.</p>
   <p>The Jews in London, Berlin, Paris, Budapest, Bucharest, Krakow, and Lemberg, also have their charitable institutions. The Jews in all of Eastern Europe have their charitable institutions, just as we have ours here in America. One can live in a large Jewish community in Europe for twenty years, and not hear a word about charity and institutions, but one can live no more than three days in a Jewish community in America without hearing a great to-do about charitable affairs, drives, institutions, etc. The Jews in London provide for <pb facs="5423972_7_0685.jpg" n="2"/>their needy as well, if not better than we in America do, and the same holds true of other Jewish communities in Europe. But one seldom, if ever, hears as much discussion of a drive, of this or that institution as is, unfortunately, much too often the case in America. The Jews in Europe give Tzdokoh anonymously; here in America, they give ostentatiously. An individual contributes a dollar and gets a thousand dollars' worth of publicity. In America, the membership of a board of directors of a certain institution is a matter of great moment, it is a question of honor, of connections, of politics, of how much one gives to the institution, etc. This situation is unknown in Eastern, and even Western Europe. The various [Charitable] institutions there are administered by boards of directors as they are here, but the people never know who compose the board of directors of this or that institution, unless a cultural institution is concerned, because the Jews in Europe give Tzdokoh, and here they have learned how to give charity; charity is not Tzdokoh.....</p>
   <p>In America everybody knows how much each person gives, when he gives, for whom and for what he gives. The donor knows the recipient and vice versa. This is <pb facs="5423972_7_0686.jpg" n="3"/>contrary to the Jewish spirit and the Jewish tradition, and is, from a Jewish standpoint, very vulgar.....</p>
   <p>The manner in which we give Tzdokoh in America is not only contrary to the Jewish tradition, but it is also one of the reasons why the American Jewry is so unproductive spiritually and why it takes so little interest in intellectual questions and affairs.</p>
   <p>If the American Jews would give Tzdokoh instead of charity, our welfare workers would have time and opportunity to do some cultural work. Tzdokoh is given not because one wants to, but because one must. The giving of Tzdokoh is a duty which must be quietly fulfilled. Tzdokoh does not simply kill time. Tzdokoh is given with no shouting, with no publicity, with no beating of drums, with no blasting of trumpets, with no drives, with no mass meetings, and with no politics. Every member of the community, i.e., every Jew is taxed according to his wealth and income. He sends his check to the community and the representatives of the community know that they will have a definite income each <pb facs="5423972_7_0687.jpg" n="4"/>year for the maintenance of all community institutions. The energetic and intelligent members of the community who feel the lack of social work, devote their time and energy to educational and cultural work. If the Jews in London, Paris, Vienna, or Berlin would make a fuss about charity such as the Jews in New York, Chicago, and Philadelphia make, there would be no intellectual Jewish life in Vienna, London, and Berlin because their entire energy would be wasted on charitable enterprises. But because they give Tzdokoh instead of charity, they have time for everything, and can devote themselves to educational and cultural work.</p>
   <p>In all of Western Europe, each Jewish community has a Jewish literary society, and the large Jewish communities have a number of Jewish cultural organizations, whose objectives are the cultivation of Jewish literature, art, erudition, etc. But in America we do not have such a thing because every Jew in America who has time and opportunity for social work, spends all his energy upon charitable activities, and has no time for cultural work. That is why the spiritual life of our people in America is so meager.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0688.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Tzdokoh is, however, impossible without a Kehilah [Hebrew term for organized Jewish community] and as long as we have synagogues and do not have a Kehilah, we must concern ourselves with charity. Even the little that we do for education is also under the "supervision" of charity. It is no honor to the American Jews that the Talmud Torahs are supported by the charities. It is simply a disgrace that Jewish education in America should come under the heading of charity. Such Talmud Torahs will produce neither scholars nor well-bred Jews.</p>
   <p>Paradoxical as it may sound, it is literally true that charity is the misfortune of American Jewry. When we stop giving charity and begin to give Tzdokoh, our life will take on a new aspect, and we will [begin to] grow spiritually and morally.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
