<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-28">Jan. 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Four Hundred People at the Annual Banquet of the Charities; Julius Rosenwald Proud of the Unity Among Chicago Jewry</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0525</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0525.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-01-28">Jan. 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">FOUR HUNDRED PEOPLE AT THE ANNUAL BANQUET OF THE CHARITIES; JULIUS ROSENWALD PROUD OF THE UNITY AMONG CHICAGO JEWRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night, over four hundred Jewish men and women attended the annual banquet and meeting of the [United] Jewish Charities of Chicago, given in the ballroom of the Hotel La Salle, Rabbi [Louis] Mann was the speaker of the evening. Julius Rosenwald presided.</p>
   <p>Mr. Alfred K. Foreman, treasurer of the Jewish Charities, reported that the expenditures of the organization during the past year, which ended December 1, amounted to $1,211,726.89; there remained in the treasury $566.77. The endowment fund is more than $80,000. Only the interest on the money was used by the various institutions which are affiliated with the Jewish Charities.</p>
   <p>Mr. Louis Kahn, chairman of the research bureau, in his report lamented the fact that only eleven thousand out of fifty thousand Jewish children in Chicago <pb facs="5423972_7_0526.jpg" n="2"/>receive a religious education. He declared that the Jewish Charities has undertaken to see that more Jewish children receive a religious education. With that end in view, Dr. Dushkin was appointed to work out the necessary regulations in co-operation with the directors of the various educational institutions.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Mann declared, in a speech that was enthusiastically applauded, that charity among Jews of all classes is nurtured by our religion. He urged that our youth be encouraged to take part in the charity work "because this work can also serve as a means of attracting them to our faith".</p>
   <p>Mr. Rosenwald said, among other things, that the amalgamation of the Orthodox Charity Federation and the [Associated] Hebrew Charities has brought the Chicago Jews closer together, a fact of which "the entire American Jewry can be proud". Mr. Rosenwald appealed to the subscribers who are behind in payment of their dues to settle their debts "so that we can do more and better work in the field of Jewish Charity in Chicago". Mr. Rosenwald also spoke about the <pb facs="5423972_7_0527.jpg" n="3"/>founding of new institutions, which are not approved by the Jewish Charities.</p>
   <p>The entire audience, acting upon a proposal made by Judge [H. M.] Fisher, stood up to honor Mr. Rosenwald "who has done so much toward building a United Jewry in Chicago".</p>
   <p>The annual meeting also adopted a few amendments to the constitution regarding the status of the institutions. The meeting also ratified the decisions of the directors of the Jewish Charities for the past two years, up to December 1, 1923.</p>
   <p>The election of the following officials for the coming year was announced: Julius Rosenwald, honorary president; Charles Rubin, president; Sol Klein, first vice-president; James Davis, second vice-president; Alfred K. Foreman, treasurer; Louis Kahn, executive director, and Marcy Berger, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
