<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-15">Nov. 15, 1905</date>, 4:3.
<title level="a">Relief Movement Grows</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1741</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1741.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-15">Nov. 15, 1905</date>, 4:3.
<title level="a">RELIEF MOVEMENT GROWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jews of Chicago are continuing to pour in upon the central committee their individual contributions to the Russian relief fund, and as the organization of the sub-committee progresses more and more effective work is being done in reaching available sources of assistance. The receipts yesterday almost doubled those of Monday with but a small percentage of the direct appeals yet distributed by post. During the day $7,601 was placed on deposit, raising the total now in the hands of the central committee to more than $12,000 exclusive of pledges.</p>
   <p>It will be impossible to estimate what progress has been made by the fifty subcommittees engaged in soliciting funds in the various trades until the general meeting Wednesday, but it is expected that their reports will materially swell the sum now in hand.</p>
   <p>Ask Lawyers to Contribute</p>
   <p>In order to facilitate the work letters were sent out to all of the practicing attorneys of Chicago last night asking their cooperation.. Mr. Greenebaum, who has charge of the central fund, held a consultation with Manager Adams of the <pb facs="5423972_7_1742.jpg" n="2"/>Auditorium yesterday with regard to the benefit matinee. December 12 was chosen, tentatively, as the date.</p>
   <p>Letters are being received in Chicago every day by relatives of the victims of Russian atrocities who have reached neutral territory. These recite with a concreteness and simplicity which adds only to the horror the acts of blood incited by race hatred and years of smoldering animosity.</p>
   <p>(A long list of yesterday's subscriptions follow with the close of the above article.)</p>
   <p>Women Join Relief Work</p>
   <p>The West Side Ladies' Russian Aid Society was organized at a meeting at 47 Johnson Street last night for the purpose of raising funds for the victims of the Jewish massacres. Over one hundred women were present. Committees of ten to act as precinct organizers were appointed, with Mrs. D. Wolf of 612 South California Avenue as chairman of the precinct organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
