<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-29">Aug. 29, 1916</date><title level="a">Buy Only Tickets with War Stamps</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-29">Aug. 29, 1916</date><title level="a">BUY ONLY TICKETS WITH WAR STAMPS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Millions of Jews in belligerent countries will observe their third Rosh Hashanah (New Year) with the roar of cannon and the flourishing of swords. In America we shall observe one second Rosh Hashoneh by offering prayers for peace and for support of the war-suffering Jews.</p>
   <p>It is most appropriate that on this sacred day every Jew should be urged to do his duty in behalf of his unfortunate coreligionists. Therefore the decision has been made to ask every synagogue as well as the broad masses of people neither to sell nor to buy admission tickets to the synagogues on the High Holidays unless they bear war stamps.</p>
   <p>A meeting was held at the O Navi Sholom Congregation by all rabbis, synagogue presidents and prominent men of the Chicago Jewry at which a War Stamp Committee was organized whose task it shall be to distribute war stamps to <pb facs="5423972_7_1473.jpg" n="2"/>all synagogues and halls. It is expected that all synagogues will co-operate in attaching stamps to the tickets. However, the broad masses are asked to co-operate by not buying tickets without war stamps.</p>
   <p>The chairman of this committee is Paul Reaseman and the secretary, Wolf Farber. A committee of three was also appointed to collect the money for the war stamps and to turn it over to the relief treasurer, Samuel Philipsohn. This committee consists of Mr. Goldstein, Mr. Feinstein and Mr. Reaseman. A ways and means committee consisting of Rabbi Ephraim Epstein, Mr. Farber and Mr. Finestein, was also appointed. All committees have immediately swung into action, and it is expected that several thousand dollars will be raised for the war-suffering Jews.</p>
   <p>A feeling of irritation prevailed because the south side committee had failed to mention, in its book of contributors, the name of each west side contributor <pb facs="5423972_7_1474.jpg" n="3"/>to the Relief Fund. Therefore, it was decided that books should be printed with the names of all west side contributors to the Relief Fund.</p>
   <p>Buy only tickets for Rosh Hashoneh and Yom Kippur [Day of Atonement] which bear war stamps.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
