<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1891-05-22">May 22, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">A Truly Benevolent Act.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Home for Aged Jews.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1891-05-22">May 22, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">A TRULY BENEVOLENT ACT.</title><title level="a" type="sub">THE HOME FOR AGED JEWS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The magnificent donation of Mr. Abraham Slimmer of Iowa, of $50,000 through Rosenbaum Brothers of this city, for erecting and maintaining a home for aged Jewish people in this city, as we are pleased to announce, elicited the philanthropic Chicagoans to enter with zeal and devotion to aid in the grand philanthropic project of Mr. Slimmer. Steps were taken to incorporate this institution; constitution and by-laws were adopted, and an election of permanent officers resulted as follows:- Mr. M. Rosenbaum, president; Mr. E. Frankenthal, vice-president; Mr. Harry Hart, secretary; Mr. B. Lowenthal, treasurer. Directors:- Mrs. M. A. Meyer, Mrs. Charles H. Schwab, Mrs. H. Klapfer, Mrs. Dora Frank, Mrs. Louis Newberger, Mrs. B. J. David, Mrs. Emma Stern, Mrs. Max Hart, Mrs. Julia Bernheimer, Morris Rosenbaum, Abraham Slimmer, Nelson Morris, H. A. Kohn, H. L. Frank, B. Kuppenheimer, J. Rosenbaum, Simon Mandel, B. Lowenthal, B. Cahn, Harry Hart, Moses Born, H. E. Greenbaum, A. Kuh, E. Frankenthal, D. A. Kohn.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0108.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The question of taking action on the admission of the Israelitische Altenheim Association as a component part of the society, was discussed, and it was decided that the Board under the by-laws, had no power to take any further action than to accept the contribution of the association on the same basis that subscriptions would be received from individuals. Since the above was in type, we learn that the President, Mrs. L. Newberger, of this society who had appointed a committee of three, to wit:- Mesdams Hannah Simon, Augusta Levy and Dora Hefter, had secured $3,000 subscriptions, and that here after, the Israelitische Altenheim would be merged into the "Home" and that from now on, they would do all in their power to promote this Jewish Old People's Home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
