<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-04-03">April 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">In Line with the Poor Who Ask for "Molo Chitim" (Money Donated for the Purpose of Providing the Poor with Food for Passover)</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Yannah Spivak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-04-03">April 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">IN LINE WITH THE POOR WHO ASK FOR "MOLO CHITIM" (MONEY DONATED FOR THE PURPOSE OF PROVIDING THE POOR WITH FOOD FOR PASSOVER)</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Yannah Spivak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Individual misfortunes, family tragedies, and scenes of poverty and dire need can be witnessed quite often. These scenes cut deeply into the heart and arouse one's sympathy. However, it is more horrible to witness a group of misfortunates and tragedies together swimming, before us, on the surface of our society. For the moment one forgets himself and thinks that everybody is exposed to want and distress.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0462.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such a horrible scene of a congregated group of misfortunes and tragedies, the writer of these lines witnessed yesterday at the Moses Montefeore Hebrew School, 1121 S. Winchester Avenue., where the "Molo Chitim" Committee distributed matzoh, meat, and cash to the needy for Passover.</p>
   <p>It is a splendid and humane custom; the ancient Jewish custom of distributing "Molo Chitim" (money or food for the poor on Passover). This is but once a year (for Passover) and therefore the "Molo Chitim" Committee is worthy of a hearty thanks.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0463.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Among the hundreds of men and women that filled the corridor and class rooms of the Hebrew school, could be seen the faces of many young men and women. The majority of them were neatly attired and conversed in English among themselves.</p>
   <p>Upon speaking to several of them, the writer learned that they were not "chronical beggars," but unemployed who were forced to bend their pride in order to provide something for their families on Passover.</p>
   <p>The Committee distributed (yesterday and today) ten thousand dollars ($10,000) in cash; thirty thousand (30,000) pounds matzohs (unleavened bread) and three thousand, and five hundred (3,500) pounds of meat.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0464.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Everyone received from three to ten dollars in cash, from fifteen to fifty pounds of matzohs (unleavened bread); and from four to eight pounds of meat, according to ones need.</p>
   <p>No one was turned down. Everything was distributed without any red rape, which is quite often the case with the scientific charity officers.</p>
   <p>The "Molo Chitim" Committee will also send matzoh and meet to the state institutions for the Jewish inmates. The following institutions are on the list of the committee: Joliet Penitentiary, Pontiac Penitentiary, County Jail, Cook County Hospital, Lincoln State School, Dixion State Hospital, Kankekee State Asylum, State School for Boys, Chicago Home for Girls, State School for Girls, Edward Heinz Hospital, <pb facs="5423972_7_0465.jpg" n="5"/>Training School for Boys, Chicago Cook County School, Rest Haven, Home for Incurable, Francis Juvenile Home, and Chicago Fresh Air Hospital.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
