<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-10">Oct. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1147</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1147.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-10">Oct. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The journey of Judge Harry M. Fisher and Max Pane to Soviet Russia and their efforts there to obtain a permit so that food, clothing, and medical supplies from America can be sent there, for distribution among the impoverished and stricken Jews [living] under the rule of the Bolsheviks, were finally successful. After a good deal of negotiation between the Joint Distribution Committee and the State Department in Washington, the united relief agency finally succeeded in obtaining permission to transport the above-mentioned necessities to Soviet Russia, in accordance with the arrangements of Fisher and Pane.</p>
   <p>The Joint Distribution Committee received the following note from the State Department: "The State Department alone cannot assist the Joint Distribution Committee in its task in Soviet Russia and cannot encourage any American <pb facs="5423972_7_1148.jpg" n="2"/>citizen to enter the territories occupied by the Soviet authorities. The State Department, however, will not object to the Joint Distribution Committee's undertaking relief work in Russia under the conditions of the contract regulating the work of the united Jewish committee to aid the pogrom victims (the contract of Fisher and Pane with the Soviet Government), which was reported to the State Department on August 11."</p>
   <p>The State Department also declared that there is no embargo on Russia, nor is there any embargo on articles which cannot immediately be used for war purposes, and that the American Government does not oppose the entrance of its citizens into Russia, providing that they do it of their own volition and without a passport.</p>
   <p>As reported from New York, the Joint Distribution Committee, upon receipt of official permission, immediately wired its representative, Dr. Frank Rosenblatt, to leave for Russia and the Ukraine at his own risk and to initiate and direct the relief work for the pogrom and war victims.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1149.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Jews of Chicago, show your true colors! See that the treasury of the Joint Distribution Committee does not remain empty. Contribute as much as you can, or at least as much as you have pledged to contribute. You have made pledges in the synagogues during the High Holidays, for our unfortunate people across the sea, and very few of you have fulfilled your pledges.</p>
   <p>Help is demanded of you to alleviate the deplorable condition of our people. Give and give again. We have not yet forwarded enough money for many of the unfortunates. So far as those in Soviet Russia or the Ukraine are concerned, our aid could not have reached them even if we had sent an adequate amount of money.</p>
   <p>Now our aid can reach those unfortunates in Soviet Russia and in the Ukraine. Let's send it to them; let's not starve them out or freeze them out. Let's not be the cause of their death from want of medicine and attention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1150.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We should not and must not let them die! Fulfill your pledges, Chicago Jews! Send your contributions to the presidents of the synagogues where you made your pledges, or send them to the office of the Joint Relief Committee, 720 Roosevelt Road, and you will receive the blessings of those who depend on your aid.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
