<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-09-05">Sept. 5, 1917</date><title level="a">Jews, Be Righteous - Do Justice!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1442</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1442.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-09-05">Sept. 5, 1917</date><title level="a">JEWS, BE RIGHTEOUS - DO JUSTICE!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not charity but righteousness is demanded now of Chicago Jews.</p>
   <p>American Jewish ignorance forgets the difference between charity and righteousness. Oftentimes we boast of our charity, and believe it to be the same as Jewish charity, but we are badly mistaken.</p>
   <p>Charity we inherited from our neighbors. Charity makes a distinction between the donor and the receiver. The donor, although he may mean well, assumes the character of a half-god or saint, who is not compelled to give but contribute for the sake of being merciful and graceful; no one has the right to dictate how much he shall give, to whom or when. He throws out his chest and proclaims to the world "Admire me, - it is evident that I am merciful, - a liberal."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1443.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>No stronger tie of fraternity can exist than that of mutual respect between the charity giver and the charity receiver. But the donor gradually comes to look upon the receiver as a sort of low creature who must bow to him, and the charity receiver must get accustomed to crawling with bowed head to receive help.</p>
   <p>Ancient Jewish institutions called it charity but today it is called social justice. The proselyte, the orphan, and the widow is entitled to a part of the country's wealth; it belongs to them, it is a constitutional duty.</p>
   <p>We say this in reference to the appeal that is now being made by the Chicago Orthodox Federated Charities, to the Chicago Jews, not to forsake their widows, their orphans, their comsumptives and their sick. This appeal is unfortunately being made for "charity." In America we have no other alternative, because the conception of Jewish charity has gradually disappeared.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1444.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, the fearful days (New Year's Day and Day of Atonement) are approaching when Orthodox Jewish consciousness becomes somewhat sentimental. This is probably the most opportune time to remind our Jews that they are not doing their duty toward the poor, who are entitled to their share of Jewish charity, which is due them in the name of justice.</p>
   <p>How can any Jew go to his synagogue on New Year's, or Atonement Day and ask for justice from his God, when he himself does not do justice for the needy?</p>
   <p>"Whoever asks for justice, must himself do justice." Every Jew shall do his share of charity, and then he will have the right to go before his God, and say "I have given away what belongs not to me, I paid my debt to the proselyte, and to thousands of unfortunate Jews, and now I may enjoy, with a clear conscience, whatever I have left."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
