<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-15">Apr. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">To the Chicago Jewry</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Chaim Weizmann</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0590</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0590.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-15">Apr. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE CHICAGO JEWRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Chaim Weizmann</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In greeting the Jews of Chicago through the Daily Jewish Courier, I wish to say that I am convinced that the developments in Palestine are as normal as was to be expected. Taking into consideration the situation of the world in general, the progress that we have made in rebuilding Palestine can be compared with the progress that has been made by other nations that have recognized governments behind them, and well-established populations.</p>
   <p>We Jews have no government to take care of us. Our people are scattered, and one-half of the Jews of the world are so utterly ruined that the burden and privilege of rebuilding Palestine falls chiefly upon the American Jewry, of which the Chicago Jewish community is a part.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0591.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I am convinced that New York will do its duty, and I believe that Chicago will follow the example set by the great city in the East. I have come here to present the cause of Zionism to this great community. I shall present all the facts and all the obstacles and all the unpleasant details, and I am sure that the Chicago Jews will respond.</p>
   <p>If we work systematically, and do not listen to what our opponents say or will say, we will accomplish great things for our land. In the words of Lord Herbert Samuel: "It is better to listen to what your friends tell you and to pay no attention to your enemies".</p>
   <p>Our work is the work of peace, justice, and civilization, which will bring honor to all Jews and to all those who have assisted us in this great, but difficult task.</p>
   <p>....In the name of the future freedom of our people, I call upon you <pb facs="5423972_7_0592.jpg" n="3"/>conscientious Jews of Chicago. It has not been easy to bring about our historic victory: the nations of the world, among them the greatest and most powerful, have recognized our right to Palestine, i. e., our right to a free and independent future. This is the only path which leads to friendly relations between us and the rest of the world; it leads to mutual understanding, which can, in due time, put an end to our spiritual suffering.</p>
   <p>Consider well the importance of this historic event and begin to work zealously, courageously, energetically, and willingly. The world has paid us an old debt. Now pay your debt to yourselves, to your future, to your people.</p>
   <p>I urge you to work. I ask of you a small offering. I request that you give our great cause a few days of your time. Let the businessmen, professional men, and workers put aside their business for a few days <pb facs="5423972_7_0593.jpg" n="4"/>and devote all of their time to the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of Zionist World Organization].</p>
   <p>Our ideal is deeply embedded among all our people. Our people are ready and willing to participate in the rebuilding of our land and our future. Everybody must be reached. Nobody must be overlooked. Donors, volunteers, and halutzim are needed in the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <p>May the Keren Hayesod halutzim here strengthen the hands of our halutzim in Palestine, and also make it possible for the great numbers of halutzim who are now en route to Palestine, to reach their goal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
