<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1931-04-06">Apr. 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Disgrace of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1931-04-06">Apr. 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE DISGRACE OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Palestine colonies, which were built with the sweat and blood of a generation of Jewish pioneers, are now in serious danger because they lack the necessary funds to repair and rebuild the colonies that were destroyed during the great war. The[World] Zionist Organization, which is today the recognized agent of the Jewish nation, cannot continue its work for lack of funds. In order to retain Palestine for the Jewish people, we must at least show that we are ready to make sacrifices. We must encourage the Zionists to go on with their work.</p>
   <p>The Jews of America were supposed to contribute three million dollars to the redemption fund. The Chicago Jews, the leaders of the Middle West were to contribute half a million dollars, a dollar for every person. The Chicago Zionists responded generously to the call of the Zionist Organization to do <pb facs="5423972_7_0430.jpg" n="2"/>their share. They promised to raise a quarter of a million dollars within a period of six weeks. They organized a campaign committee with Judge Harry M. Fisher as chairman, and other prominent Zionist leaders as members. They also appointed a subcommittee, called a big mass meeting at the Auditorium, and opened the campaign.</p>
   <p>The Jewish Courier, which understood the situation thoroughly, did its utmost to clarify and educate the Chicago Jews with regard to the urgency of this call. Although effective talks were made, and convincing newspaper articles were written, we regret to say that this drive was a huge failure.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile the desperate letters that arrive from Palestine daily make one shrink with pain. A great many letters come in from New York and the Middle West, concerning Chicago's contribution, but the city is so profoundly asleep that it cannot wake up. It is really a disgrace that Chicago, which is thought to be so responsive to humanitarian appeals, and has a growing Jewish population, should neglect her duty and her pledge to our <pb facs="5423972_7_0431.jpg" n="3"/>nation and country in this critical moment, on the eve of redemption.</p>
   <p>Who is to blame for this condition? Are the Chicago Jews to blame? No, whenever we turn to them with a specific appeal, they respond. The Chicago Zionists are also doing as much as they can, and a good many are doing even more than they are asked to do. The responsibility for this peculiar failure, which involves a quarter-million Chicago Jews, rests with a few individuals who have neglected their duties, and have undertaken great responsibilities at a time when they were unable to look after them. Those individuals are responsible to the whole Zionist movement for this moral and material failure.</p>
   <p>The relief drive started three weeks ago, and up until now, the house committee has not even met once.</p>
   <p>Well, let us forget this aspect of the situation, provided that the Zionist leaders of Chicago look after their duties in the future. They will be <pb facs="5423972_7_0432.jpg" n="4"/>forgiven for their errors of the past, on condition that the same errors do not occur again. The past years must be very carefully analyzed. The campaign committee must be reorganized, new plans must be worked out, and everything must begin again. We must not charge the Chicago Jews with being unwilling to do their duty--on the contrary, they were very eager to co-operate.</p>
   <p>Every statesman must be an optimist if he wants to gain the confidence of his public with regard to national enterprises. The truth of the matter is that the loyalty of the Jewish patriots of Chicago is not a matter of fiction, but of fact.</p>
   <p>If the campaign committee performs its functions properly, it will be a success. We, therefore, ask the Zionist leaders of Chicago to forget their mistakes of the past, and to begin to work again correctly. If you undertake to do a certain task, please don't leave it unfinished. If, for some reason or other, a committee is unable to accomplish the work assigned to <pb facs="5423972_7_0433.jpg" n="5"/>it, such a committee should be enlarged. Under no circumstances should we allow the work to stop because one or more individuals are unable to attend [a meeting]. Instead of having a committee of seven people, we may have a committee of twenty-one; instead of authorizing the power and the responsibility to one chairman, two or more officers may be held responsible.</p>
   <p>The time is short; the situation demands that great things be achieved in the future. We Jews of Chicago are not only responsible to our own conscience and to the Zionist organization, but also to the American Jews, especially to the Jews of the Middle West.</p>
   <p>Should this drive fail, we must see to it that a second catastrophe is avoided. We sincerely hope that the leaders of the Chicago Zionist organization will not wait until every Tom, Dick, and Harry openly expresses his criticism of the present situation; it is not, [after all], incurable.</p>
   <p>The hearts of the Zionists are heavy with shame and despair over this deplorable <pb facs="5423972_7_0434.jpg" n="6"/>situation. The sooner the situation is corrected, the better it will be for the Zionist leaders of Chicago, for the Jews in general, and for the Zionist movement as a whole.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
