<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-25">Nov. 25, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the Federation and Who Are its Opposers?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article Six)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1641</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1641.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-11-25">Nov. 25, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE FEDERATION AND WHO ARE ITS OPPOSERS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Article Six)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Federation office is headed by the office manager, Mr. Isadore Siegel, who has installed a splendid system of keeping records. Anyone interested in civic work could inspect his books and know immediately what is being done in the Federation. Not only are the finances, the income and expense accounts open to public inspection, but a classification of the work done by hired help and directors is displayed so that every subscriber may know what goes on in the Federation.</p>
   <p>The subscribers are classified according to their promptness in paying their pledges. Those paying promptly are in the first class; the last class consists of those who refuse to honor their subscriptions. The <pb facs="5423972_7_1642.jpg" n="2"/>directors are classified according to their work for or against the Federation.</p>
   <p>In the official classification, the sixty-six directors are grouped into six classes. The classification ranges from those who fulfill all their duties, to those who aspire to be directors for the sake of position, honor and private gain or simply to hinder the Federation.</p>
   <p>It would probably seem strange to many people that some persons who oppose the Federation are directors of that body. Yet it is a fact; a very tragic fact. It is a fact that the Federation wishes to conceal, is ashamed of, but this does not alter the situation.</p>
   <p>Presenting the directors belonging to the various classes, according to the office records, we find the following:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1643.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Class I Directors who attend every meeting, not only fulfilling their duties in the many committees, but also fulfilling many other tasks for the Federation; carrying the entire responsibility of this institution. Among them are the following: B. Hurvitch, Samuel Philipson, Judge Harry M. Fisher, A. Levinson, I. Lurie, Morris Tuer, August Turner, Sam Ginsberg, and Rabbi S. Silver.</p>
   <p>Class II Directors attending all the meetings, executing their duties as officers, attending all committees of which they are members, and lending a helping hand when called upon by those in Class I. Among them are the following: James Davis, A. S. Rod, B. J. Schiff, Harry A. Lipsky, Rabbi N. Z. Budzinsky, Mrs. Benjamin Davis, Rabbi A. Epstein, Max M. Karshack, A. Margolis, Max Schulman, S. Weinstein, George Winsberg, Dr. A. B Tudleson, Charles Harron, S. J. Rosenblott, Ben-Zion Lazarovitch, N. Balaton, and Mrs. J. B. Malcus.</p>
   <p>Class III Directors who fulfill their duties as in Class II, but, because <pb facs="5423972_7_1644.jpg" n="4"/>of various reasons cannot devote much time or as much work as those in Class II.</p>
   <p>Among them are the following: Mrs. J. Stone, Dr. M. L. Aaron, Bernard Boomgarten, I. Beezark, Rabbi Ezriel Epstein, Rabbi M. Fisher, I. Kruger, Mrs. Isadore Natkin, A. Fink, M. Stone, Rabbi S. Shach, Mrs. E. J. Robin, Mrs. M. Tuer, Paul Vitkovsky, and J. Weinstein.</p>
   <p>Class IV Directors who attend meetings, take an occasional part in the discussions, forget the Federation the minute they leave the hall, and are directors in name only. They are: H. M. Barnett, Elias Epstein, William Farber, S. Eafa, Dr. Benjamin H. Bragstone, S. H. Cohen, E. Schulman, Mrs. S. Kantarsky, M. L. Fox, and S. Gretch.</p>
   <p>Class V Directors who never attend meetings, were elected because of their name or money, and have very little to do with the Federation. Among them <pb facs="5423972_7_1645.jpg" n="5"/>are: Louie Bomash, Philip Klofter, Herman Mish, and Congressman K. J. Sabath.</p>
   <p>Class VI Directors who were wished onto the Federation or who believed that connection with this institution would increase their prestige. Some came to meetings to look for something to find fault with; others being unable to do any good seek to hinder the Federation. Some present their complaints to the board of directors. They are the enemies of Chicago's Jewish community. Among them are all the directors we have not mentioned by name.</p>
   <p>To be just, to many directors of Class VI, we wish to state that this group is divided into two parts. The first group consists of those directors who, for different reasons, cannot or do not desire to participate in any activities. The second group consists of all the others. Having definite opinions not in accord with the majority, yet unable to understand these differences, disregarding the fact that an organization is governed by a majority, they seek, by various means, to disrupt the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1646.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The reader can, in the light of these revelations, understand how these blackmailers can become so arrogant as to demand $800 with the threat to blackmail, not only the Federation, but also its active members. We intend to disclose the identity of these blackmailers who are going from door to door advising people not to pay the money they subscribed. We shall also disclose the demands to the directors of the Federation. This article will appear in the next issue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
