<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-19">May 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Buy a Flower and Help Zion.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1419</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1419.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-19">May 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">BUY A FLOWER AND HELP ZION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today is Flower Day for the National Fund throughout America, and big preparations are being made for the sale of flowers in Chicago. Several hundred of the prettiest and most attractive of Zion's daughters, on every corner of greater Chicago as well as in local Jewish neighborhoods, will sell a flower to every Jew for the National Fund.</p>
   <p>Buy a flower, because the money received from the sale of every flower with which a pretty girl will grace every Jew's lapel, will buy a brick for the great Jewish building which is about to be erected in Palestine. Zionism is on the threshold of realizing its dream, and the National Fund, the most important branch of Zionism, must have more capital with which to buy more land in Palestine for the Jewish people. Therefore, the greater the amount the flowers bring in, the more land the Jews will be able to secure in Palestine. The flower sale will be under the direction of Mrs. Belle Zinn, who is <pb facs="5423972_7_1420.jpg" n="2"/>certain of a great success.</p>
   <p>This evening at the Gymnasium Hall of the Hebrew Institute, a large mass meeting will be held with two of the most prominent Zionist leaders as the main speakers. At this meeting an announcement will be made on the results of Flower Day.</p>
   <p>Both speakers are well-known to the great Jewish masses: Dr. Ben Zion Mosensohn, who has remained in Chicago for several weeks and who has greatly distinguished himself with his remarkable speeches, and more so with his convincing arguments for the ideals of Zionism; and Professor Nachum Slushtz, one of the greatest of Jewish scientists and research workers, who has been honored in Chicago in years past. Both have something of importance to tell the Jewish people. Professor Slushtz is the recognized leader of Zionism and Judaism in France. He is professor of Hebrew at the Sorbonne, in Paris. Mr. Max Shulman will also appear as a speaker. It is, therefore, certain that a huge gathering <pb facs="5423972_7_1421.jpg" n="3"/>will come out to hear these two famous speakers and Jewish leaders. The chairman of the evening will be Mr. Nathan D. Kaplan. Dr. Mosensohn addressed yesterday, in English, the members of the Covenant Club on"Russia and the Jewish Problem". The audience showed evident response to his logical arguments when he pointed out why every Jew must adhere to Zionism and why every Jew and Jewish organization must not and cannot be neutral toward the Jewish problem, which can be solved only through Zionism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
