<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-02">Mar. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">An Enthusiastic Meeting of the Trade Union Campaign for the Palestine Workers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-02">Mar. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AN ENTHUSIASTIC MEETING OF THE TRADE UNION CAMPAIGN FOR THE PALESTINE WORKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The campaign of the Chicago Jewish trade unions in behalf of the workers in Palestine opened officially Friday evening. There was an enthusiastic and sucessful mass meeting at the Roosevelt Hall. The guest of honor and the main speaker of the evening was Max Pine, the faithful veteran of the Jewish labor movement in America. There was a crowd of five hundred people in the hall, most of whom were intelligent workers, labor leaders, and intellectuals. This crowd proved how warmly the Jewish masses have responded to the appeal of the trade unions to raise Chicago's quota--twenty-five thousand dollars--of the campaign for one hundred and fifty thousand dollars in behalf of our idealistic comrades, the builders of a Jewish home in Palestine.</p>
   <p>The first speakers were Bagadansky, Sherman, and Lorber. They spoke briefly about the importance of the undertaking as the highest expression of the solidarity of Jewish workers and as a new era of consciousness in our labor <pb facs="5423972_7_0481.jpg" n="2"/>movement, which, for certain reasons, has always taken a passive attitude toward the work of our comrades in Palestine, who are creating and building.</p>
   <p>Max Pine was greeted with a storm of applause. The young looking and warm-hearted labor leader delivered a beautifully logical speech. He gave a cold political analysis, which destroyed all the arguments of our pseudo-socialists against the Palestine settlement and its active, resolute builders. "The old leaders and fighters of American-Jewish labor," said the speaker, "who, for over thirty years, have had the closest contact with the interests, struggles, and ideals of the workers, know very well what can and what cannot be done. The old, narrow-minded ideology of unfounded mistrust, of prejudice and antipathy to the national movement and its proletarian vanguard, has outlived its time.</p>
   <p>"Next to America, Palestine is today the greatest and most promising immigration center for the persecuted Jewish people. Fourteen thousand organized halutzim <pb facs="5423972_7_0482.jpg" n="3"/>work there energetically, and with Jewish determination and enthusiasm to create sound economic, social, and cultural positions for themselves. They are organized in co-operatives, united in trade unions, which are affiliated with The International Federation of Trade-Unions at Amsterdam, just as our unions are. We must stretch out a warm, brotherly hand to the labor unions in Palestine which have turned to the Jewish workers of America for technical and constructive help. The Jewish workers of America have helped all Jewish labor institutions abroad. Delegates from the Jewish workers of Poland, Bukovina, and Galicia have never left us empty-handed. The Jewish "International" once gave one hundred thousand dollars out of its treasury to the miners' union. There was no campaign, no collection; it simply gave the money. We have not yet seen the reverse happen: a non-Jewish union giving such assistance to a Jewish union.....The Jewish workers of America should, therefore, be the first to help their comrades in Palestine in their hour of need because, after all, they are still closer to us than the non-Jewish workers....."</p>
   <p>The audience listened with rapt attention to the speech of Mr. Max Pine. This <pb facs="5423972_7_0483.jpg" n="4"/>was the speech of a serious, sincere, high-principled labor leader to the workers. Pledge cards were distributed among the audience after the speech. The sum of five hundred dollars was thus raised for the Trade Union Fund For Palestine Workers.</p>
   <p>The labor organization gave a magnificent banquet last night in honor of Max Pine, at Rosenthal's Restaurant. The collection for the Trade Union Fund For Palestine Workers was continued successfully at the banquet.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the campaign will hold a conference today, at two o'clock in the afternoon, at the Socialist Center, 1224 South Albany Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
