<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-13">Apr. 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Wealth</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editoral)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-04-13">Apr. 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH WEALTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editoral)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fact that the Jewish people are the poorest in the world has been proved so many times by the written and spoken word, from the rostrum and in the Jewish press, that the repetition thereof should sound stale and familiar to everybody. Yet, we often hear the statement made by Christians as well as Jews that Jews are extremely wealthy. This assumption, as well as others does the Jew considerable harm. [This is especially true] when the economic plight of the Jews is being widely discussed; the world does not wish to hear of it. The world believes that the Jews have wealth enough to help themselves.</p>
   <p>In reality however, where can you find another people as helpless as the Jews? Individual Jews are millionaires in this or that country, thereby making the Jews conspicuous in the eyes of the world. Because of this handful, the millions who are struggling for an existence are overlooked.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1504.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is no limit to the extent of Jewish poverty. Even the smallest and poorest nation, for example Montenegro, with a population of two and one half millions, has established enough credit to get a loan of several millions of dollars. The Jews however are unable to obtain a loan amounting to a broken farthing, because they have no credit in the world; they possess no national wealth to serve as security.</p>
   <p>With the advent of the Zionist organization, this situation has changed. The Jewish Colonial Bank and The National Fund with its subsidiary branches represent a fortune. It is a very small fortune for a nation of 13,000,000 nevertheless it belongs to the entire people. In peace times the Colonial Bank could procure a loan if it were necessary. The National Fund could do likewise. We must remember that this fortune has been built in less than twenty years. This is only the beginning of a fortune which must grow. The Jewish people are not yet dead. Zionism lives in the hearts of Jews, and all give to public charities. [For this reason alone,] the foundation which our modern pioneers have laid in Palestine is important to us.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1505.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Yeshub (collective colony) is still small, but the Jewish Colonization in Palestine represents [an achievement] unparalleled in the nineteen hundred years of Jewish history. It is the child of our hopes. [This colony in our ancient homeland, which constitutes the basis of our national wealth, deserves our wholehearted support.]</p>
   <p>For the last year and a half our courageous pioneers in Palestine have been struggling against the poverty produced by the World War and the devastation left by the locusts. As if [they were part of] the sacred ground, they stand on guard, protecting the Jewish wealth. They merit the admiration and support of all Jews, because their toil and their efforts go for all the people.</p>
   <p>But because of the dire misfortune endured by the wide masses in Europe, we often overlook the small handful of 85,000 people in Palestine. The Provisional Committee of the Zionist organization is the only body which seeks aid for them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1506.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Each month it becomes more difficult. Reports coming from Palestine indicate that life becomes more unbearable each day. The cost of living soars as high as it does in other war-ridden countries. Not less than $20,000 a month is required to maintain Palestine in this time of war.</p>
   <p>The appeal coming from the colonies in Palestine should resound in the hearts of all Jews. It not only means the maintenance of people who are starving, but also the preservation of the work of two generations of Jews and the possibility of further constructive work for the entire race.</p>
   <p>Vast sums are needed to maintain the values created by the Yeshub which will prevent the Jewish national wealth from going to ruin.</p>
   <p>Therefore may the Jews harken unto the voice of Hosannah in these trying times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
