<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-04">Mar. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Moes Chitim Time</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1590</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1590.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-03-04">Mar. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MOES CHITIM TIME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Committee, to raise Moes Chitim [money donated to provide the poor with food for Passover] in order that there be ample means to provide the indigent Jews with all necessaries for Passover, announced that it started its task of collecting money. It is of great importance that the Jewish public become interested in the work of the United Committee.</p>
   <p>Above everything, it is important that all Moes Chitim monies flow to one central authority, and that all contributions be made as early as possible. Selfishness is a curse upon the Jewish community in Chicago. There are always big-hearted people who want to do good deeds, and they make a collection calling it Moes Chitim. Regardless of how well their intentions are, these people do more harm than good. The result is that good-hearted people are troubled by a number of such as we should not appease. And on the other hand, it serves as a good pretext to those who wish to evade Moes Chitim.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1591.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All this would still not be so bad. The greatest trouble lies in the division of Moes Chitim, which results into allotting those who are mostly in need the least amounts. This is a fact well-known to those who are engaged in the distribution of Moes Chitim, and the blame lies upon the good people, who cannot, in any event, adapt themselves to the conditions, which require that we collaborate in Jewish unity for the good and best of those whom we must provide with means in order that they celebrate that great Jewish liberating holiday.</p>
   <p>A United Committee is more urgent this year than ever before. We have had a hard winter. Hundreds of families, which used to pull through the winter in some way and then provide themselves with the Passover necessaries out of the remaining resources, were forced to resort to charity during midwinter.</p>
   <p>May this be known to the Chicago Jewry, and when the committee of United Moes Chitim shall call for contributions, let's respond as Jews should, with large contributions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
