<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-09">Jan. 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-09">Jan. 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It will be of interest to my readers to learn that three years ago, Dr. Emil G. Hirsch and I agreed to publish jointly a Jewish monthly in English. It was planned that we were both to write on the same issues--he, from his point of view and I, from my point of view. The monthly was to reflect two extremes within the Jewish community, assimilation and nationalism.</p>
   <p>Everything was agreed upon and I was ready to take up the work, but Dr. Hirsch suddenly got cold feet and changed his mind. A few days after our agreement was made, he informed me, through a letter, that he withdrew from the plan. He felt that he would derive no pleasure from a literary partnership with me.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0730.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>My dear synagogue presidents have become engaged in the great task of raising a quarter-million dollars for the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization].</p>
   <p>If they adhere to this plan, I am afraid that they will raise nothing. But if they plan on raising one hundred thousand dollars, and do not theorize but put their plan into action, I am convinced that they can actually raise from seventy-five to one hundred thousand dollars because there are now approximately seven or eight thousand organized Jews who attend the synagogues. These Jews belong to the middle class and none will hesitate to give from ten to twenty-five dollars for the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <p>The only question is how can we reach these Jews? How shall we speak to them? How can we organize one hundred teams who will go out and do the work? If the presidents of synagogues will organize teams for the Keren Hayesod, then they will prove that the Chicago Orthodoxy is a great factor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
