<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-06-27">June 27, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Morris Levin Declines from Hebrew Institute.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0291</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0291.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-06-27">June 27, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">DR. MORRIS LEVIN DECLINES FROM HEBREW INSTITUTE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of the directors of the Hebrew Institute, it was announced that Dr. Morris Levin, rabbi of People's Synagogue, turned down the agreement, which was extended to him by the Hebrew Institute, in order that he might be able to continue his work as rabbi and principal of the Hebrew school.</p>
   <p>Dr. Rabbi Levin, refused to renew the contract and declared that he does not find a large enough field, in Chicago to do the work which he would like to do. Being nationalistically inclined he finds the Zionist movement too weak to absorb his energies; the Hebrew school, to which he devoted his entire energy, can not fulfill his aims, because <pb facs="5423972_7_0292.jpg" n="2"/>the Jews of Chicago still are not permanent residents. Most of them move around, and therefore a small number of students were able to attend the Hebrew school during the three years of its existence. The synagogue in the Hebrew Institute, also, does not stand upon a strong foundation. The transformation from a synagogue on Sabbath into a dance hall on Sunday does not jibe with his ideas, and therefore, he has determined to go to New York, where he will encounter a broader field for his activities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
