<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-13">Sept. 13, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Peoples' Relief Condemns the Left-Wing Blackmailers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0753</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0753.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-09-13">Sept. 13, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLES' RELIEF CONDEMNS THE LEFT-WING BLACKMAILERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is well known that the left-wing newspaper [Editor's note: The newspaper, is probably the Daily Jewish Freiheit, a communist paper published in New York] seeks to divide and destroy the Jewish labor movement in America, and that it attacks, in a sordid manner, all those who are connected with the labor movement. On Thursday, September 7, the Chicago representative of this newspaper published a filthy article about one of the oldest and most devoted workers in the Socialist and labor movements in Chicago. It is a piece of libel written in an abominable manner. In it he stated, intentionally, that Comrade Leon Hanock, who is the secretary of the Chicago United Hebrew Trades, occupies, at the same time, a paid position in the office of the Chicago Peoples' Relief.</p>
   <p>We, the members of the Peoples' Relief Executive met last Monday evening, September 11, and heard the contents of that filthy article read. We decided to express our most severe condemnation of the action of that newspaper. Moreover, we wish to declare that Comrade Hanock voluntarily offered a few hours <pb facs="5423972_7_0754.jpg" n="2"/>of his free time to this office (until a permanent manager will be engaged). He did not receive one cent pay for this work. The assertion that Comrade Hanock received a salary from the Peoples' Relief is as false as the second statement by that libelous writer--that the Peoples' Relief held a tag day in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We see in this libelous action no other aim than that of besmirching the reputation of Leon Hanock. We condemn this act as the lowest form of indecency. We refute the unreliable charges against Comrade Hanock and the Peoples' Relief as false and vile accusations.</p>
   <p>A. Lurie, chairman,</p>
   <p>Chicago Peoples' Relief.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
