<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-11">September 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Good Plan.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1693</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1693.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-09-11">September 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A GOOD PLAN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his article on Jews in last Sunday's edition of the Chicago Tribune, Mr. Henry M. Hied mentions the fact that it is a tradition among our German Jews to refer to the book of the Associated Jewish Charities and find out ones rating, when in need of information of this particular character. When someone wishes to join a Jewish club or become active in any Jewish affair, he must, first of all, be in good standing with the Associated Jewish Charities.</p>
   <p>It would be desirable if this plan were followed out by our West Side so-called orthodox Jews. It is not merely a right, but an obligation upon each organization, that whenever anyone wishes to join the organization, to investigate to what extent he is suitable, considering his financial <pb facs="5423972_7_1694.jpg" n="2"/>circumstances and to find out how much he contributes to the Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities.</p>
   <p>The man who is financially well-off and does not want to assist those who are in need of help, is certainly an undesirable and an unsuitable member in any society. On the other hand, one, who is so poor that he is unable to render any aid - a man who can barely get along himself - surely cannot spend his time with social obligations and can only become a member of an organization which was established for the purpose of helping its members.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, we have overlooked this principle. It is unbelievable, that it is a fact that there are many directors in our charitable institutions, who are not members of the Federation. There are many presidents of synagogues <pb facs="5423972_7_1695.jpg" n="3"/>and lodges, officers of various institutions, who did not even pledge to contribute anything to the Federation, or who pledged but did not contribute. These people have no moral right whatsoever to hold the positions which they occupy.</p>
   <p>It is no more than right for a director of an institution to at least assist the institution financially. The way in which the various charitable institutions are now being financed, one who is no subscriber to the Federation is excluded from the possibility of helping any charity institution, and consequently a non-subscriber is not a member of any charity institution, then how can one be a director?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1696.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The men who are looking for a variety of honors, e. g., chairmanship at meetings, political offices, to preside at eulogies, should also be looked up in the Federation's Book. We should heed our German brethren in this matter. It is a good plan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
