<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-09-06">September 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The New Million Dollar Home. the Jewish People's Inistitute</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Spivak.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Daily Forward</title>,
<date when="1927-09-06">September 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW MILLION DOLLAR HOME. THE JEWISH PEOPLE'S INISTITUTE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Spivak.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the many institutions that have shifted to the Lawndale District in the past few years, is now added the magnificent edifice of the Jewish People's Institute, (former Hebrew Institute), at Douglas Boulevard and St. Louis Avenue, which was recently opened to the public and which cost one million dollars......</p>
   <p>Before delving into any description of the various divisions in the new building of the Jewish People's Institute, it is worthy to pause, some-what, and describe the conditions that have recently changed and, also the new type of Jew that has developed and who requires new methods in the so-called social work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0166.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the time, twenty years ago, when the Hebrew Institute commenced its activities, the majority of Jews in Chicago were immigrants, who were not accustomed to the economic and social conditions of the country. They were like plants that were weeded out of one place and not transplanted in another place. And just as weeded-out plants begin to wither if they are not immediately replanted in suitable soil, so would many immigrants have remained deficient economically, socially, and culturally if they had not been adjusted to the new conditions. However, the majority of Jewish immigrants were promptly replanted and their roots were absorbed in the new American soil. At that time, the social workers and the so-called "Americanizers" helped the immigrants to a certain degree. But not all of them (social workers) have applied the best and most favorable methods.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0167.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In addition to this, the question of "we" and "they" prevailed at that time. "We," the Eastern European immigrant Jews, who entered America with disturbed souls and "they", the calm, patient, wealthy Jews of Western Europe. "We" were the Jews that have a "monopoly" on the Jewish traditions and on mores, "they," the German Jews, were only related to their Jewish brothers by throwing sops to them.</p>
   <p>But after the war the question of the Jewish "tribes" was solved automatically. A great number of Eastern Jews became wealthy and well Americanized so that the partition between the two so-called Jewish "tribes" began to fall and they assimilated through "intermarriages" the equal cultural and social conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0168.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Regarding the service and management of the Jewish People's Institute, it must be said that, even at that time when the partition between the "German" and "Russian" Jews was strong, it applied, through its able superintendent, Mr. Seman, such methods as lent dignity to the Institution, and it was recognized as a cultural andsocial center. Many young Jewish doctors, dentists, lawyers, engineers, electrical technicians, and architects, should be thankful to the Jewish People's Institute for their elementary education. Many cultural and charity institutions were revived there. It was and will remain the center or the clearing house of most of the Chicago Jewish activities.</p>
   <p>The following activities and incidents are concentrated in the present Jewish People's Institute:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0169.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Department of English; foreign languages; physical culture; historical and sociology studies; high school; elementary evening school; commercial school; extention courses in cooperation with the Chicago University; Jewish education; a library, possessing all books on Jewish problems and Jewish culture; a museum of Jewish antiques; Jewish music; Jewish dramatic art in English; Jewish dramatic art under the direction of the Jewish Literary and Dramatic Society; music; dancing classes; clubs and social activities; camps; summer work andplay grounds; scholarships for higher education; women's auxiliary; women's clubs; domestic science; department of civics; and department of citizenship.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0170.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>These enumerated activities are conducted in various class rooms, gymnasium theater, studios and roof garden which are distinguished by bearing the names of our great thinkers and leaders, who elaborated and deepened Jewish ideology.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
