<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-11-14">Nov. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Judaize and Amalgamate the Charities</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0972</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0972.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-11-14">Nov. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">JUDAIZE AND AMALGAMATE THE CHARITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have in Chicago two charitable bodies for Jewish relief work within the community, the Federated Orthodox Charities and the Associated Charities. Both these organizations are large bodies with large incomes and both have their separate budgets and separate administrative personnel. Yet both practically serve the same ends. Here is a duplication, not only wasteful, but really uncalled for. The same persons are directors on both sides, very often the same persons contribute equally to both; the two associations are ready to serve the same purpose, or can be made to serve the same purpose. Then why this duplication and waste of public funds and of effort, both the latter of which might be utilized to the good ends of either greater relief to the community or, if necessary, to the relief of our brethren in Europe and elsewhere <pb facs="5423972_7_0973.jpg" n="2"/>requiring this relief? Failure to eliminate this waste involved in the duplication of effort is a condemnation of our moral integrity and humane being. If we are sincere in our efforts, we cannot but realize that these times are too tragic to permit ourselves to waste our available funds by duplication of efforts. We venture to say that if the mass of our community were thoroughly alive to the significance of this public waste, they would compel a merger, and we are of the opinion that this merger must take place sooner or later. Then why not now?</p>
   <p>The public men of our community who are aware of these conditions should take steps toward this merger as soon as possible and should call together such a body of men as could be expected to make this merger possible. The sooner this is accomplished the better for the wholesomeness of our communal life and for our opportunity for greater service in behalf of our unfortunate brethren across the Atlantic.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0974.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this connection, however, it is well to observe a few cardinal principles essential to the proper realization of our aim. The Federated Orthodox Charities believe that the private religious feelings of every individual receiving relief are sacred and that it were altogether uncharitable to prevent such individuals from the free observance of their beliefs. Thus, in an old people's home it should be altogether within the privilege of the inmates to pray according to their conscience and to eat kashruth [kosher food] and observe all the dietary laws, if this be their wish. The same holds true of the hospital and of every place and manner of relief. In Europe, in innumerable instances, our famished brethren have refused the gifts of food proffered them and preferred to continue their hunger fast, rather than to violate the principles of their faith. Shall we here assert ourselves the rulers of the conscience of our unfortunate brethren within our own community and act otherwise? Would not many of our own fathers and mothers act in the spirit of these men and women?</p>
   <p>True charity is not merely physical relief but is also bound up with moral amelioration. You cannot outrage and degrade the conscience of those you help; <pb facs="5423972_7_0975.jpg" n="4"/>otherwise your charity is unworthy of the name. The free exercise of another's religious feelings is not to be denied, and we, last of all, should be the ones to deny it, if we but remember the sufferings of two thousand years or more that we have undergone because of these convictions, and which our brethren in many parts of the world are undergoing still for them.</p>
   <p>These few moral principles are unquestionably to be considered, and any proper consideration of them can lead but to one conclusion: that they should be observed. The rest should be easier still. There is nothing that stands in the way of a merger of the two bodies, and this amalgamation should take place within the shortest time possible, if we have a humane respect for the needs of our community and those of our brethren in the countries where the fate of our people is less fortunate than is our own here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
