<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-04">Aug. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Zionist Appeal for the National Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-04">Aug. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ZIONIST APPEAL FOR THE NATIONAL FUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Zionist Organization of New York makes the following appeal to the Jews of America: "We ask our good brothers throughout the country to respond generously to the appeal of the Jewish National Fund. Everyone knows the noble purpose of this great institution--the redemption of our Holy Land and its restoration. The custom of aiding the National Fund at Tisha Be-av, the day we mourn the destruction of the Temple, has become an accepted fact by Jews in all countries. It is fitting and proper that such a custom, which is a great aid to our people in the rebuilding of our holy land, be continued....." This appeal is signed by some of the most famous rabbis in the country.</p>
   <p>The Jewish National Fund proposes: To purchase the land of Palestine as soon as possible, as the property of all the people, so that every Jew who is physically able and willing to work the soil of the Jewish land may receive a plot <pb facs="5423972_7_1267.jpg" n="2"/>of ground at a reasonable price, and so that no land shall remain idle, in the hands of monopolists or speculators.</p>
   <p>In helping the Jewish National Fund, you are helping to rebuild the Jewish national homeland, and you also make possible its reconstruction in the ancient Jewish spirit of social justice.</p>
   <p>Today before Kinoth [Lamentations--prayers recited on Tisha Be-av] rabbis and speakers, Zionists and Mizrachists, in all synagogues, will appeal for contributions to the Jewish National Fund. The public is expected to contribute generously. Those who will not be present in the synagogues, are asked to send their contributions to the following chairmen of the National Fund in the Zionist districts: Lawndale District: B. Greenberg, 3716 Douglas Boulevard; West Side: H. Krantz, 810 Ashland Boulovard; North and Northwest Side, P. Shomer, 2437 Division Street; South Side: M. Goodman, 114 East 59th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
