<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-10">Oct. 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">To the Jewish Public.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1687</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1687.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-10-10">Oct. 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE JEWISH PUBLIC.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities in taking over the finances of all the Jewish institutions for the needy, was well aware of the heavy task it was undertaking. But knowing and understanding the Chicago Jewish community, it was certain that every Jew would do what he could to aid in the work. We knew that each and every Chicago Jew would volunteer his time, work, and money, for this huge undertaking, which the community has established in honor of their Judaism, and for the good of those unfortunates who must ask for charity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1688.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The nine months since this Federation has existed were sufficient to prove that we have made no mistake in the generosity, willingness and faithfulness of the Chicago Jew. Tonight, we prepare to go to Kol Widre. Our books show that contributions for these months amounted to more than a hundred thousand dollars. It has been marvelous how men, women and children came to this office with their small or large donations for this worthy cause.</p>
   <p>Our people should be proud to know the sense of responsibility they possess. It is an honor to be a Jew, a brother of these hundreds of people who came here to give their share.</p>
   <p>Such assurance from the great Chicago Jewish community gives us the courage again to approach the people on behalf of all the unfortunates. We wish to bring to your attention that the expenditures of these worthy institutions have greatly increased this year. The orphanage has this year 100 orphans more than last year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1689.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Old People's Home had a new wing built and an increased number of inmates; The Maimonides Hospital has just opened this year; the Hachnesess Urcheem was placed on a modern basis. More aid was extended to the Lechem Loreveem and the West Side Ladies Charity Society; the Talmud Torahs were expanded and a new one will soon be built. We will have to have more money for the upkeep. Thus although our income amounted to the colossal sum of over a hundred thousand dollars, yet our expenditures amounted to over one hundred and ten thousand dollars. We feel certain that Chicago Jews will pay this deficit and therefore take the liberty to say a few words now at the Kol Nidre.</p>
   <p>It has always been the custom on the eve of Yom Kippur for every synagogue to collect poor funds. No one starts his prayers before he has contributed something. This year instead of individual collection funds there will be only one, to include them all. This will be the Federation contribution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1690.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Jews of Chicago: Jews are coming to Kol Nidre with broken hearts. Everywhere, regardless of where a Jew may be, his heart and soul are at the Kiev Trial where the blood accusation is in process. Let us call on God tonight, to pray and repent and be charitable, that in so doing we may redeem Mandel Bailis through our generosity. In his honor let us fill the coffers of the Federation with money, just as our eyes are full of tears and our synagogues are full of prayers. Thus we may help those we can as God will help our folk Israel and enlighten our sorrows from accusations and bring us a good New Year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1691.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>With Respect.</p>
   <p>B. Horovitch, president; Samuel Philipson, first vice president; James Davis, second vice president; A. S. Rova, third vice president; B. J. Schif, treasurer; Harry A. Lipsky, recording secretary; Mrs. Julius Stone, financial secretary; Harry M. Fisher, chairman of office committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
