<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-24">Aug. 24, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-24">Aug. 24, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The plan to send clothes and food to the unfortunate Jews in Galicia, Poland, and Lithuania originated in Chicago. Chicago's Jewish relief representatives were the ones who introduced this plan before the Joint Distribution Committee for discussion, and succeeded in having the subcommittee of the great relief conference, held last Sunday in New York, approve the plan.</p>
   <p>From the brief telegram from New York, published last Friday in the Courier, our readers, naturally, obtained a very sketchy idea of the plan. Now we are in a position to print a detailed report.</p>
   <p>In order to reach the starving Jews of Europe more quickly, the Joint Distribution Committee will establish depots in the various cities of Poland, Galicia, and Lithuania. These depots will be supplied with the best food from America. When a Chicago Jew, who is anxious to have his relative or some member of his family in Europe receive a parcel of food, all he has to do is to buy a coupon for any desired amount from the local Jewish Relief Committee, 720 West Twelfth Street, <pb facs="5423972_7_1242.jpg" n="2"/>Room 88. Then he must send the coupon to the designated party, and in this way, his relative will be able to obtain the parcel of food.</p>
   <p>Subagents will be appointed in many of the smaller cities of the above-mentioned countries. These subagents will supervise the delivery of the food parcels.</p>
   <p>It is a marvelous plan to feed the hungry who have relatives here. It will serve a twofold purpose: it will decrease the enormous amount of relief work and it will guarantee that those to whom parcels of food are sent, will get them.</p>
   <p>It is now appropriate that we credit the following gentlemen who formulated this plan at the last meeting of the Joint Relief Committee, with the result that the Joint Distribution Committee accepted the plan and put it into practice. The gentlemen are: B. Horwich, Rabbi Ephraim Epstein, Rabbi Saul Silber, M. P. Ginsburg, Dr. S. M. Melamed, S. J. Rosenblatt, Max Shulman, Isadore Liederman, Julius Savitsky, Dr. George Sultan, J. Weiser, Samuel Ginsburg, Nathan Seifer, I. Lassers, J. Lassers, Max Abel. Mr. B. Horwich, who reported the plan in New York, as it was prepared in written form by Mr. Julius Savitsky, was appointed by Mr. Felix Warburg as chairman of the subcommittee to direct the whole work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1243.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The transport of food, which the Chicago Joint Relief Committee undertook to send about October 16, for the hungry Jews, will be distributed free of charge. Private parcels can be sent with this transport, but for that purpose it is necessary to inquire at the office of the Joint Relief Committee, 720 West Twelfth Street.</p>
   <p>American Jews are congratulating the Chicago Joint Relief Committee for its plan to feed the hungry, which is the most practical plan under the circumstances.</p>
   <p>The handful of Jewish women of the Douglas Park neighborhood have purchased the building at 1300 Independence Boulevard and are seeking to transform it into a day nursery for children whose mothers are compelled to work during the day. These philanthropic women appeal to the Jewish public for assistance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1244.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The handful of women have already paid down several thousand dollars on the building. Now they need at least two thousand dollars to arrange everything properly.</p>
   <p>Two thousand dollars is a very small sum and we trust that the welfare women of this neighborhood will furnish the required sum. These women should be among the first to understand and feel the need for such an institution. If they will only consider the position of a mother whose husband lies sick, or is dead, and she, rather than to earn a living and perhaps attain luxury in a "different" way, is satisfied to earn an honest living--by working. The unfortunate woman in order to be able to do her work, must have a peaceful mind and she cannot have one knowing that her children are tramping around in the streets or are at home without food or a drop of milk.</p>
   <p>Jewish welfare momen of the West Side! Fulfill your duty toward your sisters, who are not as fortunate as you are. Help them to remain honest and devoted mothers to their children. Send your contributions to the above-mentioned address--the sooner the better. Otherwise the important institution cannot be opened on December 7, as planned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
