<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-12">Mar. 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">An Evening at the Bazaar in the Labor Lyceum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0438</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0438.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-12">Mar. 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">AN EVENING AT THE BAZAAR IN THE LABOR LYCEUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Labor Lyceum is the scene of a bazaar being given to help the Jews of Russia and Poland.</p>
   <p>It is a real Jewish fair, very lively and noisy. This noise adds much color and glamor to the fair and makes it look genuinely Yiddish.</p>
   <p>Those who come from the old country still remember the holiday fairs of Russia.</p>
   <p>Elaborate fairs were held there yearly and even monthly, in cities and towns. The Jews participated in the fairs.</p>
   <p>The Jew as a broker and merchant always went to the fairs, in fact he practically lived in them. When one fair closed he immediately went on to the next one.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0439.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the fair now in progress here, one helps a million helpless Jews of Biro Bidjan, Poland, and Roumania.</p>
   <p>The huge hall of the Labor Lyceum is beautifully decorated and illuminated with numerous bright lights that add cheer and gayety to the place.</p>
   <p>The booths are displaying many lovely articles, beautifully displayed and reasonably priced.</p>
   <p>There is an attractive grocery booth and a dairy booth with a tempting display. Another booth shows smoked meats and long, polished, brown salamies that make your mouth water. Next to this booth is a display of sweets, including delicious candies, chocolates, cigars and cigarettes. There is a jewelry booth where dazzling jewels sparkle and almost blind you; curios and antiques are also sold there. Next is a paint store where paints, varnishes, and wall papers are sold almost for nothing. This really adds color to the bazaar. There are <pb facs="5423972_7_0440.jpg" n="3"/>beautiful garments for men and women priced to fit any purse.</p>
   <p>The reporter observed a woman bargaining while buying a dress. This lady argued that since the garment was donated she should be able to buy it at her own price. She also added sarcastically that the clerk would not loose his grandmother's fortune by reducing the marked price a little.</p>
   <p>Furs, radios and furniture are sold at the bazaar.</p>
   <p>In the restaurant, wholesome meals are served very reasonably, accompanied by pleasant entertainment. While eating, one is likely to forget for a moment, that there are unfortunate Jews on the other side of the ocean who have not a thing to eat. Before your eyes you see only happiness and cheer, and all your troubles vanish in this holiday atmosphere.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
