<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-11-20">Nov. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Sympathy of Jews in America - for Jewish War Sufferers Abroad.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-11-20">Nov. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">SYMPATHY OF JEWS IN AMERICA - FOR JEWISH WAR SUFFERERS ABROAD.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The suffering of Jews in the warring countries has aroused sympathy among American Jews, especially among the Chicago Jews.</p>
   <p>Nearly every countryman, verein and society is organizing to raise funds to help the needy of the town or city from which they came. The unity and sympathy among Jews prove very prominent in critical times like this. It is needless to say that all efforts must be made fruitful, to help these activities bring large sums of money. The need among the Jews of Russia, Germany, Austria, Hungary, and Turkey is great, and all the money we can raise, regardless how large the sums, may yet not be sufficient to cover the damages that the Jews in the warring countries have suffered.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1566.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Millions will be required to feed the millions of hungry Jews. It will require a fortune to provide for the children who are being orphaned, by losing their fathers in the army. There is also a large number of widows and deserted wives, and they look only to America for help.</p>
   <p>Chicago is the second largest community in America and her share will amount to a large sum of money, that will have to be raised through direct contributions by well to do people, societies and through indirect sources, affairs of various sorts, theatrical benefits, dances, parties, lectures, concerts, recitals, etc.</p>
   <p>It is a pity that the large Jewish national organizations do not unite in this relief work. There is some disagreement among them. Individual appeals are made by the B'Nai B'Rith, American Jewish Committee, United Orthodox Organizations, Radical Societies, Zion Organizations, and smaller bodies, such as the Poale Zion, Socialists, Territorialists and all others that have organized here of late.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
