<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-25">Aug. 25, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A Voice Is Calling</title><title level="a" type="sub">To Presidents of All Mizrachi Organizations and Synagogues; to All Rabbis, Lecturers, Preachers in Canada and the United States!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-25">Aug. 25, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A VOICE IS CALLING</title><title level="a" type="sub">To Presidents of All Mizrachi Organizations and Synagogues; to All Rabbis, Lecturers, Preachers in Canada and The United States!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The horrible World War visited destruction upon many Jewish Communities in both Europe and Palestine, affecting our brethren in those places not only physically but also spiritually. It shattered and destroyed many of our theological colleges and Talmud Torahs [Hebrew Schools] and other such institutions that were an honor and a pride to our people. The destruction also reached our Holy Land--Palestine--but thanks to the holiness of our land, all the theological colleges and Talmud Torahs, the institutions of charity and mercy of the old settlement remain in existence and are functioning as before, despite the material suffering they are now undergoing.</p>
   <p>In our holy city, Jerusalem, there are dozens of Talmud Torahs and theological colleges where thousands of Jewish children, both young and old, are <pb facs="5423972_7_1477.jpg" n="2"/>brought up in the Spirit of our Holy Scriptures; there are dozens of institutions of charity and mercy that house thousands of aged, destitute, infirm people, widows and orphans. All these institutions, the Talmud Torahs, the theological colleges, hospitals, homes for the aged, orphanages, homes for the blind in Jerusalem and in other holy cities such as Chevron, Zphath and Tiberia, existed and thrived on miracles even prior to the war. The expenses of these institutions were, in good times, covered by temporary donations collected in all corners of the Diaspora by authorized collectors, and even by social workers who were deeply affected by, and unflinchingly loyal to the old settlement and its institutions in the Holy Land. There was no organization outside of Palestine to raise the necessary funds for the maintenance of such institutions. But the people themselves, men and women, young and old, held it their sacred duty to aid always the old settlement which is so dear and sacred to all Jewish people. In this way these institutions continued to exist. But now that the World War has broken out, our brethren in Europe, who themselves are the victims of destruction and hunger, are unable to help support these institutions of <pb facs="5423972_7_1478.jpg" n="3"/>the old settlement in Palestine. Thus these institutions have begun to suffer terrible and dreadful vicissitudes; nevertheless, they exist. Their material condition is very tragic. The contributions for their support, collected in America, are insufficient. Both the teachers and students in the Talmud Torahs and theological colleges in Palestine need food, as do the aged, the infirm, the widows and orphans.</p>
   <p>The members of the Mizrachi here in America recognized and understood this. And our third [Mizrachi] convention in Chicago, decided to support all Talmud Torahs and charitable institutions in the old settlement in Palestine by every means possible. At a special meeting called by the above-mentioned members, the following was decided:</p>
   <p>To set aside this Sabbath as a Relief Day for the old settlement. Rabbis, lecturers, speakers and welfare workers in Canada and America are requested to encourage and urge all Jews to help the charitable and religious institutions of our old settlement in our Holy Land. Also on Sunday a collection <pb facs="5423972_7_1479.jpg" n="4"/>from house to house should be made on behalf of these sacred institutions.</p>
   <p>We now appeal to all our members, to all rabbis and presidents of synagogues that each of them should see to it that this resolution is carried through in his respective city and in his congregation and locality. May these days, this Sabbath and Sunday, be dedicated to the institutions of the Torah, to charity and compassion for the old settlement in our Holy Land. May everyone of us share responsibility in this duty to the old settlement which has been the foundation of all our hopes and of our whole future in Palestine.</p>
   <p>At a time when we are shedding tears and asking the Lord, blessed be His name, for a year of Redemption and Salvation, let us remember those who were the first to lay the foundation for the Redemption of our Holy Land. For this act, the Lord, blessed be His name, will accept our prayers, and we will have a good year, a year of salvation and consolation, a year of Redemption with honors and blessings on Zion and Jerusalem.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1480.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Local Executive Board of the Mizrachi.</p>
   <p>P. S. All money collected should be sent directly to the Mizrachi Bureaus. [Translator's note: The Mizrachi is the orthodox wing of the Zionist movement.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
