<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1928-01-23">January 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Conference Determines to Raise Ten Thousand Dollars for Hias Drive for Immigrants.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1928-01-23">January 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR CONFERENCE DETERMINES TO RAISE TEN THOUSAND DOLLARS FOR HIAS DRIVE FOR IMMIGRANTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon a conference was held at the Labor Lyceum of delegates from the Workmen's Circle branches, United Hebrew Trade Unions, Poale Zion, Jewish National Workers Alliance, and other progressive organizations and it was unanimously decided to raise the sum of ten thousand dollars towards the quota of fifty thousand dollars, which must be raised in Chicago for the Hias (Hebrew Sheltering Home).</p>
   <p>Comrade L. Benenson opened the Congress explaining the purpose of the representatives of the various organizations being called here. He introduced Dr. Friedlaender of the Hias, who presented photographs of immigrants, and of the work that the Hias does to help the immigrants in their roaming around the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0456.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Copeland, the president of the Chicago branch of the Hias, addressed the conference and declared how fortunate he feels to see the workers helping the Hias, which is the greatest source of help for the unfortunate immigrants.</p>
   <p>M. Block, the representative of the Hias of New York, pictured the condition of the wandering Jews who have no refuge, and the Hias is the only organization that comes to their assistance.</p>
   <p>The Hias organization began a million dollar drive by selling one dollar certificates. All the proceeds of these one dollar certificates go to help the immigrants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0457.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Everyone is urged to buy a one dollar certificate to help the Hias to assist the immigrants who are going to settle in Argentine, Brazil and other South American cities where the Jews are invited to settle.</p>
   <p>Mr. Block stated that Chicago Jewry is expected to raise fifty thousand dollars and that the labor organizations must assist in raising a part of that quota by selling these one dollar certificates.</p>
   <p>After the Hias representative had explained the importance of helping raise this fund, the conference then organized to carry on this work in the labor organizations. Comrade Benenson was elected chairman and Comrade Ziskind-secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0458.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The chairman appointed a credentials committee, as follows: Roofer, Siegel, Sosewitz, Cohen, and Calish.</p>
   <p>The committee reported that there were sixty-six delegates, representing the Workmen's Circle branches, trade unions, Poale Zionists, Jewish National Workers Alliance, United Hebrew Trades, and the Central Committee of the Alliance Relief Organizations.</p>
   <p>It was determined that ten thousand of the fifty thousand dollars shall be the share raised by the labor organizations. In order that this work may not be delayed for another day, it was determined that the Executive meet tonight in the Lyceum, to work out plans to carry on this drive among the organization.</p>
   <p>All the delegates in the committee of fifteen and the central bodies are urged to come to the meeting tonight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
