<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-07">Aug. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Will Soon Send a Ship with Food and Clothing to Poland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-07">Aug. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO WILL SOON SEND A SHIP WITH FOOD AND CLOTHING TO POLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, vice-chairman of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee, invited a number of prominent businessmen to a luncheon yesterday at the College Inn. Present were: Mr. B. Horwich, Major Abel Davis, S. J. Rosenblatt, Isadore Liederman, Max Shulman, Isaac Lassers of Chicago Heights, J. Lassers, A. S. Roe, J. F. Hodesman, Max Abel, Julius Savetsky, Leo Beresniac, Max Korshak, Nathan Kopal, Myer Abrams, H. Steinberg, Frank Grossman, J. Cohen, Philip Goldberg, and others.</p>
   <p>After Mr. B. Horwich and Major Davis told of their experiences in Poland, and described the tragic condition of the Jewish community there, those present undertook to send carloads of food and clothing to Poland, besides donating huge sums of money so that Chicago would be able to send a food ship to the war sufferers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1262.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following contributions were made:</p>
   <p>J. Cohen -- a carload of flour, or $2,000;</p>
   <p>Philip Goldberg, from the firm of Louis Brothers Company -- a carload of food;</p>
   <p>Leo Beresniac and Max Korshak -- $250;</p>
   <p>J. Lassers and I. Lassers -- four carloads of food;</p>
   <p>Morris Joseph -- a carload of food;</p>
   <p>Leo Shefton -- $2,000, or a carload of food;</p>
   <p>J. F. Hodesman -- a carload of groceries;</p>
   <p>Max Abel -- a carload of food;</p>
   <p>N. Yudolvitz -- a carload of flour, or $2,000;</p>
   <p>David Kolb -- a car load of flour, or $2,000;</p>
   <p>Emil Bragoda -- $100;</p>
   <p>Frank Grossman, of the Grossman Shoe Company -- $100;</p>
   <p>B. Horwich -- a carload of food and clothing;</p>
   <p>Isadore Liederman -- a carload of food;</p>
   <p>S. J. Rosenberg -- a carload of food.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1263.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A ship carrying food and clothing from Chicago Jews to the needy Jews in Poland will be sent out about October 1. The ship will be loaded in Chicago. All who wish to participate in this splendid undertaking should apply immediately to Mr. B. Horwich, chairman, or Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, vice-chairman of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
