<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-19">Jan. 19, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0725</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0725.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-01-19">Jan. 19, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I do not know whether you are familiar with the fact that five per cent of the fertile land of Palestine already belongs to us, and that the largest portion of that land was purchased by the National Fund from the pennies and nickels which were collected from the National Fund Boxes. In the course of the past year, the National Fund purchased 25,000 acres of land which can feed a few thousand Jewish families--all this was made possible by the pennies and nickels collected by the National Fund.</p>
   <p>On this occasion, I wish to inform you that we have in our midst a man known as Reverend Mandel Halperin. If you should see this man, you would think that you were in the presence of either an Arabian field marshal or possibly a wealthy Jewish merchant from Poland. And this man, whom we knew in the old <pb facs="5423972_7_0726.jpg" n="2"/>country as a Zionist worker of long standing, has undertaken to bring a little order into the Chicago National Fund. He will, therefore, see that you have a National Fund Box in your home. He will also see that these boxes are emptied and that the money is sent to the office of the National Fund. This man will visit you--give him a friendly reception. Let us all realize that from the pennies and nickels which he will collect from your National Fund Boxes, large tracts of land will be bought in Palestine for the Jewish people.</p>
   <p>The season of "drives" will soon open in Chicago. The Jewish Charities will launch a drive for a quarter-million dollars, which will also be a sort of membership drive; later there will be a drive for two and one-half million dollars for the erection of new homes for the already existing institutions; the Keren Hayesod is now organizing its spring campaign for $300,000. Dr. Chaim Weizmann and Sir Alfred Mund will arrive here soon and we must give them a grand reception, i.e., a substantial check for the Keren Hayesod.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0727.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A movement for the erection of centers for our youth will also be launched within a few weeks and a quarter-million dollars, will probably be raised for this purpose. Then, there will be a series of small drives for local institutions, such as the Daughters of Zion Day Nursery and Infant Home, and The Douglas Park Day and Night Nursery.</p>
   <p>So, try to earn a lot of money. You will soon have to donate a lot of money because we will not accept a little. Thy people, Israel, is in need; you must help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
