<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Courier</title>
      <date when="1910-05-23">May 23, 1910</date>
      <title level="a">Report of the Chicago Hebrew Institute</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0323.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Courier</title>
     <date when="1910-05-23">May 23, 1910</date>
     <title level="a">Report of the Chicago Hebrew Institute</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The president's annual report shows that the institute has been and still remains a highly beneficial institution to the city. The report is replete with information on the very fine activities of the Institute.</p>
   <p>The Finance Committee reports obtaining the sum of $22,000 with $100 contributions by 73 members. The report particularly lauds, the philanthropists, Julius Rosenwald and Charles Schaffner for their very fine interest in the Institution.</p>
   <p>Last years budget amounted to $57,000. Money went to finance the following activities:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>English Classes</cell>
     <cell>175 Students</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Hebrew Classes</cell>
     <cell>110 Students</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sabbath School</cell>
     <cell>270 Students</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sewing Classes</cell>
     <cell>63 Students</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Grade School </cell>
     <cell>50 Students</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Gymnasium</cell>
     <cell>193 Students</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0324.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Kindergarten</cell>
     <cell>25 Students</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Music Class</cell>
     <cell>6 Students</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Other than the above mentioned activities there were 43 clubs of various endeavors who made their headquarters at the Institute. The People's Synagogue conducted services every Friday night and very fine lectures were delivered on successive Fridays. The synagogue was always filled to capacity. Apparently the Religious Activity and the Gymnasium were the most popular activities, thanks to Rabbi Morris Levin and Mr. Harry Berkman.</p>
   <p>The Trade School was highly successful. Graduates of this school find it easy to obtain employment in private industry. Mr. William Kahill, the principal of this school, is the right man at the right job, as shown by the success of this school.</p>
   <p>The Public Library Branch at the Institute was indeed very popular. The facilities of the library were at all times taxed to capacity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0325.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, greater even than its influence on people who patronized the Institute was the influence it had upon outsiders who had very little to do with the Institute proper.</p>
   <p>The one sad note of last year's occurences was the fire which destroyedthe main structure. However, already $10,000 have been raised to expand the annex and thus keep in tact all the activities of the Institute prior to the fire.</p>
   <p>Some of the other enumerated activities of the Institute during the past year are, the peoples chair, the public libraby, lectures, dramatic clubs, celebrations of holidays, music club, "The Messenger," the Institute publication, worker's conferences and sports.</p>
   <p>The attendance at the Gymnasium was 7,542 on the inside, and 5,276 on the outside making a total of 12,818 people participating in gymnasium activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0326.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Institute was host to an average of 1,624 people daily. The report proved conclusively the value of this Institution to our Jewish community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
