<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, 
                <date when="1917-05-14">May 14, 1917</date><title level="a">Dr. Hirsch Appeals in Behalf of Russian Jews</title>
            </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1445</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1445.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
  <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>, 
         <date when="1917-05-14">May 14, 1917</date><title level="a">Dr. Hirsch Appeals in Behalf of Russian Jews</title>
            </bibl>
    
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last evening the Chicago Jewry celebrated the Russian Revolution, which brought complete freedom to six million Jews.</p>
   <p>Those present at mass meetings understood that freedom without bread is of no value, and therefore everyone contributed as liberally as he could towards the the million dollar fund for the war striken Jews.</p>
   <p>The meetings were followed by a banquet at the La Salle Hotel, where over three hundred of the most prominent West Side Jews assembled.</p>
   <p>Those present at the banquet will long remember the masterly speech of Dr. Emil G. Hirsch, who touched the heart of the audience and held it spell-bound throughout his discourse on the Jewish martyrdom during the reactionary Middle Ages <pb facs="5423972_7_1446.jpg" n="2"/> in dark Russia and Roumania. His description of the affliction of the Jews in the war striken countries was so touching that his listeners wept. In a rare poetic style, he pointed out how the dark clouds that hung over Russia fell upon the heads of the reactionary oppressors to cover them, and how the brilliant Morning Star spread a bright light over the horizon of the Russian people.</p>
   <p>The noted Rabbi of Sinai Temple said that his jubilee would be incomplete if we were only to rejoice with the political freedom of the Jews while they starve to death despite their freedom. He added that the Russian Jews have no one to look forward to for support except the Jews of America. The Chicago Jews especially are obligated to their brothers in Russia. With a powerful voice, he reminded the audience of Hillel's words, "If we won't help, who will? And now is the time."</p>
   <p>The audience responded warmly to this appeal by contributing eleven thousand <pb facs="5423972_7_1447.jpg" n="3"/> dollars to the fund.</p>
   <p>Mr. B. Hurvitz opened the banquet with a speech after which he introduced the toastmaster, Judge Harry M. Fisher, who strongly emphasized the great significance of this holiday for the Jews of the world. Addresses were delivered by Judge Henry Horner, Judge Palm, Judge David, Bishop Samuel Faulas, and Dr. Hirsch.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
