<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-07">Mar. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Bazaar to Aid the Jews of Russia and Poland.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1931-03-07">Mar. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">BAZAAR TO AID THE JEWS OF RUSSIA AND POLAND.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The bazaar will open tonight and will last nine days. This huge undertaking was arranged by all Jewish organizations of Chicago to help the Jews of Russia and Poland who are on the verge of ruin, on account of the economic conditions still prevailing since the great war, in which the Jews are suffering the most.</p>
   <p>This bazaar is the most gigantic undertaking ever attempted by Chicago Jewry in the last few years.</p>
   <p>Other bazaars given in previous years were quite successful. But, considering the depression we are in now, we expect this bazaar to be a phenomenal success, due to the grand cooperation of a number of Jewish organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0442.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first and most prominent work in arranging the bazaar consisted in collecting merchandise. A good deal was donated by a group of Jewish business men, who have not only contributed liberally, but also have spent much of their time and helped devotedly....</p>
   <p>Excellent work was performed by the women's organizations of the Workmen's Circle, the Jewish unions and many other groups.</p>
   <p>These people have sacrificed their food and time and worked laboriously without ceasing, day and night, in order to make this affair a success.</p>
   <p>The bazaar will open with a grand musical show. There will be a beautiful exhibition of everything a human being can use in the line of food stuffs, housewares, clothing, and other commodities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0443.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The success of the bazaar may be achieved through the cooperation and good will of the Jewish public, whom we expect to come and purchase the articles on sale, which are priced very low so that everybody will be able to enjoy real bargains.</p>
   <p>The object here is not so much the securing of bargains. The most important point in this affair is the moral success.</p>
   <p>We are almost certain that there will be many Jews who will respond to this most urgent call, and visit the bazaar in order to contribute their share, to enable us to aid thousands of unfortunate Jewish families of Russia and Poland who are on the verge of perishing morally and economically. These contributions will make it possible for us to help them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
