<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-03">Aug. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-03">Aug. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Joint Distribution Committee is the central body through which all the money that is collected, is sent to needy Jews in various parts of Europe and Palestine. The Joint Distribution Committee operates under a license issued from Washington, and so do the groups representing it--more correctly, it represents them.</p>
   <p>It is not simply a question of any organization sending money to Europe; to do so, the organization must have a license and must be able to secure one first.</p>
   <p>This fact, plus the feeling of the majority of the Jews in America that we must have a central relief organization, has abolished many landsmannschaften whose sole purpose was to gather relief money to be sent to the cities from which the membership came.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1269.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Recently, these landsmannschaften have again appeared, although even now, after the war, they cannot accomplish their purpose.</p>
   <p>The American Union of Rumanian Jews understands this situation, and from its offices in New York, has made an appeal and issued a warning to Rumanian Jews in the various states of the United States that they should not stray from the regulations pertaining to relief work.</p>
   <p>"It is not our purpose," writes the president, Dr. P. A. Ziegelstein, "to suspect anyone of questionable motives or of dishonorable intentions, but we know that the landsmannschaften do not clearly understand relief work nor how it should be done. Everyone can and should depend upon the Joint Distribution Committee because it knows where to send relief, where and how to buy clothing and food; it has qualified agents to supervise the purchasing, and to take care of the money designated for distribution."</p>
   <p>We thank Dr. Ziegelstein for these sincere and timely remarks. We do not need <pb facs="5423972_7_1270.jpg" n="3"/>any separate relief organizations other than those already authorized. The existing organizations know their work and have the confidence of the general public.</p>
   <p>We hope Dr. Ziegelstein's warning reaches all landsmannschaften in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
