<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1929-04-25">April 25, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">People's Tool Campaign.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1929-04-25">April 25, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLE'S TOOL CAMPAIGN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The People's Tool Campaign start its drive in Chicago to raise one hundred thousand dollars for tools and machinery for the declassed Jews in Russia.</p>
   <p>At the meeting of the executive committee, the main officers were elected, to carry out the drive. Those elected are Victor E. Levinson, manager of the Forward, as chairman; Louis Bomash, president of the Independent State Bank, as treasurer; and I. B. Ury, executive secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0448.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first great undertaking to raise money for the declassed Jews of Russia will be a soccer game between the Hakoah team and the Sparta team of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The game will be played on Sunday afternoon, May 12th, at Soldier's Field.</p>
   <p>The Hakoah team consists of the original Vienna Jewish soccer players, who took America by storm a few years ago when they first came here. In Chicago they were seen playing three times, and it is already three years since they last played here. In the last few months they have won every game they played in United States and became the champion team of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0449.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now they are coming to Chicago to play a benefit game for the tool campaign for the declassed Jews of Russia, with Sparta - the champion team of Chicago and one of the strongest teams in the country.</p>
   <p>The game will be interesting to the entire sport world who are patiently waiting for the 12th of May. It is expected that the Jewish heroes will receive a hearty welcome from the broad Jewish masses of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The tickets will soon be on the market. This coming Sunday morning a conference will take place of the organizations working in connection with the tool campaign, in regard to the drive in their organization, and to determine their specified quota. The conference will take place at 3420 W. Roosevelt Road. The organizations that have not yet joined the tool campaign committee can do so, Sunday at the conference through their officers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
