<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1921-03-06">March 6, 1921</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1921-03-06">March 6, 1921</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Amalgamated will build in Chicago, a Million Dollar Workers Temple.</p>
   <p>The Chicago home locals will have their own home at the corner of Ashland Blvd. and Adams St. The biggest and most beautiful workers temple will soon be built by the Chicago locals of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers.</p>
   <p>This was made known at the last meeting of the Joint Board, by Comrade Sam Levin. In his report he stated that the contract for the lots has been signed, and plans are started for the biggest temple that workers have ever built.</p>
   <p>The temple will be built so as to give the General Board and the locals all the comforts and facilities for union undertakings. There will be a hall which will hold 8,000 people. All the various activities, social, cultural, and physical, and everything that helps develop the body and spirit, will be transacted in that temple.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0220.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The members have already donated $215,000 to the building fund, of which, $80,000 were paid for the lots, and as soon as we agree to start building, we will work out plans, as to how the money necessary for the building shall be raised. The lots are 125 ft. front on Ashland Blvd. and 200 ft. on Adams St. Five occupied buildings are now on Ashland Ave., and a large court-building on Adams St., and these will naturally be sold when the place will be needed.</p>
   <p>The news that the Amalgamated plans to build the temple, has brought joy and happiness at all the locals when this report was submitted. The temple will be a source of pride for the entire labor movement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
