<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-22">Nov. 22, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish National Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1098</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1098.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-22">Nov. 22, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH NATIONAL FUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The idea of a National Fund found a sympathetic response among the Choveve Zion [lovers of Zion] as early as 1880, but it was not organized until 1901, at the fifth Zionist Congress, through the untiring effort of Dr. Herman Shapiro, a professor of mathematics in a German university. Although it has been in existence only a short time, the Jewish National Fund has won the confidence and love of the whole Jewish nation, embracing all classes, radical and conservative. This is true because it gives expression to a longing which has been smouldering in the hearts of the Jewish people during the long dark years of the Golus [Diaspora], the longing for an independent life in a rebuilt Palestine.</p>
   <p>The Jewish National Fund boldly proclaims the principles of democracy and progress for which the Jewish nation stands. To quote from its constitution: "it strives to acquire land in Palestine as the inalienable property of the <pb facs="5423972_7_1099.jpg" n="2"/>Jewish people". The land purchased is to belong to the whole nation, and to benefit it as an entity; the cultivation of the land is to be carried on by Jewish labor only. In other words, it aims to procure land for its people and people for its land.</p>
   <p>The Jewish National Fund is bound to be a very significant factor in the rebuilding of Palestine. Hundreds of immigrants are entering the country every month. Thousands are clamoring for entrance. They must be provided with land to work on, houses to shelter them until they are in a position to build their own, and loans must be made to the various co-operative groups so that they may continue their enterprises. The activities of this institution will have to be intensified in order to meet the growing demands. The whole of the Jewish people will be called upon to demonstrate their profound interest in this institution, and to show the world that we intend to rebuild Palestine along the principles of justice and democracy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1100.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In Chicago collections are being made and donations are coming in regularly. Just now preparations are in full swing for the annual tag day to be held on Sunday, December 12, 1920. Chicago young women are asked to reserve this day for service to the people--to help tag for this very important fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
