<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-03">Mar, 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Twenty-Five Hundred Dollars for Palestine Workers Raised at the Successful Banquet for Max Pine</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-03">Mar, 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTY-FIVE HUNDRED DOLLARS FOR PALESTINE WORKERS RAISED AT THE SUCCESSFUL BANQUET FOR MAX PINE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The organized Jewish workers of Chicago gave a banquet last Saturday evening at Rosenthal's Restaurant, in honor of Max Pine, leader of the drive to help the Jewish workers in Palestine. The banquet was attended by over eighty representatives of trade unions, Poale Zion [labor group in Zionist movement], National Workers Alliance, representatives of cultural institutions, individual Socialist leaders, and Jewish newspapermen.</p>
   <p>Mr. L. Hanock was the toastmaster. Many speakers expressed their hearty approval of the compaign for one hundred fifty thousand dollars for the workers in Palestine, and appealed to the audience to help the campaign, morally and financially. Among the speakers were Dr. Green, Albert Green, Abrahams, Siskind, Weisman, Poley, Risman, Dr. A. Margolin, Mason, Spiwak, B. J. Shapiro, Dr. Lorber, and Bagdansky.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0478.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The most moving speech was delivered at the conclusion of the banquet by the guest of honor, Max Pine. He expressed his satisfaction with the enthusiasm of the audience and with the important propaganda forces which Chicago possesses and can use in this campaign. The energetic labor leader declared with assurance that the drive will be a success, and that Chicago's quota, twenty-five thousand dollars, will be raised very quickly.</p>
   <p>The speaker admitted that in the Jewish labor movement there are still a few narrow-minded party fanatics who are prejudiced against the trade union campaign for the Palestine comrades. These people adhere to the narrow bounds of the "Gospel According to Marx," and consider everything that is done and created in Palestine as unkosher. The work of overcoming this opposition must be done by the Jewish workers in America, who do not need anybody's approval in order to help the organized Jewish workers in Palestine strengthen their economic positions in their new homeland.</p>
   <p>Sam Kestin, the beloved comedian of the Palace Theater, sang for the guests, and Mrs. Minnie Nazansky and Mrs. Sarah Risman gave several declamations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0479.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Twenty-four hundred and thirty dollars was raised at the banquet in response to an appeal made by B. J. Shapiro. This amount plus the sum raised at Friday's mass meeting brings the total contributions to three thousand dollars. Among the larger contributions were: one thousand dollars from the organized (right) Poale Zion, five hundred dollars from the National Workers Alliance, and three hundred dollars from the left Poale Zion. The painters' union, the waiters' union, and the Dramatic Society each contributed one hundred dollars. Individual donations ranged from five to fifty dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
