<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-01">Feb. 1, 1914</date><title level="a">A Few Words to the Donors and Receivers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1603</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1603.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-01">Feb. 1, 1914</date><title level="a">A FEW WORDS TO THE DONORS AND RECEIVERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At present, when hundreds and hundreds of unemployed seek bread to satisfy their hunger and coal to heat their homes, the amount given them is too meager and the amount received for this purpose, insufficient. In times when conditions are such that people once counted among the donors have suddenly become recipients, it is no more than just that those having the means should cast aside their complaints and demands and aid those in need.</p>
   <p>The recipients should also know that now is no time for fundamental questions. When a person is hungry, it is easy for him to become discontent, but discontent will not satiate him.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1604.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The misfortune is great. In the Jewish Ghetto, there are hundreds of men seeking employment to provide their families with the bare necessities of life. Healthy, sturdy, young men go around half-starved, without any shoes or clothing to protect them from the wind and cold. They are paupers, but on no account mendicants. Each one of them is willing to work and earn a livelihood if it were possible.</p>
   <p>Who are these present day recipients? We have before us a letter. If we were to publish all the letters which flow into the office of the Jewish Courier, we would have to transform this newspaper into a stream of tears and blood. The Chicago Jewish Ghetto would make a wry face. A loud cry would be heard, similar to the heart-rending lamentation of Jeremiah. "The entire race sighs, seeks bread. They have given up everything within their possession only to comfort the soul. Behold, <pb facs="5423972_7_1605.jpg" n="3"/>Lord, we have become gluttons."</p>
   <p>In writing to the Federation (of Jewish Charities), a Jew submits $3 as his share to the fund for those more unfortunate than he. And who is he? He is the mendicant here, just read his letter:</p>
   <p>"Venerable Officers of the Federation:</p>
   <p>"I am in receipt of your letter informing me to pay my dues. Unfortunately, it is nearly a year that I am sick. I became paralyzed, so you can readily see in what condition I am. It is thus impossible for me to pay at one time, in a lump sum. But how is it possible to deprive lonely orphans, the poor aged, and the unfortunate sick? How can anyone abstain completely from contributing to your organization, regardless of how little it may be? I have therefore decided not to see my physician this week <pb facs="5423972_7_1606.jpg" n="4"/>and not to purchase any medicine, in order to save as much as possible. In the meantime, I am enclosing a meager check for the sum of three dollars.</p>
   <p>"Hoping that I regain my health so that I can send the balance."</p>
   <p>This particular Jew is now a receiver, and in this misfortune, of course, there are hundreds like him. We can join the prophet in saying that, "those who have eaten food now wander about ravenously; those who were brought up in comfort, are now picking food from the garbage cans."</p>
   <p>This paralyzed Jew will deny himself medical attention for one week in order, as he expresses himself," not to deprive the lonely orphan, the poor aged, and the unfortunate sick." Hunger made this Jew leave his sick bed; cold weather forced him to leave his home in order to appease his appetite.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1607.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This Jew is one of the many whom the American newspapers last week depicted as nihilists and anarchists, who carry bombs on their persons and want to create another Haymarket riot. We will not disclose his name because we feel certain that when these hard times are over, he will regain his former status.</p>
   <p>As we understand it, there are many who claim that times are not so deplorable, and that giving the unemployed bread and coal will merely arouse the Gentiles' suspicion that the Jews do not amply provide for their needy, which is a dishonor, especially for the wealthy Jews.</p>
   <p>What role does a little honor play against so much hunger? Who cares what others say when hunger and cold overtake the body? The people who are worried over Jewish honor must be very well off to think of nothing but honor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1608.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Open free kitchens for the hungry, and if times prove to be so good that the unemployed will not swarm them, then so much the better.</p>
   <p>There is a maxim that poverty and want develop not because the impoverished and needy are helped, but because aid is extended to the rich, enabling them to become richer. Consequently, unemployment, want, and poverty develop. The donors should bear this in mind.</p>
   <p>And now, a few words to the recipients. It is understood that the well-fed can not sympathize with the hungry; it is therefore very natural that there should be some animosity against the donors in the ranks of the recipients. People who have to ask others for a favor, are usually embittered. But the unemployed must also realize that everything possible is done to alleviate the plight of those who apply for relief without humiliating them or offending their feelings.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1609.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>There ought to be a mutual feeling between donors and recipients, with the latter realizing that it is only a temporary ailment, and that as soon as these hard times are over, the recipients will be much the same as the donors. Many donors of today were recipients of yesterday. We are all Jews, one family. Let us rejoice all together for having in our family wealthy donors, and let us all together weep upon witnessing that among us there are so many unfortunate ones.</p>
   <p>As the sun has its spots, so has every cloud a silver lining. There are many among the recipients whom the donors should envy. After all, man can not live by bread alone.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
