<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1892-07-30">July 30, 1892</date>, pp. 510-11.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1892-07-30">July 30, 1892</date>, pp. 510-11.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago the Society in Aid of the Russian Refugees bought the four-story and basement brick building on the northwest corner of Maxwell and Clinton streets, for the purpose of having it fitted up as a Sheltering House for the Russian Refugees. Repairs have been made on this building, and the Society has taken possession of its new home.</p>
   <p>The Sheltering House is a handsome and substantial building containing 36 rooms, besides the basement and the attic. In the basement are located the bath rooms, laundry, drying and baggage storage rooms. On the first floor are the general offices of the Society, the Employment Bureau, and the clothing rooms. The second floor contains the sitting and reading rooms, dining room and kitchen, and the custodian's private rooms. The third floor comprises the sleeping rooms for women and children, and the fourth floor, those for the men. In this house the refugees are lodged and fed for three days.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0367.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Society has been in existence since September, 1891. It has and is still accomplishing an incalculable amount of good.</p>
   <p>Chicago is a distributing center and a great number of the unfortunate refugees come here from all the port cities of the land. The great bulk of them, however, come from New York.</p>
   <p>The Society distributes the refugees over the great West. It employs a traveling agent, who visits the different communities in the Western states, enlisting the sympathy and cooperation of the Jewish citizens, to find homes and employment for the refugees. The Society has the satisfaction of knowing that it has saved hundreds of these unfortunate exiles from starvation and that it has helped many a family to become self-sustaining.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0368.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The old Sheltering House Association, which existed among our Russo-Polish co-religionists, before the Society in Aid of Russian Refugees was established, is still lending a helping hand.</p>
   <p>The South and West Side Ladies Sewing Societies have liberally contributed towards the furnishing of the Sheltering Home in linens, comforters, etc.</p>
   <p>The Sheltering House is now an established institution. It is well worthy of a place of honor among the charitable institutions of our community, and fully deserving of the liberal and generous support of all friends of the poor and oppressed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
