<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-15">Mar. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Five Hundred Persons Participate in the Relief Convention of the Middle Western States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-15">Mar. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FIVE HUNDRED PERSONS PARTICIPATE IN THE RELIEF CONVENTION OF THE MIDDLE WESTERN STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Not a dole, but constructive relief work for the suffering Jews across the sea," was the sentiment and opinion of the five hundred delegates from the Middle West, who were participating in the relief convention at the Sherman Hotel yesterday.</p>
   <p>The zeal and the willingness [of the workers] in behalf of the noble relief work indicates their readiness and devotion to the cause of relief and to the Joint Relief Committee of Chicago, which called the convention.</p>
   <p>The proposal has been made that the Central Committee should request the Joint Distribution Committee to co-operate with the other relief organizations in every corner of the world, and call an international relief conference.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1169.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Central Committee should also demand that the Joint Distribution Committee, when it appoints committees to distribute relief money, should include Orthodox Jews, in proportion to their numbers; that a special commission should be sent by the Central Relief Committee to Europe to study the condition of the Heders (Hebrew schools), Yeshivoth, Talmud Torahs, and other important institutions, and to establish a middle western bureau for relief work. These are only a few of the important resolutions which were adopted yesterday.</p>
   <p>The first session of the convention was opened at 11 A. M. by the chairman of the convention committee, S. J. Rosenblatt, who, in a brief address, analyzed the importance of the convention. He then called upon Rabbi Horowitz of St. Paul to welcome the delegates.</p>
   <p>"The task of this convention is a most important one at the present time," said Rabbi Horowitz, "and may God help you to succeed in your mission. The blood of our brothers and sisters flows like water, and their suffering <pb facs="5423972_7_1170.jpg" n="3"/>and misery has gone beyond all bounds. Only we, the American Jews, are in a position to alleviate their misery. May the Almighty show you how best you can accomplish this work."</p>
   <p>After this greeting, the floor was given to Judge Joseph B. David, who, in a brilliant address, discussed the importance of the convention. "The Jews across the sea, our flesh and blood," the Jewish judge said, "turn their eyes to us, not as beggars waiting for help, but as brothers, who have a right to demand that we fulfill our duty [to them], when they are in need.</p>
   <p>"The Jews have not done enough, up until now, but it is never too late. We must help our brethren, until we are established as a nation in our own country, in Palestine. In the name of Chicago's community, I welcome you and wish you success."</p>
   <p>After this address, Mr. Rosenblatt presented the chairman of Chicago's Joint Relief Committee, Mr. B. Horwich, who was to act as chairman of the convention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1171.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Horwich reviewed the work which had been done up until now, and described [the work of] the Joint Relief Committee, which is a branch of the Central Relief Committee, representing the Jewish Orthodox masses. He pointed out the necessity of the present movement, which comes at a time when reconstructive relief work must be done; he recommended united action with the Central Relief Committee, so that the work might be carried out in the traditional Jewish spirit. He also stressed the importance of organizing a middle western bureau, which should organize and systematize the relief work in the Middle West.</p>
   <p>After Mr. B. J. Bronstein called the roll, the floor was given to Mr. Isadore Liederman, who has been the financial secretary of the Joint Relief since its inception. Mr. Liederman delivered a detailed financial report of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>From Mr. Liederman's report, it can be seen that since the founding of the Committee in 1914, the following sums were collected: [list follows].</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1172.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The People's Relief was connected with the Joint Relief until January 1, 1919. Since then, they have opened a separate office, and send their relief money independently of the Joint Relief.</p>
   <p>In the past year, $23,222.94, collected through the Courier, was turned over to the Joint Relief Committee. For the past fourteen months, the expenses amounted to only five and one-half per cent. The office also sent $16,085 to Europe for private individuals.</p>
   <p>After the report of the financial secretary, the chairman appointed a resolutions committee, a nominating committee, a ways and means committee, and an organizing committee. The floor was then given to Mr. H. L. Zelig, who delivered a masterful report on the work of the Central Committee, of which he is a director. The address is to be found on the editorial page of today's Courier.</p>
   <p>The financial report, delivered by Mr. Zelig, indicates that of the thirty million dollars collected in America for relief, nine million dollars was <pb facs="5423972_7_1173.jpg" n="6"/>collected by the Central Committee. If we included all the money that the Orthodox Jews of America have contributed to other relief committees, then we could state emphatically that the Orthodox Jews contributed the major share of the relief money.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry Bernstein, who recently returned from Poland, was one of the speakers at the morning session, where he related what he had seen and heard "in the valley of sighs". His speech made a powerful impression, and concluded the morning session.</p>
   <p>The delegates from other cities were invited by Mr. Max Shulman to the Covenant Club where a luncheon was served.</p>
   <p>The second session was opened by Mr. B. Horwich, who read a number of telegrams concerning the condition of the Jews in Poland, received from Rabbi Meyer Berlin, Rabbi Ephraim Epstein, Mr. Julius Savitsky and Mr. Jacob Goldman, who is now in Poland representing Schiff and Company State Bank, <pb facs="5423972_7_1174.jpg" n="7"/>and then he presented Mr. A. Berger, secretary of Chicago's Jewish Relief Drive. The latter reported that the nonsectarian drive has raised the sum of $2,033,000, to which non-Jews have contributed $622,000. Immediately following the report, the resolutions of the various committees were read and unanimously accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, as chairman of the organizing committee, read the fourteen resolutions which propose to establish a middle western bureau, to include the states of Illinois, Wisconsin, Michigan, Iowa, Minnesota, Indiana, and Nebraska. The headquarters of the bureau are to be in Chicago, and should be administered by the directors and officers who are to be elected at the annual convention.</p>
   <p>Dr. George Sultan, chairman of the ways and means committee, proposed eight resolutions dealing with the administration of relief activity in the Middle West.</p>
   <p>Mr. Max Shulman, chairman of the resolutions committee, brought in a number <pb facs="5423972_7_1175.jpg" n="8"/>of resolutions which read as follows:</p>
   <p>The present convention recommends to the Central Relief Committee that its representatives at the Joint Distribution Committee shall request the Joint Distribution Committee to contact all relief organizations throughout the world, for the purpose of calling and organizing an International Relief Congress.</p>
   <p>The convention recommends that the Central Relief Committee request the Joint Distribution Committee to include representatives of the Orthodox Kehiloth, in proportion to their membership, on all committees appointed to distribute relief money in war-stricken countries.</p>
   <p>The convention recommends that a special commission be sent to study the condition of Jewish educational institutions and to investigate the problem of the orphans.</p>
   <p>Mr. Liederman, chairman of the nominating committee, reported that the committee has nominated directors and officers for Chicago only, and has given <pb facs="5423972_7_1176.jpg" n="9"/>the privilege of electing directors and vice-presidents to each individual state.</p>
   <p>The elected officers and directors of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee for the coming year are: B. Horwich, chairman, S. J. Rosenblatt, vice-chairman, Samuel Phillipson, treasurer, Isadore Liederman, secretary.</p>
   <p>The directors are: Max Shulman, Max Abel, Rabbi [Abraham] Cardon, Rabbi Saul Silber, Rabbi Ephraim Epstein, Rabbi [Elazer] Muskin, I. Lasser, Judge [Harry] Fisher, S. B. Komaiko, H. Steinberg, Dr. Sultan and Nathan D. Kaplan.</p>
   <p>After the reports of the committees were heard, the floor was given to Judge [Hugo] Pam, who, in an exceptionally moving address, thanked the delegates for their part in helping the unfortunate Jewish war-sufferers.</p>
   <p>"As long as there is a single Jew who needs our help, we must not give up the task," Judge Pam said, "and until we secure justice, and make it possible for <pb facs="5423972_7_1177.jpg" n="10"/>Jews to live in this world on an equal basis with other people, we will have to be united and assist our brethren who look to us for assistance."</p>
   <p>Judge Pam was followed by Rabbi Glick of the New York Central Relief Committee. Rabbi Silber made the closing address.</p>
   <p>The banquet at the Ashland Clubhouse was a great success. The toastmaster was Mr. Shulman, who was presented by Mr. Rosenblatt. Speeches were made by: Dr. [S. M.] Melamed, B. Horwich, Samuel Phillipson, Dr. I. L. Brill, H. L. Zelig, Rabbi Saul Silber, Samuel Neveleff, and Isaac Don Levine, who described the misery and horror which Jews are experiencing in Russia, particularly from the Jewish Bolsheviks who make it hard for them to live as Jews.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
