<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-10">Sept. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago and Other Cities in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">Proposal to Unite the Two Charity Organizations by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0755</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0755.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-10">Sept. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO AND OTHER CITIES IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">Proposal to Unite the Two Charity Organizations by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some very important ideas, plans, and enterprises which affect local and national Jewish life, have originated in Chicago. They were initiated and put into effect here. We need only mention two movements which started in Chicago: the Zionist movement and the movement to consolidate the charity and educational institutions of the Orthodox Jews.</p>
   <p>In Chicago a Zionist society was organized immediately after Dr. Herzl announced his plan to establish a homeland for the Jews in Palestine. New York and other cities in America followed in Chicago's footsteps. The Jewish Federation of Orthodox Charities is another undertaking of which the Chicago Orthodox Jews are proud. They were the first to introduce one collection and one distribution agency for all their <pb facs="5423972_7_0756.jpg" n="2"/>charity and educational institutions, thus doing away with the custom of each institution raising and disbursing the money it needs. New York and other American cities followed Chicago's example. The Reform Jews of Chicago have to their credit the merger into one big charity organization of all charity organizations which individual groups had founded and maintained. They called their new organization the United Hebrew Charities, and then changed its name to the Associated Jewish Charities.</p>
   <p>It has been proposed and recommended that the two charity organizations--The Associated and the Federated--should amalgamate and become one. The members of both organizations will soon have to vote upon this proposal.</p>
   <p>Times have changed a great deal. The great division between the Orthodox and the Reform Jews in this city has almost been wiped out. The Orthodox Jews have become more Americanized, and have come to respect order and system in the field of charity. The Reform Jews have become more Jewish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0757.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They have become so conscious of their Judaism that they have left behind them those spiritual leaders who constantly complained that the Polish Jew did not and could not come up to the level of an American or German Jew; that the Polish Jew did not know how to behave, that he was a beggar, whom one should treat with contempt.</p>
   <p>During the last ten years, the Reform Jews have come in closer contact with the immigrant Orthodox Jews and their American-born children; they have become convinced that we are just as good as they and that we too have millionaires among us. We learned from them and they learned from us. We began to feel closer to each other; we have similar interests in many fields of public affairs. Gradually, very gradually, we began to realize that the two charity institutions, to which the same Jews contribute a certain sum of money each year, should merge and become one. Undoubtedly, the Jewish community of this city will gain a great deal, spiritually and economically. The Jewish community will also gain greater consideration in the eyes of the non-Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0758.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Reform Jews have agreed that all existing educational institutions, Talmud Torahs and seminaries, should be supported by the central treasury. This is the best proof that the Reform Jews are honest, serious, and aboveboard in their plan for the merger of the two charity organizations. The Reform Jews have believed for a long time that educational institutions have nothing to do with charity--that they should remain separate. The Reform Jews themselves proposed that the problems of Kosher food and religious observance in the institutions of the Orthodox Jews, should be under the supervision of the Orthodox Jews themselves.</p>
   <p>The entire plan, upon which the committees from the two organizations have come to an understanding, will soon be put before the respective boards of the Associated and the Federated. As soon as the plan is approved by the boards, it will be submitted to the general membership of both organizations. This procedure is very democratic. Mr. James Davis, the president of the Federated, is very glad that the representatives <pb facs="5423972_7_0759.jpg" n="5"/>of both sides considered and respected each other's opinions and desires, and that every member is to have an opportunity to accept or reject the entire plan.</p>
   <p>Mr. Davis tells us that an agreement has already been reached regarding the name of the new organization. Its name will be The Jewish Charities of Chicago. This is a correct and appropriate name. We also learn from Mr. Davis that the board of the new organization will consist of thirty-six members, one-half from the Associated and one-half from the Federated. This is reasonable and satisfactory. The new board, declares Mr. Davis, will be in charge of everything except the religious conditions prevailing at the institutions. The board of directors of every institution or their appointees will take care of that.</p>
   <p>It is to be hoped that the central organization will have sufficient funds, when the merger takes place, to support every affiliated organization so that it can continue its activity. The annual budget will probably be <pb facs="5423972_7_0760.jpg" n="6"/>about a million and one-half dollars, and there is no question but that the sum will be raised. It is to be hoped that the institutions of the Federated will be able to wipe out their debts when the merger takes place because it stands to reason that a well-organized Jewish Charities of Chicago, with Julius Rosenwald as one of its leaders, will not wish to have a mortgage on its property.</p>
   <p>Get ready, Chicago Jews, to vote on the merger of the two charity institutions. We hope that you will vote correctly--that is, in favor of the merger. A call for a vote will be sent out soon, and it is hoped that after January 1, the field of Jewish charity in Chicago will take on an entirely different appearance. The West Side Jews will no longer solicit the South Side Jews, and the latter will no longer feel slighted because the former do not trust them as Jews or as men. The West Side Jews will no longer be afraid that the Reform Jews want to absorb their institutions and to feed nonkosher food to all who go there.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0761.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>There is a group of Reform Jews in Chicago who have the same conception of charity as we have, but who believe that charity institutions should be conducted in a systematic, businesslike way. The plan for the Federated was borrowed from the Associated. This plan reduced the operating costs. The costs will be further reduced when the merger of the two institutions takes place. Many expenses will be reduced. Institutions that are affiliated now or that will affiliate later with the main organization, will benefit greatly by the reduced costs.</p>
   <p>The West Side will soon have, as a result of the existence of the new organization, a great, modern kosher hospital, and the nurseries and the Hebrew Theological College will have sufficient Funds to enable them to continue their activities.</p>
   <p>We hope that new institutions will arise in addition to the splendid and well-regulated hospital, and the other existing institutions, which <pb facs="5423972_7_0762.jpg" n="8"/>probably will be affiliated with the new organization. For example, we need an institution for old people who are able to pay or whose children are willing to pay for them, but who have no home. Such a home can be built by the new organization.</p>
   <p>New York and other Jewish cities in America will have, once more, something to learn from Chicago--another example to follow. Then we will be able to begin the work of uniting all local organizations into one organization in each city. The general public will then have a healthier attitude toward the Jews than it has now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
