<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-11-17">November 17, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Superintendent of the Hebrew Institute Has Arrived.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1908-11-17">November 17, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE SUPERINTENDENT OF THE HEBREW INSTITUTE HAS ARRIVED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. David Blaustein, the former superintendent of the Educational Alliance in New York, and one of the most prominent personalities among Jews in America, arrived in Chicago yesterday. He has accepted the position as superintendent of the new Hebrew Institute, Taylor and Lyttle Sts. The Dr. was at his desk at the Institute all day yesterday.</p>
   <p>To a representative of the Jewish Courier, who interviewed him, the Dr. said: "Currently I cannot say what I will do in Chicago. I must first of all become acquainted with conditions here, and then I will know what to do. Should conditions permit me, I will do in Chicago what I have done in New York. In the meantime I will make all the necessary preparations in the various departments of the institution."</p>
   <p>Dr. Blaustein briefly stated his biography to the paper's representative. Dr. Blaustein was born in Lidau, Vilno, May 5, 1866. He received his first training in a Hebrew School and Hebrew Theological College. When he was <pb facs="5423972_7_0342.jpg" n="2"/>eighteen years of age, he went to Memel, Prussia, where he studied Talmud under the guidance of Rabbi Izrael Salant. He then went to Mecklenburg, Schwerin, and studied philosophy in that university. In 1886, Germany refused him refuge on the ground that he was Russian, and he immigrated to America, settling in Boston. In Boston he opened a Hebrew school, taking courses at the same time at Harvard University. He was later elected Rabbi of a Reform Temple in Providence, Rhode Island. He constructed Hebrew schools and other Jewish institutions. He was appointed teacher of Semitic languages at Bryan University. In 1898, he was elected superintendent of the Educational Alliance of New York, a position he held until two years ago.</p>
   <p>The Daily Jewish Courier greets Dr. Blaustein on behalf of Chicago Jews, and hopes that as superintendent of the Hebrew Institute, he will perform his duties with his characteristic sincerity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
