<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Not in Comparison with Gemilas Chesed-"A Charitable Loan Without Interest."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.9"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 9</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1915-01-29">Jan. 29, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">NOT IN COMPARISON WITH GEMILAS CHESED-"A CHARITABLE LOAN WITHOUT INTEREST."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The First State Industrial Wage Loan Society, an Illinois corporation doing business in Chicago, at its annual meeting last Tuesday, heard an interesting yearly report from their manager. This corporation was founded by business men for the purpose of dispossessing the loan sharks, who take extreme advantage of the victims that fall prey to them. The society, by the way, makes pretty fair profits, according to the ancient wise maxim, "A good deed done, and much pleasure derived."</p>
   <p>The report shows that in the course of the past year the society loaned to 2,066 people, $122,000 in small loans. All loans were paid back with the exception of $145.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0414.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The total capital of this society amounted to only $50,000. The loans were made on the basis of three per cent a month. It is no wonder, that the directors unanimously decided, at this meeting to double the capital.</p>
   <p>Aside from the fact that borrowers must pay a high interest for the loan, the society does a great deal of good. This alone is a favor to a person of small means, who is forced to make a loan on his wages.</p>
   <p>Knowing in advance what per cent he will have to pay, he does not feel the danger of falling prey to the loan sharks. There is also a probability that, when the society's business increases; it will be in a position to decrease the interest. Even at that it does not compare with the Jewish Gemilas Chesed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0415.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As a rule the Jews are referred to as usurers because a few individual Jews are in business as usurers. They are often especially conscientious, but the Jewish people hate them, and when the question arises of helping Jewish people through loans he finds a free loan where the question of interest is entirely excluded.</p>
   <p>This is a Jewish institution which ought to serve our Gentile neighbors as an example.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
