<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-10-05">Oct. 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">$150,000 for War Relief by Chicago's Synagogues</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Anshe Kneseth Israel Shul Ranks First with $15,000 This Yom Kippur (Day of Atonement)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-10-05">Oct. 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">$150,000 FOR WAR RELIEF BY CHICAGO'S SYNAGOGUES</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Anshe Kneseth Israel Shul Ranks First With $15,000 This Yom Kippur (Day of Atonement)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It can be seen from the various reports received at the Courier office last evening, that over a hundred and fifty thousand dollars was given this Yom Kippur, in Chicago's synagogues, for Jewish refugees of the War.</p>
   <p>The Anshe Kneseth Israel Shul, Douglas Boulevard and Homan Avenue, ranks first, having collected the sum of $15,000.</p>
   <p>The speakers, who appealed to the people for donations, were effective; some made speeches, others read the Courier's appeal. They did not fail to inculcate the desired spirit. In many synagogues, immediately after the fast was broken, people stood in line to pay their pledges.</p>
   <p>At the Anshe Kneseth Israel Shul, the appeal was made by Rabbi Epstein. He kept the congregation spellbound with his speech which portrayed graphically <pb facs="5423972_7_1232.jpg" n="2"/>the conditions of the Jewish sufferers across the sea, bringing tears to [the eyes of] his listeners. Judge Harry M. Fisher assisted him with an appropriate speech. Mr. B. Cohen gave the first thousand dollars, after which other donations poured in until the above-mentioned sum was reached.</p>
   <p>The Anshe Kneseth Israel was followed by various synagogues with the following sums.</p>
   <p>At the Anshe Sholom where Rabbi Saul Silber made the appeal, and the Anshe Sholom Center where Mr. Max Shulman spoke--$12,000.</p>
   <p>At the Anshe Emeth where Mr. Isadore Cohen and Rabbi Hevish made the appeals--$10,500. Of this sum $2,000 was donated by Mr. Samuel Philipson who also took this opportunity of addressing the congregation.</p>
   <p>At the Kahiloth Jacob, Rabbi Shach speaking--$10,000. Thanks to the efforts <pb facs="5423972_7_1233.jpg" n="3"/>of Mr. Sam Ginsberg, $10,000 was also collected for the Talmud Torah (school) there.</p>
   <p>At the Rodfei Tzeduk, Judge Pam spoke--$8,000.</p>
   <p>The Beth Hamedrosh Hagodol, South Side, appeal by Dr. Chaim Davis--$7,000.</p>
   <p>The Tifereth Zion, appeal by Dr. S. M. Melomed--$5,000.</p>
   <p>The Anshe Ungaren, appeal by Rabbi Fisher--$4,000. Mr. B. J. Shiff contributed $1,000.</p>
   <p>The Bicur Cholim, of South Chicago, appeal by Rabbi Rubenstein--$3,000.</p>
   <p>Beth Hamedrosh Hagodol, West Side, appeal by Rabbi Israel Epstein--$2,500.</p>
   <p>The Anshe Amuneh, appeal by S. B. Kamaiko--$800.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1234.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Austrian-Galician, appeal by S. M. Melomed--$1,500.</p>
   <p>At Temple Judea, appeal by Dr. Rudolph Coffee--$1.500.</p>
   <p>At the B. M. Z. Synagogue, appeal by Mr. Isadore Goldberg--$500.</p>
   <p>The Bnai Joseph, appeal by Mr. R. Hurwitch--$400.</p>
   <p>The Sheri Torah Anshe Mariv, appeal by Rabbi Kardon--$4,000.</p>
   <p>Agudoth Sefrid Anshe Mariv, appeal by Joseph Rabinowitz--$1,800.</p>
   <p>The Atereth Israel, appeal by Rabbi Newberger--$550.</p>
   <p>At Bnai Israel, appeal by Mr. B. Stone--$15,000.</p>
   <p>Last evening, from Indiana Harbor, by long distance telephone call, Mr. Finklestein reported that $2,000 was collected there for relief.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1235.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In East Chicago also, $2,000 was contributed.</p>
   <p>Reports of other synagogues will appear in tomorrow's Courier.</p>
   <p>Preparations are being made for further appeals for the War sufferers which will be held in the synagogues on Shmini Hatzereth (holiday). Hope is entertained that, during this holiday season, the $200,000 mark, set by the Courier, may be attained.</p>
   <p>At the same time that we here received such splendid reports of the energetic work being done for Relief, a dispatch comes from Pittsburgh that Mr. B. Hurvitch, president of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee, en route back to Chicago, stopped at Pittsburgh to address a massmeeting and collected $10,000 for this same purpose. The massmeeting was also addressed by Rabbi Ashinsky and Mr. Irving Lehman.</p>
   <p>The same dispatch mentions that at a New York meeting of the Joint Distribution <pb facs="5423972_7_1236.jpg" n="6"/>Committee, attended by Mr. B. Hurvitch and Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, a sum of $200,000 was designated for establishing an express-delivery service in Poland and Lithuania by means of which packages of food, under American Relief auspices, can be sent without delay.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
