<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-04-30">Apr. 30, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A Successful Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV (Hungarian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-04-30">Apr. 30, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A SUCCESSFUL MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting called to discuss the problem of aiding the Jewish schools and universities in Hungary took place last Sunday at the Atlantic Hotel. A very large number of people who were interested in this problem were present.</p>
   <p>Joseph Rusznak was appointed temporary chairman. Louis Gottlieb, a Chicago Hungarian-Jewish lawyer who recently returned from New York, gave a report of the activities of the Hungarian-Jewish people in that city in behalf of this charitable movement. He recommended that the committee here work independently of, but in harmony with, the [committees] in other cities where similar charitable activities are being undertaken.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Berger was present and spoke very eloquently. He urged that something be done to mitigate the conditions which exist among the Jewish youth of Hungary. Ignatz Izsak then told of the hopeless future of the <pb facs="5423972_7_0470.jpg" n="2"/>Hungarian Jewish youth under the Horthy regime. Doctor Scheinman, a young Hungarian-Jewish doctor of Chicago who came to Chicago from Hungary very recently, substantiated these statements. He also spoke about his own experiences. He said that after completing his medical course with unusually high honors he was unable to get a position on the medical staff of any hospital in Budapest, because the Jews of Hungary and especially Jewish youth were being discriminated against. He then told how his ability was immediately recognized in Chicago, where he became a staff doctor in one of the Catholic hospitals and a district doctor for the Illinois Central Railroad Company.</p>
   <p>The election of officers then took place, and the following were named: Joseph Rusznak, president; M. Newman, vice-president; L. Keiszt, secretary; J. Feurzeig, treasurer; and Ignatz Izsak, honorary president.</p>
   <p>It was then decided that the activities of this group would be dedicated to the memory of Dr. Phillip Klein, who recently died in New York. This <pb facs="5423972_7_0471.jpg" n="3"/>man had sacrificed a great deal in helping both Hungarian and Jewish people abroad. At the next meeting, plans will be formulated for undertaking a campaign for contributions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
