<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-07-08">July 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">New Activities in the Jewish Home for the Aged.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 5</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-07-08">July 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">NEW ACTIVITIES IN THE JEWISH HOME FOR THE AGED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The president of the Means and Ways Committee of this Jewish institution has announced that after many hours of deliberation it has been determined to present a series of lectures, musical programs and entertainment to interest the Jewish public in the work and accomplishments of this oldest Jewish institution in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The call to the first meeting and entertainment claims that since the Federation is organized, the subscribers of the charity societies take very little interest in the combined institutions, which has resulted in so few people visiting this home for the aged, that they became almost total strangers. This is unfortunate, and the board of directors has decided to give social affairs on the next few Sundays to re-attract <pb facs="5423972_7_0039.jpg" n="2"/>the friends of the home; this will result in people visiting this Jewish institution more often and will inspire them to participate in the work. The first affair will take place at 3 o'clock this afternoon. A colorful program has been arranged, and no appeals for funds or subscriptions will be made. This magnificent institution stands on the corner of Ogden and Albany avenues, and it is hoped that this first affair will be a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
