<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-21">Mar. 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-21">Mar. 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Jews are being called upon to contribute one million dollars to the ten-million-dollar restoration fund with which the Zionists will undertake to rebuild Palestine, to create a home there for the hundreds of thousands of Jews from Eastern Europe. Will they [Chicago Jews] give the expected answer?</p>
   <p>Let's hope that they will. Let's hope that they will consider themselves part and parcel of the Jewish people, and will not remain indifferent to the appeal--the appeal for the restoration fund. The campaign is now in full swing throughout the country. The various cities and suburbs have responded enthusiastically and have resolved to fulfill their quotas. A large number of them are not satisfied with the established quota and plan <pb facs="5423972_7_1159.jpg" n="2"/>to go "over the top," a goal which they also hope to achieve. The appeals are not restricted to Jews alone, but to non-Jews as well. "The rebuilding of Palestine" Judge [Julian] Mack declared last Thursday at the Sherman Hotel, "concerns all of mankind."</p>
   <p>The full strength and power, of Jew and non-Jew, must be mobilized for this tremendous work, with the firm resolve that the campaign shall be successful. We are now stronger and better off financially than any other Jewish community (excluding New York) in the world. We must give and give freely; we must go "over the top," and raise more than the established quota.</p>
   <p>Forget your differences, extend hands to one another in order to unite for the purpose of solving the international Jewish problem through the rebuilding of Palestine. Both Zionists and non-Zionists have reached this <pb facs="5423972_7_1160.jpg" n="3"/>conclusion, one of the non-Zionists being Jacob H. Schiff.</p>
   <p>The famous banker and philanthropist appeals [for contributions] to the restoration fund. He envisions the country, under the secure protectorate of England, as one developing spiritually and economically.</p>
   <p>"Who of the American Jews," he asks, "will not be thankful and proud at the prospect of a new source of Jewish spiritual energy, which is to spring from the ancient ground, a source which will refresh the spirit of mankind, as the old one did? Of how much inestimable value will it be to the American Jews, and to Jews of other countries, when they and their posterity will be identified in the future with a community that thrives happily in a collective atmosphere, and contributes its share to the civilization of mankind? Such identification will strengthen everywhere the morale of the Jewish people generally, and of the individual Jew in particular."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1161.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Palestine, you must realize, possesses another interest for us at this moment, an immediate and urgent interest. The Jews of Eastern Europe are ruined. It is our duty to help them; no other Jews in the world are able to do it, and we must seriously undertake the preparation of Palestine for them.</p>
   <p>Do not wait until a committee visits you for your contribution to the fund. Send your contribution voluntarily to the Zionist headquarters at the Sherman Hotel, Parlor "O". The future Jewish generations will be profoundly grateful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
