<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-27">Jan. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Interesting Figures</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-27">Jan. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">INTERESTING FIGURES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: The first two paragraphs of this editorial were not transcribed, as their subject matter does not fall within the scope of this work]</p>
   <p>In Chicago neither the Orthodox Jews, nor the Reformed Jews, nor the radical Jews have done their share for the Keren Hayesod. The Orthodox Jews made a good beginning but fell down a little later, and to the present moment do not show any sign of life. The Jewish community of Chicago has thus far given forty thousand dollars in cash for the Keren Hayesod. There are about forty thousand dollars outstanding in pledges, but assuming that all those who have pledged contributions for the Keren Hayesod will pay cash, Chicago will have done less than St. Louis and less than Boston, and even less than Milwaukee, a minor Jewish community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0914.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Before we can tackle our wealthy classes and our masses in Chicago for the Keren Hayesod, we, the so called Orthodox Jews, must first give a good account of ourselves, and as long as we ourselves have not done our duty, we cannot call upon the others to give. We believe that it is possible to organize the Orthodox Jews in Chicago for the Keren Hayesod, because if it could be done in Philadelphia, it certainly could be done in Chicago, but it can only be done if there are a number of people who are ready to devote a month's time to this task. It will take a full month to organize the Keren Hayesod campaign in Chicago. We are interested to learn the names of the people who are ready to make this sacrifice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
