<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>, Vol. 27,
wk. of <date when="1904-05-28">May 28, 1904</date>. pp.314-316.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>, Vol. 27,
wk. of <date when="1904-05-28">May 28, 1904</date>. pp.314-316.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The spirit of self-betterment has entered into the ranks of the West Side Jews. A number of young men gathered together. Each subscribed a little sum as the foundation for a fund and a charter was secured, and thus the Chicago Hebrew Institute was organized.</p>
   <p>The objects of the Institute, as stated in the charter, are the promotion of education, moral, and physical culture, and civic training, and the social advancement of the Jewish residents of the city of Chicago. For those purposes the institution will maintain and conduct schools, libraries, laboratories, reading, class and club rooms, gymnasium, music and lecture halls, and acquire such lands and erect such buildings as may be required for the accomplishment of its purposes.</p>
   <p>A large sum of money is necessary for the erection of this institute, which is to be raised by popular subscription. Shares, at one dollar each, are being sold, thus enabling every man, woman, and child to actively participate in the realization of this undertaking.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0362.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The prospectus outlines a vast field of intended activities. In the department of English and Literature, there will be courses in elementary English for foreigners, and in English and American History. The curriculum provides for a department of commerce, of domestic art and science, of fine arts and music, a kindergarten with English classes for immigrant children, and a department of Hebrew language which will include classes in the Bible, Jewish History, conversation in Hebrew and Hebrew penmanship. There will be a department of moral work, with provision for a children's Sabbath School and a people's synagogue. By arrangement with several universities a course of lectures will be given each season. Concerts and entertainments will be arranged for children and adults. A Hebrew, German, French, and English library will be maintained.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
