<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-21">May 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">What Are You Doing for the Red Cross?</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Appeal by Judge Fischer to Support the Campaign of This Noble Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1415</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1415.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-21">May 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT ARE YOU DOING FOR THE RED CROSS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Appeal by Judge Fischer to Support the Campaign of This Noble Organization</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Red Cross, the most important organization [of its kind] in the world, is conducting a campaign for a fund of one hundred million dollars in order further to promote its noble and sacred work among the wounded on the battlefields and the suffering children and refugees wherever they may be.</p>
   <p>The Red Cross is an organization which belongs to no special group or religious sect; it performs its great work for every one alike. The mark 'Red Cross' is only an emblem and not an indication that it is a Christian organization. In all countries, organizations doing similar work wear the same emblem. Jacob Schiff, well known Jewish philanthropist of New York, was the treasurer of the Red Cross several years ago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1416.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In New York prominent rabbis and civic leaders issued an appeal for the support of the campaign of the Red Cross. Judge Harry M. Fischer, who is active in all war undertakings, is the first in Chicago to appeal to the great Jewish masses to contribute generously to the Red Cross fund. He does it in the following letter to the Courier:</p>
   <p>"The campaign for a fund of one hundred million dollars for the Red Cross was launched yesterday throughout America. Chicago's share to this fund is six million dollars. This money will be spent only for war work; to buy bandages and medicines for the wounded soldiers; to pay nurses for their services; to provide homes and food for the war orphans of France and Belgium.</p>
   <p>"The emblem of the Red Cross has no religious significance whatever. It is only a symbol which has been accepted for certain historic reasons by all organizations in the world doing similar work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1417.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Red Cross is the symbol of mercy and sympathy and the Jewish people, more than any other nationality, know how to support such an institution. Whatever war destroys, the Red Cross rebuilds, knowing neither friend nor enemy, nor race, nor religious sect, nor nationality. The Red Cross extends aid to all sufferers, cures the sick and saves human lives wherever it is able to.</p>
   <p>"I therefore beg of you to appeal through your newspaper to the Jews of Chicago that they should lend every possible assistance to Chicago to provide the six million dollars for this benevolent and humanitarian work.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Harry M. Fischer</p>
   <p>Judge of the Municipal Court."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
