<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-21">Apr. 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Neveleff Leaves for Eastern Europe as Relief Delegate of the Chicago Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0788</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0788.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-21">Apr. 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEVELEFF LEAVES FOR EASTERN EUROPE AS RELIEF DELEGATE OF THE CHICAGO COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Samuel Neveleff, manager of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee and the middle western bureau of the Central Relief Committee has been appointed [relief] commissioner by the Orthodox relief organization. He will go to Eastern Europe to investigate and promote the cultural work there.</p>
   <p>Mr. Neveleff is one of the best-known Jewish social workers of the country. For the last seven years he has been connected with relief work, and he has accomplished a great deal. His experience here will help him a great deal in his work there and the experience he gains there will help the relief work here, because our sisters and brothers in Eastern Europe still need our help.</p>
   <p>Mr. Neveleff leaves Chicago on Monday, April 24. He leaves New York on the <pb facs="5423972_7_0789.jpg" n="2"/>"Aquitania" on May 2 and he will be back in September.</p>
   <p>The officers of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee gave a banquet last night in his honor. The affair took place at the Covenant Club and sixty-five persons were present. Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt was toastmaster. The speakers were: Judge Hugo Pam, B. Horwich, Judge Joseph David, Isidor Liederman, Judge Harry M. Fisher, H. Steinberg, Max Korshak, and Miss Augusta Shapiro, who was appointed office manager of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee and of the midwestern bureau until Mr. Neveleff returns.</p>
   <p>The speakers spoke of Mr. Neveleff's distinguished services as a relief worker, expressed their confidence in him and his work, and wished him a happy journey. The guest of honor replied with an appropriate speech.</p>
   <p>Among the telegrams received by the guest of honor at the banquet was one from <pb facs="5423972_7_0790.jpg" n="3"/>Mr. and Mrs. S. B. Komaiko, and one from the Stanley Bureau of New York.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
