<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Charity and Education</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0896</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0896.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHARITY AND EDUCATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of education was discussed by some of the leaders of the Jewish Federation of Orthodox Charities at its last annual meeting. The men who are responsible for the policies of the Federation felt that something must be done in the field of education. The secretary of the Federation, Mr. Max Shulman, in his official report on the activity of the organization, touched upon the problem of education in connection with the work of the Federation. Judge [Harry] Fisher, in his speech, considered the problem from a general point of view. All other speakers, with the exception of Mr. [B.] Horwich, spoke in the same vein. All the leaders of Chicago Orthodoxy understand now that Jewish education in Chicago cannot continue in the same way. The Federation gives money, large sums of money, to various Jewish educational institutions, and thus thinks that it is discharging in full its duty to the Jewish youth of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0897.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Two problems were discussed at the annual meeting: first, the attitude of the Federation itself toward education, and second, Jewish education as a thing by itself, as an institution separate from the Federation. The leaders of the Federation are not in agreement among themselves on those two questions. One group thinks that the best thing to do would be for the Federation to give up its educational activity, and create a special organization that would devote itself exclusively to educational activity. This point of view is represented by the honorary president of the Federation, Mr. Julius Rosenwald, and by the secretary of the Federation Mr. Max Shulman. Mr. James Davis, the president of the Federation seems to be inclined to that point of view, but he is not committed to it, and will certainly agree to any practical proposal.</p>
   <p>There are also many influential members of the Federation who believe that the best solution of the problem would be for the Federation itself to become more interested in Jewish education. This group is afraid to take a chance <pb facs="5423972_7_0898.jpg" n="3"/>with a new organization that would be devoted only to Jewish education, because they do not believe that the Jews would support a special organization for educational purposes, or, as Mr. [J.] Leibner expressed it, that the Federation will suffer when its educational work is entirely eliminated from its program.</p>
   <p>Mr. Leibner's anxiety is entirely unfounded. All Jews know that, according to Jewish traditions, education is not a part of charity work. When the Chicago Jews support the Federation they do not do it because the Federation gives forty thousand dollars a year to philanthropic institutions. The Jews in Chicago will continue to contribute money to the Federation is primarily a charity organization and not an educational organization. Only in case of need should it devote itself to education, and when the need ceases to exist, there is not reason why a charity organization should have anything to do with cultural activity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0899.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But, after all, this is not a question of principle, but simply a question of practicality. There is nothing to argue about. The chief problem is the improvement of Jewish education in Chicago. If it is practical for the Federation alone to do it, then let it do so; however, according to Jewish tradition, this would not be right. It is also bad for the Jewish children to be conscious of the fact that the Jewish education they receive comes from a charity organization, but, under the present circumstances, we cannot consider somebody's feelings --  cannot consider that need of the moment. If it is possible, desirable, practical, to create a special organization for Jewish education, that is fine. The important thing is that something should be done immediately.</p>
   <p>We have to admit, though, that we cannot see the possibility at present of founding a special organization for Jewish education in Chicago because there are not sufficient workers available who would be willing to give up their time and money to create the new organization. Those who speak about a special Jewish education organization in Chicago mean well, but they are <pb facs="5423972_7_0900.jpg" n="5"/>not active workers. That is why we can understand very well the opinion of the more conservative elements who advise a cautious policy.</p>
   <p>For the present, at least, the Federation should occupy itself with the problem of Jewish education in Chicago. It is its duty to consider the problem more seriously, and not be satisfied with just giving some money to a couple of Talmud Torahs and one seminary. The time is past when the Federation was a collection agency only. Today it is the sole, central, community organization of Orthodox Chicago, and as such, it must assume a more serious attitude toward the problem of Jewish education.</p>
   <p>The Federation must have a board of education that would devote itself to education problems: improve the present institutions, create new institutions, introduce a common curriculum in all institutions (without affecting the method of teaching), take care of the teacher, textbooks, and so on. The existence of such a board in the Federation could accomplish a great deal for Jewish education in Chicago, and we hope that the Federation will see the need for such an organization and will create it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
