<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-16">Dec. 16, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Financial Drive for the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-16">Dec. 16, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FINANCIAL DRIVE FOR THE HEBREW SHELTERING AND IMMIGRANT AID SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are not yet able to announce the financial result of the drive made in the leading Orthodox synagogues of the city on Saturday, December 11, for the benefit of the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society of America. It is reported, however, that everywhere the congregations manifested great interest in the appeals made by their own or visiting speakers, and that this drive resulted in a better and more widespread understanding of the aims and achievements of the Society.</p>
   <p>The present phase of the Society's campaign in Chicago will come to a close with the departure of Field Secretary Rabbi Joseph Jasin on or about the 15th of December. After that, the work will be conducted in the form of a continuation campaign under the management of Mr. Adolph Copeland, president of the Chicago branch of the Society. The larger temples are conducting a mail campaign, and a considerable number of their members are still to be heard from.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1078.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A number of organizations which have promised contributions cannot act before the next general meeting, while some societies and volunteer groups are planning entertainment which require time for preparation. For these reasons, it can be seen that money will be coming in for the Society's building fund for many weeks or even months. In fact, Dr. Jasin is of the opinion that more money will be received after his departure than can be collected in the present drive under existing conditions in Chicago.</p>
   <p>This leads directly to the announcement that the building fund campaign will in no way be affected, either locally or nationally, by the passage of anti-immigration legislation now before Congress. A great many of the immigrants who come under the jurisdiction of the Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society are of the class against whom no restrictions are being proposed at present. They include wives and children of American residents, and other types whose right to enter America has never been challenged. It is important to hear this fact in mind, in order that the campaign may not be halted or weakened through a misunderstanding of the true situation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1079.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All who have contributions on hand are urgently requested to turn them over at once to Mr. Adolph Copeland, 316 West Jackson Boulevard.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
