<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-14">Nov. 14, 1905</date>, 2:2.
<title level="a">Unite to Relieve Jews Residents of Ghetto and Millionaires Contribute to Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1743</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1743.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-11-14">Nov. 14, 1905</date>, 2:2.
<title level="a">UNITE TO RELIEVE JEWS RESIDENTS OF GHETTO AND MILLIONAIRES CONTRIBUTE TO FUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Swept by a wave of feeling of almost unprecendented intensity, representatives of the Jewish race in Chicago and in America are rallying to the support of the destitute and suffering thousands in the provinces of Russia and within a fortnight will have contributed, it is estimated, $1,000,000 toward the amelioration of their deplorable conditions. As tragic chapter succeeds chapter in the long chronicle of hardships and intolerable oppression all differences of sect and caste are being obliterated in the single desire to bring relief to their stricken countrymen.</p>
   <p>Response to the call for funds has been instantaneous and the drawing-room and the tenement are vying with each other throughout all Chicago to swell the total contribution which the Russian Jewish relief committee is preparing to forward to New York. Single gifts yesterday ranged from $1000 to twenty-four cents, while contributions of $500 and $250 were common. When the books were closed for the day additional subscriptions amounting to $5,575.24 had been placed on deposit. It is expected that Chicago will contribute at least $100,000 to the general fund.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1744.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Yesterday's receipts represent voluntary offerings only sent to the central relief committee before the organization of the sub-committees which will have charge of a systematic canvass was completed and before any formal appeal had been made.</p>
   <p>Believing that the difficult task of reaching all sources of relief could best be handled by sub-committees representing the various trades, about fifty were organized yesterday and will take care of all collections in their departments.</p>
   <p>After naming the heads of the various auxiliary committees the central committee began the distribution of pamphlets containing a direct appeal to all Jews of Chicago to contribute whatever they can to swell the general fund. These pamphlets were mailed last night.</p>
   <p>Plan Theatrical Benefit</p>
   <p>To enlarge the movement Isaac A. Loeb, with several other prominent Jews, appealed to the theatrical managers of the city to give a great benefit performance at the Auditorium. Will Davis, manager of the Illinois Theatre, who was the first manager approached, gave the project cordial support and he was later joined by the managers <pb facs="5423972_7_1745.jpg" n="3"/>of all the important playhouses in the city. The date for the benefit has not yet been arranged, but the various managers have promised to offer their best talent to make the plan an artistic as well as a financial success. It is possible that Bernhardt may be included among the brilliant list of stars.</p>
   <p>Among Chicago Jews yesterday there was but a single topic of discussion how to increase the amount of the Russian contribution. By night those having the care of the central fund in charge expressed assurance that the hundred thousand mark would be passed. Secretary Henry J. Friedman of the central committee said:</p>
   <p>"The response has been general and most encouraging. We have scarcely had time to organize and the sub-committees have just been named for every trade in the city.</p>
   <p>"We expect to work rapidly, however, for the need is pressing in the extreme and we should have the bulk of the $100,000 to send within ten days or two weeks. It will be forwarded to Jacob Schiff, in New York, and he will have charge of its distribution. America should contribute not less than $1,000,000 to such a cause. New York alone expects to raise $300,000."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1746.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The singleness of purpose which animates the Chicago Hebrews was made apparent to the committee yesterday in countless contributions, accompanied by letters, in some cases the inclosure amounted to as little as twenty-five cents, but the letter accompanying the offering showed that its giving meant a sacrifice for some family. The contributor said that he could give no more, but that he would not give less in such a cause if he were obliged to do with two meals a day for a week to make the gift possible. Four or five such letters were received by Dr. Hirsch during the day. He said last night: "This movement extends to all the people irrespective of age or condition. The Sunday school class in my congregation obligated itself to do without any luxuries this week and give the money thus saved to the Russian fund. They are nothing but children, yet they grasped the significance of this important movement, and I expect the fund so collected next Sunday to amount to over $100."</p>
   <p>Stirred by the descriptions of suffering which they heard in their churches, Sunday residents of the ghetto district set about yesterday to aid their brethren in that dark Russia which many of them still remembered. The fact that hundreds of them are but recent arrivals in America and have been obliged to reduce their small hoardings to contribute to the relief fund testified to their devotion. Contributions of $5 from these people were common, although in many instances with the winter coming on <pb facs="5423972_7_1747.jpg" n="5"/>the gift meant a real sacrifice for the giver.</p>
   <p>Subscriptions taken up at small meetings in many parts of the city last night continued to swell the relief fund. Chicago lodge, No. 88, K. of P. contributed $140. Progressive lodge, No. 252, A. B. A. consisting principally of small merchants and working men, collected in one hour from among twenty-one members the sum of $392, with $400 promised.</p>
   <p>Additional contributions received yesterday follow:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>N. F. Leopold</cell>
     <cell>$250</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Fanny Bloomfield Zeisler</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sigmund Zeisler</cell>
     <cell>50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sen. A. C. Clark</cell>
     <cell>50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Isaac Kelm</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>D. Lewelewer</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Dr. E. G. Hirsch</cell>
     <cell>$150</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Mrs. M. A. Mozer</cell>
     <cell>250</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Ed. Mozer</cell>
     <cell>250</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>B. B. Baumgarden</cell>
     <cell>250</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>G. D. Glaser</cell>
     <cell>100</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>( - and many other individuals and Congregations making up the total sum mentioned in the beginning.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
