<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-10-18">10/18/09</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Home for the Aged Is Giving Up the Idea of Benefit Balls.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-10-18">10/18/09</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH HOME FOR THE AGED IS GIVING UP THE IDEA OF BENEFIT BALLS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting yesterday at the Jewish Home for the Aged was a big success.</p>
   <p>Mr. Margolis, President of the Home, made known to the public that hereafter, there will be no more annual benefit balls. It seemed that this new plan was very satisfactory to all concerned.</p>
   <p>Mr. Margolis appealed to the members and the public at large to be more liberal with their donations and that each member should raise the amount of their dues in order to meet the deficit which the former balls made up.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Benjamin Davis read a few letters from several very prominent Jewish leaders who have approved the new plan of eliminating the annual benefit balls for the Home. Mr. Siegel, the secretary and Mr. Baumgarten, the treasurer made a report in regard to the growth of the institution.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, Rabbis Epstein and Budainsky, with their able addresses, warmed the hearts of those who assembled at the meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many in the audience have immediately responded by raising the amount of their dues and pledged to do all in their power to assist in getting new members for this cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
