<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01">Dec. 1918: Jan. 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[The Midwest Aid Society Organizes Relief Work]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1919-01">Dec. 1918: Jan. 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[THE MIDWEST AID SOCIETY ORGANIZES RELIEF WORK]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Mid-West Aid Society consisting of young men and women, joined hands for the purpose of carrying through a piece of constructive relief work. The case being that of a "bread-winner" of the family who became incapacitated as a result of illness, and who could no longer attend to his regular employment. He found aid through the organization to the extent of $1,200. This sum, in this particular instance, plus a contribution which was made by the Odd Fellows Lodge, placed the family on its feet again; they having been established in a small business.</p>
   <p>The organization is interested particularly in cases of such nature. The Jewish Farmers' Colony has originally been the dream and the vision of one individual. Its organizer has the ambition of interesting one-hundred Jews who have a minimum capital of $1,000 at their disposal. The purpose is to found a colony of Jewish farmers in the State of Michigan. They have at the present time fifty members who have paid part on account, of the thousand dollars. The society has been in touch with the Secretary of Agriculture in the State of Michigan, and they are negotiating a prospective <pb facs="5423972_7_1364.jpg" n="2"/>purchase of tracts of land in that State for the establishment of their little colony. The society has distributed posters all over the West Side and has done considerable advertising in the Yiddish newspapers, appealing to Jews to join them and make their dream a reality. The Jewish Agricultural and Industrial Aid Society, through their Western representative, has been in very close touch with this organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
