<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-02">Mar. 2, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Shekel for the National Fund</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0658</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0658.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-02">Mar. 2, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A SHEKEL FOR THE NATIONAL FUND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, Purim [festival observed by the Jews on the 14th day of the month of Adar in commemoration of their deliverance from the hands of Haman], is National Fund Day. Every synagogue will take up a collection of shekels--one dollar in American money--for the National Fund, and every Jew who goes to the synagogue to listen to the story of Esther should not and must not forget to give his shekel to the National Fund. Every Jew can afford to give a dollar for Palestine. It is only logical that when you listen to the story of Haman, you should realize that the sensible way to break loose from the clutches of Haman is by rebuilding Palestine--and Palestine can only be built by purchasing as much land as possible and settling Jews on that land. The chief task of the National Fund is to purchase land in Palestine. This is the simplest but most practical plan of transforming Palestine into <pb facs="5423972_7_0659.jpg" n="2"/>Eretz Israel (Land of Israel). Nearly everything that has been built in Palestine in the past years was built by the National Fund, i.e., with your nickels, with your quarters, with your dollars which you have given to the National Fund.</p>
   <p>The National Fund Commission determined to set aside Purim as National Fund Day. The rabbis of this city promised to help carry out the plans of the Commission. We hope that the worthy rabbis will keep their promise and that the presidents of the synagogues will also do their duty in this matter.</p>
   <p>Every Jew who enters the synagogue this morning should remember to give his shekel--his dollar to the National Fund. By doing so, he will become no poorer, but Palestine will become richer.</p>
   <p>Give your shekel today for constructive work in Palestine. Today is Purim; prepare yourselves for Passover--the Liberation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
