<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-07-05">July 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Keep Your Promise.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1030</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1030.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-07-05">July 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">KEEP YOUR PROMISE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prior to his election, Judge Harry Fisher, in a letter addressed to the editor of this paper, pledged himself to come to the aid of the Jewish orphans in Ukrainia, by organizing a conference, in Chicago, with the object of bringing relief to the unfortunate little ones in the land of pogroms.</p>
   <p>Thousands of Jews in Chicago are interested in the fate and future of the Jewish orphans in Ukrainia, and everywhere attempts are being made to get them out of the country of blood and murder, and to educate them either in the western countries or in Palestine. South African Jewry has exhibited its interest in these unfortunate orphans by sending a committee to Ukrainia to bring over as many orphans as possible to South Africa.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1031.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Canadian and Australian Jewry is pursuing a similar policy, and in many Jewish communities in the United States efforts are made to rescue as many orphans as possible and to bring them here.</p>
   <p>Chicago Jewry has done little to help the Ukrainian Jewish orphans. The Jew in Chicago who knows the Ukrainian situation best, is Judge Fisher, who visited parts of Ukrainia last year and who has witnessed all the indescribable misery prevailing there. Because of his ability to help, he promised to organize the movement in Chicago, for bringing relief to our orphans in Ukrainia. We wish to remind the Judge of his promise given to the Jewish public in Chicago through the Jewish Courier. We wish to remind him of his pledge to call a conference of leading Chicago Jews to organize relief work for Ukrainian orphans. We deem it our duty to remind Judge Fisher of his solemn promise, because we notice that he has not done <pb facs="5423972_7_1032.jpg" n="3"/>anything in the matter yet and we know that the situation of hundreds of thousands of Jewish orphans in Ukrainia, is not improving, but is becoming worse from day to day. They are dying by the thousands, because of lack of food and because of all the diseases, which accompany famine and misery. The cause is a holy one. No hours should be lost in working for it. We therefore say to Judge Fisher:</p>
   <p>"Judge, live up to your pledge. We are sure that you will find cooperators once you have started. The Jewish public in Chicago will support you to the limit. The Jewish press will do likewise, and every Jew in Chicago will do his duty and come to the aid of those unfortunate ones."</p>
   <p>It is true that the season is not favorable for the initiation of a new movement. People are unwilling to attend meetings at this time of the year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1033.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Many people are out of town. Still we believe that as soon as the signal is given for the movement, thousands of Jews in Chicago will join. They are only waiting for someone to give the signal, and it is up to Judge Fisher to do it now.</p>
   <p>We hope that a second reminder will not be necessary. We hope that Judge Fisher will live up to his promise very soon, and will call a conference of leading Chicago Jews to consider the problem of our orphans in Ukrainia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
