<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-12-19">Dec. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Reaching the Quota</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0938</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0938.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-12-19">Dec. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">REACHING THE QUOTA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whatever the final result of the drive for the fourteen-million-dollar relief fund in Chicago may be, it can already be said that as far as Chicago is concerned it is a tremendous success. The quota has already been reached. One and a half million dollars has been subscribed within two weeks, and considering the abnormal times, one must admit that Chicago Jewry has every reason to be proud of this great philanthropic accomplishment. But the leaders of the drive are not satisfied with merely reaching the quota. They are out for two million dollars, and they are out for this two million dollars not because they want to skin the donors, but because they want to set an example for the whole country. We believe it is worth a half-million dollars for a Jewish community like Chicago to be called the most philanthropic Jewish community in the world. This half-million dollars above the quota will bring a million dollars more in other cities, because this additional half a million will be a source of inspiration to every Jew <pb facs="5423972_7_0939.jpg" n="2"/>interested in relief work in every city and state of the Union.</p>
   <p>To get this additional half-million dollars, the relief drive has been prolonged for another week, and instead of ending on the eighteenth, as originally planned, it will end on the twenty-fifth of December, the first day of Hanukkah, when Chicago Jewry will make a Hanukkah present of two million dollars to Eastern European Jewry--a nice present indeed.</p>
   <p>We may take it for granted that the additional half-million dollars, the present goal of the leaders of the relief fund, will be gotten within the next week, and then, after Chicago will have done more than its duty, every experienced communal worker will admit that not even a third of Chicago Jewry has participated in, and contributed towards, the relief fund. Only the prominent Jews, men of wealth and station in life, men of influence who command respect, and men in the public eye have been reached in this drive. The anonymous mass of Jews in the city of Chicago, small <pb facs="5423972_7_0940.jpg" n="3"/>tradespeople, workingmen, men of the liberal professions, etc., have either not been reached at all or they have not done their share. If every Chicago Jew would have given his share and would have done his bit, not two but five million dollars could have been collected, because those who gave, gave as much as they could, and have demonstrated by their giving the tremendous philanthropic possibilities in Chicago. There are thousands of Jews in Chicago, not in touch with Jewish life and not affiliated with Jewish organizations, who have not given anything for relief this time and have not given before either, mainly because we had no access to them and did not know how to reach them; but the leaders of a Jewish community like Chicago should find means and ways how to reach every Jew in Chicago in such an emergency. Because so many Jews in Chicago do not give a cent for Jewish charities or for any other Jewish purpose, the others must give more, and this one thing is an injustice to those whom we reach and who do give, and an injustice to the other great Jewish national enterprises and institutions which cannot get what they ought to get from those Jews who are <pb facs="5423972_7_0941.jpg" n="4"/>responding generously to relief appeals, because those who respond have also to give for those who do not give anything. If we could reach every Jew in Chicago and make him contribute his share towards such a fund as the relief fund, we could also approach the generous Jews to give something for the Keren Hayesod too, but since these generous Jews whom we reach give all they can for relief, they are not likely to give for the Keren Hayesod, and in this way the cause of Palestine and the cause of a good many other Jewish enterprises must suffer because we lack a proper communal organization in the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>American Jewry is confronted with tremendous problems, and is responsible for the welfare of the Jews in Europe as far as it can be responsible, and it is also responsible for the happiness of future Jewish generations in Palestine. This consideration alone should compel us to cause every Jew in America, every Jew in Chicago, to be on his post as a Jew, and to be within reach in case of emergency, and this is only possible through a <pb facs="5423972_7_0942.jpg" n="5"/>reorganization of our communal fabric. Now it is not organized at all. The present need of our people in Europe and in Palestine compels us to organize our community, so that we can exploit and make use of all the philanthropic energies and of all the philanthropic possibilities within American Jewry and especially within Chicago Jewry. Unless we do this, our great national enterprises will always suffer and we will always be short financially.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
