<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Honor Duty of Chicago's Jews</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN HONOR DUTY OF CHICAGO'S JEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The development of the Jewish life in America has led thereto, that small groups should unite into large units, in order to be able to better assist the individual, whom nature did not bless with riches, or to help the one, who is a victim of circumstances and conditions. The philanthropic life of the American Jews evinces a tendency of centralization. This is the best demonstration that American Jewry is developing itself in a normal manner.</p>
   <p>When the philanthropic centralization of the Jews in America will be more complete, then the other interest groups will also unite. Instead of congregations we shall have a Kehilah; in place of small groups and cliques, we shall have powerful organizations. But in order to reach this position <pb facs="5423972_7_1366.jpg" n="2"/>of a unity of the forces, it is our duty first to complete the philanthropic unity.</p>
   <p>Every Jew in this country who supports the federated charities of his city not only helps the poor and the sick, the orphans and the aged, but he also helps to strengthen the unity of the Jewish forces in this country. The Federated Charities of the Orthodox Jews of Chicago which is now conducting a campaign for thirty-six thousand dollars, is one of those central organizations of the Jews in America, which is a positive and constructive force. In it already rests the possibility of a united Jewish Kehilah in Chicago, and to assist this Federation to do its work is not only a pure human and a real Jewish duty, but is also a political duty of every Chicago Jew. The Federated cements the Jewish forces of Chicago; it is the center of Jewish life in Chicago, and the stronger it is the stronger <pb facs="5423972_7_1367.jpg" n="3"/>is the Jewish unity in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The major part of the work which should be done by the Kehilah, is performed by the Federated. It maintains an orphanage, a home for the aged, and a consumptive society. It is the organizing force of the Talmud Torahs, it provides food for the hungry through the society "Bread for the Hungry" and garments for the dead through the society of "Free Burial Association"; it supports the Yeshivah Etz Chaim. In short, it cares for those, who cannot endure the struggle for existence themselves and, as far as possible, it also helps to preserve and attend to the spiritual interests of the Chicago's Jewry by supporting the Jewish education of the youth.</p>
   <p>So far, the Federated has performed its task in such a manner, that every Jew of Chicago could be proud of its activity. It was a helping and constructive power in the midst of the best Jewish forces in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1368.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>While the Federated is now conducting a campaign to be able to carry on its work, no Jew in Chicago should refuse in helping this body, which provides food for the poor, a resting place for the aged and an education to the young. It is the honor duty of every Jew in Chicago in whose heart lives a spark of Jewishness and an interest for the fate of the suffering and tormented, to help the Federated with all his power, to give until it does good....</p>
   <p>New problems now appear before the Federated, which should be solved at once. The influenza has brought chaos into the Jewish neighborhood, has torn away parents from many poor Jewish children; many unfortunate orphans must be reared; the Jews of Chicago must provide for their orphans like any other Jewish community. With the funds which the Federated has now at its disposal, it cannot rear the large number of new orphans. It must have financial assistance in order to be able to proceed with this sacred task, <pb facs="5423972_7_1369.jpg" n="5"/>otherwise the children will grow up bad Jews and bad humans....</p>
   <p>Is there a Jew in Chicago who has the heart to refuse help to the orphans? Is there a Jew in Chicago who does not care to provide the orphans with a proper, and good Jewish education? We think too much of the goodheartedness of the Jews of Chicago, to believe for a moment, that they will refuse to help the unfortunate orphans, and we are convinced that when the Federated will stretch out its arm for the sake of the orphans, every Jew in Chicago will give his utmost.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, we want to call our readers attention to another important point. The Federated, in reality, is an organization of Eastern European Jews. Until a few years ago, the German Jews in America would always claim that they had a right to be the political and spiritual leaders of the Eastern European Jews, because they provide for their philanthropic needs; <pb facs="5423972_7_1370.jpg" n="6"/>they, the German Jews, are the givers, and we, the Eastern European Jews are the receivers. But when the Eastern European Jews provide themselves for their poor, sick and wretched, no one then will have the audacity to play the role of their guardians.</p>
   <p>We, Eastern European Jews, can defend our democracy only through our philanthropic emancipation. When we help ourselves, we could and should have our own leaders, guiding us politically and speak for us through our own representatives.</p>
   <p>It is also to be noted that to help the Federated is more than a philanthropic act.</p>
   <p>And, therefore, every Jew in Chicago who possesses a feeling of mercy for our poor and sick and a feeling of independence as Jew and human will help the Federated, and make its campaign a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
