<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-01">Feb. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Facts and Figures about the Chicago Joint Relief Committee</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0519</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0519.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-01">Feb. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">FACTS AND FIGURES ABOUT THE CHICAGO JOINT RELIEF COMMITTEE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Joint Relief Committee had a meeting last Tuesday night at the Hebrew Theological College. Rabbis and representatives of synagogues and organizations were present at the meeting. The noble work which the Chicago Joint Relief Committee has been doing for the souls and bodies of the Jews of Eastern Europe and Palestine, stood the committee in good stead at that meeting. Mr. [B.] Horwich, the chairman and his co-workers had planned to discontinue the activities of the Chicago office. Miss Augusta Shapiro, the manager of the Chicago office, had prepared her resignation. Her reasons for resigning were: first, people do not respond properly any more to appeals for money, and second, people from other organizations seek to concentrate the entire attention of the public upon their work. Those present at the meeting, after listening to the final report of Mr. Howrich on the activities <pb facs="5423972_7_0520.jpg" n="2"/>of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee, asked Mr. Howrich, in fact, they ordered him and the other relief workers to go on with their work.</p>
   <p>It was an inspiring moment. Everybody present at the meeting was convinced that the Jews of the European countries cannot, as yet, take complete charge of their own affairs; that the effects of the war are still present; that the cultural institutions of Eastern Europe and Palestine are in need; that the Central Relief Committee, of which the Chicago committee is a part, is the only organization which can and must continue to help those institutions. Everybody present promised co-operation.</p>
   <p>Chicago Jews will thus continue to be among those who support the theological seminaries of Slobodka, Telz, Lomza, Ponevez, Kir, and dozens of smaller seminaries, and hundreds of Talmud Torahs in Eastern Europe and Palestine, which the Jews there cannot themselves maintain.</p>
   <p>Mr. Horwich delivered a complete and detailed report on the activities of <pb facs="5423972_7_0521.jpg" n="3"/>the Chicago Joint Relief Committee since its inception. He read the auditor's report of the income and expenditures of the office during that time. Those present fully approved the report and pledged themselves to co-operate in further relief work.</p>
   <p>A committee of nine was at once appointed to administer the office in co-operation with Mr. Horwich. The committee will consist of three members from the Theological college and three members from the United Orthodox Congregations; the remaining three are to be appointed by the chairman.</p>
   <p>Here are a few facts and figures which may be of interest to you. They are taken from Mr. Horwich's report and from the auditor's report.</p>
   <p>The total income of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee from December, 1914, to December, 1923, was $3,328,920.59. The administrative expenses during that time were $109,131.11. The year 1920 was the best year the Chicago Joint Relief Committee ever had. It raised $1,065,880.91 that year, while during the <pb facs="5423972_7_0522.jpg" n="4"/>preceding year, 1923, it raised only $74,554.50. The expenses last year were $7,406.75. A good deal more money could have been raised last year if proper co-operation had been obtained and if all the pledged contributions had been paid.</p>
   <p>It cost the Chicago Joint Relief Committee about three and three-eighths per cent to raise a sum exceeding three million dollars. The Chicago office, besides raising money for relief, was also busy sending food to Russia and other places, and giving out information about conditions across the sea.</p>
   <p>Only one man went to Europe at the expense of the Chicago Joint Relief Committee. That man was Mr. Samuel Neueleff. His trip cost $3,400. Mr. B. Horwich paid his own way. The cost of the trips of Judge Harry M. Fisher and Julius Sauitsky were covered by the Joint Distribution Committee. Fisher's trip cost $5,500--$3,500 was paid by the Joint Distribution Committee and $2,000 by private subscriptions. He has done important work and deserves our thanks. Sauitsky was a member of a group, which had been favorably mentioned <pb facs="5423972_7_0523.jpg" n="5"/>by Dr. Bogen.</p>
   <p>The Joint Relief Committee, to whom all the money contributed by American Jews for relief is turned over, received $56,213,335.20 and distributed $52,493,335.22 in forty-one countries. The sum of $3,720,000 has been assigned for further work. Seven million dollars, out of the fifty-six million, was spent in Palestine, the Jewish population of which constitutes one per cent of the Jewish sufferers in the entire "progrom and war territory". Palestine has thus received fourteen per cent of the entire sum spent on relief. The money was distributed there in the following manner:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>General Relief</cell>
     <cell>30%</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Medical help</cell>
     <cell>10%</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Reconstruction</cell>
     <cell>25%</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Children</cell>
     <cell>15%</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Culture</cell>
     <cell>2%</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0524.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Every Jew will rejoice at the publication of these figures. We hope that even those Zionists who complain about the relief work, for personal reasons, or because they are overenthusiastic about the Zionist ideal, will also be satisfied.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Joint Relief Committee shares with the American Jews the blessings showered upon us by the Jews across the sea who have received help. The committee has done its work brilliantly; it has helped to keep up the spirit of the Jews in the pogrom-and war-suffering countries. The Chicago Jews, for whom it does this noble work, are proud of it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
