<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-16">Feb. 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Finally</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-16">Feb. 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">FINALLY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish public has finally awakened to the consciousness of its duty concerning the business of M'shulochim [agents representing charitable institutions and theological seminaries; most of them represent out-of-town and foreign institutions]. Letters from all parts of the city flow into this editorial office daily. These letters criticize the irresponsibility prevailing in this city in the field of foreign charities. Since we began to publicize this evil in our philanthropic life, we have become aware of various angles of the M'shulochim business. From the information we receive from trustworthy and reliable sources, we can state, without exaggeration, that a certain type of M'shulochim confiscates ninety per cent of the money which he collects, and many others pocket all of the money for themselves. To which category the "noted" M'shuloch Hirsh Teilzin belongs, we cannot say, but we have learned that he is a M'shuloch of a certain office in New York, which <pb facs="5423972_7_0690.jpg" n="2"/>commissions M'sholochim throughout the country in behalf of dubious institutions, and that he pockets nine tenths of the money for himself.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, Hirsh Teilzin is not the only "specialist" in this field. Chicago Jews who have been prominent in public life for many years, know of many scandalous cases.</p>
   <p>The result is that legitimate institutions suffer most of all. While the students of large theological seminaries in Lithuania are starving to death, the M'shulochim are plundering the Jewish districts of America and stuffing their pockets each year with thousands and tens of thousands of dollars. As long as we tolerate the existence of such a situation, we are aiding the swindlers to extort money from Jews, and are helping to ruin necessary and legitimate institutions.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of the [Jewish] leaders of this city to put a stop immediately to this deplorable situation. An authoritative committee must forthwith be <pb facs="5423972_7_0691.jpg" n="3"/>organized to regulate the whole M'shulochim business. The whole work of foreign charities must be controlled not by individual trustees, but by a group of rabbis and prominent leaders. If each M'shuloch has the privilege of selecting his own trustee in this city, he will not be able to establish order because the trustee will not, and cannot know what the M'shuloch is doing and how much money he is collecting. A committee can control a M'shuloch--and without the control of a committee, nothing can be accomplished.</p>
   <p>A meeting will take place Monday evening in the Hebrew Theological College, at which rabbis and prominent leaders will consider this question. We hope that this meeting will establish order in the field of our philanthropic work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
