<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-17">Sept. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The New Emissary</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-17">Sept. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW EMISSARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Who is this Rabbi Moses Weinstok, and what kind of an institution is the United Home for Old Men and Women in Palestine, for which he is collecting money in Chicago? People say that Rabbi Weinstok enters a Jewish residence or store, makes himself at home, as if he had known the family for a long time, and claims that one or another rabbi of Chicago will vouch for him. He ends his speech in a mixture of Yiddish and English: "The old people of the institution, four hundred strong, are praying for the donors at the Wailing Wall and at the grave of Mother Rachel, God bless her memory." This Rabbi Weinstok is now operating on Randolph Street. Max Malter has been his victim twice, and paid a dollar each time.</p>
   <p>What kind of a new plague is this on Jewish picketbooks? This is even worse than Rabbi Bzalel Silberman who wanted people to trust him personally. He <pb facs="5423972_7_0752.jpg" n="2"/>looked like a typical Jew from the old country, with his flowing beard and sideburns. The newly arrived beggar, however, refers to other people who say they have never heard of him. No rabbi in Chicago has ever issued any credentials to him.</p>
   <p>It would thus seem that Jewish pockets are free pickings. This is the result of not having an organized rabbi rate in Chicago and not having proper supervision of the activities of the collectors in Chicago who claim to represent philanthropic institutions. The sad part of the story is that the honest collector suffers because of the faker. In many Jewish homes where the householder has discovered that he has been fooled, no exception is made now, and the honest collector as well as the crook is chased away.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
