<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-21">Nov. 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-21">Nov. 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The thousands of Jewish wanderers, who are now arriving here from Eastern Europe, are war- and pogrom-victims; they are not merely escaping from religious and political persecution, or from economic pressure; they are escaping a veritable hell. They are escaping in order to save their lives, which are always in danger from bands of bloodthirsty murderers who can spill Jewish blood with impunity. All of Eastern Europe is rife with pogroms. Pogroms and the slaughtering of Jews have become daily occurrences, rather than exceptions, as they used to be.</p>
   <p>The Jewish wanderer, in flight from the menace of pogroms in his native land, has no time to think of his future in a new country. When one flees from a fire-stricken area, one is satisfied to escape with one's life. There is no time <pb facs="5423972_7_1102.jpg" n="2"/>for a person to think of providing himself with clothes, or of saving his last personal belongings. If the wanderer does succeed in taking anything with him, it soon disappears in the long and tiresome journey; he must undergo untold tribulations before he finally lives to see the blessed shores of America. It has always been a noble and sacred duty to help the lonely Jewish immigrant, when he lands on these shores, but it is even more so now, when every new arrival is a victim of the war or of pogroms.</p>
   <p>The Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society is the only great organization of American Jewry which takes care of the immigrants. Fifty thousand Jewish immigrants have already landed here this year, and this is only the beginning of the tremendous stream of immigration. The arriving Jewish masses must be assisted when they land here. Their relatives, from whom they have been separated as a result of the war, must be found. The American Jews must also be given assistance in locating their relatives across the sea; these relatives must either <pb facs="5423972_7_1103.jpg" n="3"/>be helped in their native land, or they must be brought over here; war and pogroms have driven them from their former homes. Two hundred thousand persons here applied to the Society last year for help in locating their relatives in Eastern Europe. In the New York office alone, more than thirty thousand affidavits were made out to bring relatives over here; thousands and thousands of such affidavits were made out in the branches of the national organization, of which the Hebrew Sheltering Home on Morgan Street is one, and relatives [of American Jews] were contacted in this way.</p>
   <p>This is a small example of the colossal and manifold activities of the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society, which naturally needs large financial resources. Not long ago, the Society launched a drive throughout the country to raise four hundred thousand dollars in order to be prepared for the great stream of immigration, which has just begun. The quota for Chicago has been set at fifty thousand dollars, and Rabbi Jasin of New York, together with <pb facs="5423972_7_1104.jpg" n="4"/>Mr. Adolph Copeland, president of the local Hebrew Sheltering Home, are heading the drive to raise this sum.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Jasin, Mr. Copeland, and a committee of well-known men and women are working diligently to make the drive a success, and the drive will be successful, if everyone contributes as much as he possibly can. The fifty thousand dollars must be raised. Chicago Jews must not lag behind other cities. Every Jew of Chicago, regardless of rank, must contribute his share to the fund, which benefits immigrants of all classes.</p>
   <p>If you have not yet performed your duty, you must hasten to do so. Remember that this is for the salvation of thousands upon thousands of your brothers and sisters who are seeking to flee from the sword and flame. The headquarters for the drive are located in the establishment of Mr. Copeland, 316 West Jackson Boulevard, where personal contributions can be made, or can be sent through the mail. Make your contribution soon!</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1105.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The experiences of everyday life show us that people spend time and energy in the field of social work, but as soon as they cease to be active, or, God forbid, if they should die, their entire work is forgotten overnight. The development of Chicago owes a great deal to the energy, courage, and self-sacrifice of the Jewish pioneers who settled here in the forties; they helped Chicago reach its present position, its present greatness and wealth.</p>
   <p>Gentiles have a custom of making a record of every event, and of placing it in historical archives, so that future generations may know what took place in the past and how to adjust themselves in the future.</p>
   <p>For many years, Mr. H. L. Meites, one of the intelligent Jews of Chicago, an artist in the local world of printing, had a plan in mind to publish in book form The History of The Jews Of Chicago, which would give an historical account of all the events in the development of Jewish life in Chicago; how the various institutions were founded and developed, and who the guiding spirits were who helped <pb facs="5423972_7_1106.jpg" n="6"/>in this development.</p>
   <p>Thousands and thousands of dollars were spent in gathering the necessary material, and Mr. Meites was also successful in arousing the interest of such personalities as Julius Rosenwald, Judge Julian W. Mack, Dr. Emil G. Hirsch, M. E. Greenebaum, etc!, in his undertaking. However, as a result of the war, the work stopped and the [Jewish Historical] Society dissolved.</p>
   <p>Now the well-known social worker Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt has become interested in this undertaking. He decided to reorganize the Jewish Historical Society of Illinois; to take in new forces and to publish this important book: The History Of The Jews Of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rosenblatt is of the opinion that a volume of this sort will not only give deserved credit to the community leaders, but will also serve as a model for our children and our children's children, that they may continue our work.</p>
   <p>"It is very important," said Mr. Rosenblatt, "that we develop in our youth a <pb facs="5423972_7_1107.jpg" n="7"/>desire to become interested in community work, for no one lives forever, and we must see that the work for which we have sacrificed so much, is continued in the same spirit. The historical work which Mr. Meites plans to publish, will serve not only as an inspiration to our children, but will also close the mouths of the anti-Semites, when they see, from historical documents, how much our Jews have contributed to the development of Chicago, as well as in the field of Charity and Americanization."</p>
   <p>This enterprise is certain to be a success. True, it is a stupendous undertaking, and will cost an enormous sum of money. But such trifles do not frighten Mr. Rosenblatt. He does not undertake anything unless he is certain of success. This case will be no exception.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
