<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-17">Aug. 17, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Large Crowd </title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1488</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1488.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-08-17">Aug. 17, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">LARGE CROWD <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last evening a large crowd attended the mass meeting at the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>esis Israel Congregation to hid the relief emissary to Europe, Rabbi <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>B. Abramovitz of St. Louis--the representative of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>erican Orthodox Jewry--a hearty farewell and wish him success in his great and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ous undertaking. All those present expressed great satisfaction with the Joint Distribution Committee's resolution which calls for the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of a commission of five renowned personalities to study the condition of the war-suffering Jews and to investigate in what manner the American relief money is being distributed among the Jewish war victims.</p>
   <p>The speakers treated the relief work<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> distribution questions very carefully. As chairman Rabbi Ephraim Epstein explained the purpose of this meeting and explained what Rabbi Abramovitz's trip means to the Jews. In a moving speech, Rabbi Abraham Cardon described the horrible sufferings the war has brought to the majority of Jews, and wished the relief emissary <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>safe <pb facs="5423972_7_1489.jpg" n="2"/>journey.</p>
   <p>The keynote speech was delivered by Mr. Leon Zolotkoff, who shed light on the strife between the nationalistic elements and the "assimilators" who control the distribution of money among Jews in nearly all the belligerent countries. Because the German assimilators and their agents in Warsaw and elsewhere have been making exceptions in the distribution of American relief money, it was resolved that an American commission should be sent to investigate this matter thoroughly and also to improve the system of distributing relief money. Mr. Zolotkoff proposed a resolution demanding that American relief money not be given into the hands of the European assimilators who make exceptions in the case of the nationalistically inclined elements. In an inspiring message, Rabbi Saul Silber supported this resolution. The resolution was unanimously adopted by those assembled.</p>
   <p>The last speaker was the relief emissary, Rabbi Abramovitz, who was given a <pb facs="5423972_7_1490.jpg" n="3"/>grand reception as he presented his plans to the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>udience. After the meeting Rabbi Abramovitz immediately departed for New York, from where he will sail for Europe on August 23, with five other members of the commission.</p>
   <p>Another member of the commission, also representing the Middle <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>est, is Mr. Jacob Billikopf of Kansas City. Mr. Billikopf will soon pass through Chicago on his way to New York. He is one of the most prominent Jewish social workers and also the superintendent of the Kansas City Educational Institute.</p>
   <p>The relief emissary was accompanied to the depot by a committee of prominent rabbis and laymen, the same group which had welcomed him upon his arrival at the station. In the afternoon the local rabbis and prominent laymen conferred with Rabbi Abramovitz about the future of Orthodox Jewry in Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
