<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-23">July 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Jewish Educational Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-23">July 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEWISH EDUCATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Chicago's West Side and in other parts of the city where Jews live, this rule prevails: "Keep the youngsters occupied", but prominent Northwest Side Jews have apparently not yet heard of this slogan. Their Jewish Educational Alliance is not an institution of which they can be proud.</p>
   <p>There are several thousand Jewish children on the Northwest Side who have nothing to occupy their time after they return from school or business. They actually have no Jewish Center because the Educational Alliance is not an institution, but is simply a structure with four bare walls. Bare walls, of course, hold little attraction for the Jewish children of the neighborhood. In its present condition, what is there that one can do at this institution? Can the children listen to recitations, read, write, or prepare their studies? In its present sadly neglected state, the Alliance can offer nothing of either a social or intellectual nature to the Jewish children of the neighborhood. The building <pb facs="5423972_7_0232.jpg" n="2"/>which houses the Alliance is not modern, nor does it possess the equipment which would offer the Jewish youth a chance to develop their bodies and souls. Jewish youth, living in the vicinity of the Educational Alliance, actually have no Center. Lacking it, they grow up without knowledge of the Torah and without respect [for Judaism]. Thus the young people spend their free time at nickel shows, go from there to pool rooms and cheap cabarets. The results of such education can easily be foreseen.</p>
   <p>The responsibility for part of the general as well as Jewish education of the youth of the Northwest Side rests upon the prominent men of the neighborhood, whose duty it is to establish a Center for the neighborhood youth.</p>
   <p>A Center would provide opportunities for the development of their bodies and souls, and would thus keep them on the straight and narrow path.</p>
   <p>Up to the present time, the community leaders have neglected their duty to the Jewish youth of the neighborhood, and have, therefore, sinned greatly against the community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0233.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Jews of the Northwest Side cannot demand that people in other parts of the city should do their work for them because they are, thank goodness, prosperous and well able to support an institution such as the Educational Alliance. This institution is not, and should not be limited to any special class, but should serve all classes of the Jewish community. The prominent men who should support the Alliance will, by so doing, serve their own children.</p>
   <p>I believe that an institution such as the Educational Alliance is not a luxury, but is rather, an absolute necessity. Through the Educational Alliance, if it has the proper foundation, we can rear a generation of healthy individuals, healthy Jews. It is not enough to send your children to Talmud Torahs. When the child reaches the age of fifteen, a place must be found where he can spend his time in a Jewish atmosphere, and where he can continue his general as well as Jewish education. Since there is no Center, no up-to-date Educational Alliance, the Jewish youth of the neighborhood is driven to cheap movies, cheap cabarets, and pool rooms which have a demoralizing effect upon young minds. These very dubious places would have fewer customers, and the number of idle youth on the Northwest Side would be considerably less if you, the prominent <pb facs="5423972_7_0234.jpg" n="4"/>householders of the Northwest Side, would do your duty to the Jewish youth of the neighborhood.</p>
   <p>If you continue to neglect your youth, and do not provide a Center such as a Jewish Educational Alliance for them, to help them build their bodies and souls, then you will see, in the very near future, a generation of which you cannot be proud.</p>
   <p>Twenty-five or thirty thousand dollars is needed in order to reorganize the Educational Alliance on a modern basis, to attract the youth, and to offer it everything it needs. Let the total sum required, remain a secret between us; if you want to, you can secure this sum without any trouble. You know that we don't have to make collections for you; if God has been good to you, why shouldn't you want to help your children?</p>
   <p>We urge you, therefore, to roll up your sleeves, put your hands deep into your pockets and give to the men and women who approach you regarding the Jewish <pb facs="5423972_7_0235.jpg" n="5"/>Educational Alliance. If you are a gentleman, you will certainly do so, and hundreds of Jewish children will thank you.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
