<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-15">Feb. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Report of the President of the Chicago Branch of the H. I. A. S. (Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society)</title><title level="a" type="sub">Submitted by Mr. Adolph Copeland at the Annual Meeting Held February 2, 1924 (In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-15">Feb. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE PRESIDENT OF THE CHICAGO BRANCH OF THE H. I. A. S. (HEBREW SHELTERING AND IMMIGRANT AID SOCIETY)</title><title level="a" type="sub">Submitted by Mr. Adolph Copeland at the Annual Meeting Held February 2, 1924 (In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the directors of the Chicago H. I. A. S. and the members of the Jewish Charities of Chicago:</p>
   <p>Again we gather, having been spared by a kindly Providence, to review a year's work. Much has been done by our organization since our last annual meeting, which I fear is not known as well as it ought to be in the community. We are workers, not advertisers. We approach our task with a sincere desire not only to minister to the needs of those who are without shelter in our midst, but also to extend aid, material as well as moral, to our harassed <pb facs="5423972_7_0487.jpg" n="2"/>brethren overseas to whom the Jewish Dispersion is a tragic reality, physically as well as spiritually. We are not of the kind that go about their work with a flourish of trumpets, and, therefore, the average person who is impressed with noise and trimmings is apt to think that our work is of minor importance. That is why it is a compelling duty when we gather as at present in annual meeting, to emphasize and make clear to all what we are trying to do, and what we are actually doing.</p>
   <p>This is not the first time I have taken pains to point out that we are much more than an hachnosis orchim, a shelter for indigent wayfarers, important as that endeavor is, and earnestly glad as we are to apply ourselves to it, and do attend to it with the result that there is not a better Jewish shelter in the world than the one we are conducting with great credit to the Jews of Chicago. But it is in the important field of immigrant aid, that we do our most far-reaching work, work that is pressing and that is not attended to systematically and responsibly by any other body than the one we are proud <pb facs="5423972_7_0488.jpg" n="3"/>to be affiliated with, H. I. A. S., to which Jewish immigrants the world over have come to look not in vain for help in their great extremity. To this sacred work we owe, we have pledged, and we are giving our best thought and effort. The record of our work in this field during the past year, as in previous years, is impressive and inspiring. We have gladdened the hearts of many who bless us for it, during the past year as in former years, and this makes us all happy. The individual cases we have helped are too many to enumerate in the body of this report, to which I am, therefore, adding an appendix of some of the more important cases handled during the past year, which I trust you will all read carefully. Only by so doing can an understanding be gained of the intimate, personal work we are doing.</p>
   <p>The past year was the first in our history that we have operated in affiliation with the Jewish Charities of Chicago, the central united community organization which came into existence with the beginning of the past year. Our relations with the Jewish Charities, I am glad to say, have been as pleasant and as <pb facs="5423972_7_0489.jpg" n="4"/>loyal as they always were with the Federated Charities, with which we were previously affiliated. We realize that the organization of the Jewish Charities of Chicago marks a step in advance, that it was established with the object of developing Jewish philanthropic effort in Chicago to the highest point of efficiency. Under the able administration of Mr. Louis M. Kahn, there is no doubt that this splendid objective will constantly be kept in view and will be fully realized. We pledge ourselves to continue to co-operate in the fullest degree by conducting our work in the most efficient and economical manner possible. We want the Jewish Charities to regard what we are doing with the most critical eye, and we are always happy to put into effect constructive suggestions offered by its skilled workers, that give promise of real improvement and advancement. That is their duty, and it is furthest from our thoughts to resent suggestions "from outside". But just as we welcome suggestions from the Jewish Charities, so, too, we feel that the Jewish Charities expects us to come before it in a manly way, making it clear what, in our opinion, is required, financially and otherwise, <pb facs="5423972_7_0490.jpg" n="5"/>if our work is to be done in a wholehearted way, as well as on the business-like basis the Jewish Charities is properly and commendably trying to place all institutional effort in our community. Supplying sheltering facilities and meeting the needs of our immigrants driven from pillar to post, is as much a specialty, and requires as careful study as any other branch of communal philanthropy. No institution, no matter how comparatively modest its allotted budget is, can be neglected by those who are charged with its proper management, or those pledged to support it. Either an institution is needed and should be properly and adequately maintained, or else it is not needed and has no reason for existence.</p>
   <p>Since occupying our present building, we have operated under an agreement, first with the Federated and now with the Jewish Charities of Chicago, whereby we have been allotted the sum of $10,000 annually for our work. Since entering into this agreement we have loyally abided by it, although much more is needed by us, as I have pointed out on several occasions, if <pb facs="5423972_7_0491.jpg" n="6"/>we are to attend properly to our immigrant aid, both nationally and locally, as well as our local sheltering work. We are still waiting patiently until the important work we are pledged to do as the Chicago Branch of the H. I. A. S. will be recognized by the Central Charities Body, and we will by enabled by a greater allowance annually than the amount we are now receiving, to do that work thoroughly.</p>
   <p>There are peculiar circumstances at present, that make us hopeful that we will be better able to make the Charities heads see eye to eye with us in the matter of our immigration work, than has heretofore been the case. At present, it is everywhere recognized that there is no more important question in this country than immigration. With the immigration restrictionists and exclusionists in the saddle in Congress, it is necessary to give more earnest attention than ever before to our unfortunate brethren abroad who cry with the Psalmist "Whence cometh my help". There is one body and only one body in existence that is adequately prepared to grapple with the problem, this <pb facs="5423972_7_0492.jpg" n="7"/>great Jewish world problem, and that is H. I. A. S, whom we represent in Chicago. In the problems that have arisen in connection with the present unfair and cruel quota law, the H. I. A. S. organization has borne the brunt of the burden and it is ready to go on bearing this burden, but it cannot do this unless it is properly supported by the Jews in every community in the land. Chicago, the second largest Jewish community in the country, is not doing, and never has done its full duty by the H. I. A. S., and there is a growing feeling that it ought to. When this is recognized by the Charities' heads, there will be no difficulty in adjusting our varying viewpoints, and the goal we have been striving for these past years, will be attained. May this be done speedily.</p>
   <p>Progress in enlightening the Charities' heads with broader and more significant features of our work, I feel I can confidently report, as a result of a special visit to Chicago made last December by Mr. Adolph Held, national H. I. A. S. director, and formerly commissioner in charge of H. I. A. S. work in Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0493.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Together with Mr. Held, your president arranged for a conference with Mr. Louis Kahn at his office. At this conference matters were gone into in detail, covering our local work and also the national work of the organization of which we are a part. Mr. Kahn showed great interest in what was brought out at this conference, which was brought to a close in a most cordial way. As a result of this clear-up conference, I feel our work and viewpoint are better understood by the central charities' heads.</p>
   <p>When we attempt to summarize the work done by our organization during the past year, we are impressed by the great amount of detail that has to be attended to patiently and intelligently. Our office last year handled 16,633 separate cases requiring attention, some brought to our notice by the national office, others by the persons directly concerned themselves. We filled out 6,880 affidavits required of immigrants abroad or at Ellis Island. We forwarded over $159,000 in remittances for Europe, handling this without cost to the sender of any kind except a nominal exchange <pb facs="5423972_7_0494.jpg" n="9"/>charge with our established practice in American dollars, not in European depreciated currency. There is, as you know, opposition in certain quarters in this community and other communities, to this feature of our work. The claim is made that it is a mischievous and unwarranted interference with the business of firms engaged in forwarding remittances abroad, and that those forwarding money to needy relatives in Europe are able to pay, and should pay the nominal amount charged for this service by private agencies. Not all private agencies, however, I regret to say, are reliable, and, therefore, we have done this work and will continue to do it to give security to those forwarding money abroad. The reason why so many come to H. I. A. S. to forward remittances to Europe is because they know H. I. A. S. does not speculate in depreciated European currency as some private agencies are known to do, not merely to avoid payment for the honest firms doing business in foreign exchange and shield the innocent from being victimized by dishonest "Bankers".</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0495.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>We received last year 1,500 requests to locate lost relatives and succeeded in finding 605 of these. This work requires the most painstaking attention and follow-up effort, the sending of many telegrams, writing of numerous letters, and the publication of notices in the papers.</p>
   <p>We are called upon also, to do considerable citizenship work. We are the logical Americanizing agency for immigrants we have helped. Last year we assisted 280 persons in filing petitions for first papers, and 378 more in filing petitions for second papers.</p>
   <p>Last year we met 635 immigrants at various depots, transferring those who were bound to points further west, south, or north, to other depots, directing them on their way and taking care of all in need of shelter.</p>
   <p>This personal service taxes our office force to the limit. The best way to get an idea of the enormous detail work done by us daily is to visit <pb facs="5423972_7_0496.jpg" n="11"/>our headquarters any day or evening. It is impossible to give an adequate appreciation of the actual work done in an annual report.</p>
   <p>Last year we sheltered 1,381 persons, to whom a total of over 13,000 meals were served at a cost of about twelve cents a meal. The meals served were wholesome and ample. The decency of accommodations provided and care given makes us particularly and properly proud. Our shelter stands out as an inspiring contrast to that of the average hachnosis orchim, which, in most cases is little better than a dungeon. We have removed that stigma in our community, and will, under no consideration, allow our shelter standards to be lowered. We protest, too, against the maintenance of unofficial shelters, private shelters, operated by individuals on their own account, without being authorized by the community to do so. We have ample accommodation to take care of all who apply for shelter and are entitled to it, and if we need more accommodations, we will go to the Jewish Charities and ask for these additional accommodations. The reason that is given for the operation of <pb facs="5423972_7_0497.jpg" n="12"/>other shelters than those authorized and maintained by the community, a reason that, in my opinion, is not made in good faith, is that it is necessary to assure thoroughly kosher conditions, particularly of diet, that will meet the test of a competent rabbinical board. Such conditions, it is needless for me to say, prevail at the shelter we operate, which has the approval of our rabbis. The real reason is that a number of private individuals want to operate an organization of their own, whether it is really needed or not. These are [not] willing to abide by the principle that prevails in our community, that there shall be one centralized body in charge of all our institutions, Orthodox and otherwise. The operation of two or more shelters complicates the shelter problem. It encourages pauperization, for the standards of the unofficial shelters are not as strict as they ought to be regarding admissions. There is no way of controlling them. Persons of prominence who are approached to lend their names to these unofficial shelters are not as strict as they ought to be regarding admissions. There is no way of controlling them. Persons of prominence who are approached to <pb facs="5423972_7_0498.jpg" n="13"/>lend their names to these unofficial shelters that seek in this way to have a semblance of public sanction, should withhold their names and their hands from such effort. There is room in our community for only one decent, well-conducted shelter. We look forward to the day, which we hope is not far off, when all unofficial shelters will be eliminated and forever made impossible.</p>
   <p>In my report last year I made two recommendations which, I regret to say, have not been carried into effect. One of these recommendations was the installation of a disinfecting room, the need of which is imperative in our work, and the other, is the provision of separate quarters for women and children. At present, we are not equipped to take care of the latter, who are in as great need as the men whom we exclusively shelter. Special provision has to be made outside our shelter for such cases at present. This makes extra work and expense. We are not a shelter in the full sense of the term unless we provide shelter for all, irrespective of sex.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0499.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>I regret, too, to say that no provision has been made with respect to another very important matter which I also called to your attention in my last annual report. We are still without a ladies' auxiliary. Such an organization can render great service. It is commonly known that no workers can compare with women workers, especially Jewish women workers. They are intelligent, enthusiastic, and tireless. By their enthusiasm they encourage and inspire others to do better work. That is why I so strongly urge the immediate formation of a ladies' auxiliary of the Chicago Branch. Every other organization of importance has a ladies' auxiliary. Our directors' wives and daughters are the logical nucleus of such an organization, and our work is of such a far-reaching and appealing character that it is bound to attract hundreds of earnest Jewish women eager to render social service of very necessary and ennobling character. I trust before the new year has proceeded very far, that the first steps will be taken toward the organization of a large and strong ladies' auxiliary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0500.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>I am glad to say that greater interest has been shown during the past year by our directors than ever before. Attendance at meetings was better and more visits were made. Committee work, too, was more carefully attended to. The housecleaning of the board of directors that took place after our last annual meeting was effective. Dead timber was removed and as a result better work was done. We have at present a splendid board of directors, one that [it] is a pleasure to work with and be associated with. Not that there is not room for improvement. There is, and I hope that during the coming year every member of the board will strive to give of his strength, his time, his interest, and his support to the limit. Particularly devoted and effective last year were the following, who I feel, without reflecting on the work of other members of our board, ought to be singled out for special attention and praise: Mr. Morris Tower, chairman of the house committee, who discharged his duties last year with his usual fidelity and solicitude; and Messrs. Natenerg, Blonder, and Durschlag. Our secretary, Mr. Isidor Tow, also attended to his duties in <pb facs="5423972_7_0501.jpg" n="16"/>commendable fashion.</p>
   <p>As for myself, although the work has taxed my time and my strength during the past six years that you have continuously honored me with the office of president, I have been, and shall continue to be at your service, in the ranks as well as in the high and responsible office to which you have seen fit to elevate me. I have never sought office and will never seek office just for the sake of holding office. I believe in working myself as hard as I know how, and in others working also as hard as they possibly can. No one has a monopoly on the office I hold. Let him hold it who can do the most and get the best results. But no one can do very much or get very far who is not supported to the full by every director. Ours is not a one man's institution. It belongs to all. Whoever is chosen president, should have and must have full co-operation. Electing a man president or to any other office and then abandoning him, or failing him when he needs help, is as poor as it is unworthy a policy. Let our slogan <pb facs="5423972_7_0502.jpg" n="17"/>for 1924 be, "Forward Together". Let there be no shirkers and no stragglers. Whoever is chosen to lead, let him be given the chance to lead, not deserted and obliged to lead an almost forlorn cause. A story is told of Abraham Lincoln which is in point. When he was first elected to the Illinois legislature, he found himself without funds to buy suitable attire to go to Springfield. Approaching one of his friends, he asked the latter if he had voted for him. Upon being assured that he had, Lincoln asked him for a loan to enable him to provide himself with proper clothing, on the ground that he was "responsible" for Lincoln's being delegated to go to Springfield. Everyone who elects another to office is responsible for the one elected being able to discharge his duties properly.</p>
   <p>I cannot conclude this report without tendering our deep thanks to the press, Jewish and non-Jewish, for its invaluable help in giving publicity to our work during the past year, and also assuring all who have given us their help, that we are deeply grateful for their help.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0503.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>We trust that during the coming year the circle of our true friends will become wider so that whenever H. I. A. S. calls on behalf of the "eternal wanderers," a host will be found in Chicago, not only responding to the cry for help but keenly interested in following the work of mercy and redemption of our great national organization, whose distinguished chief is honoring us with his presence tonight. Let us make him feel by the interest shown tonight that Chicago H. I. A. S. is loyal, eager for service and sacrifice, and a mighty link in the chain that binds Jewish hearts together the world over.</p>
   <p>Respectfully submitted,</p>
   <p>Adolph Copeland, president,</p>
   <p>Chicago Branch, H. I. A. S.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
