<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-02">June 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Jews in Rumania Hover between Life and Death</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-06-02">June 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JEWS IN RUMANIA HOVER BETWEEN LIFE AND DEATH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon Rumanian Jews of Chicago received a sad and heart-rending message from their sisters and brothers in Rumania. It was brought to them by Mr. L. D. Fisher, a businessman from Milwaukee, himself a Rumanian Jew, who just returned from a trip to that country. He addressed a gathering of his landsmen in the Douglas Park Auditorium.</p>
   <p>At this opportune time, at the invitation of Mr. B. J. Brownstein, Major Davis and Judge Harry Fisher also spoke. Major Davis relayed a message similar to that of Mr. L. D. Fisher, as regards the Jews in Galicia, Poland and Ukrania. Judge Fisher appealed to those present to fulfill a holy mission by aiding as much as possible those who find themselves in dire need in the above mentioned countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1335.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The situation in Rumania is bad because of scarcity of food and clothing," Mr. L. D. Fisher said, "yet the Jewish problem is a thousand times worse. Thousands of Jews die there of hunger. They are practically barefoot and naked. Of the food sent to Rumania by the United States, no part of it is received by the Jews."</p>
   <p>"In distributing the food, Jews are placed in a separate line. Rumanians are the first to receive the rations. By the time the Jews are reached, they are told there is no more and are turned away empty-handed after having to wait from four o'clock in the morning until late in the afternoon."</p>
   <p>"In visiting all the towns and villages," Mr. Fisher continued, "I witnessed so much misery, so much wretchedness, that words fail to express it. The need is so exceedingly great that if immediate aid <pb facs="5423972_7_1336.jpg" n="3"/>is not sent, all of Rumanian Judaism may perish."</p>
   <p>Mr. Fisher related how he approached a Rumanian official to inquire why Jews received no food. The other, not knowing that Mr. Fisher understood Rumanian, spoke in his language saying, "We will give Jews bread just as we will give them equal rights."</p>
   <p>Mr. Fisher also told how Jews are persecuted by the Rumanian government. As an example, he told the following fact: The Rumanian government organized a Jewish battalion to fight the Germans. But, all the officers, from the lowest to highest ranks, were non-Jews. In this same battalion every soldier was put to death, not on the battlefield, but by Rumanian murderers. They, the Jewish soldiers, never even saw the battlefield.</p>
   <p>In closing, Mr. Fisher appealed to the Jews to do their duty and give as <pb facs="5423972_7_1337.jpg" n="4"/>much as they can, and more, for the unfortunates.</p>
   <p>"Much can be done, if an American Jewish committee were sent to Rumania to look after the food distribution. Then Jews, too, would get their share, because the Rumanian government knows that America is at present the only land that can feed Rumania; therefore, the American word carries great weight. Thus, if American Jews would partake in the distribution of food, Rumanian Jews would benefit greatly. But American Jews must give more money, so that food may be sent direct to Rumania from here."</p>
   <p>In his speech, major Davis, after presenting the misery of Jews in Galicia, Poland, and Ukrania, explained that Jews are faced with a great hatred. They are despised and beset by pogroms. He says that he has changed his mind regarding non-protest. "We should," he called <pb facs="5423972_7_1338.jpg" n="5"/>out, "protest all the more in order to stop the murderous hand of Poland."</p>
   <p>Judge Fisher moved the assembly to tears. A resolution was adopted for more active relief work to be accomplished by Rumanian Jews in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
