<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-13">May 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Ezrath Torah and Central Relief</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-13">May 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">EZRATH TORAH AND CENTRAL RELIEF</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the annual meeting of the Union of Orthodox Rabbis in Lakewood, Rabbi Rosenberg of New York issued a detailed report on the work of the Ezrath Torah [an organization assisting European rabbis] and proposed that an attempt be made to consolidate it, inasmuch as this is, after all, the only organization doing something concrete for the advancement of Torah in Eastern Europe and in other parts of the world.</p>
   <p>The Central Relief Committee has certainly done a great deal for the European seminaries and for the advancement of the Torah, but had it not been for the work of the Ezrath Torah, many rabbis and their families would have surely starved to death.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Rosenberg is right in demanding that the Ezrath Torah be so consolidated <pb facs="5423972_7_0567.jpg" n="2"/>as to remain a permanent and productive organization for the next ten years. The fate of the Central Relief Committee has not been determined as yet. The wish of the leaders of this committee, that it be maintained even if the Joint Distribution Committee is dissolved, may or may not be fulfilled, since its maintenance does not depend on the leaders alone. If the Central Relief Committee in America should disintegrate, which is not so very improbable, then the furtherance of Torah will depend solely upon the Ezrath Torah, and for that reason the Ezrath Torah must become so consolidated that, in case of need, it should be able to continue at least in part the work of the Central Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>We maintain that the preservation of the Ezrath Torah is an absolute necessity, not only from a purely religious and philanthropic standpoint but also from a political one.</p>
   <p>If the Joint Distribution Committee dissolves, the People's Relief Committee will not. The radical elements in the American Jewry will undoubtedly continue <pb facs="5423972_7_0568.jpg" n="3"/>to succor their radical comrades in Eastern and Central Europe, and should the Central Relief Committee, despite the ardent wish of its leaders, be unable to maintain its organization, the conservative and Orthodox elements of our people in Europe will meet with difficulties. The radical institutions will exist and blossom, while the Orthodox institutions will disintegrate, with the result that radicalism will be the dominating force in the Jewish life of Europe. That would be a misfortune, both spiritually and politically, for the Jews there. In order to avert this catastrophe, an attempt must be made to place the Ezrath Torah on a solid foundation and in a position not only to carry on its work but also to take over a portion of the work that has been until now carried on by the Central Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>There are various ways and means of accomplishing this. First of all, the rabbis of America must induce the synagogues, as organizations, to do their duty. Let every synagogue, whether small or large, make an annual contribution of twenty-five dollars to the Ezrath Torah. Second, let every synagogue have a permanent Ezrath Torah committee. Third, let the Union of Orthodox Rabbis, which <pb facs="5423972_7_0569.jpg" n="4"/>is somewhat influential in this country, organize a membership drive throughout America with a view to obtaining one hundred thousand permanent members for the Ezrath Torah. We believe that there are in America one hundred thousand Orthodox Jews who are willing to contribute from two to ten dollars a year for the purpose of that organization. This seems to us to be the only possibility to develop the Ezrath Torah and enable it to function in a respectable manner. We believe that the rabbis of this country agree in the idea of consolidating the Ezrath Torah, even if, unfortunately, they are not exerting any effort for its realization. They should be among the foremost to work for a larger Ezrath Torah, yet they are not doing enough in this direction.</p>
   <p>This year the main work of the Union of Orthodox Rabbis should be directed toward the development of the Ezrath Torah, for the duty of the rabbis in this country is not only to speak for a larger Ezrath Torah, but also to do some work. They must establish in every city of America permanent Ezrath Torah committees, and they must be the leaders of this movement, for if the rabbis will not work for <pb facs="5423972_7_0570.jpg" n="5"/>this cause with life and soul, who will?</p>
   <p>We can assure the worthy rabbis that as soon as they begin this work, they will find many assistants. Their greatest support will come from the Jewish press, which understands the importance of this undertaking and will do everything it can to enlighten the public on this problem and induce it to do its duty.</p>
   <p>The rabbis, however, must take the initiative, since in a matter of Torah, they must act as leaders and spokesmen, thus setting a good example for the laymen.</p>
   <p>If the rabbis in America approach the question tactfully and energetically, we do not doubt that a year from today we shall have a larger and more efficient Ezrath Torah than the one we have at present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
