<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-07">May 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">In Honor of Jacob M. Loeb</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_0209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-07">May 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IN HONOR OF JACOB M. LOEB</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A banquet will be given this evening at six o'clock at the Covenant Club in honor of Mr. Jacob Loeb. His friends and all those who are prominent in the field of Jewish charity and civic work in Chicago will attend. Rabbis Emil G. Hirsch and Stephen Wise will speak. Julius Rosenwald will be master of ceremonies. A crowd of several hundred men and women is expected.</p>
   <p>This evening's banquet in honor of Mr. Loeb is in recognition [of his work] as president of the Hebrew Institute, but all those who will attend, will honor Mr. Loeb not only as the head of the institution on Taylor Street, but also as the man who brought honor to the Jews while he was president of the Chicago Board of Education. They will honor him as an honest and punctual businessman, and as a prominent and successful leader of charity campaigns, for which he has the blessings not only of the Chicago poor, but also of the poor people across the seas.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_0210.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Loeb is setting a fine example to many, many Jews of his class, thanks to his good citizenship and his Jewish activities. Many of them have come closer to us, thanks to his influence, and have given larger sums to charity than they would have previously given. Mr. Loeb is not only an example to the local Jews of his class, but also to the Jews of his class in other cities of America. It is true that the chairman of the last relief drive was Mr. Brown, who worked very hard and sacrificed a great deal for his work, but the credit for raising the major part of the seventeen million dollars goes to Mr. Loeb.</p>
   <p>We do not have many Jews like Mr. Loeb among the so-called German Jews or American Jews in Chicago or anywhere in the United States. Mr. Loeb fully deserves all the honors that will be paid to him this evening. We unite with all his close friends and all those who admire and appreciate Mr. Loeb's position in the community and his untiring work for the public good, in wishing him, Mrs. Loeb, and their children, health, happiness, and a long life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
