<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-05-06">May 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Peoples Relief Make Important Decisions.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-05-06">May 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLES RELIEF MAKE IMPORTANT DECISIONS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the Peoples Relief took place yesterday at the West Side Auditorium. Socialist party, Workmen's Circle branches, and trade unions were represented by delegates; all have decided that it is necessary to put the Peoples Relief on better resulting basis.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hyman Kahn, Chairman of the Peoples Relief, opened the meeting with an appeal to the representatives of the labor organizations, to do all in their power that the relief work shall not be hindered and to help the million sufferers across the sea. Dr. Kahn, after his opening address, turned the gavel over to Julius Savitsky.</p>
   <p>Dr. Ari, Secretary of the Peoples Relief, after his report of the previous meeting, reported on the Relief Campaign, showing that $23,467.66 were raised, of which $2,690.22 came through the office of the Daily World.</p>
   <p>It was determined that an auditing committee be elected to audit the books of the relief office, and send a copy to every organization represented at this conference. Strasman, Yoketson, and Ziskind are the auditing committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1428.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The second session of the conference was opened with Dr. Nadler as chairman. It was determined to send greetings in the name of the Peoples Relief to the Workmen's Circle convention in Pittsburg.</p>
   <p>Secretary Ari reported that the Peoples Relief raised the sum of $37,000, beside the $100,000 campaign, which already has raised $23,000. The conference ended with the election of a new executive board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
