<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-21">Sept. 21, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">An Inspiring Campaign</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_7_1012</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-11">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1012.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-09-21">Sept. 21, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">AN INSPIRING CAMPAIGN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hundred-thousand-dollar campaign, inaugurated by the Federated Orthodox Charities to relieve the financial burdens of the institutions affiliated with it, is not only successful, but is inspiring. The earnestness of the workers, the zeal and industry of the campaign chairman, Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, and the devotion of the leaders to the cause is typical of the idealism of service of our communal leaders. They are not only conscious of their duty to the various institutions affiliated with the Federated Charities, but they are also conscious of their duty as leaders of the community, and they consider their work for the Federated part of their general communal work. It is this spirit of consciousness of duty toward the community at large that makes the present campaign not only successful, but inspiring.</p>
   <p>When the leaders of the Federated had decided upon the inaugurating of this <pb facs="5423972_7_1013.jpg" n="2"/>campaign, the fear was expressed that, in view of the unfavorable business conditions, the drive might not be a success. Therefore, in order to insure success, Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, an expert organizer and keen public worker, was entrusted with the conducting of the campaign. Although it cannot be denied that the campaign chairman is largely responsible for the tremendous success, it must be conceded that the devotion to the cause of each and every one of the workers, and the noble spirit by which they are all animated, is largely responsible for this display of idealism of service.</p>
   <p>The members of the fair sex are also making every effort not only to fill their quota, but to go over the top. One lady, Mrs. Shiffman, has raised the sum of five thousand dollars within a week, and the other ladies have also done extremely well. Mrs. S. J. Rosenblatt and Mrs. Harry Fisher, for example, have undertaken to collect the modest sum of four hundred dollars, and have already collected eleven hundred dollars, and have promised to collect more. The leaders of the Federated have also already done more than they had promised. Judge Harry M. Fisher had undertaken to collect two thousand dollars, and has <pb facs="5423972_7_1014.jpg" n="3"/>collected four thousand dollars. Judge Joseph Shulman undertook to collect five thousand dollars, and has already raised four thousand. He expects to raise three thousand more. The B. M. Z. Circle and the North Shore Auxiliary have also done yeomen work in connection with this drive.</p>
   <p>One can thus readily see that each and every one of the workers is anxious to do more than his or her share. This anxiety to go over the top in this noble service can be ascribed to the strong Jewish consciousness, and to an intensified Jewish idealism. It is true that the philanthropic deeds of men like Julius Rosenwald and James Davis, the head of the Federated, are sources of inspiration to all connected with this work of philanthropy, but in the main it is the well-developed consciousness of duty toward the community and the intensified Jewish idealism among the leading Jews in Chicago that make this drive such a tremendous success. The leaders of the community are aware of the fact that Chicago Jewry is much ahead of New York, Philadelphia, and Boston, as far as philanthropic work is concerned. They are proud of this fact, and this feeling is, of course, both encouraging and inspiring.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_7_1015.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We have reason to believe that when the drive is over, the chairman of the campaign, Mr. S. J. Rosenblatt, will be able to announce to an enthusiastic gathering of workers and helpers that the total sum has been raised, and that the various institutions affiliated with the Federated are now provided with sufficient funds to carry on with their work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
