<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-26">Nov. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Facts Concerning the Bohemian Aid Society Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-26">Nov. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FACTS CONCERNING THE BOHEMIAN AID SOCIETY UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesky Vypomocny Spolek Union (Bohemian Aid Society) has proved, whenever an occasion has arisen, that it has a firm foundation. The Bohemian aid societies are known to be organizations established upon firm and healthy foundations. These societies are annually accredited by the state; the accreditation may be pointed to with pride since it indicates the kind of work which our aid societies are doing, work which serves as an example to other societies and is worth following. Among these aid societies there is one which takes special pains to show not only to its own members but to the general public, whenever an occasion presents itself, that it has firm foundations. This organization, according to a report prepared by its conscientious secretary, Mr. Joseph P. Vesely, 4026 West Roosevelt Road, has been in existence for the past thirty-six years. It is a fact also worth mentioning that during that long time it has had only one treasurer. This is a record seldom heard of among other aid societies, and it is quite possible <pb facs="5418478_5_1240.jpg" n="2"/>that it stands alone.</p>
   <p>The treasurer is Mr. Jan Hovorka, Sr., 5116 West 23rd Place.</p>
   <p>Although the Spolek faced many hardships, it proved its stability and honesty of purpose; so has its treasurer. [Translator's note: The writer of this article wished to say that the treasurer was a man worthy of trust just as the Society is a trusted institution.] And it was mainly through the work of the treasurer that the Spolek survived [the vicissitudes of time] and that it attained its present high status: for during the entire history of the Spolek its treasurer worked honestly and conscientiously for the greater honor of the whole Spolek and not for personal credit.</p>
   <p>It is also worthy of mention that at the last directors' meeting of the Spolek, the secretary, Mr. Vesely, pointed to the fact that the treasurer will soon celebrate his seventy-first birthday.....Mr. Vesely stated that as the secretary of the Spolek he considers it an honor and a privilege <pb facs="5418478_5_1241.jpg" n="3"/>to express best wishes to Mr. Hovorka in the name of the entire board of directors. He emphasized that the Spolek should consider it a real honor to have found a treasurer who so unreservedly devoted his time for thirty-six years to the welfare of the Spolek and all of its members. Being also one of the charter members of the board of directors, Mr. Vesely expressed his pleasure in being associated with two such dependable and loyal men as are Messrs. Hovorka and Vitek. He recalled the early days in the history of the Spolek, the office of which used to be located in Mr. Hovorka's kitchen, finally reaching its present state of development which is something to be pointed to with pride by our Czechoslovak people.</p>
   <p>The good wishes of the secretary were fully shared and acclaimed by all the members of the board of directors and all the officers of the Spolek. Mr. Hovorka was visibly affected by this expression of confidence, and was glad that he was able to contribute to the growth of the Spolek Union, bringing it to its present healthy development.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
