<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-07-21">July 21, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Meeting of the Sbor Ceske Utulny a Sirotcince</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0806</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0806.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-07-21">July 21, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEETING OF THE SBOR CESKE UTULNY A SIROTCINCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the sbor Ceske Utulny a Sirotcinec v Chicagu (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage Association of Chicago) was held last night in the Czechoslavonic Benevolent Societies' Hall, 18th and May Streets. The meeting was attended by many delegates. The minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read.</p>
   <p>The reading of communications followed. Washington Lodge No. 22 of the Czechoslavonic Fraternal Benevolent Union sent its quarterly dues amounting to $6.75. The relatives of Mr. Ferdinand Wimr announced that the application for his acceptance in the institution was withdrawn.....</p>
   <p>The treasurer, Mr. Frank Petru, reported that the F. Pechar and Son Company, a stonecutting establishment, would be willing to buy the piece of land called Spice (The Point), owned by the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec, and produced a check for $200 as a deposit. The report caused a heated debate. This unfortunate matter has been dragging along from the meetings of the Sbor Ceske Utulny <pb facs="5418478_5_0807.jpg" n="2"/>a Sirotcinec to the meetings of the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova (Board of Delegates to the Bohemian National Cemetery Association) for several months and the delegates of both associations cannot come to an understanding. The most discouraging fact in this matter is that the majority of the members are delegates to both these associations and that none of them can give a satisfactory explanation. The majority of the delegates to the Sbor Ceske Utulny a Sirotcinec believed that the entire piece of land was offered for sale to the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova, but in the meetings of the Cemetery Association only the Spice was discussed and the board of directors of that Association refused to buy because of its uselessness. And because of this misunderstanding much valuable time was uselessly spent and several personal attacks were made with the result that several good workers, who worked for the benefit of both these institutions, will turn in their resignations.</p>
   <p>After a heated debate in which many delegates took part the situation cleared up. A mistake was made and as the chairman of the Sbor Ceske Utulny a Sirotcinec, Mr. J. Suchy, admitted that the mistake was made by the Sbor Ceske <pb facs="5418478_5_0808.jpg" n="3"/>Utulny a Sirotcinec because the offer regarding the sale of the said piece of land was not sent to the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova officially but through private channels. Mr. Suchy recommended that the bid of the F. Pechar and Son Company be temporarily refused, and he also recommended that another letter be sent to the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova offering the entire piece of land for sale. The motion was carried but it did not bring the desired appeasement because, at the end of the meeting, a new motion was made recommending that the piece of land not be sold at all.</p>
   <p>The results of further proceedings are not known to our reporter, for the meeting, because of more or less useless debates, was a prolonged one and our reporter had to leave.</p>
   <p>Receipts for the month of June amounted to $2,759.85; expenditures totaled $3,094.51.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the meeting of the board of directors, held July 1, follow:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0809.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The meeting of the board of directors was visited by a committee of Bohemian physicians consisting of Dr. O. S. Pavlik, Dr. Joseph Jaros, and Dr. Sproc. The committee was sent by the Spolek Ceskych Lekaru (Bohemian Medical Society of Chicago) in order to assist in the management of the institutions, especially with regard to the hygienic conditions. The committee inspected both institutions, and its report read about as follows:</p>
   <p>By Dr. Pavlik: The buildings, the bedrooms, the beds, the dining room, and the ice box in which the provisions are kept, are kept clean and in good condition. As far as the buildings, equipment, and maintenance are concerned, the committee has nothing to censure. The committee recommends the change of the playground for the children from time to time. From the standpoint of safety it is recommended to dispose of the cows and buy milk. The children should be given milk instead of coffee. Sixty quarts of milk should be used daily in the Orphanage. The children should get more fresh fruit and vegetables; meat should be served only twice a week. A regular menu which would satisfy the modern requirements as far as the nourishment <pb facs="5418478_5_0810.jpg" n="5"/>of children is concerned should be prepared because only in that way is it possible to bring up healthy children--and that is and must be the purpose of our institution.</p>
   <p>Dr. Jarosh and Dr. Sproc agreed with Dr. Pavlik and made further recommendations. They recommended that a matron and a trained nurse be hired. Especially a trained nurse was considered by them as an absolute necessity. They approved the projected swimming pool and also recommended the establishment of a vegetable garden. The physicians also recommended that the children be measured and their weight ascertained at regular periods. According to the opinion of the physicians, the progress of the institution should be measured according to the progress of the children and not according to financial conditions.</p>
   <p>In order that everything the physicians recommended be attained, the Spolek Ceskych Lekaru is willing to co-operate; it will arrange for the services of a physician and will do everything possible to guard the health of the children.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0811.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>According to the financial report, the receipts for the month of June amounted to $3,123.96; expenditure totaled $2,734.85.</p>
   <p>At the present time there are 99 children in the Orphanage and 31 men and women in the Old People's Home; a total of 130 inmates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
