<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-13">Sept. 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Speedy Help for Russia</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial Comment)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-13">Sept. 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">SPEEDY HELP FOR RUSSIA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial Comment)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is extremely important that the world should form a correct opinion about conditions prevailing in Russia and should decide what is to be done in order to give that country the necessary and proper help. That opinion must be formed as soon as possible. In the course of the last six or seven years the world has become accustomed to take the attitude of patient waiting toward Russia, which can never lead to rapid and effective help, and which necessarily results in very inadequate assistance or none at all.</p>
   <p>One of the most characteristic qualities of the human spirit is its difficulty in realizing its own obligations. According to both Bolshevik and anti-Bolshevik news, the conditions in Russia are such as to make it absolutely imperative that they be dealt with without any delay. A short while ago, in <pb facs="5418478_5_1493.jpg" n="2"/>a meeting of the Allies' supreme council in Paris, Mr. Lloyd George, who is by no means a pessimist, declared that the hunger in Russia, and the consequences of it, may cost the world more than the whole World War, and that it would be foolish--in fact, that it is impossible--to remain indifferent toward it.</p>
   <p>This statement of the British prime minister was more than strengthened by Mr. Herbert C. Hoover, United States Secretary of Commerce and chairman of the American Relief Administration, when he replied to the invitation of Mr. Ador, former president of the Swiss Federation, to join the conference on Russian conditions which was to be held in Geneva. Mr. Hoover expressed his willingness to have the American Relief Administration send its representatives to Geneva, but declared very definitely that the conference at Geneva must adopt the proper attitude toward all questions in point without any tendency to evade any one of them if it expects to achieve any worth-while results. These questions, according to Mr. Hoover, are: First, that the hunger in <pb facs="5418478_5_1494.jpg" n="3"/>Russia is of such a scope that no private charity in the whole world can possibly cope with it. Second, that, provided that a sufficient amount of money is raised for foodstuffs, it will be necessary to help Russia also by the rehabilitation of her means of communication, her agriculture, and her industrial management; and these are matters that go much further than that which can be handled by charity. Third, that there will be a famine in Russia every year, as long as additional and much more far-reaching changes are not made in the Russian economic system.</p>
   <p>But neither the declaration of Mr. Hoover nor that of the British Premier should be taken as an expression of pessimism in regard to, or dispair over, Russia. The purpose of these statements is merely that of clearly telling the world what kind of a task it is that awaits its intervention, and that the solution of the Russian</p>
   <p>problem is absolutely imperative. Nor was it Mr. Hoover's purpose to say that private charity is superfluous in Russia. Just the opposite.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1495.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He says very plainly in his letter Mr. Ador that as many lives as possible should be saved by private relief and thus mitigate the catastrophe. Finally, Mr. Hoover makes the promise that as far as America is concerned, the best methods will be used in dealing with that matter, and that no efforts will be spared that will help in getting the best possible results. He considers it of the greatest importance that every organization should ascertain for how many persons it is in a position to assure food until the next harvest, when it can start the relief action proper, and what financial means it has available.</p>
   <p>The all-important thing in this relief is, without any doubt, its rapidity. And because the relief is imperative, those who are undertaking it must not shirk any sacrifice. The task itself is so enormous that it needs never expect difficulties, one of them being the usual delays and procrastination in regard to everything that concerns Russia. Here, there must be no delays, no procrastination; there must be an immediate and gigantic effort.</p>
   <p>The principal cause of delays, and these delays may easily go on if no definite <pb facs="5418478_5_1496.jpg" n="5"/>effort is made to stop them, is the lack of confidence in the political motives of countries offering to help Russia. In this respect the United States has set an excellent example. Running the danger of the reproach that it does not want to co-operate with other nations, it has refused to make any move that may have a tinge of political interference. Washington has declared very definitely that the only motives for help on the part of the United States are humanitarian. Our government has no political aims, and its representatives will have nothing to do with any action which is not as entirely nonpolitical in its character as that of our Relief Administration. In this attitude the United States is most vigorously supported by the British prime minister, who declared that all those who are, or expect to be, concerned in the action must do so on the principle of humanity and must tolerate no political exploitation of the situation.</p>
   <p>One of the main obstacles to be overcome is the attitude of the Moscow Soviet government, which seems to continue objecting to persons selected for the <pb facs="5418478_5_1497.jpg" n="6"/>distribution of relief in Russian territories. As a rule, the most able men are most strongly objected to in Moscow, are regarded with the greatest amount of suspicion. Anyone who is desirious of sending a relief expedition to Russia must give a definite proof of the purity of his motives, of complete disinterestedness in any intrigues against the Soviets. But Russia must be helped, and must be helped immediately. There never was more truth than now in the old proverb: "He twice gives who gives at once".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
