<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-30">May 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Cesko-Amerika Nemocnice</title><title level="a" type="sub">Constitutional Amendments Adopted at Yesterday's Mass Meeting Attract Valuable Working Forces</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-30">May 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CESKO-AMERIKA NEMOCNICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Constitutional Amendments Adopted at Yesterday's Mass Meeting Attract Valuable Working Forces</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As had already been announced several times in reports of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice (Bohemian-American Hospital), a mass meeting of the Hospital Association was held last night in the building of Sokol Chicago. The purpose of the meeting was explained in detail by the organization's president, Mr. John A. Cervenka, after the meeting had been called to order. He pointed out that it was the necessary and desirable amendment of some articles of the constitution, as well as the supplementary election, which necessitated the calling of this meeting, and he requested the secretary, Dr. G. Fisher, to present a report of the activities in the interest of building a Bohemian hospital in Chicago, which would measure up to present-day standards. The secretary in his report called attention to the fact that the efforts of the board of trustees were directed toward securing sufficient money to finish paying for the property, on which there is still <pb facs="5418478_5_0679.jpg" n="2"/>four thousand dollars to be paid. This amount, however, under favorable circumstances, will soon be on hand, because at present there is $2,500 in the treasury, and there are fully justified hopes that the issuance of the directory will bring further sums. Moreover, the Hospital is to receive one thousand dollars which was bequeathed by the late Mr. Morris. Hence it will be possible to make the last payment on the property in the near future, after which it will be possible to think of the interior furnishings of the Hospital and, finally, of the desired addition to the present structure. In his report the secretary touched on the attitude toward applicants of the Hospital which, in spite of all assertions of the enemies of the undertaking, will be impartial, non-sectarian and simply humane and Bohemian, and for Bohemians without regard to creed. The secretary described the Hospital's relations with the Spolek Ceskych Lekarek (Association of Bohemian Women Physicians) and other women's organizations, a misunderstanding which has been removed by mutual agreement, and by now forgotten, so that the way to mutual co-operation with these organizations is now cleared. This co-operation is expected to result in increasing support and should soon bring about the opening of the Hospital.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0680.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Fisher's speech was followed by a discussion of changes to be made in the Association's constitution and bylaws. To the article enumerating the active members of the Association, the Spolek Ceskych Lekarek was added. The article dealing with contributing members was amended by a provision according to which all individuals contributing one hundred dollars or more at once become life members of the organization. The number of members of the board of trustees was enlarged from fifteen to twenty-one, the additional six members being three laymen and three women physicians. This change made necessary a corresponding change in the article dealing with the election of the members of the board of trustees. The article referring to the Hospital staff was changed to the effect that members of the staff may be selected from the membership of both the Spolek Ceskych Lekaru (Association of Bohemian [Men] Physicians) and the Spolek Ceskych Lekarek.</p>
   <p>As a result of these changes, supplementary elections to the board of trustees became necessary. One member had to be elected to fill the place left by Mr. Otto Kubin, who resigned some months ago, and also six new members who <pb facs="5418478_5_0681.jpg" n="4"/>had been authorized by the meeting, these being three laymen and three women physicians. The president appointed a nominating committee of five members, consisting of Mrs. Mazac, Mr. Pregler, Mr. Chvatal, Dr. Fisher, and Dr. Jirka, who adjourned to the adjoining room to prepare a list of nominees for the seven vacancies.</p>
   <p>While the committee was deliberating, Mr. Cervenka presented a brief statement on the financial status of the organization. He said that two thousand dollars in pledges still remained to be collected. The directory is expected to net approximately six thousand dollars and will be published shortly. The inside furnishings of the Hospital will require close to two thousand dollars, while the addition will require almost fifteen thousand dollars. This money, or at least a large portion of it, will have to be secured by a loan the character of which remains to be decided upon. At this point in the discussion Mr. Cervenka suggested that there is a large national [Bohemian] institution lending money at four per cent interest, which takes other peoples' [non-Bohemian's] securities as collateral, and consequently should also be willing <pb facs="5418478_5_0682.jpg" n="5"/>to take a Bohemian's security, for the real estate owned by the Hospital Association, even if the building is not included, is worth more than the amount of the loan to be made. He said, however, that there is practically no hope of securing a loan from that institution, even though it would be its duty to grant it.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, the nominations committee returned and submitted a list from which the following new members of the board were elected by acclamation: for the Spolek Ceskych Lekarek: ladies: Dr. Ring for three years, Dr. Kapsa for two years, and Dr. Zelezny for one year; Mr. Anton Pecival to fill the vacancy made by the resignation of Mr. Kubin; and three laymen: Mrs. Machek for three years, Mr. Bolek for two years, and Mr. Bouse for one year. All accepted and were welcomed by the president. Mrs. Machek represents the Damsky Dobrocinny Krouzek Ceske Kalifornie (Charitable Circle of Ladies of Bohemian California), Mr. Bouse, the Pilsen Camp of Modern Woodsmen, and Mr. Bolek, the Cesko-Americka Jednota (Bohemian-American Unity). Mr. Pecival's membership is one ad personam--unattached.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0683.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mr. Bolek in a short speech expressed thanks for the honor given him and promised to do all he could for the interests of the Hospital; this pledge was repeated by the other newly elected members of the board of trustees.</p>
   <p>The Damsky Dobrocinny Krouzek Ceske Kalifornie [Charitable Circle of Ladies of Bohemian California] presented to the treasurer its contribution of $100.57; and Mrs. Mazac for the Ceska Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Benevolent Sisterhood) and its chapters, $16 for including their names in the directory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
