<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-10-21">Oct. 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphan Asylum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1032</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1032.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-10-21">Oct. 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND ORPHAN ASYLUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's well-attended meeting of the delegates of the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) was called to order by the president, Mr. Vojtech Suchy, at the usual hour, and the secretary, Mr. V. K. Soukup, immediately began to read the minutes of the past meeting. These were approved as read. The secretary then read a communication from the Illinois grand committee of the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Benevolent Sisterhood) announcing that the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota had accepted as an obligations the duty of urging each member to make a voluntary contribution to the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec of ten cents a year. The Sesterska Podporujici Jednota sent a check for $709.10 as head tax from 7,091 members. This announcement pleased the attending delegates immensely, and the president remarked how beautiful it would be if all the other Bohemian societies and organizations followed the noble example of the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota. Then, he said, the Ceska <pb facs="5418478_5_1033.jpg" n="2"/>Utulna a Sirotcinec, two of our foremost and most needed institutions, which can never be renounced by anybody, would not have to beg for support and eke out a bare existence on alms. But at the same time he expressed a firm hope that all the other Bohemian societies will follow this example and then conditions may become altogether different.....</p>
   <p>Mr. V. K. Soukup, temporary warden, reported that at the present time there are seventy-three boys and forty-five girls, altogether one hundred and eighteen inmates, in the Orphan Asylum. In the Old People's Home there are twelve men and sixteen women. Thus there are, in all, 146 inmates in both of these institutions....</p>
   <p>Mr. Soukup presented a list of debtors, that is, a list of persons who obligated themselves to pay the expenses of certain inmates and who now, depending upon the leniency of the board of directors, are becoming tardy. A resolution was passed to the effect that all the debtors shall be reminded of their obligations and court action be started against those who remain delinquent.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1034.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Suchy voiced the opinion that a regular warden should be appointed to fill the office temporarily held by Mr. Soukup. After a brief discussion, the position was offered to Mr. Soukup, who later was appointed as the regular warden of the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec. The committee in charge of running the farm reported the following yield: One thousand nine hundred and ten quarts of milk, which amounts to $286.50; seventy dozen eggs, $35.27; eleven spring chickens sold for $11. Total income from the farm in the past month was $333.77. The live stock consists of six milking cows, two heifers, and one calf. There are eighty-five chickens plus a number of spring chickens....</p>
   <p>Total receipts of the past month amounted to $5,485.79. Total disbursements amounted to $3,592.70. The total receipts of the tag day held on October 18 were $1,536.42; total disbursements, $79.01; net proceeds, $1,457.41.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
