<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-14">Apr. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">In Behalf of the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-14">Apr. 14, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IN BEHALF OF THE CESKA UTULNA A SIROTCINEC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following is the list of gifts and contributions received by the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec v Chicagu (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage of Chicago) during the month of March, 1921:</p>
   <p>Denni Hlasatel, $131.73; Bohemian Ladies' Relief Committee, $124.10; Daily Svornost, $94; Vetev Ceske Vlasti Lodge No. 5 of the Central Union of Bohemian-American Women, $25; Mrs. Marie Urbanek, $20; Grand Lodge of the Bohemian-Slavonic Union, one-cent head tax collected from subordinate lodges, $17.83; Grand Lodge of the Bohemian-American Union, one-cent head tax collected from subordinate lodges, $10; Mrs. K. Gruenwald, $10; Mr. Kristina Honomichl, $10; Mrs. Bozena Krabec, $8.75; Mrs. Dusicka and Mrs. Kosak, a collection, $8.25; Cechie Court No. 20 of the Bohemian-American Foresters, $10; Sumava Lodge No. 10 of the Bohemian-American Union, $5; Palma Vlasti Lodge of the Bohemian Ladies' Unity, $5; Vlastimila Ruzicka Lodge No. 93 of the Bohemian Ladies' <pb facs="5418478_5_1537.jpg" n="2"/>Unity, $5; Hvezda Zapadu Lodge No. 45 of the Bohemian Sisterhood, $5; Ladies' Auxiliary of Sokol Berwyn, $5; Svornost Club, $5; Society of Bohemian Patriots, $5; Vopat's family, $5; Kardas Lodge No. 35 of the Czecho-Slavonic Fraternal Benevolent Societies, one-cent head tax collected from subordinate lodges for a period of three months, $4.92; Jan Amos Komensky Court No. 14 of the Bohemian-American Foresters, $3.99; Drahomira Lodge No. 66 of the Bohemian Ladies' Unity, $3; Mrs. Amalie Fantl, $3; Miss Irma Kalbas, $3; Karel Havlicek Lodge No. 4 of the Bohemian American Union, $2; Zofie Podlipsky Lodge No. 21 of the Bohemian Sisterhood, $2; Mrs. Anna Nepil, $2; Miss Antonie Rados, $2; Mrs. Vodak, $2; Vondrousek's family, $2; Karlin Lodge No. 111 of the Bohemian Ladies Unity, $1.50; Mrs. Chmelar, $1; Mrs. Anna Pertl, $1.</p>
   <p>Used clothing was donated by the following: Mrs. Anna Schwartz, 1213 South Elmwood Avenue, Berwyn, Illinois; Mrs. Marie Dvorak, 1909 South Lawndale Avenue; Mrs. Frank J. Prasil, 4410 South State Street; Mrs. Karolina Hruby, 3622 West 22nd Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1538.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Bread and pastry was donated by the following: United Bohemian Societies of Irving Park, Chicago; Mrs. A. Polak, 2530 South Lawndale Avenue.</p>
   <p>Various preserved fruits and catsup were donated by Mrs. Anna Brychta.</p>
   <p>Mr. Holman donated a quantity of pads and a violin for the children. Mr. Joseph Brunclik, 1236 South Karlov Avenue, donated an alto trumpet for the children. Through the efforts of Mrs. Emilie Hrisny, a minstrel show was arranged for the inmates of the institution by Mr. Lester W. Groom and his orchestra, Sunday, March 13.</p>
   <p>I hereby thank all the above-mentioned patrons for their gifts and I express a hope that they will remember our institutions in the future. Special thanks <pb facs="5418478_5_1539.jpg" n="4"/>should be given to the members of the Bohemian Dentists' Society who donated their services free.</p>
   <p>For the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec,</p>
   <p>V. K. Soukup, Manager.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
