<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-06-23">June 23, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">[A Good Mutual Benefit Society]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0580</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0580.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-06-23">June 23, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">[A GOOD MUTUAL BENEFIT SOCIETY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not only among Bohemians, but also among other nationalities, people are seeking the cheapest life-insurance never the safest. The other day we read in a newspaper of another nationality a paragraph which closely applies to our conditions; therefore we wish to acquaint our readers with it. The article stated that people between the ages of twenty-one and twenty-five years pay only forty five cents a month and those between twenty-five and thirty years pay fifty cents and for this, in the event of death, their families receive $1,000.</p>
   <p>There are many mutual societies which strive to gain members by low monthly dues. It is understood, that every person has the right to join any society that pleases him and whose conditions seem to him to be most advantageous. So far as we are concerned, we do not like to mix in these matters because we are often wrongly accused of evil intent by the various and their many members and it is really foolishness to make enemies unnecessarily. However, when a matter which influences the fate of hundreds of thousands of families is being dealt with, it is the duty of a newspaper to discuss the matter in a calm, impartial manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0581.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It would be shameful not to do so just because some individuals do not like it. No insurance society- regardless whether it is a mutual or a stock company- can pay back to it's members more than they have paid in; to this may be added interest, but proper expenses must be deducted. Therefore if a person twenty-five years of age joins a society and pays fifty cents a month dues to the age of seventy-five years, he will have paid during that time a total of $300. When proper expenses are deducted the society can hardly fulfill its agreements even if compound interest is added and consideration given to the fact that many members withdraw in the course of time. It is necessary to realize that very few people reach the age of seventy-five and that the increase from that source is insignificant. So far as the withdrawal of members from a society is concerned, experience shows that it is lowest in societies having low rates.</p>
   <p>While the insured are young and only few of them die, everything goes well and new members apply plentifully; but when the insured age, and deaths increase, difficulties arise, assessments must be increased, and new members do not join, and wherever possible members leave the society.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0582.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many of these mutual insurance societies have been forced to disband for these reasons. The survivors of their deceased members were thrown into dire need because the societies were unable to pay the insurance money The money paid into the society is a total loss and the former members are at an advanced age and can hardly be accepted for membership in a reliable insurance company and if they are accepted elsewhere must pay large premiums. Whoever wants to provide a sum of money for his loved ones after his death, must first of all make certain that the society under consideration can carry out it's promises. Whoever insures himself should see to it that he really is insured. The society that tries to pay back three times as much as it's receipts amount to, will not be able to carry out its agreements very long. Therefore it is better to pay a slightly higher premium to a complex which promises only that which it can perform.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
