<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-13">Dec. 13, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Joint Committee of the Bohemian Charitable Institutions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0874</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0874.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-13">Dec. 13, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">JOINT COMMITTEE OF THE BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE INSTITUTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The joint committee of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association), Utulny A Sirotcince Svobodomyslnych Cechu Chicagskych (Old Peoples Home and Orphanage), and the Katolickeho Sirotcince Sv. Josefa (St. Joseph's Catholic Orphanage) met Monday evening under the chairmanship of Mr. John A. Cervenka to hear reports on the negotiations in the matter of the Czech concert. Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan reported that Miss Emma Destinn is unable to appear in Chicago. She is very sorry, and would like to accept the invitation, but she is strictly bound by her contract. The board of directors of the Metropolitan Opera Company, after last year's difficulty with the German Press Club, resolved that it would not allow its artists to participate in any concert under any circumstances, not even excepting charity concerts. Mister Cervenka then referred to the negotiations with the management of the Auditorium.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0875.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was there with Mr. Ploc [first name not given] and they were informed that the rental of the Auditorium would be $1,000, which for Charity concerts can be reduced one hundred fifty dollars at the most. Mr. Slezak, [first name not given] whose New York manager approached the Committee, asks $1,500 for the services of himself and his pianist. After thorough consideration, the committee decided to give up the idea of a concert at this time, because under such circumstances it is impossible to figure a profit suitable to be divided among three institutions. However, it was resolved that the committee should remain intact and interest itself in questions which are common and highly important to all three institutions. Messrs. Joseph Z. Uhlir and Ploc took upon themselves the task of finding out under what conditions the Bohemian Charitable Societies could share in the proceeds of the big tag days. They are also to investigate the manner in which needy children are assigned to orphanages by the Juvenile Court. The idea of a joint Charity Day, which would be held in the Pilsen Brewery Company's park next summer, will be discussed at the next meeting of the joint committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
