<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-08-29">Aug. 29, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Report from the Utulna a Sirotcinec</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-08-29">Aug. 29, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT FROM THE UTULNA A SIROTCINEC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The report of Cenek Bolek, the manager of the Utulna A Sirotcinec (Old People's Home and Orphanage) for the period from July 14 to August 18, 1912, shows the names of contributors together with amounts and articles donated as follows: [Translator's note: The report lists many articles of clothing, foodstuffs and other needs in addition to sums of money.]</p>
   <p>During the school vacation the children are kept occupied with tasks which may benefit them at some later date. The many visitors were not niggardly in their admiration and praise of the exemplary cleanliness and order within and without the Home, and they classed our Institution as one of the best in America in every respect. It must be admitted that Mr. and Mrs. Siman deserve the full recognition of the Association for the work accomplished; in the provision of everything necessary, industry and economy are displayed by the housekeeper, <pb facs="5418478_5_1111.jpg" n="2"/>Mrs. Siman. Proof of good management is given by the bills, which were reduced by almost one half while the number of wards of the Institution increased. Stocks of firewood speak for the janitor who, with the aid of two inmates, provided both Homes with firewood for the winter and, in addition, performs many other tasks.</p>
   <p>The health of all the inmates with but few exceptions is very good.</p>
   <p>For the board of delegates of the Utulna A Sirotcinec,</p>
   <p>V. Suchy, president,</p>
   <p>Joseph Trnka, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
