<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-01-11">Jan. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Association News</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0448</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0448.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-01-11">Jan. 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ASSOCIATION NEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The headquarters of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) issued a call which is especially interesting because it concerns to some extent the fusion of our fraternal organizations. At the last convention held in Milwaukee, it was resolved that one member would be elected from every state; these in turn would form a committee to get in touch with unrepresented members of societies or organizations, in order to make them join the Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies. Therefore, it was to be a fusion such as was discussed in the Sokols' Union; but according to the sense of the agreement, it is merely a proposal whereby weaker organizations might find it profitable to join a powerful body.</p>
   <p>Apparently the office has received no report in reference to this act so far, and therefore it appeals to the committee to submit a report on which societies and associations would like to join, a statement of the number of members, their ages, the amount of insurance, etc., so that,if this proposal <pb facs="5418478_5_0449.jpg" n="2"/>could be realized, the convention would be able to act upon the matter without further investigation.</p>
   <p>It is not yet publicly known whether the convention will take any action in this matter or whether some of the associations or individual organizations have signified their willingness to join. But the mere fact that the matter is under advisement is not without interest for our benevolent organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
