<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-06">Oct. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To Czech Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0827</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0827.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-06">Oct. 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO CZECH WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Children's Benefit League will conduct a Tag Day October 14. Our Bohemian Orphanage is a member of that charitable association. For this reason, we urge Czech women to participate actively in this event. We ought to appear in large numbers as ladies of other nationalities will take part. The latter give such energetic support that there really is a surplus in their ranks. For this reason, their collections are usually larger than ours.</p>
   <p>We know that our women are goodhearted, possibly more than others. Still we wish to call their attention to the fact that, at present, with prices rising everywhere, the maintenance of our Orphanage is becoming more difficult, while the number of wards is steadily increasing. There are 130 of them now, and they are just as eager to fill their little stomachs as they were before the war broke out. The new building of the orphanage is encumbered with a $22,000 loan, the interest on which constitutes a considerable <pb facs="5418478_5_0828.jpg" n="2"/>burden for the institute.</p>
   <p>Our ladies have always shown tender consideration for the forsaken children, all of whom love them for their charitable spirit. Our women are urged to appear in the Pilsen Sokol hall, Ashland Avenue and 18th Street, on October 12, at 7 P.M. They will be provided with badges, tags, and collection boxes, and necessary instructions will be given. Workers may sign up with any representative of the Orphanage, or at the following addresses.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
