<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-01-30">Jan. 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Special Meeting of the Utulna a Sirotcinec</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0866</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0866.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-01-30">Jan. 30, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">SPECIAL MEETING OF THE UTULNA A SIROTCINEC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special meeting of the Utulna A Sirotcinec (Old Peoples Home and Orphanage) Association was called yesterday for the purpose of approving changes in the bylaws. The amendments are insignificant. Section 5, paragraph 6, which sets forth that every inmate has the privilege to leave if he or she finds that they can no longer remain in the institution. In such cases their deposits, minus a deduction for their support, will be refunded to them. The charge for their support in such cases must not exceed five dollars nor be less than two dollars and fifty cents per week. A further amendment was that wards of the institution are to remain until they are sixteen years of age, instead of fourteen years of age. Section 5, paragraph 4, was amended to read: "This institution may accept as inmates persons having some means of support, if they or their relatives agree to pay the institution an amount such as may be required by the Board of Directors from time to time. This amount may consist of either bequests or cash payments. In the case of <pb facs="5418478_5_0867.jpg" n="2"/>bequests, the Board of Directors will have in its keeping all papers relating thereto. These inmates must observe the rules of the institution the same as those who are admitted free of charge. People of sufficient means will not be admitted to the institution without paying for their upkeep." Several ladies moved to amend the bylaws with a provision that no one be elected to the Executive Committee unless they are members of the Association. This motion was directed at the present secretary, Mrs. Maravek, and the financial secretary, Mr. Novak, both of whom were unanimously reelected to office by the Association even though they were not reelected as delegates to the Utulna A Sirotcinec Association. On this subject there ensued a lengthy debate, which was very much out of order, because it ended in a regular vote upon a subject which should not have been discussed at this meeting. In the end, however, the motion was defeated.</p>
   <p>The Utulna A Sirotcinec is the property of all the Bohemian people, and there is no reason why any restrictions should be placed upon anyone who <pb facs="5418478_5_0868.jpg" n="3"/>wants, and is willing, to work, and who is recognized as capable by the Association. The Utulna A Sirotcinec Association has, and always shall have, the right to elect to office officials whom it recognizes as capable. Mr. Novak started a practical set of books for the Association and performed this work free of charge, because the salary which he receives as financial secretary is not enough to pay for one day of such work. The canvass of the votes cast at the last meeting, in favor of building a tavern on the Utulna A Sirotcinec grounds, or opposed to the undertaking, was postponed to the regular meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
