<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1908-05-14">May 14, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Special Meeting of the Board of Directors of the Bohemian Orphanage Asylum.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0889</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0889.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1908-05-14">May 14, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">SPECIAL MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF THE BOHEMIAN ORPHANAGE ASYLUM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1, col. 4 - A special meeting of the Board of Directors of the Bohemian Orphanage Asylum was held last night at 8 o'clock, first to decide on the admittance of the four surviving children of the deceased Frank Sykora, 300 West 20th Street, who was recently buried.</p>
   <p>After the opening of the meeting a lengthy debate was held on the entire case; the secretary read the names and ages of these children: James, 15; Marie, 13; Stephen, 11; and Rose, 9. These children have a stepmother and are neglected by her. They inherited a small sum of money from their father. The committee consisting of Police Officer Turek and attorney Mr. Joseph Smejkal, insisted that the children be admitted and taken proper care of.</p>
   <p>The vice-president, Mr. C. Bolek, suggested that this small inheritance be set aside for these children and be given to them when they become of age, and a guardian be appointed by the Probate Court. As soon as Mr. Bolek finished he was immediately recommended for this task, of course, subject to the approval of the Probate Court; he said he would accept and see to it personally that these children would get the best of care and that their money be safely invested <pb facs="5418478_5_0890.jpg" n="2"/>so that when they become of age, they will receive this money with interest, and use it to give them a start when they leave the orphanage.</p>
   <p>The children were admitted. Another question raised was whether donations should be accepted. This also brought about a lengthy debate and it finally was decided that the orphanage would accept under the one condition, that donations of any kind be used only for the orphans. This was agreed upon and Mrs. Bajer was charged with the arrangements for the transportation of donated goods from the various dealers as grocers, butchers, clothing, shoe and department stores.</p>
   <p>The meeting was adjourned and every one seemed much pleased.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
