<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-20">Jan. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Yearly Meeting of the Sbor Zastupcu Utuiny a Sirocince</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-20">Jan. 20, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE YEARLY MEETING OF THE SBOR ZASTUPCU UTUINY A SIROCINCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The yearly meeting, one of the best attended [so far], of the Sbor Zastupcu Utulny a Sirocince (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage Association) was held yesterday evening in the hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podrorujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) on 18th Street.</p>
   <p>The meeting was convened at the usual time by the chairman, Mr. V. Suchy, after which the minutes of the previous meeting were read by the secretary, Mr. Trnka, and approved as read.</p>
   <p>The correspondence was heavy and referred to the sending of membership dues and New Year's gifts to our institution.</p>
   <p>The itemized list of donors and amounts sent will be tabulated by the manager, Mr. Dusek, who will then send the finished report to the newspaper offices, and <pb facs="5418478_5_1054.jpg" n="2"/>the report will appear in print two or three days later.</p>
   <p>Letters were read announcing the names of newly elected delegates or the reelection of those already functioning.</p>
   <p>Among the many letters read was one from Mrs. Marie Beck asking that her four children be admitted to the institution because she is suffering with an incurable disease. The Association decided to take steps to have the juvenile court order such a course.</p>
   <p>The receipts of this meeting amounted to $1,072.14, and the expenditures of the institution were $1,862.87. All bills payable were ordered paid.</p>
   <p>.....The new delegates of the many societies were now greeted by the chairman. Upon the recommendation of Delegate Tichy the reading of the report of the directors was dispensed with because of the election of the officials of the Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1055.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The chairman presented the next order of business, which was "for the good of the Association," and a member of the building committee, Mr. Novak, presented his report.</p>
   <p>According to the report the carpenter work in the institution is going on slowly. The contract for the building of the laundry has been signed, and the equipment of the kitchen will soon be open for bids.</p>
   <p>Mr. Novak now presented a complaint that certain rumors are being circulated that the building committee is accepting favors in the form of "commissions" from the firms receiving the contracts. He called attention to a saving of $3,165.50 on work let out, and if that is considered "commission," then the building committee admits its guilt. Nevertheless, Mr. Novak presented a resolution at this open meeting, which the secretary read, complaining of these rumors and asking that they be investigated, and that the persons guilty of spreading said reports be called to account.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1056.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>After a lively debate concerning this resolution Mrs. Urbanek made a motion, which was carried, that Mr. Novak name the persons making the foregoing insinuations; and Mr. Novak named Mrs. Smolar, Mrs. Hrych, and Mrs. Liska.</p>
   <p>On the proper way to settle this controversy opinions differed widely. Many motions were offered, and finally Mr. Svitak's was favorably voted on, namely. that a committee be chosen and a report be presented at the next meeting. The members chosen to form this committee are Mr. Basta, chairman, Mrs. Mazac, and Mrs. Souhrada.</p>
   <p>After the arrangement of this matter the election of officers was next in order, and when the bonds and the salaries of the officials had been fixed, the voting proceeded.</p>
   <p>Mr. Suchy was elected chairman, Mrs. Katerina Greenwald vice-chairman, and Mr. Josef Trnka secretary; after long urging Mr. Antonin Zahrobsky was elected <pb facs="5418478_5_1057.jpg" n="5"/>treasurer. Mr. Charvat, Mrs. Zarobsky, and Mrs. Mazac were elected unanimously to serve on the board of directors for three years. The chairman named the following ladies and gentlemen to serve on the investigation committee: Mr. Velik, chairman, Mrs. Hora, Mrs. Tejcek, Mr. Josef Oborny, and Karel Janda. The auditing committee is now composed of Mr. Freiler, Mr. Kusta, and Mrs. Fara. These ladies and gentlemen were selected to serve on the propagation committee: Mr. F. J. Petru, who will act again as chairman, Mrs. Zarobsky, Antonin Charvat, Otto F. Dusek, Ludvik Jaros, Vaclav Janda, Mrs. Lonek, and Mrs. Urbanek. To the Children's Benefit League the following representatives were elected: Mrs. Bican and Mrs. Vonasek.</p>
   <p>Finally a motion was made and carried that the Sbor Zastupcu Utulny a Sirocince shall go on record as manifesting the fullest confidence in the integrity of the building committee.</p>
   <p>After the announcement that the receipts of this meeting had amounted to $3,022.59, and the expenditures to $1,862.87, the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
