<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-10">Dec. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Is Doing its Duty for the Czecho-Slovak Legionnaires [Abstract]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-10">Dec. 10, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO IS DOING ITS DUTY FOR THE CZECHO-SLOVAK LEGIONNAIRES [Abstract]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The central committee in charge of all collections to be made for the fund to aid the Czechoslovak Legionnaires and the widows and orphans of Czechoslovak Legionnaires is pleased to announce that this cause found great sympathy among the Czechoslovak people of Chicago and vicinity....The present state of this action gives us hope that its results will be most gratifying. It is imperative that this be so, for the coming winter will bring with it misery and want. The success of this affair will divert such misery from the threshold of these sufferers. It is true that besides the Legionnaires there are many similarly afflicted and needy people among our countrymen, but these are being taken care of by the various charitable and benevolent organizations whose work it is to comfort the poor. And yet, even their means are rather limited. Therefore, it is our duty not to increase their burden by asking them to care for the Czechoslovak Legionnaires and the families of those who fell in battle. It is our duty to do all <pb facs="5418478_5_1232.jpg" n="2"/>we can to bring aid to these people. It is the sad bequest which our revolutionarywar left to us. But without these Legionnaires we could never have won our independence; it is they who now look to us for aid.</p>
   <p>Let us not grumble because "there are collections for this and collections for that, and there is no end to these collections". War invalids are everywhere; they may be found in every country, even among the citzens of powerful and well-established nations....No! Our people, who in times of great need were always ready and willing to help, will not allow these poor invalid Legionnaires and their families to grieve hopelessly, but will extend to them their helping hand and thus make possible their survival, no matter how modest.....</p>
   <p>The goal,set at $100,000 for the Czechoslovaks of America, found a ready response among the Czechoslovak people of Chicago, because our countrymen here have fully comprehended the meaning and value of the aid we bring to these, our unfortunate Legionnaires.....</p>
   <p>It is not easy for these boys to be aware of the fact that a collection is being <pb facs="5418478_5_1233.jpg" n="3"/>made in their behalf....But there is no other way out.....</p>
   <p>Our quota for Chicago is $35,000. If we are to prove that Chicago is really the metropolis of the Czechoslovaks of America, then it will be necessary not only to fill that quota but greatly to exceed it. This may be done by the full co-operation of all of us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
