<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">Apr. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation to the Bohemian People of Chicago by the Trustees of the Bohemian-American Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0642</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0642.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">Apr. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION TO THE BOHEMIAN PEOPLE OF CHICAGO BY THE TRUSTEES OF THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The trustees of the projected Cesko-Americka Nemocnice (Bohemian-American Hospital) have called a public meeting for next Thursday in the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Company. The purpose of this meeting is to give a report of the sale of the hospital property on Albany Avenue and 14th Street. The trustees will also report on all other moneys held in trust for the Nemocnice.</p>
   <p>All those who have contributed so generously to the building of the projected hospital, and who are interested in its further progress should attend this meeting and bring their friends with them. It is also imperative that all those who are intimately acquainted with the present building conditions and costs of equipping institutions of this kind attend the meeting so that their <pb facs="5418478_5_0643.jpg" n="2"/>counsels, suggestions, proposals, and advices may be heard; and that their expert knowledge may be utilized in the future development of the hospital in question. Officers of the board are: Dr. Karel Neumann, secretary; Mr. Jan A. Cervenka, president; Mr. Frank G. Hajicek, treasurer.</p>
   <p>What the decision of the board will be it is difficult to say, but we may assume that numerous countrymen of ours, especially those who contributed to the project, will come to the meeting and give their opinions as to what steps are to be taken. The board of trustees, after selling the old hospital property, holds $30,000 in trust, and our people are requested to express their views as to what is to be done with the money. The question is: Should this money be used for the building of the projected hospital or devoted to some other cause? The views differ, of course, but one view which seems to prevail is that it will be very difficult to arouse new and sufficient interest for securing more funds for a project so difficult and expensive as the building and equipping a modern hopital. Since the funds could be realized only by <pb facs="5418478_5_0644.jpg" n="3"/>means of collections or similar methods, it would take a long time to accomplish such a project. It is held under these circumstances it would be wiser to divide the sum which is kept in trust, and make contributions to the already existing benevolent and charitable institutions, such as the Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) and the Sirotcinec Svateho Josefa V. Lisle (St. Joseph's Orphanage of Lisle, Illinois). These institutions, which are constantly pressed for more funds, would thus profit by it, and the action would surely find the approval of our Bohemian people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
