<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-21">June 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Monthly Report of the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0949</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0949.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-21">June 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A MONTHLY REPORT OF THE BOHEMIAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND ORPHANAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The gifts of various kinds which reached the office of the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) between May 15, 1922, and June 15, 1922, amounted to $360.76. The following individuals and organizations contributed: [Translator's note: The names of contributors and the amounts contributed, a list one column long, is omitted in translation.] Besides these gifts in money, other contributions were made to the Utulna. Messrs. Charles Kubik and John Albrecht gave their tonsorial services gratis to 55 inmates. Mr. Stepan Havel, a barber, gave free haircuts to 35 inmates. Mrs. Emilie Forst, of 3405 West 26th Street, made a gift of clothing, as did the Misses Nevolo and Hrisny. The Pilsen Brewing Company and Mr. John A. Cervenka gave us a set of books valued at $60..... Mrs. Roubal, of 4808 Elizabeth Street, gave us a trombone. Mr. J. Richter painted the bass drum belonging to the children's orchestra. Mr. Charles Novak, of 1652 Blue Island Avenue, donated five gallons of paint. The management of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) gave us a quantity of fresh flowers and <pb facs="5418478_5_0950.jpg" n="2"/>was also helpful in delivering to us certain necessities. The firm of J. F. Lalla made us a gift of candies and fruits for our children. We wish to express our deep gratitude to all of the generous givers, anticipating that our friends will continue to show us their favor in the future. Our Utulna A Sirotcinec occupies a unique place among our humane institutions, and it is noticeable that it enjoys a good reputation.....</p>
   <p>Bohumil Fiser, office manager.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
