<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-12-16">Dec. 16, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Constitution Amended Union of Czecho-Slovak Knights and Ladies Ended Their Meeting for the Amendment of Their Constitution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0595</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0595.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-12-16">Dec. 16, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">CONSTITUTION AMENDED UNION OF CZECHO-SLOVAK KNIGHTS AND LADIES ENDED THEIR MEETING FOR THE AMENDMENT OF THEIR CONSTITUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After an all day and a long evening session the representatives of the lodges of the Czecho-Slovak Knights and Ladies ended a joint meeting which was held for the purpose of amending the constitution. The work which they accomplished will have a far reaching effect on the further progress of this flourishing society. Laws subjected were amended as follows: A special scale of rates was formulated for a new classification in which insurance to the amount of $250.00 can be obtained. In this classification can be insured not only all young persons from fifteen to eighteen years of age, for whom new lodges will be created, but also older persons up to fifty years of age.</p>
   <p>Persons from forty-five to fifty years of age cannot in the future be insured for more than $250.00 or $500.00.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0596.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Proof of age will be required of all persons thirty-five years or older and from younger persons if their appearance creates any doubt as to their age.</p>
   <p>The number of medical examiners, who are to examine candidates proposed for membership, is governed by the National Society.</p>
   <p>Certificate of Membership must be written, whenever a member transfers from one lodge to another or whenever a member changes her name by marriage not later than sixty days following transfer or marriage.</p>
   <p>It was decided, that every lodge in the Union must have by-laws. The by-laws are to be in conformity with the Constitution as amended and are to be formulated by a committee of nine members. The National Lodge will approve them when they are presented. This committee will amend and work-out a Ritual Manual.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0597.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The amended constitution becomes effective on April 1, 1903. The Directors are authorized to have them printed and to seek bids for 4000 copies.</p>
   <p>It was resolved that for the next four years, the headquarters of the National Society shall be in Chicago and at the expiration of that period, the first convention of representatives is to be held there.</p>
   <p>With that the program of the meeting was exhausted and after chairman F. A. Dostal, thanked the assembly for its impartial proceedings, the meeting was declared adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
