<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-09">Dec. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-09">Dec. 9, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We recently mentioned the slack attendance at the meetings of our organizations. This, of course, has slowly become the rule among our societies. Today conditions are not far different from what they were last year and in the years preceding it. This is evident in the letters reaching us from various organizations.</p>
   <p>A communication from the Cesko-Slovanska Podporující Spolecnost (Czecho-Slav Aid Society) speaks frankly of this state of affairs. This special article May be taken as typical of almost all of our Czech organizations. We offer and excerpt:</p>
   <p>Much care should be given to the aim of making the meetings occasions for diversion as well as hours of routine business. The meetings of members <pb facs="5418478_5_0306.jpg" n="2"/>should be made attractive and should awaken the desire to attend, not only for administrative reasons, but for sociability as well. Members should consider their meetings as places for mental relaxation and intellectual delight, where reasonable information of educational value can be obtained.</p>
   <p>Do not let us permit our social life to decay because of monotony! Formalities seem to dominate the meetings and so contribute to the decrease in interest.</p>
   <p>Our meetings are being shaped after one pattern, and even our entertainments are being arranged in a similar stereotyped fashion. Many members, especially the younger ones, do not like to come in contact with old-fashioned formalities, and consequently they stay away from the meetings. It is necessary for our organizations to change their exteriors from time to time and to adopt more modern methods of transacting business. We have sublime aims, superior to those pursued by organizations of other nationalities; we should, therefore, <pb facs="5418478_5_0307.jpg" n="3"/>be constantly preoccupied with the problem of how to pursue our purpose in the most efficient manner. We should also devise new ways of increasing membership. Do not let us overlook those of our people who are willing to work. Let us give them the opportunity to contribute their share of patriotic work. When they fail to come up to our expectations, we should not hold it against them.</p>
   <p>Presidents should make their organizations as independent as possible, and they should educate members to perform the work allotted to them; these members should be responsible for the execution of their tasks.</p>
   <p>Wielding the gavel should not constitute a barrier to peaceful discussion, but rather it should furnish a means for quieting troubled waters. Every brother should develop definite traits of character in himself. Sisters should take upon their shoulders the same responsibilities as the men. They should have the same rights and the same obligations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0308.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Let us give every brother and sister an opportunity to work and also to observe the results. In this way we shall inspire them with courage and enterprise. We shall thus bring up and educate new members and new leaders whose support will be a paramount need in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
