<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-18">Jan. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For Vilem Koukola's Destitute Family</title><title level="a" type="sub">Further Contributions Amount to $65</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-18">Jan. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR VILEM KOUKOLA'S DESTITUTE FAMILY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Further Contributions Amount to $65</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fate which has befallen the Evanston gardener, Mr. Vilem Koukola, of 108 Ridge Avenue, whom we mentioned in this newspaper recently, has aroused, as we expected, a lively and well-deserved interest. Yesterday's mail again brought a number of contributions, which prove to us that our appeal was not in vain....[There follows a list of names and the amounts of contributions.]</p>
   <p>A letter signed, "From a Day Laborer's Family," reads as follows: "We read about the Evanston gardener with deep sympathy. His case moved me and my wife to tears. We, too, were very poor and therefore can understand his plight. Whoever reads such a piece of news and does not contribute because of selfishness brings harm only to himself. Someday a similar misfortune may befall him and he will be punished. But to you, gentlemen of the Denni Hlasatel, I send my congratulations for your notices about a poor man so cruelly visited by fate. Thanks and honor to you. I have a family and do not possess any property, <pb facs="5418478_5_1477.jpg" n="2"/>but a contribution of two dollars for such a good cause I must send to you because my human feelings dictate it."</p>
   <p>....All in all, $65.60 reached our office, and we are sending this amount today to Mr. Vilem Koukola. The amount which reached our office before this has already been forwarded to him.</p>
   <p>It is not our intention to drag out this affair unnecessarily. We therefore ask all those who sympathize with Koukola and his family to make their contributions in behalf of the poor man as promptly as possible. If help is to be effective, it must be immediate. We shall gratefully publish the names and the amounts of gifts, no matter how small they may be, for we believe that every little bit will help. We should also like to see help coming from the members of the society to which Mr. Vilem Koukola belongs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
