<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-17">Jan. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For Vilem Koukola's Destitute Family</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-17">Jan. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR VILEM KOUKOLA'S DESTITUTE FAMILY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Sunday notice, in which we pictured the cruel fate which our countryman, Mr. Vilem Koukola, a gardener of 108 Ridge Avenue, Evanston, Illinois, seems to have brought good results. It found a ready echo in the hearts of a great number of Bohemians who are new rushing aid to the family. This aid is coming from Bohemians living in every part of Chicago. When the representative of this newspaper and the detective sergeant, Mr. Albert Mikes, called on the unlucky man, they ascertained that Mr. Vilem Koukola's grief is founded on fact....and that his desire to start his life anew is worthy. Therefore, our representative him self contributed a small amount to the good cause and assured the unhappy man that this newspaper will do all in its power to create an interest in Mr. Vilem Koukola's plight among our countrymen, whom he knows to be good and compassionate people.</p>
   <p>When the representative of this newspaper assured Mr. Koukola that action would be taken, he was convinced that it would prove to be successful, and the <pb facs="5418478_5_1479.jpg" n="2"/>results now show that he was not mistaken. Contributions started to come in the first day; others reached us yesterday. [There follows a list of names and amounts of contributions.] Up to and including yesterday, we received $55.50, which is being sent by check to Mr. Vilem Koukola himself.</p>
   <p>All subsequent contributions will be published during the current week. We ask all our countrymen to help according to their means; to help a man who cannot be blamed for the bad fortune which has befallen him and his brought him and his family to the brink of despair.....We do not want any donations from those people who are unwilling to contribute. Mr. Vilem Koukola fully deserves this help, and whoever renders it immediately will make these donations doubly effective. We, ourselves, are of the opinion that as a Czechoslovak newspaer in America, it is our duty to help Czechoslovaks who settled in America in cases where help is actually needed.....Will there be more such good people who will contribute generously when a case such as this demands it?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
