<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-15">Feb. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For St. Benedict's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0974</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0974.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-15">Feb. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR ST. BENEDICT'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Domov Svateho Benedikta (St. Benedict's Home) of Chicago, for the aged of both sexes and for destitute girls, is the only Bohemian Catholic institution of its kind in America. It ranks among the youngest charitable institutions built and kept up by the generosity of the ever-sacrificing Bohemian Catholics in America. The charter meeting of the board of delegates of the Domov Svateho Benedikta took place on February 12, 1921. During the first year of its existence, the Domov gained its most effective support--more than three thousand dollars--from the St. Wenceslaus pilgrimage and church festival, which was arranged by the Chicagsky Distriktni Svaz (Chicago district) of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America). The Ustredna (Central office) of the Narodniho Svazu Ceskych Katoliku, contributed $500 from the Svatovaclavska Dan (St. Wenceslaus Tax) of 1920, and a tidy sum was also contributed by many generous benefactors, both individuals and corporations, especially during the Christmas season and again on New Year's day of 1922.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0975.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Special mention should be made of the tireless and self-sacrificing work of the women of the Sdruzeni Chicagskych Spolku Katolicke Ustredni Jednoty (Chicago Alliance of the First Central Union [of Bohemian Catholics]) who have independently contributed more than $2,000 for the benefit of the Domov Svateho Benedikta This latter amount was collected as follows: During the St. Wenceslaus pilgrimage, $1,800; and during a mass visit of the Domov Svateho Benedikta on February 6, 1922, $300; the total, therefore, is $2,100, besides many useful articles which the women have begged from their acquaintances and others who are friends of the Catholic home for our aged people..... The next in order for special mention are the Sdruzeni Ceskych Katolickych Lesniku (Catholic Order of Foresters), who are arranging an entertainment next Sunday, February 19, in Pilsen Park in Chicago. They will devote one half of the net proceeds from the entertainment to the Domov Svateho Benedikta..... Our women [it seems] do not wish to lag behind, and so the Sdruzeni Ceskych Katolickych Lesnic (Catholic Order of Foresters [women]), according to information that has reached us, will arrange a public entertainment for the <pb facs="5418478_5_0976.jpg" n="3"/>benefit of the Domov Svateho Benedikta.....Finally we wish to announce to the general public that many businessmen, lawyers, priests, physicians, and other prominent people have willingly contributed to the upkeep of our charitable institution, but as a rule, most of the gifts come from the common, hard-working people.</p>
   <p>Send all further contributions to the Domov Svateho Benedikta, 1818 South Paulina Street, Chicago, Illinois. With a countryman's greeting to all generous benefactors!</p>
   <p>Signed: Reverend Frantisek Bozenek,</p>
   <p>corresponding secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
