<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-06">Apr. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title><title level="a" type="sub">Aid Our Countrymen, Victims of the Tornado!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1760</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1760.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-06">Apr. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title><title level="a" type="sub">Aid Our Countrymen, Victims of the Tornado!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The tornado which visited our city on March 28 damaged 225 houses in Chicago and vicinity. Out of that number, 125 houses were completely destroyed and 100 houses were damaged to such an extent that they became unfit for further use. Among the victims are many of our countrymen, and our first endeavor should be to help them.</p>
   <p>The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) which has assisted in every charitable endeavor in which our countrymen have been concerned, hereby appeals to our countrymen of Chicago and vicinity for help. The tornado damaged many of the houses of our countrymen; they found themselves in a pitiful situation. Those, whose properties are mortgaged were especially hard hit. It is the first duty of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost to help them. We know of two cases in which the properties of our countrymen were utterly destroyed, with a loss amounting to $5,000. Without help these two <pb facs="5418478_5_1761.jpg" n="2"/>would be ruined.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost appeals to all those who are able to help to send their contributions to the office of the treasurer of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, Mr. Louis Solar, 2603 South Kedzie Avenue.</p>
   <p>Contributions will be published in Bohemian newspapers and will be used only in the most urgent cases. If this relief action is directed by the American Red Cross, as is expected, then the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost will transfer all the collections to the office of the treasurer of the American Red Cross, and it will request that proper attention be paid to Bohemian cases just as was done in the Eastland catastrophe.</p>
   <p>We also request that all needy victims of the tornado call at the office of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, 2603 South Kedzie Avenue, and report their cases. Office hours are from 9 A. M. to 12 P. M.; telephone: Rockwell 1787.</p>
   <p>For the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost,</p>
   <p>Stanislav J. Loula, president;</p>
   <p>Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
