<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-18">Mar. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Bohemian Charitable Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-18">Mar. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the board of directors of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) took place yesterday in the offices of the Association, located on Kedzie Avenue near 26th Street. Mr. John A. Sokol presided. The reason for this meeting was the election of officers for the ensuing year. Reverend Vaclav Vanek, who is the secretary of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, read the minutes of the previous meeting, which were approved..... A new member of the board of directors, Mr. Tomas Chval, was introduced. Mrs. Marie H. Krizan, the office manager of the association, read a letter from the Chicago Federation of the Aged and Adult Charities, in which the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost is informed that the membership fee for the year 1922 is five dollars. This amount was paid to the Federation. At this point, there was an election of representatives of the Spolecnost to the Chicago Federation. Three ladies were chosen for this appointment. They are Mesdames Sophie Kremba, Antonie Kybic, and Marie Krizan. Thereupon, the president declared that election of officers for the <pb facs="5418478_5_1408.jpg" n="2"/>fiscal year were in order. The results were as follows: For the office of president, Mr. Anton J. Cermak; for vice-president of the first district, Mr. John A. Sokol; vice-president of the second district, Mr. Charles J. Novak; vice-president of the third district, Mrs. Josefina Beranek; vice-president of the fourth district, Mr. Karel V. Janovsky; vice-president of the fifth district, Mr. John Krupka. Reverend Vaclav Vanek was re-elected to the office of secretary, and as his amanuensis, Mr. Josef F. Bolek was chosen. Dr. F. L. Fortelka retained his office of financial secretary and treasurer, and Mrs. Antonie Kybie was elected to the office of investigator. After the elections, Mr. Sokol relinquished his post to Mr. Cermak. The latter gentlemen delivered a brief address of acceptance, and the meeting continued.</p>
   <p>Since the tag day of the Chicago Federation of the Aged and Adult Charities will take place on May 15, 1922, and since our Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost will take an active part in it, the appropriate committee for this occasion was appointed, consisting of the following members of the board of directors: Mrs. Antonie Cervenka, chairman; members of the committee, Mesdames Kybic,</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1409.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Krupka, Krizan, Kreml, Zeman, Hajicek; and Messrs. Bolek, Chval, Novak, Janovsky, Stepanek, Pflaum, and Laadt.....Since there was no more business, the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
