<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-16">June 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Cesko-Americka Nemocnice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-16">June 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKO-AMERICKA NEMOCNICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the board of representatives of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice (Bohemian-American Hospital) held a most important meeting in the premises of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) under the chairmanship of Mr. John A. Cervenka.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank C. Hajicek submitted to the meeting a report showing that $440.25 in taxes will have to be paid on the hospital property this year.....</p>
   <p>The building committee submitted an estimate of the cost of the addition to be built, the furnishings, and the running costs of the hospital. The report of the committee shows that the building costs, including masonry, carpenter work, plumbing, plastering, heating system, ventilations, elevators, etc., would amount to $20,145; this does not include the cost of tile work and painting. The equipment for thirty-five beds, twenty-four in two wards and <pb facs="5418478_5_0665.jpg" n="2"/>eleven in private rooms, is estimated at $10,703.</p>
   <p>The building and equipment would take some $30,000 if managed economically, and the committee warned the Board that it would be extremely difficult to raise such an amount of money in these days.</p>
   <p>Another point which must be considered is the difference between prospective income and expenses. According to competent estimates, the income from the beds would amount to $20,700 and other income from sundry services to $3,000, while the expenses are estimated to run about $28,600, or $5,000 over the estimated income.</p>
   <p>Asked about his opinion on the matter by Mr. John A. Cervenka, Dr. Chvatal corroborated the calculations of the committee. He asserted that these calculations agree with figures furnished by several hospitals, especially one of forty beds. According to the experience of that hospital the equipment would cost over $10,000. Running expenses for thirty out of forty beds would <pb facs="5418478_5_0666.jpg" n="3"/>be $31,262 per year, or would yield an income of $62 per bed. But taking into consideration that there are always some unexpected expenses, this little profit would soon change into a loss, probably running to $2,000 a year. This proves that the hospital, in order to become a paying proposition, would have to be built for fifty beds. After the presentation of these figures the majority of the representatives present were inclined to believe that under these circumstances it would be difficult to decide for the building of the addition, but no decision was made in this respect. Mr. Cervenka expressed the opinion that a special meeting should be called for the specific purpose of making the final decision on this question. This meeting will be held next Tuesday, and all representatives will be sent an urgent notice to be present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
