<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-07">Nov. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Detailed Financial Report of the Bohemian-American Commercial Expedition to Czechoslovakia Receipts:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1274.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-07">Nov. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A DETAILED FINANCIAL REPORT OF THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN COMMERCIAL EXPEDITION TO CZECHOSLOVAKIA Receipts:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>In membership fees ($5 per capita)</cell>
     <cell>$1,632.71</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Collection made on board ship</cell>
     <cell>320.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Bunco party</cell>
     <cell>50.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Moneys received for insignia</cell>
     <cell>177.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance left from advertisements</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$2,280.71</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Disbursements:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Newspaper publicity</cell>
     <cell>$ 201.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Printed matter and postage</cell>
     <cell>78.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>An American flag</cell>
     <cell>68.90</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Insignia and little flags</cell>
     <cell>217.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cablegrams to Bremen and to Czechoslovakia</cell>
     <cell>13.80</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$ 580.15</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1275.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance carried forward</cell>
     <cell>$1,700.56</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Other Receipts:-</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>From the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery)</cell>
     <cell>500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>From Mr. Anton J. Cermak</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total to be given to charities</cell>
     <cell>$2,300.56</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>Disbursements made in Bohemia [to the various institutions and charities as follows:]</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Ceskoslovensky Cerveny Kriz (Czechoslovak Red Cross) [Amounts given in Czechoslovak crowns]</cell>
     <cell>10,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Repatriation Fund for the descendants of Bohemians banished from Bohemia after the battle of the Bila Hora (White Mountain)</cell>
     <cell>10,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Bakulova Druzina (Bakula's Group)</cell>
     <cell>10,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Narodni Jednota Posumavska (Bohemian Forest National Union)</cell>
     <cell>10,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Narodni Jednota Severoceska (National Union for Northern Bohemia)</cell>
     <cell>10,000</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1276.jpg" n="3"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Spolek Vdov A Sirotku Po Padlych Legionarich (Bohemian Legionnaires' Widows and Orphans Society)</cell>
     <cell>6,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Brnenska Utulna (Old Peoples Home at Brno, [Czechoslovakia])</cell>
     <cell>5,500</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Jedlickuv Ustav Pro Hrzacky (Jedlicka's Institution for Crippled Children)</cell>
     <cell>5,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Skola Komenskeho (John Comenius School) in Vienna</cell>
     <cell>5,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Druzina Osleplych Legionaru (Society of Blind Legionnaires)</cell>
     <cell>5,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Prazdninove Osady Delnickych Deti (Summer Vacation Camps for Workingmen's Children</cell>
     <cell>5,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>For the erection of a monument to Jan Zizka of Trocnov in the town of Trocnov</cell>
     <cell>5,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>(Besides the above last item the following private individuals have contributed to the same cause: Mr. J. K. Valha 5,000 crowns; the Reverend Vaclav Vanek 2,500 crowns; Mr. F. J. Skala 1,500 crowns; Mr. V. L. Rezabek 1,000 crowns.) To the children's libraries in Slovakia</cell>
     <cell>4,000</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1277.jpg" n="4"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>To the poor people of Prague, (amount delivered to the mayor of Prague)</cell>
     <cell>4,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Spolek Vdov Po Ceskoslovenskych Zaloznich Dustojnicich (Society of Widows of the Czechoslovak Reserve Officers)</cell>
     <cell>3,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Masarykova Liga Proti Tuberkulose (Masaryk's Anti-tuberculosis League)</cell>
     <cell>1,500</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the poor people of the town of Plzen (Pilsen) (delivered to the mayor of the town)</cell>
     <cell>1,500</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To the Detska Utulna "Jesle" (children's home "Crib") in the town of Plzen</cell>
     <cell>1,500</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>For a wreath to be placed on the grave of the unknown soldier of Czechoslovakia</cell>
     <cell>1,000</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>For a wreath to be placed on Vojta Naprstek's urn</cell>
     <cell>250</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>To two families of Russian refugees</cell>
     <cell>1,312</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>To the office manager of the Expedition (Mr. Tuma) for office expenses, rental, the hiring of taxis, the transportation of hand</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1278.jpg" n="5"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>baggage, and in salaries to the employees of said office; total</cell>
     <cell>9,872</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>For the express charges of large baggage</cell>
     <cell>662</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total of disbursements made in Bohemia, in Czechoslovak crowns</cell>
     <cell>115,096</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>There was a committee appointed at a special meeting to distribute the above funds, as itemized. The committee consisted of the following Czech editors: Mr. Vincenc Cervinka, editor of the Narodni Listy (National letters); Mr. Prokop Vavrinek, editor of the Narodni Politika (National Politics); Dr. Adolf Kunte, editor of the Cas (Time); Mr. Bohumil Muehlstein, editor of the Ceske Slovo (Czech Word); Mr. Josef Novak, editor of the Pravo Lidu (Rights of the People); and Mr. Josef Marek, editor of the Venkov (Countryside) All of these newspapers published glowing articles about the shining example of patriotic sacrifice of the Czechs of America.</p>
   <p>A beautiful silken American flag was presented to the capital city of Prague, following a decision reached between the committee of the Expedition <pb facs="5418478_5_1279.jpg" n="6"/>and that of the Czech newspapermen. Mr. Karel Vesely, a Chicago, attorney, who was a member of the committee of the Expedition, and who presented the flag to the city of Prague, received a letter recently; it was signed by the presidium and the chief magistrate of the city of Prague and addressed to Mr. Vesely here in Chicago. Its contents follows:</p>
   <p>"On August 9, 1922 you delivered to the presidium in the Staromestska Radnice (old town [council] hall of Prague a flag which was presented to the capital city of Prague by the members of the Ceskovensko-Americka Obchodni Vyprava (Czechoslovak-American Commercial Expedition) of 1922, and of which Expedition you yourself were a member.</p>
   <p>"I have received the said flag in today's meeting of the executive commission of the united communities of Prague, and consider it to be the property of the community. The executive commission passed a resolution to express its <pb facs="5418478_5_1280.jpg" n="7"/>sincere and warm thanks to the givers.</p>
   <p>"I hasten to fulfill this beautiful task of conveying to you this expression of gratitude of the executive commission, and ask you to accept the thanks of the entire population of Prague which I have the honor to represent, and to transmit this expression to the rest of the gentlemen who were members of your Expedition.</p>
   <p>"The attention by which you have honored the capital city of Prague, touched our sentiments in an unusually interesting way; for it is a new proof that our American brothers have not ceased to look upon Prague as a city which always has and always will be most intimately connected with the history of the Czechoslovak nation.</p>
   <p>"The starry banner of your new homeland--a gift of an extraordinarily artistic <pb facs="5418478_5_1281.jpg" n="8"/>workmanship--will forever be placed in a conspicuous place in our ancient Staromestska Radnice as a glorious proof that the American Czechoslovaks, who were our staunchest supporters during our darkest and most trying days when we fought for our self-determination, will not forget us in the days yet to come, a proof that they are with us in body and soul.</p>
   <p>"Once more a hearty and warm thanks from us all to all of you. With an expression of specially friendly feelings,</p>
   <p>Yours</p>
   <p>Dr. Baxa</p>
   <p>president of the central executive commission of the capital city of Prague."</p>
   <p>The last meeting of the entire committee of the Czechoslovak-American Commercial Expedition was held last Friday. It was presided over by Mr. Jan K. Valha, and the members who were present in this meeting were the following: Messrs. Vanek, Rezabek, Skala, Vesely, and Pecha. The recently arrived....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1282.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>treasurer of the committee, Mr. Josef Dusek, was also present. The members expressed their sympathy over the death of his faithful spouse, whose demise occurred during the visit in Bohemia, and rose to their feet in silent tribute to the departed. After reading the above financial report preliminary to its publication in the Czech dailies, Mr. Dusek turned over to the committee an additional sum of $300, which remained as a balance of the fund of the Expedition; a fund which was created for the support of charitable institutions in Czechoslovakia.</p>
   <p>The committee was unanimous in its decision to send $150 of this balance to the Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old Peoples Home and Orphanage); $100 to the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association); and $50 to two orphanages in Czechoslovakia for which the secretary of the committee has started a Christmas gift collection.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the meeting the committee decided to thank Mr. F. J.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1283.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Skala, as director of the local branch of the U. S. Lines, for the fine service given to all the members of the Expedition, and all the friendly aid given by him personally. Thus ended the meeting of the committee of the ....Expedition in friendly mood.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
