<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-15">Sept. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Resolution Concerning the Unification of Bohemian Fraternal Benevolent Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-15">Sept. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A RESOLUTION CONCERNING THE UNIFICATION OF BOHEMIAN FRATERNAL BENEVOLENT ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A resolution which was approved at the meeting of the officers of Bohemian fraternal benevolent organizations' lodges, orders, and courts, held under the sponsorship of the unification committee, Thursday, September 9, 1920, at Mr. Novak's, 25th Street and Homan Avenue, Chicago, Illinois, reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We recognize the absolute necessity for the unification of Bohemian Free Thought fraternal benevolent organizations into one body;</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The unification committee's plan is recommended and in the best interests of members of the above-mentioned organizations;</p>
   <p>"Whereas, One of the above-mentioned organizations sent in its application which fundamentally corresponds with the principles of the unification <pb facs="5418478_5_0111.jpg" n="2"/>committee's plan; therefore, be it</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That this plan be recommended to the offices of Bohemian fraternal benevolent organizations for approval, and at the same time be it agreed that the unification committee take such action as will be necessary to gain a sufficient number of charter members for a new body which would take in all members of existing organizations whose members decided to participate in the unification; and be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That this resolution be drawn up by the secretary of the unification committee and sent to the offices of Bohemian fraternal benevolent organizations and also to our Bohemian newspapers with the request that this resolution be published.</p>
   <p>"For the members and officers of the Bohemian fraternal benevolent organizations' lodges, orders, and courts who attended the meeting,</p>
   <p>"John Hribal, Acting Chairman,</p>
   <p>"Vaclav Havelka, Secretary."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
