<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-06-04">June 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">To All Members of the Cesko-Slovanske Svobodomyslne Podporujici Spolky the United States and Canada an Appeal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-06-04">June 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL MEMBERS OF THE CESKO-SLOVANSKE SVOBODOMYSLNE PODPORUJICI SPOLKY THE UNITED STATES AND CANADA An Appeal</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the year 1911, a movement was started for the adoption of the so-called Mobile bill. The movement is backed by large insurance companies and there are many state insurance commissioners who are in favor of it. So far the Mobile bill has been adopted, either in its original form or with minor changes, by sixteen state legislatures, and its further adoption was prevented by the concentrated efforts of benevolent societies. It is a well-known fact that the adoption of that bill would be detrimental to their interests and might mean the discontinuation of their future existence.</p>
   <p>Because of this danger, a meeting of representatives of all the Cesko-Slovanske Svobodomyslne Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Freethinking Benevolent Societies) [which no doubt means the exclusion of similar Catholic societies] was called for the purpose of organizing a Svaz (Federation) which would <pb facs="5418478_5_0418.jpg" n="2"/>protect our benevolent societies and prevent any further inroads of adverse legislation in the future. The Svaz has now been organized.</p>
   <p>Its experiences and deliberations have shown that under prevailing conditions, nothing can be achieved against the pressure of large insurance companies unless we concentrate all our powers and put forth all our efforts in one single direction. In order to bring this about, we urge all members of the Bohemian-Slavonic Freethinking benevolent societies to help us realize this great idea, the enormous consequences of which cannot yet be fully foreseen. It is clear that the salvation of our benevolent societies and their future lies only in pooling all our resources.</p>
   <p>It is therefore our purpose to unite all our Freethinking benevolent societies into one great organization.....and we outline in the following paragraphs the advantages which such a unification would bring about.</p>
   <p>We therefore urge all members of our Freethinking benevolent societies to <pb facs="5418478_5_0419.jpg" n="3"/>support this unification, which would be of great importance to all Freethinking Bohemians. As a step in this direction, the Svaz Cesko-Slovanskych Svo Bodomyslnych Podporujicich Spolku proposes to call a convention of delegates of all benevolent societies. An invitation to participate in this convention will be sent to each society. We therefore urge all members of the respective societies to see that the delegates elected to represent the societies at the convention receive instructions favorable to this idea and helpful toward its realization. We trust that every member of these societies fully appreciates the importance of this idea and thoroughly understands all the issues involved in the present situation.</p>
   <p>We are ready to answer all inquiries and questions concerning the details of our proposal. Those should be addressed to our secretary, Mr. Otto T. Pergler, 1808 South Avers Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
