<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-01-12">Jan. 12, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Standpoint of the National Grand Lodge of the Czecho Slavonic Benevolent Societies Concerning the Unification of All Czech Benevolent Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-01-12">Jan. 12, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">STANDPOINT OF THE NATIONAL GRAND LODGE OF THE CZECHO SLAVONIC BENEVOLENT SOCIETIES CONCERNING THE UNIFICATION OF ALL CZECH BENEVOLENT SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The National Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, in its meeting held on December 3, 1919, discussed all points and forms of a proposal for the unification committee, and sent to us by that committee, that we might accept it without change.</p>
   <p>After a thorough consideration of the separate sections and the proposal as a whole, the acceptance of the proposals was voted upon and unanimously turned down, or rather rejected for the following reasons:</p>
   <p>The sixteenth convention of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies held last year agreed in its resolutions that those societies in favor of the unification, should employ or hire expert actuaries, so their financial standing, strength, valuation of certificates, average age, and any other <pb facs="5418478_5_0160.jpg" n="2"/>requested details are known, and the existence of any society, favoring the unification will not be threatened.</p>
   <p>After this is accomplished, a convention of elected delegates from each society should be held to take the following into consideration:</p>
   <p>(1) By-laws of the new society.</p>
   <p>(2) To prepare identical average rates.</p>
   <p>(3) To prepare sickness and accident benefits.</p>
   <p>(4) To set a limit on the death benefits.</p>
   <p>(5) To prepare an average reserve fund.</p>
   <p>(6) To take care of all other details, which would insure the life and <pb facs="5418478_5_0161.jpg" n="3"/>existence of all the united societies.</p>
   <p>The unification committee of Chicago approved this agreement as we were informed in a letter sent to us by brother Fr. Strunc, dated July 4, 1919, as follows:</p>
   <p>"In the committee for a unification, all these following societies are represented: Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies (Cesko Slovanske Podporující Jednoty), Czecho-Slavonic Brotherhood Benevolent Societies (Cesko Slovanske Bratrske Podporující Jednoty), Taborite Society (Jednota Taboritu), Bohemian-American Foresters (Jednota Cesko Americkych Lesniku a Lesnic), Czecho-Slavonic Society (Cesko Slovanske Jednota), Bohemian-American Society (Cesko Americka Jednota), Czecho-Slavonic Ladies Benevolent Society (Cesko Slovanska Damska Podporující Jednota).</p>
   <p>"In the last meeting of this committee, it was decided to request all of these Grand Lodges, including even those which did not approve the<pb facs="5418478_5_0162.jpg" n="4"/>unification, to report the number of their members, tables of rates, certificates from the State Commissioner, the limit of death benefits, reserve funds, in short everything that would be useful in preparing the skeleton of unification, which afterward would be placed before the members for ratification."</p>
   <p>This was agreed on by the unification committee of Chicago, but afterward laid aside, which is apparent from a motion of the unification committee, published in our latest monthly journal.</p>
   <p>The agreement of the sixteenth convention of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies was made on the foundation of the law, to which the Chicago, committee refers as the so-called "Mobile Bill," which expressly reads:</p>
   <p>Unification and Transfers <pb facs="5418478_5_0163.jpg" n="5"/>"No domestic society shall unite or accept transferred members, or receive any funds of any other society, unless this unification was approved by a written contract, containing all the circumstantial details of this unification and transfer and sent to a Superintendent of Insurance of that certain state, together with a verified financial standing of each of said societies, made out and sworn to by the President and Secretary or similar officials, with a certificate of these officials, verifying that this unification or transfer was approved by at least two-thirds of the members or governing body of each of the said societies.</p>
   <p>"The state Superintendent of Insurance, after receiving said contract, financial standing and certificates, shall examine everything and finding that each financial statement is correct and said contract meets all the requirements of this section, and that such unification or transfer is honest and just to all members of each of said societies, he shall approve this unification and contract, and shall issue a proper certificate, after which said contract for unification or transfer is in force and valid.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0164.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"In case such contract is not approved, contents of such contract shall not be revealed by the state Superintendent of Insurance."</p>
   <p>As is evident, the societies and members are protected by a state law in case of unification, so that no loss is suffered by them. It could easily happen that the unification of some societies could completely ruin the existence of a society, originated from this unification.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, the unification committee of Chicago proposes to unite all the members of these societies into one society. The National Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies cannot, and will not agree to form such a new society, because it is governed by resolutions so distinctly expressed in the sixteenth convention of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the National Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, according to the law, cannot take over or transfer the members or funds of other societies, until the time when such unification is approved <pb facs="5418478_5_0165.jpg" n="7"/>by the state Superintendent of Insurance. This applies to all others, and no society can transfer its funds into a corporation which is in formation only.</p>
   <p>What we can do is to follow the resolutions of the convention of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, based on the law called "Mobile Bill," and forego the transferring of our funds into the hands of others until the unification is carried through in the joint convention and approved by the State Department of Insurance.</p>
   <p>We repeat our expression published in our monthly journal, and also sent to the unification committee of Chicago during the month of September, addressed to its secretary, brother Fr. Ort: Decidedly and sincerely we are in favor of bringing this important matter to a happy, safe, and successful end.</p>
   <p>We request, therefore, in determination, that the National Grand Lodge be <pb facs="5418478_5_0166.jpg" n="8"/>not suspected of opposing unification of the other Bohemian (Czech) benevolent societies with the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies.</p>
   <p>The National Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies is acknowledging the work of the unification committee of Chicago, because this preliminary work makes the forward movement more easy, but still we declare that not until the financial standing, strength, valuation of certificates, average age of members, and any other requested details indicated in the last convention of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies are known, we refuse to participate in any further dealings.</p>
   <p>We would not stand for, nor permit our highly deserving members of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, who were elected in the sixteenth convention of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies to be altogether ignored.</p>
   <p>The National Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies represents more than twenty-three thousand members, and in this respect <pb facs="5418478_5_0167.jpg" n="9"/>is duty bound to see to it that it knows the condition, financial standing, average age, etc., of its new associates.</p>
   <p>For that reason, we must insist that the convention resolutions of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies be carried out and respected.</p>
   <p>How could we take the responsibility for a deed which might be harmful to most of our members? This same responsibility rests upon all the other societies also.</p>
   <p>So in respect to this responsibility, to ourselves, and to our members, we must insist on the carrying out of every point of the convention resolutions.</p>
   <p>Willingly and sincerely, we want to co-operate within the specified resolutions of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, but we will not go any other way. We ask that this expression of ours be taken into consideration, and that you will acknowledge our viewpoint as members of the Czecho-Slavonic <pb facs="5418478_5_0168.jpg" n="10"/>Benevolent Societies in regard to the unification as just.</p>
   <p>This matter cannot be carried out in an easygoing manner. Where thousands of widows and orphans are concerned, we could easily create a situation where thousands of elderly members would be forced out by high rates. The surviving wives would lose all the benefits for which their husbands have worked by paying dues throughout their whole mature lives.</p>
   <p>This standpoint of the National Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies was unanimously accepted in the meeting of the National Grand Lodge, held on December 3, 1919, and published in our monthly journal.</p>
   <p>For the National Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies.</p>
   <p>Signed: K. Bernreiter, president.</p>
   <p>J. V. Lunak, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
