<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-24">Feb. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Aid Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0245</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0245.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-24">Feb. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR AID SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The semiannual conference of the Narodni Bratrsky Congres (National Brotherhood Congress), which was held in Chicago recently, was attended by many presidents and officers of various aid societies.</p>
   <p>Many subjects were on the program for discussion. The most important, however, were how to support the United States Government in cases of insurance for soldiers and how to propagate the sale of war-savings stamps. Leaders of large brotherhoods had already been called by the authorities in Washington for a conference in order to settle these two questions.</p>
   <p>The conference dwelt upon the effect of the war on the aid societies. The consensus centers upon the fact that an increased mortality must be expected and preparations for this eventuality must be made. A delegate from Columbus, Ohio, declared that a higher insurance rate will have to be introduced in all brotherhoods in order to keep the confidence of the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0246.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The trustees of the Jednota Ceských Dam (Czech Ladies Union) published the financial report on activities since the Union's existence. The total assets amount to $48,526.89, consisting almost exclusively of gilt-edged bonds, which are constantly increasing in value and bearing interest. The day is not far off when the Union will be able to begin building a splendid home.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Jednota (Bohemian-American Union), one of the younger brotherhoods, has taken in 730 new members in the past year. This is remarkable for these times, which have proved very trying for most aid societies. The average age of the insured members was 30 years. They were insured for the total amount of $609.50.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
