<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-20">Oct. 20, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Conference</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-20">Oct. 20, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">AN IMPORTANT CONFERENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great deal has been said recently among our public about the attempts for the realization of plans that would result in the unification of all Catholic Jednoty [fraternal, benevolent associations, that is larger bodies having a number of lodges, camps, courts, etc.] into one great and powerful organization. These plans have been discussed not only in the Catholic daily press but also in the organs of the various associations, which have been publishing most interesting articles giving their writers' points of view, ideas as to advantages or disadvantages to be derived from such a unification, and also the various obstacles that stand in the way and how they should or could be overcome. This matter has aroused the attention it deserves because of its great importance. This being the case the various associations of our Catholic countrymen have made arrangements for their representatives to meet and subject the matter to a most thorough discussion. The conference was called to Chicago and met yesterday in the offices of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Czech Catholics) in the building of the <pb facs="5418478_5_0069.jpg" n="2"/>Lawndale State Bank on West 22nd Street near South Kedzie Avenue.</p>
   <p>The meeting, attended by many men and women delegates, was opened yesterday at ten o'clock in the morning. The meeting was held for consultation purposes only and no decisions or recommendations it might make were considered binding on the bodies represented. All that the representatives were expected to do was to discuss this question, which is of such great importance to the Czech Catholic public. It had been brought up by public organs and, after thorough study, many bodies have passed resolutions in favor of the unification. So, for instance, one of the best Catholic bodies, the Katolicky Delnik (Catholic Workingman) has issued a special proclamation to its membership reading as follows;</p>
   <p>"The tendency for unification of various death benefit organizations is very general. Also we see a possible advantage in unifying the Czech Catholic benevolent bodies provided this unification will involve both the ideological and financial aspects, the financial part being regulated by the results of <pb facs="5418478_5_0070.jpg" n="3"/>computations and tables prepared by skilled actuaries so that the whole membership would receive the benefit of proper insurance and just adjustment of dues."</p>
   <p>The Katolicky Delnik also adopted a resolution providing for the appointment of a committee for the purpose of formulating a plan to bring the Katolicky Delnik to the highest possible degree of economic perfection. The fourteenth general convention of the Katolicky Delnik held in Omaha in January of this year adopted a resolution according to which all Czech Catholic benevolent or insurance organizations should be apprised of this move of the Katolicky Delnik. The Katolicky Delnik went so far as to charge its lawyer, Mr. Karel Kovar, to get in touch with an experienced actuary to assist in preparing this step, that is, to figure out an acceptable way in which the legally required solvency [sic] of the Katolicky Delnik would be reached in case of the unification.</p>
   <p>Similarly, the Wisconsin Jednota issued to its membership a proclamation which reads as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0071.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Whereas, Both the first and second national conventions of the Narodni Svaz have received letters urging the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku to take steps leading toward the unification of all Catholic benevolent bodies, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, All action of this kind exceeds the authority vested in the Svaz by its constitution and bylaws; therefore be it</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we recognize the full judicial authority of the Svaz assembled in convention and recommend that all our Jednoty take up this question in their general conventions."</p>
   <p>Yesterday's conference is the result of negotiations which took place between the various Jednoty. At that conference were represented:</p>
   <p>The Prvni Ustredni Jednota (First Central Union) of America by Vinc. Kolda of Bay Village, Ohio and Dr. M. E. Lorenz of Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0072.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Katolicky Delnik by Lawyer Chas. Kolar of Le Sueur Center, Minnesota, and Jos. F. Reznicek, whose proxy was Dr. Lorenz.</p>
   <p>The Ustredni Jednota Zen Americkych (Central Union of American Women) by Mrs. Rozalie Nedved of Berwyn, Illinois, president of the Grand Court, and Mrs. Anna Bilek of Chicago, Illinois, secretary of the Grand Court.</p>
   <p>The Ustredni Jednota Katolicka (Central Catholic Union) of Wisconsin by Jan Paulu, president, and K. Koubek, secretary, both of Milwaukee, Wisconsin.The Zapadni Ceska Katolicka Jednota (Western Czech Catholic Union) by L. J. Kukrna of Wahoo, Nebraska.</p>
   <p>The Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku was represented by Jan Straka, Reverend F. Jedlicka, Jos. J. Janda, Ant. Vaclav Tesar, J. Kesner, and V. Havel. Also present was the Reverend Vaclav Mikolasek of Lankin, North Dakota, who was greatly interested in the unification. The Katolicka Jednota (Catholic <pb facs="5418478_5_0073.jpg" n="6"/>Union) of Texas was not represented because of the great distance, but its president sent a written advice that there is no intention on the part of his Jednota to make any difficulties or in any way oppose the unification.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kolda of Bay Village, Ohio, was elected chairman of the conference, the Reverend Jedlicka, its secretary. Many of us are quite unaware of the fact that this was the first time after a long period of years that the representatives of various Czech Catholic organizations got together for a sincere discussion of a matter of such great importance to the lives of Catholic Czechs in America. Individual representatives offered their suggestions and recommendations, brought messages from their home bodies and all proposals were subject to a most thorough discussion.</p>
   <p>It must be stressed that all discussions were most sincere and cordial, as friendly as could be, and that the conference would be successful was already apparent in the morning. Lawyer Karel Kovar, representing the Katolicky Delnik, was most frank and candid in his recommendations. He presented a <pb facs="5418478_5_0074.jpg" n="7"/>very clear plan and explained fully the ways and means to a unification. His deductions were very well received and applauded. It was most inspiring to note that all representatives were in favor of the unification and aware of the advantages which that move would bring to Czech Catholics in America. All these workers, most of whom have become gray in service to their Jednoty, talked to one another as brothers should. Mrs. Nedved, as president of her Jednota Zen Americkych, said that the question of unification had not been discussed in any of its meetings, but that she is certain that her Jednota will not only not oppose it but will give substantial help to achieve it.</p>
   <p>The unification is an immense problem of far-reaching importance, and happy contentment appeared on the faces of all delegates when it became apparent that it is being discussed with rare unanimity of purpose.</p>
   <p>The first concrete result of the meeting was that every Jednota represented in the conference will take steps to reach that degree of solvency required by the laws of the state in which it is incorporated. All the delegates <pb facs="5418478_5_0075.jpg" n="8"/>present pledged themselves to urge the application of all means to achieve that end in as short a time as possible.</p>
   <p>Further, the conference agreed to form a permanent committee, membership of which includes all those present at the conference, which will be officially known as the Vybor Zastupcu Pro Slouceni Ceskokatolickych Jednot (Committee for the Unification of Czech Catholic Unions). Its chairman is Mr. Vinc Kolda; secretary, Mr. V. B. Havel. The purpose of the committee, as its name indicates, is to work for the unification by urging it in the members' bodies, and by supplying and exchanging information; and its members promised not to stop working until the aim is definitely reached. The representative of the Prvni Ustredni Jednota declared that his union is already working on reaching the solvency required by the law, and that it will succeed in a short time. The Katolicky Delnik is in a very similar situation.</p>
   <p>The conference chairman thanked all those present for their contribution to the proposed end. He called this a memorable meeting, one that will be <pb facs="5418478_5_0076.jpg" n="9"/>remembered for a long time. He thanked the Narodni Svaz for acting as an intermediary and assembling the representantives of such a large number of unions around one conference table.....</p>
   <p>Thus, what a short while ago was not even a dream now is becoming a reality. Every hour of the conference was used for purposeful discussion; not a minute was wasted. The conference achieved a success of which all those can be proud who are interested in the preservation of the American branch of our nation. The meeting ended at six o'clock in the evening.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
