<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-01">Apr. 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A Dangerous Bill</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cesko-Slovanska Jednota V Americe Starts Adverse Propaganda</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-04-01">Apr. 1, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A DANGEROUS BILL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cesko-Slovanska Jednota V Americe Starts Adverse Propaganda</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's meeting of the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota V Americe (Bohemian-Slavonic Union in America) was called for a discussion of the Mobile bill which will come up for a vote in the State Legislature this year, and for the discussion of the only possible means of self-preservation for our benevolent societies--their fusion. Those present at the meeting debated the question of how such a fusion should be attempted, and it was finally agreed that each delegate who was present at the meeting should explain to the body he represented the nature of the bill and its danger to our societies. Each representative will report at the next meeting of the Jednota, which will be held April 5 at the hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) on May Street, as to what action his society proposes to take. It should be clearly understood that the proposed fusion should not involve a pooling of financial resources. As several of the representatives have already explained, there is no doubt that the bill is nothing more than a <pb facs="5418478_5_0490.jpg" n="2"/>death blow aimed at our benevolent societies, and that behind this bill stand huge financial interests, in other words, large insurance companies. The Mobile bill, as Mr. Rudolf Janda has shown, contains a number of useful provisions, but in principle it militates against all fraternal benevolent organizations, and its passage would mean their early destruction. This bill also gives unlimited arbitrary power to the superintendent of the Department of Insurance of the State of Illinois. At the coming meeting the question of whether or not it is possible to accomplish a fusion of all our benevolent societies, and the best method of achieving such a union, will be discussed.</p>
   <p>The meeting was attended by representatives of the following societies: [Translator's note: Eight benevolent societies are mentioned, most of them represented by two, some by three, and one by four delegates.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
