<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-23">Dec. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovak America Must Perform its Duty</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Everything for Children in the Czechoslovak Republic!" Must Be Our Motto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1661</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1661.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-23">Dec. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAK AMERICA MUST PERFORM ITS DUTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Everything for Children in the Czechoslovak Republic!" Must Be Our Motto</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Herbert Hoover, who was sent to Europe during the time of the World War to direct relief activities and to become a food dictator, just recently inaugurated a drive throughout the United States to raise a sum of thirty-three million dollars to save the children in Europe, in Central Europe especially, from starvation. Part of this amount will be used by him to save children in Czechoslovakia. There are many children who need relief. They are perishing because of undernourishment and cold weather. They are exposed on all sides to tuberculosis! We cannot afford to be indifferent to their fate. We cannot afford--nor will our consciences permit it--to look on, from this land of plenty, with coolness and indifference while, in our recently liberated old homeland, our children, the most beautiful and the most promising future of the whole Czechoslovak nation, are perishing. Mr. Hoover is willing to help them. Therefore Czechoslovak America must help Mr. Hoover in <pb facs="5418478_5_1662.jpg" n="2"/>his drive. The more Czechoslovak America helps Mr. Hoover in his Christmas and New Year's drive, the more Mr. Hoover, again, will help our people in Czechoslovakia.</p>
   <p>Christmas time, a joyous holiday of the whole world, is here. Let us accomplish a good deed at least during these holidays. The greatest and best deed can be accomplished by us if we remember a suffering child of Czechoslovakia and if we deposit a contribution in his behalf. Let us invite such a child, as an invisible guest, to our Christmas or New Year's dinner. Let us contribute the sum of ten dollars or a smaller amount in behalf of this invisible guest. Let us deposit this amount with the Bohemian department of Hoover's relief committee. By doing so we save the child from dangerous sickness, or death, for a period of one year. A year from now conditions may improve. By that time a crop will be harvested, and there will be something to live on. Today, there is a limited supply of food and medicines in Czechoslovakia. Every invisible guest of ours will be grateful and will thank us from the bottom of his heart for what we do for him during these times. To <pb facs="5418478_5_1663.jpg" n="3"/>help Mr. Hoover and the Czechoslovak children is one of our most sacred duties. That this duty be recognized by us and that we give it our whole-hearted support is ardently recommended by the Ambassador of the Czechoslovak Republic, Dr. Bedrich Stepanek, who, through his representative, Dr. Suma, whom he sent to Chicago and Pittsburgh for that purpose, is calling to Czechoslovak America:</p>
   <p>"Help and help immediately! By helping immediately you will help twice! Because of undernourishment and cold weather, our children are perishing in Czechoslovakia! For them, do the best you can! You can help in the most effective way if you contribute to Mr. Hoover's relief action. Contribute and send your contribution at once. By it you will accomplish a most beautiful and noble deed, because you will show your love for a child. Follow the example of our great President Woodrow Wilson, who invited twenty such invisible guests to his Christmas dinner. Each Czechoslovak who can afford it should invite at least one such invisible guest!"</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1664.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Kindly send your contributions at once to the office of the Denni Hlasatel, because the drive will not last very long. The Denni Hlasatel will acknowledge every contribution. Just before the drive is concluded, all contributions will be sent to the Czechoslovak Ambassador, Dr. Bedrich Stepanek, who will turn over all the money collected among American Czechoslovaks to Mr. Herbert Hoover. Therefore, attend cheerfully to the beautiful, noble, and purely humane work!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
