<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-17">Mar. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">We Did All We Could</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-17">Mar. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WE DID ALL WE COULD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we have previously informed our readers, midnight of Tuesday, March 15 terminated the collection undertaken by our newspaper for the benefit of the Hoover Relief Fund. People all over the United States contributed to the Fund, which is a gift from the American people to the suffering children of Central and Eastern Europe.</p>
   <p>Having concluded this collection, we consider it our duty to place the result of the work before our people; we do so by publishing this report. We do so gladly, because on this occasion it is possible for us to inform you that our work has not been in vain, but, on the contrary, taking into consideration the prevailing conditions, it met with success as did the entire campaign in behalf of the Hoover Relief Fund.</p>
   <p>Before reporting on our collection it will be necessary to state that this <pb facs="5418478_5_1568.jpg" n="2"/>superhuman work undertaken by Mr. Herbert Hoover, the present Secretary of Commerce in President Harding's Cabinet, started shortly before the Christmas holidays last year. The Czechoslovak-American Committee, which took care of the collection among Czechoslovak people of America, was formed soon afterward through the efforts of Dr. Bedrich Stepanek, Czechoslovak Ambassador at Washington D. C. Dr. Stepanek sent his special representative in the person of Dr. A. Suma who called a meeting of representatives of the Czechoslovak daily press. The meeting was held in the office of the local Czechoslovak consul, Dr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka, on December 22, 1920. In this meeting, plans were laid out for a campaign among the Czechoslovak people of America, especially those of Chicago, in behalf of the Hoover Relief Fund. The Czechoslovak-American Committee, representing our foremost national, benevolent, and other organizations, was formed. In this meeting it was also emphasized that the success of the Czechoslovak-American relief campaign would mostly depend upon the support of our daily newspapers. For that reason, an appeal was made to the representatives of the Czechoslovak press to support this campaign to the best of their abilities, because only in <pb facs="5418478_5_1569.jpg" n="3"/>that way could the action undertaken in behalf of the Hoover Relief Fund be crowned with success, and the aid, which is so desirously expected, for Czechoslovakia assured.</p>
   <p>This appeal touched our hearts and we attacked the task with great energy, love, and enthusiasm. We began to work on the task around Christmas time, and since that time we daily appealed to the readers of our newspapers for contributions in behalf of poor suffering children in Czechoslovakia. Our readers, notwithstanding the fact that they were more than once bitterly disappointed in their faith, responded to our calls. At the beginning they were somewhat slow but later on they contributed more readily. The first contributions started to roll in first from the ranks of individuals, from our common poor people. Later on, but slowly, our well-to-do-people responded; Czechoslovak enterprises and rich corporations did not remain deaf to our calls. The month of January was one of the best months of the campaign because during that month we appealed to our people daily. During the months <pb facs="5418478_5_1570.jpg" n="4"/>of February and March contributions were rolling in slowly. Therefore, it may be said that the task was accomplished by us in the period of only about six weeks.</p>
   <p>All we have accomplished was done gladly because we considered it our duty. We did everything possible. For the results achieved we do not give credit to ourselves, but to them who responded to our appeals--to them who contributed. They deserve the credit. But the greatest of credit must be given to our common, plain people who do not come from the ranks of the rich and well-to -do class, but from the ranks of the poor. Without them the result of our collection would not have been as it is.</p>
   <p>Up to midnight, March 15, the sum of $6,555.17 was collected by us. To this amount we added the sum of $16.26 which we received as interest from the bank. Therefore the total amount collected by us is $6,571.43, which sum, according to the present quotation, is equivalent to five hundred thousand Czechoslovakian <pb facs="5418478_5_1571.jpg" n="5"/>kronen. A check for the above-mentioned amount (in dollars) will be sent by us today to Dr. Bedrich Stepanek, Washington D. C. He is requested to give this check to Mr. Herbert Hoover as the amount collected by our newspaper in behalf of his Relief Fund.</p>
   <p>The final meeting of the Czechoslovak-American Relief Committee was held in the office of the local Czechoslovak consulate yesterday. In this meeting, the final report on the collection was presented. We are publishing the report in another section of this newspaper.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
