<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-17">Mar. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Report on Czechoslovak Activity in Behalf of the Hoover Relief Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-17">Mar. 17, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A REPORT ON CZECHOSLOVAK ACTIVITY IN BEHALF OF THE HOOVER RELIEF FUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechoslovak-American Committee which directed the campaign undertaken for the benefit of the Hoover Relief Fund among Czechoslovaks of America, held its final meeting in the office of the local Czechoslovak consulate on Wednesday afternoon, March 16, 1921. The meeting was presided over by Mr. Charles J. Vopicka. The secretary, Mr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka, local consul of the Czechoslovak Republic, made it known that the Hoover Relief campaign, undertaken by Mr. Herbert Hoover in the United States for the benefit of the suffering children of Central and Eastern Europe, was successful in obtaining the sum of thirty-three million dollars. Even the Czechoslovak participation in this campaign was, considering the prevailing conditions, very satisfactory. In Chicago alone almost eighteen thousand dollars was collected. Mr. Hoover was constantly kept informed as to the progress of his campaign among us Czechoslovaks. This resulted in his increasing the original allotment of provisions for children of Czechoslovakia from one hundred thousand dollars to two hundred <pb facs="5418478_5_1573.jpg" n="2"/>and fifty thousand dollars. In addition, medicaments will be provided for Czechoslovak children from the funds collected by the American Relief Council.</p>
   <p>The detailed report on the activity of the Czechoslovak-American Committee of Chicago was prepared by Mr. V. B. Kosner, official of the local Czechoslovak consulate. The report reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Czechoslovak-American Committee was formed to take care of the campaign which started on December 22, 1920 and ended yesterday, March 15, 1921. During the said time the sum of $17,892.80 was collected. The administration work of the Committee was taken care of by the personnel of the Czechoslovak consulate of Chicago. Lieutenant Jarolim, who was appointed to take care of the administration work by Dr. A. Suma, economic attache of the Czechoslovak Embassy of Washington D. C., devoted most of his time to propagation.</p>
   <p>"During the campaign three thousand five hundred letters were sent out to organizations and individuals. Through the courtesy of Reverend Dr. Vaclav Vanek, the <pb facs="5418478_5_1574.jpg" n="3"/>directory of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) was used. Dr. Vanek, because of his experience, was found to be very useful in helping the office routine and his counsel proved to be of advantage. Several meetings were arranged with the Priadky (Ladies Auxiliary of the Slovak League) and the Vcelky (Ladies Auxiliary of the Czechoslovak National Alliance), and one mass meeting was held in Sokol Chicago Hall where Dr. Jaroslav F. Smetanka, Dr. Anna Berkovec, and Mrs. Anna Novak, chairman of the Chicago Vcelky, were the speakers.</p>
   <p>"More than one third of the total amount was collected by the Denni Hlasatel. Since the beginning of this campaign, the publishers of the Denni Hlasatel ardently co-operated with the Committee, and thanks to the unceasing efforts of Mr. Albert J. Havranek, a member of the editorial staff who was in charge of the propaganda, the Denni Hlasatel, by collecting the sum of $6,571.43, attained first place. Second place was attained by the Slovaks of Chicago who immediately comprehended the significance of this campaign and collected the sum of $2,129.10. Taking into consideration that there are not very many Slovaks in <pb facs="5418478_5_1575.jpg" n="4"/>Chicago, the result may be called excellent. Third place was attained by the Daily Svornost, which collected the sum of $1,619.</p>
   <p>"Following is the list of our organizations and amounts they collected: The Chicago Vcelky, $1,011.39; the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe (Czecho-slovak National Alliance of America), $913.30; the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Unity of Bohemian Ladies), $881.50; Catholic organizations, $767.50; the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Sisterhood), $388; the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies), $299.15.</p>
   <p>"A beautiful example of generosity was shown by the children attending the Vojta Naprstek Free Thought School who, under the leadership of their teachers, collected $81.18. The sum of $1,299.40 was collected from individuals. The total amounts received by the office of the Committee were: $9,192.27 from the Bohemian section; $2,129.10 from the Slovak section; total, $11,321.37. This amount, according to the receipts of the treasurer of the Committee, was deposited in the Lawndale National Bank. The collection of the Denni Hlasatel, <pb facs="5418478_5_1576.jpg" n="5"/>according to the announcement of its publishers, amounted to $6,571.43, and was desposited at the Kaspar State Bank. [The names of organizations that contributed $100 or more to the Relief Fund are omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>"In concluding its report, the office of the Committee announces the names of the good workers who made the success of the collection possible. Besides the above mentioned gentlemen (Reverend Dr. Vaclav Vanek and A. J. Havranek), the following deserve special mention: Mesdames Novak, Beranek, Smetanka, Kovar, Hulka, Ruzek, Polak, Martisovic, Buchta, Kuss, Sopociovy, Schustek, Fajnor, Kosman and Michalic; Messrs. Votava, Kovar, Vrablik, and Poliak.</p>
   <p>"Our organizations, without exception, labored in behalf of the Hoover Relief Fund, and in spite of the fact that an industrial stagnation existed during that period, the results were astonishing. The Czechoslovak-American Committee extends its most sincere thanks to all the contributors and fellow workers who have striven to make this collection a success. The knowledge that they have contributed and labored in behalf of those little innocent victims of the World <pb facs="5418478_5_1577.jpg" n="6"/>War is a sufficient reward for their efforts."</p>
   <p>The report was unanimously approved. Mr. Frank G. Hajicek, treasurer of the committee, was requested to send the amount of $11,321.37, now deposited at the Lawndale State Bank, to the Ambassador of the Czechoslovak Republic, Dr. Bedrich Stepanek, in Washington D. C., with a request that he personally deliver this amount to Mr. Herbert Hoover. Mr. Albert J. Havranek, reporting for the Denni Hlasatel, stated that the publishers of the Denni Hlasatel will also send the amount of $6,571.43 to Dr. Bedrich Stepanek immediately.</p>
   <p>In regards to contributions which may be yet received, it was resolved to send these contributions directly to the Ceskoslovenska Pece o Dite (Czechoslovak Child Welfare Association of Prague, Czechoslovakia).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
