<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-27">Mar. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Czechoslovak Ambassador Voices Thanks for Relief Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-27">Mar. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECHOSLOVAK AMBASSADOR VOICES THANKS FOR RELIEF FUND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently we received a letter from Dr. Bedrich Stepanek, Czechoslovak Ambassador at Washington, D. C., in which he acknowledged the receipt of money sent to him by us as the proceeds of a collection undertaken in behalf of the Hoover Relief Fund for the benefit of suffering children in Czechoslovakia. In his letter, Dr. Stepanek expressed his recognition and also thanked us for the work accomplished. By publishing this letter today, we are not doing so for egotistic and boastful reasons. We decline Dr. Stepanek's recognition and thanks because we think it is not due. We did no more than perform our duty, and this we are willing to do at every opportunity. Dr. Stepanek's recognition and thanks belong, in the first place, to those who helped us in our work, to those who so generously responded to our appeals, to those who contributed. Were it not for these good souls our action would not have been so successful. Because we are fully aware of this fact, we do hereby acknowledge that the letter of thanks which was sent to us belongs, in fact, to everyone who helped to make <pb facs="5418478_5_1554.jpg" n="2"/>our action, undertaken at the behest of the Czechoslovak Ambassador, successful. Therefore we publish the letter today, and we publish it also for the reason that we want everybody who contributed to directly hear from Dr. Stepanek himself that the money collected by us was received by him.</p>
   <p>The letter received by us from Dr. Stepanek reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Washington D. C. March 23, 1921.</p>
   <p>"To the publishers of the Denni Hlasatel,</p>
   <p>1545 West 18th Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen!</p>
   <p>"With sincere joy I read your letter of March 17, 1921 in which you reported to me the results of a collection undertaken by you in behalf of the Hoover Relief Fund, at the behest of Czechoslovak Embassy at Washington D. C. I was <pb facs="5418478_5_1555.jpg" n="3"/>pleasantly surprised by the results. I see that you kept your promise to support this important campaign to the best of your ability.</p>
   <p>"I esteem your co-operation very much, and I thank you and your fellow workers for your exemplary zeal which made the success of your action possible. I will personally deliver the inclosed check for $6,571.43, together with other checks received by me from all parts of the United States, to Mr. Herbert Hoover as a contribution from Czechoslovak-Americans toward his fund for the suffering children in Czechoslovakia.</p>
   <p>"I should like to extend my individual thanks, as far as possible, to all the co-workers and patrons of the Hoover action. Therefore, I should be very much obliged to you if you would send me a list of their names.</p>
   <p>"Permit me to make an allusion to a paragraph in your letter in which you manifest a hope that even in the future you will be able to co-operate in all matters concerning the good and the success of the Czechoslovak Republic. I <pb facs="5418478_5_1556.jpg" n="4"/>accept joyfully your promise, and I count on your co-operation in all the great tasks for the success of which we shall all strive in this great and wonderful land in behalf of our Czechoslovak nation.</p>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"Dr. Bedrich Stepanek,</p>
   <p>"Ambassador of the Czechoslovak</p>
   <p>Republic."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
