<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-01-29">Jan. 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">In Behalf of Children in Czechoslovakia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-01-29">Jan. 29, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IN BEHALF OF CHILDREN IN CZECHOSLOVAKIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Quite often it is asserted that children who are born or brought up here in the United States cannot sympathize with Czechoslovakia, the birthplace of their parents, like those who were born in Czechoslovakia and who came to the United States to live here. We agree with this assertion, but only to a certain extent. We are neither willing nor able to agree with this completely.</p>
   <p>We know that very much depends upon the education which the children receive at home. If at home the parents speak only with love and reverence for their native land, then at least some feeling for the old country may be instilled into the hearts of their children. In all of its actions, a child responds solely on the basis of emotion rather than reason. Therefore, if the parents who were born in Czechoslovakia teach their children to love.the homeland, then the children could learn to sympathize with Czechoslovakia, and the Czechoslovak-American children would adhere to our old homeland with more love and reverence than they seem to have today.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1619.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It would be sufficient, for example, to speak before the children about the glorious past of the Bohemians, to tell them about the terrible oppression and suffering that the Bohemians, Koravians, Silesians, and Slovaks had to endure just because they loved their country. It would be sufficient to tell them about the great and superhuman sacrifices which our people had to perform before their long-deserved freedom was gained.</p>
   <p>Mr. and Mrs. Cunat, of 1236 South Kildare Avenue, seem to be rearing their granddaughter, Lillien Cunat, in just this way. Lillien, who is only nine years old, seems to have learned how to perform good deeds, as was demonstrated last Wednesday when she was celebrating her ninth birthday. On that day, she received a monetary gift from her grandfather and grandmother and was told to buy something for this money. But Lillen bought nothing. She added the money to her own savings and sent the total sum, amounting to six dollars, to our office through our fellow-employee, Mr. Stanislav Trnka. She sent word that the whole amount was to be added to a collection undertaken by Mr. Hoover for poor children in Europe. She learned that children in Czechoslovakia are suffering, <pb facs="5418478_5_1620.jpg" n="3"/>and therefore she would like to help them. Her grandfather and grandmother give her everything she needs, and she would rather send the money to the children in Czechoslovakia than to buy sweets for herself. She would also like to hear that her example is being followed by many Czechoslovak children who reside here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
