<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-17">Nov. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For the Invalids of the Czecho-Slovak Legion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1260</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1260.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-17">Nov. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE INVALIDS OF THE CZECHO-SLOVAK LEGION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last meeting of the Chicago committee in charge of collecting funds for invalid Czech legionnaires and the widows and orphans of fallen Czech legionnaires, held on November 14, it became apparent that our consciences are being stirred in behalf of the invalids and the destitute families of the fallen men. Not only were all the members present, but representative members of the committees of the Pilsen, Bohemian California, Town of Lake districts, and North Side of Chicago, as well as a five-member committee of the Svazova Druzina Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru (Local Branch Group of the Federation of Czechoslovak Legionnaires), attended the meeting. The last named committee consisted of J. Bukovsky, Alois Bedrna, J. J. Fekl, S. J. Hajn, and Emil Korinek. The various committee reports sounded very encouraging.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1261.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the so-called Little South Side district things are moving along, too. A meeting was held in that district on November 13 in a public school building at the corner of West 30th Street and Lowe Avenue. As president, pro tem, Mr. Josef Dusek of 3002 Emerald Avenue was elected. His telephone number is Boulevard 6427; Mr. Frantisek Sroufek, of 2925 Emerald Avenue, was elected secretary, and Mr. Vaclav Cizek, 924 West 29th Street, treasurer. Mr. Cizek's telephone is Boulevard 0763. The next meeting is to be held on Sunday, November 19. At that meeting a permanent committee for the South Side will be elected, and the entire district will be subdivided for purposes of work. The volunteer workers will then be assigned to their respective parts of the district. The meeting will again be held in the school building at the corner of Lowe Avenue and West 30th Street, and will start at 2:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>Originally the entire North Side of Chicago (everything north of Jackson Boulevard) was to be regarded as one area for purposes of work. It was later found that this area was too large, and it was, therefore, subdivided. Thus, <pb facs="5418478_5_1262.jpg" n="3"/>Irving Park and Jefferson Park form one part, in which the meeting will be held on November 20, at 8 P.M. in the Sokol Krivan, 4942 West Lawrence Avenue. Fourteen volunteers have already signified their willingness to work in this part of the city. The neighborhood adjoining the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) will be worked by Mrs. Sistka, Mr. Urbanec, and Mr. Kolbaba.</p>
   <p>The second part of the North Side is bounded on the east by Halsted Street, on the north by Fullerton Avenue, and extends west to the city limits. We may augment our previous report by adding the name of Mrs. Anna Schustek, 1538 West Chicago Avenue (telephone Monroe 4694), who is also a member of the committee on organization and, as such, will procure more volunteer workers. Volunteers may communicate with her directly.</p>
   <p>On Saturday, November 18, there is to be a meeting of the workers of this section of Chicago in the office of the firm Augustin and Fabry, 1543 West Chicago Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1263.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>To co-ordinate the work done in all parts of the city, representatives for each section have been appointed by the central committee. These representatives will be in contact with the work of the various committees, and will endeavor to aid the workers to make the collecting of funds efficient and successful. The secretaries are hereby directed to communicate with the office of the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada (Czechoslovak National Council), 3734 West 26th Street, where they may secure a sufficient number of collection booklets, credentials, etc., and where they may get any essential information which has a bearing upon the subject at hand. Upon completion of the work, the receipts for funds will be sent to the Narodni Vybor (National Committee) in Cleveland, Ohio, but the executive committee, consisting of the officers of the National Council in Chicago, and of the officers of the local collection committee for Chicago and vicinity, will have charge of all books or records by means of which every contribution together with the name of the contributor may be ascertained, and any other information concerning these transactions, given.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1264.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Our Czech and Slovak newspapers of Chicago are hereby requested to be so kind as to send their reporters to the meetings of the [central] committee. These meetings are held every Tuesday. The president of the Narodni Rada, Mr. John A. Cervenka, reported that the management of the Pilsen Brewing Company had consented to the sending of the sum of $250 as a contribution to the cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
