<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-01-20">Jan. 20, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Annual Meeting of the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1021</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1021.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-01-20">Jan. 20, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE ANNUAL MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND ORPHANAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the board of delegates to the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) was held last Friday at the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies' hall, 18th and May Streets. The meeting was unusually well attended by the delegates, and the harmonious proceedings of the meeting gave proof of an unusual interest by all the delegates in the welfare of both of these institutions. The meeting was called to order by Mr. Vojtech Suchy, the president, and when it became known that the secretary was not able to attend this meeting because of illness, Mrs. Josephine Vodak was appointed to take her place. The minutes of the December meeting were approved as read. The names of individual delegates were then read. [There follows the list of delegates of various organizations which are represented in this body.]</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Trnka, secretary of the board of directors, then read the minutes <pb facs="5418478_5_1022.jpg" n="2"/>of the previous meeting of the board. The minutes of this meeting will be published in the Denni Hlasatel tomorrow.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vojtech Suchy introduced a new delegate, Mr. Karel Hribal, a former inmate of the Sirotcinec who now occupies a seat among other delegates as a representative of the Praha Lodge No. 13 of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies. Mr. Hribal, from now on will help to manage the institution of which he was an inmate and to which he is obliged for his education. The young lad was greeted with applause and, apparently deeply touched, took his seat among the other delegates.....</p>
   <p>The nominations and elections were next in order. Inasmuch as the delegates recognize the unselfish work of their old executive officers, the elections ran smoothly. Mr. Vojtech Suchy, in particular, would not accept the nomination, saying that twelve years in the office of president was enough. But, urged by the delegates, he finally changed his mind was unanimously reelected to the presidency. Mr. Frank J. Petru, treasurer, was also prevailed upon to satisfy the wishes of the delegates, and he will retain his office <pb facs="5418478_5_1023.jpg" n="3"/>for another year. The election of a secretary was postponed until the next meeting.....</p>
   <p>Following the reading of receipts and expenses for the month of December, the meeting was adjourned. Receipts were $4,827.03; Expenses, $1,935.50.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
