<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-18">Dec. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Large New Hall of Sokol Chicago Was Opened Yesterday with a Dignified Cermony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-18">Dec. 18, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE LARGE NEW HALL OF SOKOL CHICAGO WAS OPENED YESTERDAY WITH A DIGNIFIED CERMONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opening of the remodeled hall of Sokol Chicago was celebrated in a dignified manner by our Ceska Kalifornie (Bohemian California District) yesterday afternoon. This celebration deserves to be ranked as one of the finest arranged by us in recent times. The program was very brilliant and dignified and will surely add to the credit and honor of the Program Committee.</p>
   <p>The festivities were begun with the playing of the "March of the Gladiators" by Jureny's Band. Following this the orchestra played the overture "Light Cavalry" by Suppe. Both numbers were received with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>The Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor (Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society), <pb facs="5418478_5_1207.jpg" n="2"/>under the direction of Mr. John Kalas, then sang "O, Hory, Hory V Mlhave Dali" (Oh Mountains, Mountains In The Hazy Distance). After this Mr. V. Roubal, president of Sokol Chicago, appeared and briefly but heartily welcomed the guests. He said, "We invited you here, so that we could give you the opportunity to see the project of our dreams, a project which in itself is worthy of your favor. That project, about which we had doubts, upon which we looked with unbelief, is today a reality. All obstacles have been overcome. That entire difficult task has been carried out. Today there stands here a representative building, in which, in the future, our youth is to be educated, where the dramatic arts are to be developed, where physical culture and the Sokol idea are to be propagated. No one knows with what obstacles and difficulties we had to contend. Nevertheless, today all our efforts are crowned with success and I turn this hall over to you with the request that all of you continue to favor Sokol Chicago in the future as you have in the past. I thank you for your generous participation and <pb facs="5418478_5_1208.jpg" n="3"/>I hope that we shall often meet under this roof."</p>
   <p>These heartfelt words were re-echoed by the audience, which expressed its approval by thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>The representative of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union), Mr. Layer, then appeared and with enthusiastic words gave recognition for a magnificent undertaking not only in the name of the Narodni Jednota Sokolska and the Czechs of Chicago, but also in the name of all the Czech people in America.</p>
   <p>The audience was then addressed by the instructor of the Central Sokol Circuit, Mr. Styblo, who also gave enthusiastic recognition for the entire undertaking. He said that the hall will surely become a center for Czech intelligentsia, which will be the greatest reward for the enterprise and sacrifice of Sokol Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1209.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Novy, the architect under whose supervision the construction of the hall was carried out, heartily greeted the people, and gave a brief description of the structure. One thousand seats can be placed in the main hall easily, and the gallery will hold four hundred additional seats. The gallery is provided with four safety and fire exits. The stage is modeled after the example of the most modern theaters. All scenery is raised and lowered mechanically. The dressing rooms are comfortably and modernly equipped. Under the main hall is a spacious dining room where four hundred persons can be accommodated comfortably. A kitchen is located here which is equipped with a gas range, two bar rooms, a cloak room, toilets, etc., all built to comply with existing city health and safety ordinances. Fronting the street is an assembly hall for lodges. It is furnished with all modern conveniences, is well-lighted and perfectly ventilated. It should be added that beneath the hall the central heating plant is located, containing the finest boilers which render remarkable service.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1210.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Then followed a tableau, "Nas Ucel" (Our Goal), which was arranged by Mr. Bares. The tableau was beautiful. It was a pity, however, that the lighting effects were not properly carried out as this was to no little disadvantage.</p>
   <p>The orchestra ended the program with a splendid rendition of "Slavonic Dances" by Dvorak.</p>
   <p>The evening program was no less beautiful and was participated in by such well-known vocal and dramatic artists as Mrs. Frydl, Mrs. Ruzicka, Messrs. Keclik, Sulc, and Hofreiter, all of whom were rewarded with a storm of applause for their performances.</p>
   <p>We do not believe it necessary to give a more minute description of this magnificent hall, because we feel certain that sooner or later every countryman will vist this new building, which is today without <pb facs="5418478_5_1211.jpg" n="6"/>question the most beautiful and most luxurious hall not only in Chicago but in all Bohemian-America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
