<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-30">Dec. 30, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Interest in Hoover's Relief Action Is Growing</title><title level="a" type="sub">Voices Supporting Hoover Are Not Voices Crying in the Wilderness</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-30">Dec. 30, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">INTEREST IN HOOVER'S RELIEF ACTION IS GROWING</title><title level="a" type="sub">Voices Supporting Hoover Are Not Voices Crying in the Wilderness</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hearts of the Czechoslovak people of Chicago have been stirred already. Contributions for the benefit of starving children in Czechoslovakia are coming in. In some cases these contributions are unusually large. But most of the contributors, although they are not rich, are sending the sum of ten dollars, which will provide food for one Bohemian or Slovak child until the next crop is gathered.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak committee for Hoover's relief action made large gains when, at the last meeting of the committee, Mr. Karel J. Vopicka, until recently our United States ambassador to Rumania, promised all possible help and accepted the chairmanship of the committee. Mr. Vopicka recently returned from Europe, and he knows very well from his own experiences how the poor people of Central Europe and Czechoslovakia, especially, are suffering.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1646.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although at present he is busy writing a book about his World War experiences of many years, nevertheless he recognizes the importance of the relief action, and he is willing to help as much as he can.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank G. Hajicek, president of the Lawndale National Bank, accepted the office of treasurer of the Czechoslovak committee.</p>
   <p>Collection books, each containing twenty-five receipt sheets, are ready for distribution. A number of zealous and willing workers called for these books. Anybody who wants to help our children can get these collection books from the treasurer of the committee at the Lawndale State Bank or at the office of the committee, 3734 West 26th Street. The collected amount will then be deposited at the office of this newspaper. The name of every contributor will be published. The money will then be sent to Dr. Bedrich Stepanek, Washington, D. C., who will deliver the total amount collected among the Czechoslovaks of America to Mr. Herbert Hoover, the originator of this great campaign. The purpose of this campaign which is being undertaken throughout the United States <pb facs="5418478_5_1647.jpg" n="3"/>is to collect thirty-three million dollars needed by Mr. Hoover to provide food for children of Central Europe until the time when the next crop is harvested. The sum of ten dollars is sufficient to feed one Bohemian or Slovak child until that time. Would it be possible for anybody here to eat heartily, knowing that although he could afford it, he had done absolutely nothing for the starving children? Therefore, help and help at once!</p>
   <p>If the relief action undertaken by Mr. Herbert Hoover with such love and enthusiasm were not so important and meritorious, then it surely would not be recommended by President Woodrow Wilson. He himself was among the first to respond and contribute a large amount. This relief action is also recommended by the newly elected President, Senator Warren G. Harding, who contributed a large amount.....</p>
   <p>A Czechoslovak of Chicago must follow these above-mentioned examples. By not doing so, he will prove that he has a heart of stone. And a Czechoslovak of America never had such a heart. By his sentiment he always proved that he <pb facs="5418478_5_1648.jpg" n="4"/>can act in an American, Czechoslovak, and human way. He has always worked willingly and enthusiastically. He has never given alms, but he has always performed his duty. And at this time he will certainly not evade this purely human, Czechoslovakian, and, in fact universal duty. He surely will convince Mr. Hoover that if he, as an American, has been able to work and accomplish a great deal for Czechoslovakia during the past, then so much the sooner, must a Czechoslovak of America perform his duty toward his old homeland, knowing that Mr. Hoover will give his support to Czechoslovakia again.....</p>
   <p>In conclusion we say this: We do not ask everybody to contribute the whole ten dollars. Everybody should contribute as much as he can, according to his circumstances. But everybody should contribute at least something toward this noble cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
