<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-17">Aug. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Regular Meeting of the Delegates to the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0776</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0776.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-17">Aug. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A REGULAR MEETING OF THE DELEGATES TO THE BOHEMIAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND ORPHANAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular meeting of....the delegates to the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) was held last night in the lower hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) on May and West 18th Streets. The meeting, which was not well attended, was presided over by Mr. Vojtech Suchy. Immediately after the opening of the meeting, Delegate Lehman gained the floor and asked why all the officers were not in their accustomed places; the said officers took the hint and seated themselves accordingly. The minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read by the secretary, Mrs. Bozena Brabec. The reading of correspondence followed. The Order of the Ceska Narodni Osveta cislo 58 (Bohemian National Culture No. 58), of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, announced the appointment of its new delegate, Mr. K. Klimunda. That gentleman was properly welcomed. The next letter was from the Patronat (Board of Managers) <pb facs="5418478_5_0777.jpg" n="2"/>of the Ceska Svobodomyslna Skola, F. B. Zdrubek (F.B. Zdrubek Bohemian Free Thought School) of Irving Park, asking for a decision on the question of teaching the inmates of the Sirotcinec. After listening to the remarks of the delegates Mr. Rada, Mrs. Rek, and Mrs. Hrisny, the request of the Zdrubek School was granted. In answer to the request of the Patronat that a delegate of the Utulna be sent to the meeting of the Patronat, it was maintained that the Utulna never sends its delegates anywhere, and cannot grant that request.....Then, to the great astonishment of all present, a letter of resignation from the secretary of the board of directors, Mr. Josef Trnka, was read. The president, in the name of the board of directors, stated he was sorry to see Mr. Trnka go, for that gentleman was an industrious and hardworking officer, and he expressed his hope that Mr. Trnka would reconsider the matter and recall his resignation. The matter was discussed by the delegates Lehman, Zrust, and Mrs. Gruenwald, and it was decided that the president should try to have Mr. Trnka change his mind, so that he would remain in office at least until the end of the year.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0778.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next item was the reading of bills for the past month. The president....then stated that in view of the fact that there had been no meeting of the board of directors in July, he personally had examined these bills and found them to be correct with one exception. This was a bill for $151.59 made out by Mr. Fottr, owner of a hardware and paint store. The store is in the vicinity of the Utulna, on Crawford Avenue, and the purchases were made by Mr. Fischer, the former business manager of our institution. During the past three months the business manager is said to have purchased about five hundred dollars worth of supplies which now cannot be found. When Mr. Fottr was asked about this bill he stated that after having made the purchases, Mr. Fischer had requested that the amount of the invoice be split up into three parts, one part to be billed each month, in order that the whole amount might not seem too conspicious. Mr. Fottr, of course, agreed to do this and delivered the goods. The office expenses, too, were found to be disproportionately high by Mr. Suchy; the items listed being carfare, postage and sundries.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0779.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Following the discussion of these matters, the bills were approved and it was announced that in the future these matters should be handled differently. Mrs. Marie Svach, reporting for the entertainment and concert committees, stated that the merchants should be notified through our daily press to the effect that our ladies will be calling on them to ask them to purchase advertising space on the printed program. This was approved. The investigation committee reported that it was compelled to reject the application for admission of the seventy-one-year-old Josef Taborsky, for the reason that the applicant has well-to-do children who are able to care for their aged parent.</p>
   <p>The Order of Caslav No. 205 of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies asked by letter to have four children admitted into the institution. They are the children of one of their members, a Mr. Josef Hasek of 3238 South Kedzie Avenue. The society stated that the mother of the aforesaid children is mentally unbalanced and is at present committed to the [state] institution for the insane at Dunning, Illinois. It was decided to admit these children through the medium of the juvenile court, and it was ordered that the Order of Caslav be informed <pb facs="5418478_5_0780.jpg" n="5"/>accordingly. The investigation committee then received the application of the nine-year-old Anna Danes, whose mother is a widow and earning her living by doing domestic work.</p>
   <p>The president then announced that the semi-annual financial report was to have been submitted in this meeting, but that Mr. Fischer whose duty it was to do so, and who promised on his word of honor to have the report ready, failed to keep his promise. When the president reminded him of the promise by telephone, Mr. Fischer is said to have answered that his connections with the institution and with him [the president,] have ceased to exist, and that, if he is to render such a report, he must be paid to do so. The president stated further that the monthly financial report for July was likewise not ready. Mr. Soukup, who was formerly the business manager of the Utulna, and Mr. Suchy also announced that Mr. Fischer left all the books, etc., in great disorder. Delegate Lehman then suggested that it was not necessary to accuse the absent Mr. Fischer, the former business manager, and that it would be <pb facs="5418478_5_0781.jpg" n="6"/>better to wait until the next regular meeting of the board of delegates, at which meeting Mr. Fischer will also be present, as a delegate of his own society. Nothwithstanding the above suggestion, and on motion made by Mr. Petru, it was decided to have a three-man committee appointed which would call on Mr. Fischer and bring these affairs into order. The members of this committee were Messrs. Petru, Lehman, and Charvat.</p>
   <p>The disbursements for the past month were $1,908. Since there were no entries showing the amounts received, it is impossible to report what the receipts were for the same period.</p>
   <p>The new business manager, Mr. Anthony Smith, was then introduced to the delegates and the meeting ended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
