<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-03">Feb. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Report of the Ladies' Auxiliary of the Bohemian Charitable Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-03">Feb. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE LADIES' AUXILIARY OF THE BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hubbard Memorial Church, 2520 South Lawndale Avenue, was the place in which the Ladies' Auxiliary of the Bohemian Charitable Association held their annual meeting in the month of January [exact date not given]. Mrs. Mary Krupka, the re-elected chairman, presided. She thanked the members for their collaboration last year, and expressed hope that their performance would be repeated in the coming year.</p>
   <p>A motion picture exhibition, for which the hall and all the other necessary equipment were loaned by Mr. Vaclav Dibelka without any charge; various gifts and collections, arranged among the members, brought a considerable amount of money into the treasury. The Strawberry Festival, so popular and delightful among our public, also yielded a nice profit, as did the assessments and the membership fees. The total receipts represented the sum of $930.79. Our expenses, with all the different kind of charities <pb facs="5418478_5_0155.jpg" n="2"/>donated, amounted to $467.25, and the sum of $400 was handed over by the Ladies' Auxiliary to the treasury of the Bohemian Charitable Association.</p>
   <p>Our ladies were also very active in seeing that the ball arranged by the Bohemian Charity Association was a great success. This yielded more than $1,500.</p>
   <p>In spite of all this work, the Ladies' Auxiliary did not forget that in the far off old country of ours the hands of innocent and unhappy children, victims of the War, are extended to us, asking for help, and, therefore, during the month of May sent to them the following articles: fifty-seven aprons, eighty-seven suits, sixty bundles of calico of from eight to ten yards each, eight bundles of flannel, eight yards each, thread, tape, forty-eight dozen fleece-lined union suits, thirty dozen overalls, twelve dozen small caps, forty-nine large caps, thirteen pairs of shoes, and one thousand bars of soap. We made most of the dresses and aprons ourselves. The total value <pb facs="5418478_5_0156.jpg" n="3"/>of these shipped articles was $872.50. To this amount, Mr. Joseph Dusek, well-known philanthropist, contributed the sum of one hundred dollars; Mrs. Josephine Beranek donated a beautiful fur, which, after being auctioned, brought one hundred and fifteen dollars; Messrs. J. J. Lalla and A. Krupka sent one hundred dollars worth of soap, and the rest was raised by various collections among the ladies. The Ladies' Auxiliary thanks all the donors and patrons who collaborated with them last year, and begs for continued support.</p>
   <p>For next year, the following officers were elected: Mrs. Marie Krupka, president; Mrs. Terezie Hajicek, vice-president; Mrs. Antonie Kybic, secretary; Mrs. Frantiska Stejskal, accountant; and Mrs. Sophia Kreml, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
