<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-26">Nov. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Charitable Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-26">Nov. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday the directors of the Bohemian Charitable Association held a meeting which was called to order by the chairman, Judge Joseph Z. Uhlir. The secretary, Mr. Otta Fuerst, read the minutes of the previous meeting and these were accepted as read. A communication from the Old People's Home and Orphanage expressing gratitude for gifts received from the Bohemian Charitable Association was read. Another communication indicates that Mr. Frank G. Hajicek received a further contribution of ten dollars for the Association. Mr. Frank J. Petru announced that two dollars were turned over to him by the St. Ludmila Society for tickets. It was resolved to give a vote of thanks to the arrangements committee--Messrs. K. Novak, Stanley J. Loula, Jan (John) A. Sokol, Roman Sedlacek, and Frank J. Petru. To be sure, the energetic ladies who helped in every way possible to make the dance a success should not be forgotten. Receipts for the past month....total $81. The Bohemian Charitable Association found work for four clients; in two cases <pb facs="5418478_5_0500.jpg" n="2"/>arrangements were made whereby the County defrayed funeral expenses; four families were provided with coal; four families were provided with food stuffs; one person was sent to a hospital; rent was paid for one client; clothing was provided in five cases. The chairman, Mr. Joseph Z. Uhlir, turned in a check for twelve dollars, which amount was collected at the celebration of the 35th birthday anniversary of Mr. Stanislav Simecek, held in Mr. Anton Snabl's place at 26th Street and Trumbull Avenue. For the Christmas gift distribution which will be made to families suffering want, an investigation committee was appointed. With the coming of winter, the office of the Bohemian Charitable Association will become busy and for that reason some help should be secured in time so that aid may be rendered quickly and in the right places. The executive itself will decide in the matter. A motion was adopted which resulted in a lively debate among those present. It was said that with the help of our most popular artists, such as Emma Destinn, Slezak [first name omitted], and others who will be in our metropolis this season, a concert should be given in the Auditorium, the net proceeds of which are to be donated not only to the Bohemian Charitable <pb facs="5418478_5_0501.jpg" n="3"/>Association but also to the Old People's Home and Orphanage and to St. Joseph's Orphanage. In that way the proceeds would be divided into three equal parts. For that purpose, Mr. John A. Cervenka will notify all societies which are to be represented and each of them will elect three delegates who will then work jointly toward the desired goal. Messrs. John A. Cervenka, Joseph Z. Uhlir, and Vaclav Vanek were elected to represent the Bohemian Charitable Association. This is surely a great idea and therefore it is necessary, in a matter so noble and for such a noble cause, that all should work together. Not only would there be prepared for the music-loving public a highly uplifting entertainment, but all three of the above-mentioned institutions would be helped very much. The committee from the Bohemian Charitable Association and the committees from the Old people's Home and Orphanage and St. Joseph's Orphanage are to work together to secure the artists for this concert and are to carry on an active agitation. Chairman Mr. Joseph Z. Uhlir mentioned that there was a surplus in the treasury and he was told to take the matter up with Mr. Frank G. Hajicek. The meeting then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
