<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-06-29">June 29, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Meeting of the Svaz Cesko-Slovanskych Jednot a Spolku</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-06-29">June 29, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S MEETING OF THE SVAZ CESKO-SLOVANSKYCH JEDNOT A SPOLKU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the delegates of the Svaz Cesko-Slovanskych Jednot a Spolku v Spojenych Statech Severni Ameriky a v Kanade (Alliance of Bohemian-Slavonic Societies and Lodges in the United States and in Canada) was brought to order at 8 P. M. yesterday by the chairman, Mr. Fiedler. Present in the meeting were delegates from the following societies: Rady Cesko-Slovansky Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies); Lesnici (Foresters); Taborite (Taborites); Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Bohemian-Slavonic Society); Clevelandska Jednota (Cleveland Society); Cesko-Americka Jednota (Bohemian-American Society); Velkorad Cesko-Slovanskych Podporujicich Spolku (Grand Lodge of the Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies); and the Narodni Hlavni Rad Cesko-Slovanskych Podporujicich Spolku (National Grand Lodge of the Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies). The meeting began with the reading of the minutes, which were approved as read. Then followed the reading of communications: One came from the Federated Fraternities and one from the grand lodge of the Taborite Society. Both communications were accepted and filed. The reading of reports followed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0479.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In reference to Article VI, wherein it is stated that it shall be the duty of the Alliance and of every member to help and support in every legal manner, either by court or proper political influence, either at the ballot box or in other ways, any member of this Alliance whose just rights and advantages may be endangered, it was requested by individual members that the said article be adopted with the exception that the part which calls for support at the ballot box be omitted. The article was corrected in that sense.</p>
   <p>In Article IV are specified the per capita dues which the member organizations of the Alliance are required to pay. Also they are required to pay on a per-centage basis toward the defrayal of the Alliance's expenses if the annual dues are not sufficient. This article was adopted after a debate during which opinions were exchanged as to what was really meant. Also under discussion was a motion that each society should keep a register of those who do not want to pay their dues, in order to prevent these persons from going from one society to another. It was decided to amend Article VI by the supplement: "Societies represented in the Alliance are requested to exchange journals so that each will have a list of expelled members."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0480.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next subject under discussion was the number of copies of the amendment which should be printed. It was decided to have two thousand copies printed in order that each society might be supplied with enough to meet the needs of its membership. Chairman Fiedler brought the meeting to a close.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
