<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-11-23">Nov. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Activities of the Vcelky</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-11-23">Nov. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVITIES OF THE VCELKY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The California branch of the Vcelky (Bees) [Ladies' auxiliary of the Czechoslovak National Alliance of America] recently received two communications from Czechoslovakia, both of them recognizing the meritorious work of this indefatigable national organization:</p>
   <p>"Prague, September 25, 1920</p>
   <p>"To the Vcelky of the Czechoslovak National Alliance of America:</p>
   <p>"We take the liberty to inform you that your shipment of goods, consisting of three boxes weighing three hundred and seventy-nine, one hundred and seventy-seven, and one hundred and eleven pounds, respectively, was received by us. We hereby tender our cordial thanks for your noble comprehension of the solemn tasks which confront the Czechoslovak Red Cross and inform you that all the shipments heretofore received shall be used in the first place for the benefit <pb facs="5418478_5_1691.jpg" n="2"/>of our fallen legionnaires and then wherever such aid is really needed. Your impressive love for our republic and its suffering inhabitants shall be a brilliant example to us and an encouragement to further work.</p>
   <p>The Central Offices of the Czechoslovak Red Cross:</p>
   <p>Alice Masaryk"</p>
   <p>"To the Vcelky of the Czechoslovak National Alliance of America:</p>
   <p>"I hereby acknowledge receipt of the sum of twelve thousand and thirty Czechoslovakian kronen received by me as a gift of the California branch of the Vcelky for children of our institution through Mrs. Magda Kos and Mrs. F. Trnka. For the poor Bohemian children, I hereby express my sincere thanks to all who contributed.</p>
   <p>The Coe College Camp, a children's camp of the American association Komensky <pb facs="5418478_5_1692.jpg" n="3"/>in Cernovice, near Tabor, Czechoslovakia:</p>
   <p>[Signature illegible], Director"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
