<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-26">Nov. 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Cesko-Americka Nemocnice Hopes for a Share of L. Morris Estate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-26">Nov. 26, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKO-AMERICKA NEMOCNICE HOPES FOR A SHARE OF L. MORRIS ESTATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As our readers will well remember, the late Mr. L. Morris, well-known millionaire and president of a Stock Yard firm, bequeathed considerable amounts of money to specified charities, in addition to $50,000 the distribution of which he left in the hands of Mrs. L. Morris, his widow and the executor of his will.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cervenka, president of the board of representatives of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice (Bohemian-American Hospital) and probate clerk, knew about this provision and, acting in the interest of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice, addressed to Mrs. Morris a letter asking for an opportunity to present a request for a part of this money on behalf of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice, an institution which is just being started and hence needs considerable financial support. Mrs. Morris received Mr. Cervenka and referred him to her director, <pb facs="5418478_5_0708.jpg" n="2"/>Wilson, and her son, which two men she had authorized to work out the best way of disposing of this amount, and whom Mr. Cervenka visited yesterday. He was promised that the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice will be taken into consideration when the distribution of the money is taken up. No doubt that after a promise of this kind it is much more than probable that the Nemocnice will share the bequest, an expectation which will make all friends of the Institution just as happy as were its directors when this news was disclosed to them at the meeting they held last night....</p>
   <p>According to the report presented by Neuman, the contract for the printing of the directory has been signed and the actual work on it will start soon....</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank G. Hajicek offered to those who will be working on the directory the use of his old office. After this generous offer a debate about the matter of issuing membership certificates to contributors developed; particularly, <pb facs="5418478_5_0709.jpg" n="3"/>however, the minimum amount of money which would entitle the contributor to a membership certificate was discussed. Finally the amount of ten dollars was agreed upon.</p>
   <p>The meeting agreed to appoint a committee of two who, together with the officers of the Organization, would prepare collection lists for seven pairs of members on the basis of which the pairs would undertake the collection of money pledged by the friends of the Hospital Association. Mr. Walleck and Mr. Loula were appointed members of the committee.</p>
   <p>Doctor Chvatal made a report on the collection he had undertaken from those who had pledged, and submitted a list of those who had promised to send in remittances against their pledges in the near future.</p>
   <p>Treasurer Hajicek reported that up to the day he had approximately $6,700 in <pb facs="5418478_5_0710.jpg" n="4"/>cash on hand.</p>
   <p>Dr. Pavlik opened the question as to what would be the best way of contacting Bohemian organizations. It was decided to start by addressing letters to the grand lodges of all Bohemian orders and other similar organizations, requesting their financial support, together with support in the form of propaganda, for the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice in their member lodges.</p>
   <p>The income reported in yesterday's meeting was $3,955.75. [Translator's note: The article further lists the names of contributors and the amounts contributed. These range from five hundred dollars down to fifty cents.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
