<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-06-22">June 22, 1880</date><title level="a">Convention of the "C.S.P.S." (Czecho-Slovak Benevolent Association)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0622</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0622.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1880-06-22">June 22, 1880</date><title level="a">CONVENTION OF THE "C.S.P.S." (CZECHO-SLOVAK BENEVOLENT ASSOCIATION)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of the fraternal brotherhood, the "C.S.P.S." (Czecho-Slovak Benevolent Association) was brought to order by brother Robt. Pitte, yesterday morning with a hearty welcome to the visiting delegates from all the cities where the C.S.P.S. has its branches.</p>
   <p>Then came roll-call and the presentation of credentials by the delegates. The chairman's gavel was turned over to Brother Rychlik, of Cleveland, the retiring chairman of the National Grand Lodge. The new chairman expressed the thanks of those present to the Grand Lodge of Illinois for the work and time it devoted to making the arrangements for this convention. After a short welcoming address by Brother Pitte, the convention proceeded to administer the third degree to those Brothers not previously so honored.</p>
   <p>Next in the order of proceedings was the election of committees, namely two. (1) A committee to examine the credentials of delegates. (2) A committee to work out rules of procedure for the daily order of business. These committees were composed of one delegate from each State.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0623.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On the first committee representing the State of Missouri is Bro. Klobasa, Ohio.--Bro. Vanek, Illinois.--Bro. Drabek, Michigan.--Bro. Kunsky, Minnesota.--Bro. Jurka, New York.--Bro. Vojtisek, Massachusetts.--Bro. Vojtisek, Pennsylvania.--Bro. A. Novak, Iowa.</p>
   <p>The second committee was as follows: Illinois--Bro. Svojse; Missouri--Bro. Miksicek,; Ohio--Bro. Zbornik; New York--Bro. Bunata; Pennsylvania--Bro. Popelik; Michigan--Bro. Zbornik; Minnesota--Br. Jurka, Wisconsin--Bro. Prosen; Massachusetts--Bro. Bunata; Iowa--Bro. Novak; Maryland--Bro. Svotse.</p>
   <p>A motion to have a committee decide who shall be officers was defeated and the delegates elected officers from their midst. A further motion was made, that all delegates who have had the third degree conferred on them should, as guests of the convention, be assigned to their seats in the convention hall, after which the convention adjourned until tomorrow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
