<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-28">Mar. 28, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">In Recognition of Meritorious Activity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1548</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1548.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-28">Mar. 28, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IN RECOGNITION OF MERITORIOUS ACTIVITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Narodni Socialni Beseda J. V. Fric (J. V. Fric National Socialist Club of Chicago), which in its annual meeting again remembered the Bohemian minority in Czechoslovakia, received the following communication from the Narodni Jednota Posumavska (National Union of Bohemian Foresters) of Prague, Czechoslovakia:</p>
   <p>"To the Narodni Socialni Beseda J. V. Fric in Chicago.</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen: We hereby, sincerely and with thanks, acknowledge the receipt of your monetary gift amounting to one thousand Czechoslovakian kronen which sum was transmitted to us through the Bohemian Industrial Bank of Prague, February 1, 1921. The gift, which we have accepted as an evident proof of your favors and in accordance with our activity, is that much more valuable to us since it comes from our remote dear brothers who in that way manifest that even beyond the ocean our activity is followed. As a modest proof of <pb facs="5418478_5_1549.jpg" n="2"/>our gratitude, we will send to the Narodni Socialni Beseda J. V. Fric a diploma of charter membership in our Union.</p>
   <p>"Begging that you remember us by your favors in the future, we remain,</p>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"The central committee of the Narodni Jednota Posumavska."</p>
   <p>[Names of committee members are omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>The Narodni Socialni Beseda J. V. Fric intends to devote still greater interest to the program of our defense organizations, which already have done so much good among the minority groups in the Sudeten district of Bohemia, and for that purpose is arranging a humoristic soiree on April 30 of this year, at Sokol Karel Jonas. The entire proceeds of this affair will be earmarked for the work among our minority.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
