<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-20">Jan. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech-American Foresters</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-20">Jan. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH-AMERICAN FORESTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The third and last meeting of the rally of the Order of Czech-American Foresters began yesterday at 9 A. M. It was opened by Chief Forester Z. Chobotsky. Almost all the delegates were present.....Secretary V. Hajek read the minutes of the previous meeting. Letters of congratulation were read, among them one from the Sdruzeni Ceských Svobodomyslnych Skol (Association for the Maintenance of the Czech Free Thought Schools). It requested the Order to further patronize the Free Thought schools.</p>
   <p>The executive committee of the Sokol Community of America requested by letter the moral support and co-operation of the Order, especially in the realm of education, and particularly as far as the preservation and propagation of our mother tongue in America is concerned.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0267.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following resolution was passed:</p>
   <p>"To Woodrow Wilson, President of the United States of America. Washington, D. C. The seventh congress of the Czech-American Foresters, male and female members, held in Cicero, Illinois, from January 17 to January 19, 1918, has passed the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, This, our adopted country, has entered the war alongside of other democratic nations in order to preserve liberty, equality, and rights for which our ancestors fought, which they attained, and which are jeopardized by a militaristic and tyrannical nation; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The United States, in going into this war, is doing what it did in the past only for the sake of oppressed nations, among which the President of the United States has mentioned the Czechoslovak nation; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, we consider it to be our sacred duty to offer our services to these <pb facs="5418478_5_0268.jpg" n="3"/>United States in their noble fight for freedom and liberty; therefore be it</p>
   <p>"Resolved, That we pledge our loyalty and support in every respect to the President and Administration of the United States for the purpose of attaining that sublime aim.</p>
   <p>"For the Committee on resolutions,</p>
   <p>"Signed, R. Raisl, Fr. Blaha, and Fr. Blasek."</p>
   <p>The resolution was passed unanimously.</p>
   <p>The committe for the revision of the rites of the Order asked that the recommendations made be referred to the grand lodge. It was pointed out that the reading of all the proposed changes would take up much time, without giving the delegates enough opportunity to realize their significance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0269.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There ensued a lively discussion about the ritual employed at the initiation of new members. Some called the old procedure "antediluvian," demanding a modernized and "democratized" one. "Others, again, contended that the old-fashioned ceremonies attracted multitudes of curious people. The working out of a new ritual for these occasions would take up too much time. Brother Raisl declared outright that tomfoolery entertains, and if the people want it, they should have it."</p>
   <p>Another member, in countering, spoke of a case where a new member's leg was broken at one of those prankish affairs. There is much to be said against eccentricities. Numerous other members joined in the controversy, until it was resolved to leave the decision on rituals to the committee to be worked out with the next assembly of the grand lodge.</p>
   <p>Motions concerning routine business were heard.....Mr. V. Hajek, secretary, proposed an addition of four pages to the official organ of the Order. These are to be printed in the English language. It would promote the creation of <pb facs="5418478_5_0270.jpg" n="5"/>English-speaking clubs in the various lodges. On the motion of Brother wolf, the proposal was referred to the grand lodge, which is expected to solicit membership of young people who would be entrusted with the English part of the organization's correspondence.</p>
   <p>Brother Hudecek proposed that the reward for the acquisition of a new member be raised from one dollar to one dollar and fifty cents, at the same time suggesting that this payment be deferred six months until the qualification of a new member is established......</p>
   <p>Brother Adamec, representing the lodge Dvur Ceska Koruna (Bohemian Crown), demanded to know what attitude the Foresters intend to take in regard to the five-cent head tax per month for the Czech National Alliance. Brother Slauf answered that every Forester ought to pay five dollars per month for this purpose and do it by his own free will.....Brother Wolf advocated contributing to the Czech National Alliance; he would, however, like to see an accounting from that organization. Mr. J. Novak assured the Foresters that such an <pb facs="5418478_5_0271.jpg" n="6"/>accounting will be published after February 10, 1918, the date of the conference of district committees of the Alliance in the United States.</p>
   <p>Mr. Novak explained that as long as America was not in the war, no accounting could be published, for the obvious reason that this would have created the impression of a violation of neutrality. Today, however, with America in the war, the Czech National Alliance will not hesitate with the publication of its accounts, probably in newspapers. At that conference it will be stated how much was collected and how much was collected and how much expended.</p>
   <p>A majority of delegates declared that their lodges are willing to pay five cents per month as a national tax, under the condition that there be no coercion, and that everyone be governed by his own free will. The issue will be taken up by the committee on resolutions.</p>
   <p>The committee on auditing found all the books in perfect order. It was then <pb facs="5418478_5_0272.jpg" n="7"/>suggested that contact with some bank which would extend credit on money deposited by the Order be made. The bank should pay interest on any deposit over one thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Election of officers resulted as follows: Zikmund Chobotsky, Chief Forester; Jan V. Budilovsky, assistant; V. T. Hajek, secretary; Frank Mancl, treasurer. Messrs. Marek, Jiruska, Wolf, Martinek, and Mrs. Stepanek are members of the board of directors; Messrs. Chlupsa and Sindelar, guards; Mr. V. T. Hajek, editor of the organization's official organ.</p>
   <p>The election took place in the afternoon meeting, in which a contribution of twenty-five dollars for the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage was also voted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
