<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-22">June 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Old People's Home and Orphanage</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mr. Bunata the Manager of the Institution Was Forced to Tender His Resignation, Which Was Accepted</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1121</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1121.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-22">June 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND ORPHANAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mr. Bunata the Manager of the Institution Was Forced to Tender His Resignation, Which Was Accepted</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the delegates of the Old People's Home and Orphanage was held last night. In the absence of the chairman Mr. Frydl, the meeting was called to order by the vice-chairman Mr. Leopold Ruzicka. The minutes of the previous meeting were read and approved without correction. The semi-annual report and the report of the management committee were read and approved as read.</p>
   <p>Karel Havlicek Lodge No. 18. C. S. J. (Czech Slovanic Unity) announced as their delegate Mr. Joseph Machar; Mrs. Frantiska Hlavacek, appeared as the delegate for Lodge "Snezka."</p>
   <p>Thirty-five dollars was turned in as a legacy from the estate of Anna Salek.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1122.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The bond of the financial secretary Mr. Ferdinand Svoboda was accepted without protest.</p>
   <p>Several applications for admission to the Home and the Orphanage were referred to the investigation committee.</p>
   <p>Plans of the newly surveyed property of the Institution were introduced and the question was brought up as to whether or not it would be better to move the old building or erect a new building on the north side of the creek, that is, where Mr. Vlaciha's monument works are now located.</p>
   <p>The committee substantiated its view in this respect by the fact that the Institution's taxes would be less and also that the Institution would benefit financially, for Foster Avenue is to be put through and thereby the new tavern would be located at the corner of Fourtieth Avenue and Foster Avenue, while the buildings of the Institution would remain isolated <pb facs="5418478_5_1123.jpg" n="3"/>on the other bank of the creek. In this way the continuous reference to the tavern in the immediate vicinity of the Institution would be avoided, thereby making it much easier to establish contact with various welfare societies which would yield from $1,500 to $2,000 yearly for the benefit of the Institution. A committee of six members was appointed to take the matter under consideration and with the management decide whether the old building should be moved or a new building erected, and also whether the saloon license can be transferred to the new location.</p>
   <p>The complaint of the manager Mr. Bunata against the management committee and Mrs. Blafka created a painful impression. He complained that the committee was careless and as proof brought forward a certain bill on which he claimed eighteen dollars could have been saved. There is no doubt that Mr. Bunata was mistaken in this respect, for the bill was for kitchen necessities which the women of the committee look after and their <pb facs="5418478_5_1124.jpg" n="4"/>many years of sacrificing labor in behalf of the Institution is well known.</p>
   <p>The committee completely ignored the charges brought by Mr. Bunata and introduced some facts concerning the manager for consideration, asking the delegates to decide whether or not Mr. Bunata should remain in his position as manager. A lengthy debate ensued until Mr. Bunata, on the advice of several more moderate delegates and to avoid a public scandal, handed in his resignation which was unanimously accepted, whereupon the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
