<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-12">June 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Cornerstone of the Sokol Chicago Hall Addition Laid in a Festive Manner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0541</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0541.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-12">June 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE CORNERSTONE OF THE SOKOL CHICAGO HALL ADDITION LAID IN A FESTIVE MANNER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was a significant and grand celebration which was held yesterday afternoon in our Bohemian California. The cornerstone of the addition to the hall of one of the most active sokol Societies of America, Sokol Chicago, on Kedzie Avenue and Twenty-fourth Street, was laid. Sokol Chicago plays an important part in the social life and educational activities in Bohemian California. For that reason, it was not strange that on this significant occasion the entire Bohemian quarter was on its feet, that an enthusiastic holiday mood prevailed, that wherever a person looked, it was apparent that something significant was going on.</p>
   <p>The celebration began shortly after noon when the various sokol societies and delegates of other patriotic bodies began to assemble at Twenty-third and Spaulding Streets so as to take part in a parade. This was assembled <pb facs="5418478_5_0542.jpg" n="2"/>around two P. M., and proceeded to the Sokol Chicago Hall.</p>
   <p>The parade, which had a dignified appearance, moved along Twenty-fifth Street to Kedzie Avenue, and then to the building site. There it spread out before the Sokol Chicago building, to which two large wings are being added, and here the band played "Kde Domev<gap unit="char" extent="3" reason="illegible"/>uj? after which Mr. Roubal came forward and delivered an appropriate speech, calling attention to the significance of the occasion. The cornerstone of the present building of Sokol Chicago was laid in the year 1899. At that time Lohemian California was just in its iafaney. Sokol Chicago, upon its organsation, had only sixty-seven members, but it went to work energetically and perfermend a task, of which it can be groud. Erecting a splendid building, it brought a gigantic but upon itself. Even its friends doubtel that it gould be able to for the hall. Sokol Chicago paid off the debt within eight years, Which is the best proof of the zealousness with which it worked. After paying for the hall, its <pb facs="5418478_5_0543.jpg" n="3"/>development in no way shackened, it continued to expand further, until it became evident a few years ago that not even that spacious hall would suffice for the full expansion of its powerful wings. The enlargement of the hall was beginning to be thought of, and now, finally, steps have been taken toward its accomplishment. Plans were made, and if success is met with according to these [plans], Sokol Chicago Hall will become one of the largest Bohemian national halls not only in Chicago, but in all America.</p>
   <p>After the cornerstone had been placed at the corner of the north wing, the parade was reassembled and proceeded to the Pilsen Park, where the festive program was continued. Dr. Rudis-Jicinsky, editor of Sokol Americky, of Cedar Rapids, Iowa, addressed those present, calling attention to the fact that the cornerstone of one of the largest Sokol buildings in America had been laid. He then spoke of the many sided activities which Sokol Chicago developed, as in the spiritual field so in physical development, <pb facs="5418478_5_0544.jpg" n="4"/>dramatic art, and all knowledge, which tends toward the good and beautiful. He called attention to the great task which this society has taken upon itself, expressing the hope that the people will not forget it in its hard fight, but will support it, because Sokol Chicago is not working for its own good only, it is working for the good of the entire Bohemian public. The entire Bohemian public benefits from its activity. The speaker named all the sokol societies which participated in the celebration, and proclaimed, convincingly, that none of them would forsake Sokol Chicago, that none of them would withhold a helping hand in time of need.</p>
   <p>After a short intermission, various drills were performed under the direction of instructor Thomas Kocka. One hundred twenty-five girls performed calisthenics to the accompaniment of music. Then one hundred twentyfour boys performed calisthenics. Then followed thirty-two women sokols whose performance aroused general admiration. The program was concluded <pb facs="5418478_5_0545.jpg" n="5"/>by a company of twenty-four sokols, who performed exercises on parallel bars and buck under the direction of Commander, Sokol Rudolph Langer. Exercises which will be performed in the competition at Cedar Rapids, Iowa, on July 4 were demonstrated.</p>
   <p>The Croatian singing society, Zora, arrived, even though somewhat late, and sang several beautiful songs under the direction of its choirmaster, Mr. Coufal.</p>
   <p>The celebration came to an end with a dance in the pavilion, at which the younger generation, after all the hardships of the day, "kicked up its heels."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
