<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-13">Nov. 13, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0502</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0502.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-13">Nov. 13, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTY-FIFTH ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Podporujici Spolek Plzenskych Rezniku (Pilsen Butchers' Benevolent Society) has completed twenty-five years of its activity. It celebrated this jubilee last Saturday in a dignified celebration held in the Pilsen Sokol hall on Ashland Avenue. In spite of the fact that a heavy downpour and stormy weather threatened to spoil the celebration, our Czech butchers and their many friends were not frightened or kept away from the affair.</p>
   <p>After nine o'clock, the hall began to fill and soon was full of dancing couples. The hall was gayly decorated with luxurious flowers. The guests were welcomed at the entrance by the Misses Ciha and Horacek, who presented each lady with a beautiful rose, and the gentlemen with a carnation.</p>
   <p>After several dance numbers, Mr. Ludvik Jaros, the president, gave an <pb facs="5418478_5_0503.jpg" n="2"/>address of welcome to the gathering. He gave a brief sketch of the history and activities of the society. In his enthusiastic speech, he brought out that in the year 1886, when almost all people began to organize for the purpose of more easily procuring their needs, the betterment of conditions, and assuring a brighter future, several assiduous Czech butchers met together. They resolved to organize a society for the improvement of the butcher trade. The initiatory meeting was called for October 24, 1886. The meeting was called by Brother Cyril Fiala, and was attended by sixteen butchers, who approved of the organization of the Society. The society was organized under the name "Klub Plzenskych Rezniku." (Pilsen Butchers' Club). A committee was elected at this meeting. The society's headquarters were in the Cesko-Americke Svobodomyslne Skole (Bohemian-American Liberal School) on 18th Street. The new society soon gained great popularity, and its membership quickly rose to a large number. It accepted a constitution on December 19, and the present name was adopted at that time. A year and a quarter later, <pb facs="5418478_5_0504.jpg" n="3"/>the Society purchased a banner which its color sergeant of many years presents here.</p>
   <p>The society thus formed flourished satisfactorily and grew strong not only in membership, but financially as well, proof of which is that from the date of its organization up to the present time, there were nominated 345 candidates for membership; of these twenty-two were rejected. Sixty-three members were expelled from the Society. Thirty-two members died. Receipts from dues, entertainments, interest, and other income amounted to $28,687.83. Disbursements were : $11,204.03; sick benefits $4,207; death benefits $4,696; for charitable purposes $529.53; for the national and educational cause $416.50. Total $21,053.06. Today, after twenty-five years of existence, the Society has $7,634.77 and numbers 211 paying members and two honorary members.</p>
   <p>The president then introduced to the public the charter members of the society: Messrs. August Spicka, Emil Fiala, Cyril Fiala, Frank Smolik.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0505.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Frank Zahrobsky, Vaclav Jaros, Vaclav Klaus and Vojtech Prucha. He thanked these briefly and sincerely for their work on behalf of the society. Then, as a token of love and recognition, he gave each of them a gold monogram watch fob as a memento of the occasion...</p>
   <p>The program committee was composed of Messrs. Ludvik Jaros, Vaclav Salat, Vaclav Illich and Frank Ciha.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
