<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-03-29">Mar. 29, 1903</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Amendment Permitted. the Czechoslovak Knights and Ladies Unity Is Allowed to Accept as Members Persons Over Fifteen Years of Age.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0591</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0591.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-03-29">Mar. 29, 1903</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">AMENDMENT PERMITTED. THE CZECHOSLOVAK KNIGHTS AND LADIES UNITY IS ALLOWED TO ACCEPT AS MEMBERS PERSONS OVER FIFTEEN YEARS OF AGE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The State Superintendent of Insurance, in agreement with the States Attorney General, recognized as lawful and permitted the amendment of paragraph eight in the charter of the Czechoslovak Knights and Ladies Unity, according to which this benefit society now has the right to accept into its membership persons having reached the age of fifteen years. This is the first Bohemian benefit society to receive this right, and no doubt it will be welcomed by the entire Bohemian public, for it is the first death-blow against purpose less clubs, in which not only money is wasted by our youth but what is more important they degenerate both morally and physically. Now they can become members of the growing Unity of Czechoslovak Knights, where as was resolved in amended laws they can be insured for $250 for the insignificant sum of thirteen cents as assessments, and when they reach the age of eighteen years, they can increase their insurance to either $500 or $1000.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0592.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is no doubt that our Bohemian parents will insure their children's lives in the Bohemian society in preference to placing it with insurance companies of other nationalities. Not only is the cost of insurance in the Czechoslovak Unity smaller, monthly it amounts to twenty-six cents, but the principal sum $250 is larger, where as with most other insurance companies the sum is $175 at a cost of forty cents per month. These young members can form separate lodges or join those already existing.</p>
   <p>This change is of the greatest importance, because the children of Bohemian parents will become identified with Bohemian unity; and growing accustomed to it, will remain as members after they have matured; thereby replenishing it's ranks, which are being thinned by death and the grave. Then they will not give preference to foreign societies, from which they may be forced to resign in later years because of high assessments, if the organizations do not actually dissolve.</p>
   <p>The benefits which this change affords to the younger generation will surely receive the attention it deserves, and many, we hope will join in order to receive to benefits.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
