<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-24">Jan. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Aid for Vilem Koukola's Destitute Family</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-24">Jan. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AID FOR VILEM KOUKOLA'S DESTITUTE FAMILY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our Sunday issue we announced that the collection attempted by us in behalf of the unfortunate family of the Evanston gardener, Vilem Koukola....would terminate, and also we published the names of contributors, together with the amounts which reached us before noon on Saturday. But on Saturday afternoon and Sunday, more contributions came to us from outside the Chicago area, and it is therefore our duty to inform our reading public of this by publishing the names of the generous donors together with the amounts sent in by them. [There follows a long list of contributors and the amounts contributed.] The total was $107.50, and this was sent to Koukola this forenoon.....</p>
   <p>Koukola informs us by letter that the Pilsen Lodge No. 272 of the Independent Order Of Odd Fellows sent him a check for fifty dollars, and other contributions were sent directly to him by his personal friends. He sent letters of thanks to each one of them. He also informs us that he will be able to reopen <pb facs="5418478_5_1453.jpg" n="2"/>his hothouses in March and that he will raise radishes, turnips, lettuce, and cucumbers, since it is too late now to begin growing flowers. Also his former employer, Mr. R. J. Widler, of 6638 Ridge Avenue, Chicago, Illinois, asked Koukola to help him prune his roses for a few weeks. Koukola is now busily at work. He and his family again express their gratitude to all who have helped them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
