<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-25">Nov. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Tag Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-11-25">Nov. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A TAG DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Nemocnice (Bohemian-American Hospital) needs a considerable amount of money in order to build an addition to the house it has already purchased. However, in spite of the tireless and unselfish support which our countrymen have been giving to the plan of building a Bohemian-American hospital, the money so far collected is not sufficient to realize the plans of the board of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice--that is, to adapt the building to the needs of a hospital in order to start receiving patients. Therefore, the board has decided to try an idea which has proved to be successful many times--that of organizing a tag day. Thanksgiving Day was selected for this purpose, and Bohemian ladies, both matrons and girls, have been requested to offer their services in this charitable, humane enterprise. Some ladies have already complied with this request, and they received full instructions and suggestions in the meeting held in the offices of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) last night. A check-up has shown, however, that there <pb facs="5418478_5_0671.jpg" n="2"/>are by far not enough ladies to cover all of the most frequented corners in parts of Chicago inhabited by our countrymen. In fact, so far only thirty ladies have offered their services.</p>
   <p>The board of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice needs at least thirty more ladies, and the members are appealing to our public-spirited gentler sex to apply today or tomorrow at the offices of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost on Kedzie Avenue near 26th Street. There they will receive buttons which will be used as tags, containers for money which will bear the name of the "tagging" lady, and advice as to the location of each one's activity.</p>
   <p>Since yesterday's meeting of the board of representatives of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice was devoted to the tag day and to the transaction of business with the ladies who agreed to take part in it, the current affairs of the Nemocnice will be discussed in a special meeting to be held two weeks from yesterday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
