<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-19">Oct. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage</title><title level="a" type="sub">Minutes of the Last Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0915</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0915.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-19">Oct. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE BOHEMIAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND ORPHANAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Minutes of the Last Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Mr. Suchy, president of the board of delegates to the Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage). It began at the appointed hour and was well attended. Due to the absence of the regular secretary her place was taken by Mrs. R. Lorenz, who read the minutes of the previous meeting. The minutes were approved as read. Mr. Suchy pointed out an error, which had been missed both in the minutes and the press report of the meeting, pertaining to the resignation of Mr. Smith, former business manager of the Utulna. According to a report in the minutes Mr. Smith is supposed to have resigned because the renumeration was insufficient. This was incorrect because Mr. Smith resigned on account of the poor health of his wife, and he asked that a correction be made in the minutes accordingly. The president then introduced the new business manager, Mr. Jan Patak, announcing that he is subject only to <pb facs="5418478_5_0916.jpg" n="2"/>the authority of the board of directors. The delegates were requested to take cognizance of this fact and were instructed not to try to question his decisions as it would only tend to confuse matters. Mr. Patak has shown himself to be a competent and meticulous manager and, being accountable only to the board, will work for the good of the whole institution. The secretary read the correspondence which did not contain anything important. The board will send a letter to the Ceskoslovenska Hudebni Unie (Czechoslovak Musical Union) in reply to their letter which was written in the form of a complaint. The answer will stress the fact that the board recognizes that an error has been committed and that it is fully aware of the merits of the Union and its accomplishments in behalf of the Utulna; further, that no insult to the Union was intended.</p>
   <p>The treasurer, Mr. Petru, read a report on disbursements for the past month but, since the business manager did not have time to present his report, no total was given. The president reported that Mr. August Geringer made a gift of $200 to the Utulna and it was decided that a letter of thanks be sent to him <pb facs="5418478_5_0917.jpg" n="3"/>The president further reported that the Tag Day collections for this year were much smaller than those of last year, the amount for last year being $2,000, whereas this year only a little more than $900 was collected [Translator's note: The correct amount was $973.21]. It would be worth while to find out the reason for such a discrepancy so that it could be rectified in the future.</p>
   <p>It was pointed out that the playgrounds of the institution are not well located, and that it would therefore be desirable to change their location, building a lawn instead, and thus giving a more attractive appearance to the premises. The playgrounds ought to be located in the rear of the buildings. The house physician, Dr. Stulik, found the state of health of our children to be much better than at the time of his last examination; the dentist's report was similarly encouraging. The board of directors decided to keep the cows despite the fact that recommendations were made to obtain milk for our children from other sources, and that the latter method would prove to be more sanitary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0918.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our milk supply will be used for the manufacture of butter and cheese. The application of Mrs. Marie Chmelir for admission to the institution was rejected by the board; that of Mrs. Barbora Balej was favorably acted upon and the applicant will be admitted.</p>
   <p>According to Mr. Petru, the treasurer, Attorney Lewy Mayer, recently deceased, bequeathed $100,000 to charitable institutions without specifically naming any. Mr. Petru mailed a request to the executor of Attorney Mayer's estate asking that our institution be remembered; his letter was answered by the executor who said that the request of the Utulna will be given consideration when the will of Attorney Mayer is probated.</p>
   <p>A concert will be given for the benefit of the Utulna and the delegate, Mrs. Sedlacek, has suggested that Mr. De Rubini, whose real name is Evzen Plachy, be asked to perform some of his tricks on that occasion, thus making the concert more attractive. Mr. De Rubini will be requested to appear. The entertainment <pb facs="5418478_5_0919.jpg" n="5"/>committee reported that an excellent program has been arranged and that anyone staying away would regret not having attended.</p>
   <p>Milada Pechal, a five-year-old girl, has requested admission to the institution; her father died recently. The proper committee will investigate this case. Otilie Pechal, a three-year-old sister of Milada, also requested to be admitted. This application will be handled similarly.....Tomas Berdel, aged 10 years and living at 2551 South Troy Street, has also applied for admission. Another application was that of Frank Groessl, aged 82 years, residing at 3620 Southport Avenue. The applicant was born at Rousperk near Pilsen [Czechoslovakia] and speaks a broken Bohemian. He has seven children. This application was referred to the investigation committee. The parties who made application in behalf of the Pechal children are to call on Mr. Josef Oborny, at 1842 Fisk Street.</p>
   <p>An election was held to fill the office of recording secretary to replace Mrs. Krbec; one member of the board of directors was to be elected also to replace <pb facs="5418478_5_0920.jpg" n="6"/>the retired Mr. Trnka. Mr. Jan Lehman was nominated for the office of secretary, and when the nominations were closed, he was unanimously elected. The newly elected secretary was introduced by the president and took over his duties immediately. Mrs. Anna Kosandr was nominated as a new member of the board of directors. The nominations were closed and Mrs. Kosandr was unanimously elected. The new member of the board was....greeted by the president and she, too, took over her duties at once.</p>
   <p>At the last convention of the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Sisterhood) a banquet was given in honor of the delegates. At this banquet a collection was taken up for the benefit of the Utulna and realized the sum of $84.60. This amount was now presented to the treasurer by Mrs. Brychta, who accompanied the gift with a nice speech. Mr. F. J. Petru presented $18.50, collected in behalf of the Utulna during the convention of the Illinois aid societies meeting in Peoria, Illinois.....During an intermission in this meeting an apron was raffled off for the benefit of the institution. The raffle netted $7.30 and Mrs. Kosandr won the prize.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0921.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: A list of persons who took part in the Tag Day activity on October 16, 1922 is omitted in translation. There were forty persons who volunteered. After each name is listed the amount collected, the total being $973.21.]</p>
   <p>Thanks are due to all the Bohemian daily papers for their announcements made during the week preceding the Tag Day--the Denni Hlasatel and the Svornost. We are likewise grateful to the management of the Pilsen Sokol for the use of their hall on that occasion; we thank Mr. and Mrs. Zika for their work and patience, and finally we thank all the noble ladies for taking part in the Tag Day activity itself; without their help there would have been no returns.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
