<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-01-21">Jan 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Representatives of the Utulna a Sirotcinec Hold an Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-01-21">Jan 21, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">REPRESENTATIVES OF THE UTULNA A SIROTCINEC HOLD AN ANNUAL MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's meeting of the board of representatives of the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec was an annual meeting in which the election of officers of the institution took place. In most cases, the election was unanimous, since all the nominees were persons of vast experience and prestige in the organization.....Mr. Vojta Suchy was elected president;....Mrs. Katerina Gruenwald, Vice-president; ...Mr. Josef Trnka was re-elected secretary; and Mr. Ant. Zahrobsky, after some hesitation, again accepted the office of treasurer.</p>
   <p>Also elected were the members of the investigations committee,...the auditing committee,....and the nine members of the committee on propaganda, while the building committee, elected recently, will function with its present membership.....</p>
   <p>[There follow two columns of names of donors and the amounts they have given.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1072.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The list ends with:] Mr. Otto Horacek, jeweler, at 1834 Blue Island Avenue, ten dollars and an offer to donate the net profits of the performance by the Sokol Chicago of the drama, "Louis XI," on the condition that the ladies and gentlemen who are members of the committee on propaganda will agree to sell tickets for the performance. The offer was accepted.....</p>
   <p>Finally, a letter from the judge of the Juvenile Court, N. W. Pinckney, was read. The judge sent his thanks for the donation of an attractive embroidery which had been reserved for him at the reserved exhibition of handiwork at the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec.....</p>
   <p>All committees postponed the presentation of their reports until the next meeting because of the late hour.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
