<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-05">Sept. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Jednota Ceskych Dam Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">The First Session</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-05">Sept. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEDNOTA CESKYCH DAM CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">The First Session</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The delegates of 144 lodges of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies Unity) convened yesterday morning to open the first session of this powerful women's organization. Almost all the delegates were present at the opening of the convention. Proceedings of the first session were characterized by harmony and evident desire of all the delegates to see that the results bring the greatest benefit to the organization.</p>
   <p>Sister Bohumila Ludvik [sister is an appellation commonly used among members of this organization], chairman of the central committee, opened the convention and greeted the delegates, mentioning the importance of the work which is ahead of them. Then she briefly reported on the activities of the organization since its last convention and spoke of the progress which had been achieved in spite of all the unfavorable conditions. She also encouraged the delegates to harmonious and energetic work which will lead the organization to further success <pb facs="5418478_5_0143.jpg" n="2"/>and new achievement.</p>
   <p>The present officers of the central committee were appointed officers of this convention: Sister Bohumila Ludvik, chairman; Sister Anna Stolfa, secretary; Sister Alzbeta Lisy, financial secretary; Sister Marketa Stuchlik, treasurer; Sister Barbora Sinkule, sergeant at arms. Sister Karolina Rychlik was elected honorary chairman, and Sister Amalie Janis of St. Louis, Missouri, past chairman.</p>
   <p>Sisters Marie Stepanek, Bozena Stolfa, and Marie Ruzicka were appointed members of the committee on credentials. This committee reported soon afterward that all the credentials were found to be correct, and all the delegates were pronounced official delegates of their respective lodges.</p>
   <p>Sisters Anna Stolfa, secretary; Alzbeta Lisy, financial secretary; and Marketa Stuchlik, treasurer; then presented their detailed reports of activities of the organization since the previous convention. The reports showed the excellent financial standing of the organization and gave proof of its growth and progress.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0144.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The delegates heard with satisfaction the report of the present central committee which, during its whole term of office, worked with all its might to enable the Jednota Ceskych Dam to continue to grow and be one of our largest national and benevolent associations.</p>
   <p>Then members of various committees were appointed as follows: Members of the resolutions committee: Sisters Turecek, Petrzilka, Prosek, Zeman, Liska, Havranek, and Lala; members of the ways and means committee: Sisters Brejcha, Vohanka, Chleborad, Zikmund, and Rypka; members of the auditing committee: Sisters Vojtisek, Huspaska, and Viskovsky. [Translators note: There follows a long list of members of the committee on the constitution and bylaws.]</p>
   <p>Originally the intention of the delegates was to do only the most urgent work on the first day of the convention, and that was to organize the convention and to appoint various committees. But becuase Sunday was to be devoted to the golden jubilee celebration and Monday to the excursion, it was decided to hold an afternoon session and accomplish as much as possible. Therefore, the session continued in the afternoon; and when the delegates convene again next Tuesday, <pb facs="5418478_5_0145.jpg" n="4"/>it will be possible for them to proceed much faster. After yesterday's session ended, the delegates went to their homes and then met again in the evening at the Pilsen Park pavilion where a reception was held in their honor.</p>
   <p>A brilliant celebration of the fiftieth anniversary of the Jednota Ceskych Dam will be held at the Pilsen Park pavilion this afternoon. It is expected that not only members of the organization, but also a large number of our people who recognize the merits of this great organization will attend. For this celebration an interesting program has been prepared which will surprise every body. A new lodge bearing the name of the late chairman, Klara K. Klaus, will be initiated as a part of the many other numbers on the program. The celebration will start at 2 P.M., and after the program is finished, an informal entertainment and dance will take place. In view of the significance of the golden jubilee of our oldest and largest ladies' organization, and in view of the priceless, meritorious work which the organization has accomplished for the American branch of the Bohemian nation during the past fifty years of its existence, the golden jubilee should be a celebration of not only the Jednota Ceskych Dam, but of all Chicago Bohemians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
