<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-23">Nov. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For the Czechoslovak Legionnaires Cause</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-23">Nov. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE CZECHOSLOVAK LEGIONNAIRES CAUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the committee for Chicago and vicinity was held last Tuesday, November 21, 1922, in the offices of the Ceskoslovenska Narodni Rada (Czechoslovak National Council). Reports from the various districts were received as follows:</p>
   <p>The Pilsen district: The Slovak and the Bohemian Catholic workers were given their collection booklets. The freethinkers should show greater interest by joining this activity. It was recommended that the Sokol unions be appealed to. The next meeting will be held on Friday in the Cesko-Americka Sin (Bohemian-American Hall), and immediately following that meeting the volunteers will begin collecting funds in their own district which extends from Western Avenue east to the Chicago river and south to the Chicago, Burlington, and Quincy Railroad.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian California and Lawndale districts: Many of the collectors of funds received their collection booklets earlier, and one volunteer has it <pb facs="5418478_5_1245.jpg" n="2"/>filled already. It is Mrs. Anna Nedved who collected $74.85. The following officers were elected: Mr. V. Jedlicka, secretary; Mr. Jan Podmajersky, treasurer. Their office is in....the offices of the Narodni Rada, 3734 West 26th Street, and they will be on hand every evening from 7 to 8 P.M. All volunteers may obtain their booklets there. The next meeting of the district committee will be held on Friday, November 24, in the offices of the Narodni Rada.</p>
   <p>The Merigold district: The organizational committee is busy and hopes that on Friday, November 24, it will start collecting. On that day there will be a meeting of all volunteers of the district in the Sokol Tabor Slovenske Lipy. Time: 8 P.M.....</p>
   <p>The Cicero and Berwyn districts: The collections have already started. The next meeting of the district committee and of the volunteer workers will be held on Friday in the Sokol Karel Jonas.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1246.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Oak Park district: The volunteer workers of the Jednota Sokol Oak Park (Oak Park Sokol Union) who were previously active in nationalistic work promised their co-operation. But since they are at present busy with other public work, they will not call a meeting until Tuesday, December 5, 1922. The work of collecting the contributions will therefore be delayed, but the members will be better able to concentrate their energies on this work.</p>
   <p>The Town of Lake district: At the last meeting of the district committee Mr. Vladimir Peterek was elected secretary to replace the temporary secretary, Mrs. Vones. Mr. Peterek lives at 4627 South Hermitage Avenue. The booklets will be distributed at the meeting to be held on next Wednesday.</p>
   <p>The "Small South Side" district: This district has been subdivided into nine parts and collectors were appointed for each division. Collection booklets will be distributed at a meeting which is to be held next Thursday <pb facs="5418478_5_1247.jpg" n="4"/>in the school building located at West 30th Street and Lowe Avenue.</p>
   <p>The Jefferson Park and Irving Park districts: A committee was organized at a meeting held in the Sokol Krivan on November 20, 1922. The following officers were elected: chairman, Mrs. Alzbeta Sopoci, 4316 North Keeler Avenue; treasurer, Mrs. Emilie Kovac, 5493 Higgins Avenue; secretary, Mrs. Ernestina Kis, 4775 Milwaukee Avenue. In the next meeting the booklets will be distributed to the volunteers. That meeting will be held on Monday in the Sokol Krivan. There are several Slovak collectors ready to start work, but we need our countrymen living in the neighborhood of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery); they should show greater interest and understanding.</p>
   <p>The Pullman district: Messrs. Josef Matusek, 100 West 107th Street, Karel Stranovsky, 10512 South LaSalle Street, and Stefan Albert, 10657 South Wentworth Avenue, have taken charge of activities. A meeting will be called <pb facs="5418478_5_1248.jpg" n="5"/>on Friday, November 24, in Mr. Stancik's hall.</p>
   <p>The Gary, Hammond, and Whiting, Indiana districts: These districts were organized directly by the Narodni Vybor Invalidni Sbirky (national committee to collect a fund for invalids), located in Cleveland, Ohio. All checks should be made out to the Vybor Invalidni Sbirky. Mr. J. Kesner, Mr. Martin Huska ....and Mrs. C. Ruzek are the officers responsible for that body. A five-thousand-dollar bond must be made by the treasurer.</p>
   <p>It was reported in the meeting of the all-Chicago committee that the Bohemian daily, Denni Hlasatel, appointed a reporter to cover the activities of the committee, and write three publicity articles each week for the benefit of the fund; it is desirable that these articles be put in the most conspicuous place in that newspaper. Also $100 was received as a gift from the publishers of the Denni Hlasatel. We acknowledge with thanks the receipt of the aforesaid sum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
