<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-29">Jan. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For Vilem Koukola's Destitute Family</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1448</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1448.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-29">Jan. 29, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR VILEM KOUKOLA'S DESTITUTE FAMILY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A week ago today we announced that the collection in behalf of the sorely tried gardener, Vilem Koukola, who resides at 108 Ridge Avenue, Evanston, Illinois, was terminated. Despite our announcement, however, we expected that there would be more contributions reaching us from localities outside of Chicago. Just as we expected, these contributions did arrive, but together with them there were still others from Chicago, so that we shall not be able to publish the results of the collection until about one week from today.</p>
   <p>Koukola acknowledged the receipt of every check we mailed him, and yesterday morning he surprised us with a visit, bringing his whole family to thank us for what we were able to accomplish in his behalf. We told Koukola that we never expected any expressions of gratitude for ourselves. We emphasized the fact that whatever we have done has been on the basis of our human conscience acting as one fellowman toward another. Koukola, his wife, and his four <pb facs="5418478_5_1449.jpg" n="2"/>children are therefore indebted to all the generous folk who remembered them in their hour of need: He assured as that he will never forget the good will and kind hearts which guided the donors to offer gifts which were so unusually plentiful. [There follows another list of contributors.]</p>
   <p>The total amount which has reached us since the last report is sixty-six dollars, which we shall forward to Villom Koukola tomorrow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
