<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-27">Mar. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Growth in Membership of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1551</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1551.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-27">Mar. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">GROWTH IN MEMBERSHIP OF THE CESKA DOBROCINNA SPOLECNOST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The membership committee, whose purpose is to obtain ten thousand new members for the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost v Chicagu (Bohemian Charitable Association of Chicago), recently launched a lively campaign by mailing several thousand letters to our countrymen. In these letters, the committee appeals to the good will and philanthropy of our countrymen, and requests them to become members of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost. Why this action was undertaken is very well known to our readers by previous reports. The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost is surely an institution which works among us with quiet and reserve, but with great efficiency. The Association was not founded for the purpose of providing well-paid jobs for a number of people; it is not here to maintain luxuriously equipped offices which would serve as a meeting place for members; it does not uselessly spend a penny of the money collected as other similar institutions do, but honestly, conscientiously, and scrupulously is following the aim it has set before itself. The Association works to the <pb facs="5418478_5_1552.jpg" n="2"/>best of its ability only for the benefit of the Bohemian poor, and its members and officers do not expect any reward for themselves. As a result of the philanthropy shown by the Association during its existence, it drew the attention of other foreign language groups. It is these groups which point to our Association as an example for other similar institutions.....</p>
   <p>It is possible for us to announce with pleasure that many corporations and individuals have become new members of our institution. [List of corporations and individuals that became members of the Association and the amounts contributed by each are omitted in translation.] Contributions should be sent to the treasurer of the committee, Mr. Thomas Kallal, 3245 West 26th Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
