<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-09">Apr. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[The Bohemian-Siavonic Unity].</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-09">Apr. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[THE BOHEMIAN-SIAVONIC UNITY].</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Bohemian-Slavonic Unity) is one of the Bohemian fraternal benevolent societies which, with unusual interest, particpates in any action concerning our Bohemian schools and our public life. The Jednota is especially concerned in our young people and tries, by arranging informative lectures and noble entertainment, to influence them and preserve them for our fraternal benevolent societies. This year the Jednota launched a campaign for the purpose of securing new members, especially children for its juvenile department, for which a certain amount of money was appropriated. There are no charges for physical examination because these expenses are paid by the Grand Lodge.</p>
   <p>That the members are devoted to their Jednota is shown by the noticeable activity in every lodge. The proof of it was given last Sunday April 3, at Marquettee Hall, where the initiation of new members to the Loze Bila Ruze (White Rose Lodge) was held. Sister M. Blazek secured the applications for <pb facs="5418478_5_0078.jpg" n="2"/>membership of ten adults and twenty-one children. The news was joyfully received by the officers of the Grand Lodge who also participated in this affair. The president of the Grand Lodge, Dr. K. Neuman, initiated the officers of the Lodge and then spoke briefly to the members about the necessity of supporting their officers and facilitating their work.</p>
   <p>After the installation of the officers and the initiation of new members, most of whom were young people, Dr. Neuman spoke briefly about the campaign which was launched for the purpose of securing new members, and also mentioned the work which the Jednota attempts to accomplish. Dr. Antonin Mueller, in his usual inexhaustible humorous way, called the attention of the gathering to the fact that the meal is ready and waiting. This occasioned much laughter among those present and the entertainment which followed was hearty and natural.</p>
   <p>That the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota is progressing is shown by the work already accomplished and by the new work which it intends to do. The Jednota fulfilled its duties in every respect, particularly in the punctual payment of death claims.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0079.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The wonderful work of Sister M. Blazek, the present president of the Loze Bila Ruze and a member of the executive committee of the Grand Lodge, will have its reverberations in stimulating all members of the Jednota. This Jednota will be a proud example of work because it follows a promising road by including entire families among its members who are to strengthen the friendship not only among themselves, but in the whole Jednota and outside of it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
