<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-11">Aug. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0184</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0184.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 1 (Slovak)</item>
     <item>II B 3 (Slovak)</item>
     <item>I G (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-11">Aug. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Narodni Hlavni Rad, C. S. P. S. [Grand Lodge of the Ceskoslovanska Podporujici Spolecnost (Czecho-Slav Aid Society)] recommends a new schedule for dues which is sure to become the subject of serious discussions at the coming general meeting. It proposes that those who became members before the year 1900 be charged with dues according to the age they had reached on January 1, 1900. This would mean that the dues for old members would be raised, yet this measure is considered by experts as necessary. The conclusion was arrived at after examination of figures which showed that the amount paid in was not sufficient to take care of all cases of death, and, furthermore, that the dues paid did not conform with the tables set up as a standard by the Bratrsky Kongres (Brotherhood Congress). As a result of the former conditions, provisions for the security of the insurance have become imperative. Brother Lunak, secretary of the Society, has written a pertinent article about this change <pb facs="5418478_5_0185.jpg" n="2"/>of dues.....</p>
   <p>The question of the treatment which should be accorded to members who have enlisted in the United States Army or the Czechoslovak has not yet received conclusive consideration from our brotherhoods and other societies. The Slovak Sokols also are tackling the problem. The Slovensky Sokol (Slovak Sokol), their representative organ, speaks about it in the following editorial [printed in the Slovak language]:</p>
   <p>"Officers of our organizations are asking themselves what should be done about members enlisted in Uncle Sam's or the Czechoslovak army. The point is this: Who is to pay their dues? Or should they be dropped from the list of members? To strike out the name of a man who has done his duty as a United States citizen, or who has joined our revolutionary Czechoslovak Army, and so is unable to pay dues, would mean to act against any human feeling and to violate Slovak Sokols' principles.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0186.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"In correspondence received by us there are alternatives. Some want, first, that the volunteers be dropped from membership; second, that the dues in question be paid from the lodge treasury; third, that the volunteers' relatives be approached to pay the dues. Those relatives, however, decline to make 'such great sacrifice'.</p>
   <p>"We are not dictating to you what to do. Do not ask your societies what to do with the volunteers. Let your conscience and humane feeling be your guide. Relatives? Why, they are the first to claim death benefits, but for the living man they harbor no such thing as brotherly feelings.</p>
   <p>And further, to drop a brother Sokol from membership means to forget that he is the real Sokol, that he gives his life for Sokol ideals--that he left to fight for those very same relatives who refused to pay for him, and also for those Sokol brothers (?) who are ready to strike his name from membership.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0187.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"It is impossible to speak to such people of a Slovak's duty toward his nation, for they are utterly devoid of human feeling. Meanwhile, the volunteer is fighting in France, and drenches the soil with his blood; he dies, or returns a cripple. And you will be asking him who had sent him there. Shame! To raise a voice against the volunteer!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
