<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-04-28">Apr. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">New Bohemian Settlement Dedicated</title><title level="a" type="sub">Two Meetings Yield $2,500 in Contributions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-04-28">Apr. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">NEW BOHEMIAN SETTLEMENT DEDICATED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Two Meetings Yield $2,500 in Contributions</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two celebrations which were held yesterday afternoon and evening in the new Bohemian Settlement on Center Street were attended by a multitude of people who came to witness the dedication ceremonies and to inspect the interior arrangements of the building.</p>
   <p>The afternoon dedication ceremonies were conducted in the English language and presided over by Reverend John Timothy Stone, pastor of the Fourth Presbyterian Church to which the elite of Chicago society belong. The musical portion of the program consisted of two selections presented by the Bohemian Settlement Girls' Singing Society; one selection was sung in Bohemian, the other in English. In his speech Dr. Stone eulogized the Bohemians as a nation of intrepid fighters for religious freedom. In the field of music, he said, they cannot be surpassed by any nation in the whole world. He talked about his church community men's club which <pb facs="5418478_5_1186.jpg" n="2"/>consists of eight hundred members who arrange a number of evening entertainments every year with artistic programs, each featuring the music, dances, handicraft, and other accomplishments of one particular nation; and during the last two years the Bohemian night attracted a larger attendance than that of any other people.</p>
   <p>Dr. Shaw, pastor of the Second Presbyterian Church on Michigan Avenue, who described our Reverend V. Vanek as one of the great workers among the Bohemian people, was the second speaker on the afternoon program. The third speaker, Dr. Edgar P. Hill, in an elaborate speech expressed his pleasure on the successful conclusion of the work connected with the establishment of the beautiful new Settlement.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian dedication ceremonies took place in the evening. A most delightful musical program was given by the Bohemian House Mixed Quartet--Mr. Fiser, Miss El. Hoffman, Mrs. J. F. Smetanka and tenor Mr. Hurt, for whose lovely solo the Bohemian poet, Mr. A. Havranek, <pb facs="5418478_5_1187.jpg" n="3"/>composed the words. All three musical selections were rendered with delicate skill and artistic understanding.</p>
   <p>The formal dedicatory sermon, which by its profundity of thought made a great impression upon the audience, was delivered by Reverend Barta of Dubuque, Iowa. The meeting was also addressed by Reverend V. Backora, director of the Slavonic Settlement in Gary, Indiana; and Reverend Miloslav Filipi of Tyndall, South Dakota. The evening meeting was presided over by Reverend V. Vanek.</p>
   <p>The collection of contributions taken up both in the afternoon and evening meetings yielded about $2,500, so that the total debt on the building, which cost over $46,000, is not more than $7,000.</p>
   <p>Tonight Dr. Barta will speak on the topic, "Bohemians in America". Admission is free. The series of ceremonial events will come to a close tomorrow night with a meeting of the Bohemian Evangelical Congregations of Chicago, at which the pastors present will be the speakers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
