<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-07">Feb. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For the Starving Children of Russia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-07">Feb. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE STARVING CHILDREN OF RUSSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are very pleased with our people, and justly so, because the money gifts for the poor Russian children have been reaching our offices, and many of them have been cent anonymously. Our people seem to be glad to lend a helping hand to a Russian Slav child, and that is as it should be. Some people write in: "Please forward the collected amounts quickly so that they [the Russian children] need not wait too long." Oh, yes, be are quick about it, and in our next report we shall give an account of our first shipment of money, which has [already] been seat. The gifts we have received have come from all parts of the country settled by Bohemian-Americans; the gifts are accompanied by letters which are full of warmth and Slavonic feeling.</p>
   <p>Since our last notice the following gifts have reached us: [Translator's note: There follows a long list of names of contributors and the amounts contributed]. The previous total was $187.50; the new total is $281.25. This sum was collected during three short days. We can easily understand the suffering of the <pb facs="5418478_5_1437.jpg" n="2"/>innocent children of our Slavonic brothers. We do not forget that Slavic Russia, in her dealings with us, showed her fraternal attitude; and during the time we lived under the Austrian regime, we benefited by her undisguised Slavonic love. We did not realize then that a time would come when thousands of Russians would have to leave "Mother Russia." that other thousands would be dying daily in their own homeland under conditions--suffering, want, disease, hunger--too horrible to describe; and that thousands of their children would anxiously ask for food.</p>
   <p>Today we come to pay back with love for love given. Alas! We do it with feelings of sorrow and pain, under conditions which we should like to forget. We believe, however, that Russia, that great Slavonic Empire, will rise again and shake off its present shackles. Today, all one can do is to organize aids to save Russian children as much as possible.....Whoever can should help; whoever has a warm Slavonic heart, let him not hesitate to offer aid. This request is for the children of those who always loved us best among the Slavs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1438.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Send your contributions quickly.....Send them to the newspapers or directly to us: Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America), 3207 West 22nd Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
