<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-25">Mar. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech-American Union Growing</title><title level="a" type="sub">One Hundred New Members of Three Lodges are Inducted</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-25">Mar. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH-AMERICAN UNION GROWING</title><title level="a" type="sub">One Hundred New Members of Three Lodges are Inducted</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Celebrations such as the one held by the Cesko-Americka Jednota (Czech-American Union) last Saturday are rare, yet very important. The scene of activity was the Pilsen Brewery Park pavilion; the arrangements were made by the grand lodge of the Jednota, supported by all local subsidiary lodges. About one hundred women became members of the organization. They were grouped into three newly formed lodges which were formally inducted: The Gabriela Preis No. 19, Lodge Cicero No. 20, and Lodge American Red Cross No. 21.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Moravek, vice-president of the grand lodge, opened the meeting and introduced Mr. Jan Jelinek, editor of the Vestnik (Messenger), who spoke on the importance of child insurance, which was adopted by the organization recently. He said:</p>
   <p>"I take pleasure in presenting to you the youngest branch of the Czech-American <pb facs="5418478_5_0223.jpg" n="2"/>Union, the children's section; which was inducted a short time ago. It is often contended that the American branch of the Czech people is dying off, and that the time is not very distant when it will be dead. It is, therefore, our duty to insure the future of our Czech branch. Children are our own future. We must rear them properly so that they will proudly pledge allegiance to their Czech descent. It we do not fail in this duty, our future in America will be secure.</p>
   <p>"Our young people frequently join organizations of other nationalities and are thus lost to us. We must attract them to our groups, to our sterling Czech-American Union. At a time when our sons or fathers are fighting for the liberty of all nations, it is the responsibility of those who stay at home to fulfill their obligations not only toward America, but to our Czech people as well. And this can be done by giving our children an education in the true Czech national spirit. We must save our youth for ourselves. If the Czech-American Union is good enough for you adults, it is certainly good enough for your children. Bring your children, your hope, to our Union and do not permit <pb facs="5418478_5_0224.jpg" n="3"/>them to join some foreign, capitalistic establishment. I am certain that from our children's section, we shall later draw six hundred desirable members for the Czech-American Union, which has been making good progress. I am certain that it will advance still farther, just to show what Czechs in America can do, and that they are neither dying nor even sinking."</p>
   <p>Mr. Jelinek then turned to the children and addressed them as follows: "My dear children, do not forget that the nation from which you came is an outstanding one, for it has had a glorious history. You come from a nation of which you may justly be proud. From this nation there issued men who led the Czechs in the struggle for right and truth. Always proclaim joyfully that you came from this nation. Be mindful of the words of the poet: 'He who is ashamed of his parents deserves the scorn of all men'. Honor this emblem of the Czech-American Union in which the American and the Czech flags are harmoniously combined. I welcome you under our roof!"</p>
   <p>Dr. Antonin Mueller, chief physician of the Union, spoke primarily on the <pb facs="5418478_5_0225.jpg" n="4"/>significance of the names which the three newly inducted lodges adopted for their groups. "The members of the Union were among the first to answer the call of the Liberty bond campaign," the speaker stated. "The members of the ladies' lodge No. 19 did not commit any error in selecting the name 'Gabriela Preis,' one of our famous writers.....</p>
   <p>"The name 'Lodge Cicero No. 20' reminds us of the famous Roman orator. Those of us who studied Latin and Greek in the old country had to study his speeches, and if we did not, we flunked!"....Cicero, a Czech Chicago suburb, is a prosperous community which remains faithful to its Czech descent, as is demonstrated by the new lodge.</p>
   <p>"Members of the Lodge American Red Cross [sic.] will be glad, I am certain, to hear something about the history of the Red Cross....."</p>
   <p>Mr. W. Havelka, secretary of the grand lodge, read telegrams and various other communications; Mr. Joseph Kratochvil, president, presented the newly inducted <pb facs="5418478_5_0226.jpg" n="5"/>lodges with the charter. "He who wins the women wins the entire nation," he proclaimed.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wm. K. Pflaum addressed the gathering in regard to the sale of war-savings stamps. He spoke in English.</p>
   <p>The Czech-American Union is to be congratulated upon its rapid growth. May it continue to prosper and help preserve our Czech branch in America!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
