<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-10">Feb. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0247</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0247.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-10">Feb. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What can be accomplished in the acquisition of new members by vigorous agitation was demonstrated on the occasion of the awarding of prizes in the Cesko-Americka Jednota (Czech-American Union). The contest yielded 560 new members for this organization, a figure of which the Union may surely feel proud. Each lodge showed some increase; a few lodges had truly remarkable success. Lodge Cesky Lev (Czech Lion) gained 47; Vltava (the Vltava river), 40; California, 28; Nova Vlast (The New Homeland), 26. This was the work of a few zealous individuals. Besides these, there are many others who deserve recognition.</p>
   <p>Mr. August Kopta, a member of the lodge Cesky Lev, won the first prize, $50, for having introduced 43 members. The second prize, $40, went to Jos. Kalivoda of lodge California; the third of $30 to Karel Nudera of lodge Nova Vlast, etc.</p>
   <p>The membership campaign cost very little and produced excellent results, which proves that Chicago is still fertile soil for active solicitation of members <pb facs="5418478_5_0248.jpg" n="2"/>for our aid societies, especially in view of the enthusiasm displayed, as in the case of the Czech-American Union.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Slovanska Podporující Spolscnost (Czecho-Slavonic Aid Society) has given 362 of its members to the American Army and Navy. The records are by no means complete. Many members who were called for service have not informed their lodges of this fact, so that it may be expected, judging by the present rate, that the number given above will soon be doubled.</p>
   <p>Jednota Taboritu (Union of Taborites) has also introduced the head tax, which will serve to build up a fund from which compensation will be paid for casualties among members now enlisted in the United States Army or Navy. The tax will be collected at the rate of three cents per month on each one-hundred-dollar policy.</p>
   <p>We reported previously that the main unit of the Czecho-Slavonic Aid Society introduced the head tax for a similar purpose; it is expected that other units <pb facs="5418478_5_0249.jpg" n="3"/>will soon follow this example. Under the existing conditions, it is advisable that aid societies prepare for emergencies created by the war.</p>
   <p>We published the tragic story of a young fellow countryman who was killed in an accident recently. Although married, he did not belong to any aid society which would have insured his survivors against want. There are other young men who should join the ranks of our fraternal societies: With immigration on the decline, our adolescents are the only source from which we may hope to draw new members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
