<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-19">Jan. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech-American Foresters</title><title level="a" type="sub">Second Day of Meeting (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-19">Jan. 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH-AMERICAN FORESTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Second Day of Meeting (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Almost all the delegates were present when the second day of the meeting of the Order of Czech-American Foresters was opened yesterday at 9 A. M. Brother Chobotsky, Chief Forester, announced that Mr. Kubec, a member of the Sokol and president of the local district of the Czech National Alliance in America, was present.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kubec was asked by Mrs. Stepanek to take the floor. He expressed the thanks of the Alliance for all that has been done for it by the Foresters, and depicted the sufferings of the Czech people in the old country in these times of war. From them, he declared, sprang the movement for the liberation of the old homeland and its establishment as an independent state. He does not believe that Czechs here or anywhere else could be daunted by the utterances <pb facs="5418478_5_0278.jpg" n="2"/>of Lloyd George and President Wilson concerning the preservation of Austria-Hungary. He is, on the contrary, of the opinion that the Czech-American people will continue in the movement for liberation and will double their efforts toward that end. They know what would be lost if they failed in this endeavor. For this reason, Mr. Kubec admonished his audience, it is necessary that the delegates and members of the Order begin to work immediately after their return, that they expend great energy and develop an intense interest for the activities of the Czech National Alliance. They should not be concerned with the persons who are the directing minds of the Alliance. They should, instead, become imbued with the spirit which guides the Alliance.</p>
   <p>According to Mr. Kubec, a peace conference--its time is not very remote--is unthinkable without a solution of the Czechoslovak problem.</p>
   <p>After the applause following the address had subsided, Chief Forester <pb facs="5418478_5_0279.jpg" n="3"/>Chobotsky assured Mr. Kubec that the Order of the Foresters will pay due attention to the movement for liberation.</p>
   <p>Brother Hajek read the minutes of the previous meeting.....Letters of felicitation were read.....It was voted that a letter of condolence be sent to Brother Bobisud, whose wife had died.</p>
   <p>The committee on resolutions recommended that in death cases the survivors should be urged to buy a union-made coffin, for it is much cheaper than one from the casketmakers' trust.</p>
   <p>The behavior of certain undertakers was criticized, which prompted Mrs. Stepanek to express regrets over the discussion "which deals with the dead, instead of the living". The motion recommending union-made caskets was passed.</p>
   <p>It was further resolved to postpone the question of insurance for children.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0280.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>....The schedule of dues and other payments will remain unchanged.....The statutes of the Order were read, and occasional corrections were made.</p>
   <p>Several complaints against certain physicians were expressed when the bylaw concerning their duties was discussed. The committee on statutes was requested to work out a passage which would bestow authority upon the grand lodge to discharge physicians who fail in the performance of their duties.....Suspended members, delinquent in payments of their dues, may be reinstated if payments are made later.....</p>
   <p>After adjournment the meeting was continued until the afternoon. Several letters were read in which gratitude was expressed for the work done by the Foresters; they came from the grand lodge of the Czech-American Union, Sokol Karel Jonas, and the Bohemian Orphanage and Old People's Home. In a letter of acknowledgment sent to the latter, the Order complained about an aged members of the Order who was abandoned by his children but was refused <pb facs="5418478_5_0281.jpg" n="5"/>admittance to the Old People's Home. A reconsideration of his case was requested.</p>
   <p>The committee on resolutions recommended the introduction of instructive and interesting lectures in the meetings of the various lodges, since such entertainment attracts many members. The lectures will not interfere with routine business, which is better suited to those who do not like to strain their brains too much. Concerning this point, Brother Raisl pointed out that the benevolent and aid societies are not merely business organizations, but are brotherhoods which have certain obligations to the members. He advocated the opening of instructive lectures, and his proposal was accepted unanimously.</p>
   <p>The meeting will be continued on January 20.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
