<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-02">Nov. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Czechoslovak Orphanage in the Old Homeland Appeals to the Czechoslovaks of Chicago for Help</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-02">Nov. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A CZECHOSLOVAK ORPHANAGE IN THE OLD HOMELAND APPEALS TO THE CZECHOSLOVAKS OF CHICAGO FOR HELP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Reverend Vaclav Vanek of Chicago recently received a touching letter from the Ceskoslovenska Spolecnost Pro Dobrocinnost Krestanskou v Cechach (Czechoslovak Association for Christian Charity in Bohemia). The Association, the seat of which is in Prague, wrote the letter in behalf of the boys orphanage in Teleci, near Policka, and the girls orphanage of Krabcice, near the Rip mountain. We publish an excerpt from that letter as follows:</p>
   <p>"The manager of our orphanage in Teleci, Brother Ondryas, informed us that you visited our orphanage in the company of Reverend Krenek and the university professor, Dr. Smetanka. The manager states that you inspected the orphanage and assured yourself of the need of supporting that institution.</p>
   <p>"The autumn season has just begun and with it the increased cost of running <pb facs="5418478_5_1290.jpg" n="2"/>an orphanage. The contributions which could meet that cost are, however, in spite of our great efforts, not in evidence. We just purchased two carloads of coal for the use of both of our orphanages; this item requires the outlay of about 4,500 Czechoslovak crowns, an amount which we still owe. The boys need shoes, clothes, and stockings for the winter; these will cost about 6,000 crowns. In addition we must install bathtubs in both orphanages and make certain small building repairs at the Krabcice orphanage. Due to an increase in applications for admission to the institutions we ordered ten new children's beds costing about 8,000 Czechoslovak crowns, and as yet we do not have that amount on hand. Of the 32,000 crowns needed for thorough repairs of the Krabcice orphanage, we still owe 20,000, and must pay interest on that amount. The manageress of the Krabcice institution just reported that due to the recent windstorm the newly repaired tiled roof was again badly damaged and many of the tiles broken. The roof repair of that building is therefore absolutely necessary.</p>
   <p>We are often greatly worried about our future, but as for me, I put my trust <pb facs="5418478_5_1291.jpg" n="3"/>in Him who is the Father of all orphans. During the years 1919 to 1921 America helped us a great deal, but this year the contributions decreased while our needs increased. And daily letters are reaching us with applications for the admission of children and furnishing creditable proofs that the conditions of these children are almost too horrible to relate. Due to our limited means we must reject these applications, thus dooming these children both temporally and eternally. If we were to send you the case histories of our children, the descriptions of conditions in which they lived before they were admitted to our institutions, you would be amazed at the possibility of such [misery]. We beg of you, dear brother, to help us for Christ's love...."</p>
   <p>Reverend Vanek asked the Denni Hlasatel to publish the above, and now addresses all kind-hearted people and all the Czech readers of the Denni Hlasatel who are acquainted with the two aforesaid Bohemian brethren institutions, to contribute their bit for their support. After receiving <pb facs="5418478_5_1292.jpg" n="4"/>the letter, Reverend Vanek collected about 1,000 Czechoslovak crowns ($35) for this cause. The collection was made last Sunday in his own church where he gave a lecture about Czechoslovakia. He would like to collect at least 5,000 crowns for each one of the above-named orphanages, and send the money in the name of our Bohemian-American countrymen so that it could reach its destination on Thanksgiving Day. Whoever is able should send his contribution to Reverend V. Vanek, 2324 South Central Park Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. The names of contributors and the amounts of their contributions shall be published....in the Denni Hlasatel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
