<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-11">Sept. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Ninth Convention of the Jednota Ceskych Dam</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0117</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0117.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-11">Sept. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">NINTH CONVENTION OF THE JEDNOTA CESKYCH DAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The delegates to the ninth convention of the Jednota Ceských Dam (Bohemian Ladies' Unity) gave up half a day of their regular work and spent a few hours visiting the Bohemian National Cemetery and the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage. Ever since the very beginning of these important charitable institutions, the Jednota Ceských Dam has been their greatest supporter and benefactor. By its generous and never-ceasing donations, the Jednota has helped to build, maintain, and secure the existence and future of these institutions. Therefore, yesterday's visit to the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage was of great significance, and it is necessary to mention that even on this occasion, the generosity of our ladies was again manifested. The ladies were cordially welcomed by the management, and the inmates and delegates from other cities were pleasantly surprised by the growth and development of these institutions. While at the <pb facs="5418478_5_0118.jpg" n="2"/>Bohemian National Cemetery, the delegates visited and placed a wreath upon the grave of their late chairman, Sister Klara M. Klaus.</p>
   <p>Then the ladies were entertained at the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage, and the excursion, as a whole was pleasant in every respect.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's session was called to order by Sister Bohumila Ludvik at 9 A. M. with all the delegates present.</p>
   <p>The secretary, Sister Anna Stolfa, read the congratulatory communications.</p>
   <p>Then the minutes of the preceding session were read and approved after a few minor changes.</p>
   <p>Then the articles referring to the duties of the central committe were debated. All of these articles were accepted almost without any change. The article referring to the duties of the treasurer was amended and reads that <pb facs="5418478_5_0119.jpg" n="3"/>it is her duty to deposit the funds at places designated by the central committee.</p>
   <p>Surety for the secretary of the central committee was stipulated at $500, financial secretary at $1,000, and surety for the treasurer at $7,000, which is $2,000 more than the present stipulation. This increase had been recommended by the present treasurer. Surety for the first member of the board of trustees was set at $500; for the second member at $200.</p>
   <p>Compensation for the officers of the central committee was stipulated as follows: the chairman, $150; vice-chairman, $50; secretary, $500; financial secretary, $650; treasurer, $75. To members of various committees, an increase of five dollars was allowed.</p>
   <p>Further, the articles referring to the state grand committee's duties were discussed.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, Dr. Jaroslav E. Vojan and Mr. V. Cada appeared at the <pb facs="5418478_5_0120.jpg" n="4"/>session as representatives of the Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers, in order to address the delegates. Both gentlemen congratulated the ladies at the convention and expressed their gratitude for all that has been done by the Jednota Ceských Dam for the benefit of the Free Thought movement. They also mentioned the National Tax of Freethinkers, which will be collected next month, and expressed the hope that the Bohemian women will also perform their duties. Doubtless, this matter will be discussed by the resolution committee.</p>
   <p>The session adjourned at noon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
