<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-15">Oct. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Tag Day for the Benefit of the Orphans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-15">Oct. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">TAG DAY FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE ORPHANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual tag day for the benefit of the various Chicago orphanages will take place tomorrow. Among the orphanages which will profit by it is our Bohemian orphanage which is a part of the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage), located near the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery). It is desirable that the tag day be as profitable as possible for our own Czech orphans. This public collection is made only once a year, in fact, it is one of the tag days which is universally sanctioned even in these hard times when we hear so many protests against other collections which are made for various causes.</p>
   <p>Many hundreds of matrons and girls will endeavor to make the results of the collection as plenteous as possible, and the committee in charge hopes to be able to obtain the sum of $100,000 by this means.</p>
   <p>Previous collections have been divided among no more than thirty institutions <pb facs="5418478_5_1302.jpg" n="2"/>for which the tag day was organized. This system does not prevail any more. According to decisions reached by the collective board, each institution has its own taggers who endeavor to collect as much as possible for their own institutions. The tag day for the Czech orphans will therefore be planned only in the Czechoslovak neighborhoods of Chicago and its environs, and the total thus reached will accrue to our own Sirotcinec.</p>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon there was a meeting of our ladies who will take part in this charitable occupation. The meeting was held in the Pilsen Sokol Hall. There was a large number of ladies who were willing to do the work, and the most advantageous spots in our Czech neighborhoods have already been assigned. The committee of the Utulna A Sirotcinec hopes that our own public will respond most generously to the appeal made, but every contribution, no matter how small, will be most welcome. Let no one forget our orphans. Since the tag day occurs only once a year there should be nobody who would refuse to contribute to this charity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
