<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-26">Jan. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Significant Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">Forty-fifth Anniversary of Palacky Lodge</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0044</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0044.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-26">Jan. 26, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">SIGNIFICANT CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Forty-fifth Anniversary of Palacky Lodge</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At approximately three o'clock yesterday afternoon, a large crowd of people assembled in front of the Pilsen Sokol Hall on Ashland Avenue and 18th Street. Curious passers-by soon learned that this large assemblage consisted of delegates from various lodges who had arrived in Chicago from [various parts] of the country to help celebrate the forty-fifth anniversary of the founding of the oldest Bohemian lodge in Chicago affiliated with the Independent Order of Odd Fellows.....In this celebration the Vlast Rebekah Loze Cislo 165 (Homeland Rebekah Lodge No. 165) of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows participated.....The Palacky Lodge No. 630 of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows is really an old organization, and there are only two charter members who are alive today. They are Brothers Frantisek Fucik and Eduard Holy, whose presence at this celebration will evoke much interest among the members. The Palacky Lodge is not only the oldest Bohemian lodge of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows in Chicago, but it is also the oldest Bohemian lodge in America. Its present <pb facs="5418478_5_0045.jpg" n="2"/>officers are Messrs. Albert Tejcek, Frantisek Hejhal, Frantisek A. Slepicka, John Kostka, and Antonin J. Zahrobsky. The officers of the sister organization--the Vlast Rebekah Loze Cislo 165 Independent order of Odd Fellows--are the following ladies: Mmes. Ella Slepicka, Terezie Sindelar, Bohumila Krejci, Marie Dobes, and Barbora Sedlacek. The director of physical education is Mrs. Josefina Sikel. According to our information, the Palacky Lodge is also the strongest of all Bohemian lodges, for it boasts of a membership of one thousand.</p>
   <p>Last night was ladies' night at the Pilsen Sokol hall. We must say that it was very successful. This evening the members of the Vlast Rebekah will entertain the visitors from Cedar Rapids, Iowa, in the same hall, while the new members of the Palacky Lodge will be initiated into the Order by the brothers of the Cedar Rapids lodge in the hall of the Auditorium on Ashland Avenue and Van Buren Street. All in all, there will be about 135 new initiates. Tomorrow will be devoted to a joint banquet which will also be held in the Auditorium. It is expected that there will be about two thousand members who will attend <pb facs="5418478_5_0046.jpg" n="3"/>the banquet. The purpose of the banquet will also be to celebrate a new goal--one thousand members in the Palacky Lodge.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
