<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-11">Sept. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Resolution of the Illinois Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0114</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0114.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-11">Sept. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A RESOLUTION OF THE ILLINOIS GRAND LODGE OF THE CESKO-SLOVANSKE PODPORUJICI SPOLKY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The office of the unification committee of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) recently sent out a call to officers of the Bohemian Free Thought benevolent lodges urging them to send their membership applications to a new body which would take over the obligations of those organizations which are willing to unite. The Illinois grand lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky earnestly warns all the officers of our subordinate lodges not to participate in this movement for the following reasons:</p>
   <p>The matter of unification is of such importance that it will be necessary to place it before all our members for a decision. No individual lodge or grand lodge has the right to decide upon this matter but must submit itself to a decision of the whole organization. The officers of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky will not allow their names and positions to be used to <pb facs="5418478_5_0115.jpg" n="2"/>the detriment of the organization or in a way not consonant with its point of view.</p>
   <p>The Illinois grand lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky is not against the unification. On the contrary, each action and attitude of the Illinois grand lodge has always been in favor of this cause. As a representative body of the Illinois lodges, it must insist that each step leading toward the accomplishment of this cause must be undertaken within the constitution of our societies and in harmony with the decisions of the whole organization. Every organization must be guided by its regulations; otherwise decadence and disorder will follow. Even if the decisions of the superior bodies or the whole organization were unfavorable to us, we must submit ourselves to the will of the majority as a representative democratic body. Therefore, even in this matter, we must wait for a decision from the national grand lodge or a membership vote or eventually a convention, and up to that time we must refrain from any decisive steps.</p>
   <p>We call the attention of the officers of our lodges to the fact that by <pb facs="5418478_5_0116.jpg" n="3"/>joining a new organization, they work against the organization which they promised to support. We do not doubt that only a few such members could be found in our ranks. We firmly believe that every officer of our organization is an enlightened and conscientious man and will not harm his own organization. Let us work for our principles within our ranks.</p>
   <p>The office of the unification committee, and eventually the unification committee itself, went beyond its authority in the organization of a new body, because as far as we know, the lodges and societies who sent their representatives to the unification committee did not authorize in any way the said committee to organize a new body, but to work upon the unification only.</p>
   <p>For the Illinois Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky: Otto Pergler, president, V. K. Soukup, secretary.</p>
   <p>Members of the resolution committee: Jan Pecha, Jos. A. Smejkal, Joseph Jurka.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
