<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-22">Oct. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of the Board of the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1076</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1076.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-22">Oct. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF THE BOARD OF THE CESKA UTULNA A SIROTCINEC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A regular meeting of the board of representatives of the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) was held in the hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podpoujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) on 18th Street last night.....</p>
   <p>As was reported, it was agreed at the last meeting by a vote of fifty-three to two to build a new building for the orphanage. The building committee has now received the approved plans and in the next meeting will have available a preliminary budget of expenses. The work will start immediately.....</p>
   <p>Mrs. Rose Novak, the treasurer of the Ustredni Vybor Jednoty Ceskych Dam (Central Committee of the Bohemian Women's Unity), advised the board by letter that a check for $200 for the Utulna a Sirotcinec was being mailed to the secretary. This sum was appropriated for this purpose at the recent convention of the Jednota Ceskych Dam held in St. Louis.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1077.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The chairman asked the assembled ladies whether they had obtained any poultry for the institution. The ladies presented him with a list of names of the prospective donors. These individuals will be called upon and the poultry receipted. Mr. Janda reported that the Chicago Butchers Association promised to supply any poultry that might be needed after the poultry already promised is delivered to the institution.....</p>
   <p>The building committee will issue booklets for signatures of those who will donate building material and other equipment for the new building.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
