<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-03-23">Mar. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration of the Sixtieth Anniversary of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky v Americe</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-03-23">Mar. 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATION OF THE SIXTIETH ANNIVERSARY OF THE CESKO-SLOVANSKE PODPORUJICI SPOLKY v AMERICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday was a significant day in the annals of our oldest and most flourishing associations in the United States. Thousands of our brothers and sisters celebrated the sixtieth year of beneficent work of their Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies). In two of our largest auditoriums, true expressions of enthusiasm were exhibited for the mighty organization which has been doing valuable work in the field of philanthropy and national progress for sixty years. Bohemian Chicago, in which more of our members (over one third) reside than in any other city in America, commemorated in a dignified manner the founding of our organization, the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky.</p>
   <p>It was one of the most outstanding events ever celebrated among us, and the supreme council and the grand lodge of Illinois who had arranged this celebration, deserve the commendation and thanks of all our members for their work <pb facs="5418478_5_0425.jpg" n="2"/>in this dignified historical commemoration.</p>
   <p>The celebration was divided in two parts. In the afternoon a large artistic musical program in the Sokol Chicago hall was presented, and in the evening a theatrical performance in the old building of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky on 18th Street was given.</p>
   <p>The afternoon celebration in the hall of Sokol Chicago was a great manifestation of enthusiastic comradeship. This sentiment was also expressed in the colorful program of artistic entertainment, all the numbers of which were performed successfully and with exemplary precision. The attendance was large, because hundreds of our good brothers and sisters made it a point to add to the prestige of this most significant day by their presence. We must, however, admit that the attendance should have been still greater, that the hall should have been really filled. In addition to many local brothers and sisters, the celebration was attended by a delegation from Coal City, consisting of members of Lodge Hornik No. 128 of the Cesko-Slovansky Podporujici Spolek. The guests were cordially welcomed, not only by the organizers of the <pb facs="5418478_5_0426.jpg" n="3"/>celebration and the officers of the grand lodge, but also by everyone present with whom they came in contact during the day.....</p>
   <p>The afternoon program started with the beautiful overture to the opera "Vlasta," by Napravnik, which was skilfully rendered by the excellent orchestra conducted by Mr. Rudolph Rubringer, and was the first to be rewarded by thunderous applause. Mr. Jan Pecha, chairman of the grand lodge, appeared on the podium and heartily greeted everyone present. He spoke with deep feeling of the first difficult struggles of the lodges of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky and their final great success, documented by the fact that there are now more than 25,000 wide-awake members. He referred to the great accomplishments in charitable work which the organization in its sixty years of existence has achieved, in addition to the splendid results of its national endeavors. He urged the members to remain alert, and his sincere words were received with due appreciation by the large gathering. The rest of the program consisted of a number of vocal and instrumental selections presented by accomplished Bohemian artists, an address in English by Dr. Emerson Roberts, and a speech in Bohemian by Dr. Frank Iska.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0427.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>So many letters and telegrams of congratulations were received that President Pecha had to limit himself to the reading of the names of lodges which sent them. Mr. E. St. Vraz sent the following message from Prague:</p>
   <p>"If we congratulate a man or a woman who is a worthy member of our nation on his or her sixtieth birthday, we do this with two distinctly different feelings. Realizing the merits of the honored one, we show our pleasure and recognition of all that he has accomplished for the common good, and we are glad that he is still among us. But this joy is dimmed by the fear that the merciless laws of nature will grant him little more time to stay with us.</p>
   <p>"In these days all of progressive Bohemian-America is celebrating the sixtieth anniversary of the birth of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky, and its joy is not marred by any bitterness. We fervently hope that this mighty tree will spread its branches still further and let new fruit ripen in the shade of its wide-spreading crown, and that it will protect many a new generation of Bohemian-Americans--children of wide-awake Freethinkers, proudly professing their adherence to the Bohemian-Slavonic nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0428.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"This organization of Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky has no wrinkles in its face; it is not frail in body; it stands here strong, solid, and healthy, full of manly vigor and with promise of future activity!</p>
   <p>"May the children of our children be fortunate enough to celebrate the one-hundredth anniversary of this, our most worthy national organization. May brotherly love continue to bind them together, inspire them to all that is good; may it teach them to feel both as Americans and Bohemians; may it continue to bind them for the pride of our nation, for our prestige, and for the welfare of the country far overseas which has become our new home from which the transplanted branch of our nation, facing an uncertain future, may receive encouragement in times of need.</p>
   <p>"To this sincere expression of my gratitude and good wishes for continued success, I am prompted not only as a representative of the all-inclusive Narodni Rada Ceska v Praze (Bohemian National Council in Prague) and the Ustredni Matice Skolska v Praze (National Scholastic Association in Prague), but also by my personal devotion.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0429.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"With a deep feeling of thankfulness, I am taking this beautiful occasion to recall all those never-to-be-forgotten days among the Bohemians during my travels in America, and my enjoyment of the sociable time spent in the hospitable quarters of our national organizations, in the friendly, truly fraternal circle of members of the lodges of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky.</p>
   <p>"It was there that I watched with pleasure the well-informed, industrious people, the flower of American immigration; where, as in other Western lodges or among the Sokols, my heart warmed with pleasure over our Bohemian-Slavonic people. The hope strengthened within me that our Bohemian national feeling even here in America will never die! Many thanks to the Cesko-Slovansky Podporujici Spolek for all the good that it has disseminated, and success to your future activity!</p>
   <p>"In sincere friendship, E. St. Vraz."</p>
   <p>The evening program consisted of a theatrical performance of the comedy "Free <pb facs="5418478_5_0430.jpg" n="7"/>Masons," at the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky hall on 18th Street. The play was directed by Mr. Joseph Jurka, and the audience was kept in a constant uproar of laughter all evening. The play was certainly a success, and the attendance was enormous.</p>
   <p>Thus ended the commemoration of the anniversary of Cesko-Slovansky Podporujici Spolky. The success of the event is due to the work of the following members of the grand lodge of Illinois: Jan Pecha, J. A. Smejkal, B. V. Sedlacek, Frank Boucek, Rudolph Janda, Emanue Frydl, Joseph Kriz, Karel Brabec, Jakub Janda, and Karel Pergler.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
