<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-02">Sept. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Rally of the Czechoslovak Union</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-02">Sept. 2, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RALLY OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK UNION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first session of the sixth rally of the Czechoslovak Union was held in the Vojta Naprstek Czech language school, South Homan Avenue, yesterday forenoon. This is a holiday rally, for it celebrates the twenty-fifth year of existence of this aid society. Dr. Joseph Pecival opened the conference in the festively decorated hall. Almost all the delegates from the Chicago and out-of-town lodges were present. Doctor Pecival, who is president of the Grand Lodge, first suggested several improvements in the management of the Union. Among these was the establishment of a permanent office directed by the secretary, who is to devote his whole time to the organization. The president, the vice-president, the treasurer, the physician, and three members of the supervising committee, together with an organizer, should form the staff <pb facs="5418478_5_0318.jpg" n="2"/>of this main office. He further suggested the readjustment of the dues rates, one of the main issues to be discussed in the sessions. He also declared the unification of all Czech aid societies was an urgent necessity, though previous attempts in this direction have proved abortive.</p>
   <p>Doctor Pecival broached the question of loyalty of the Czechs during the War, and also the consequences of the world conflict upon aid societies and the insurance of children. He pointed out the patriotic obligations which the organization owes to this country, and acknowledging the praiseworthy efforts made by the organization in this respect, he emphasized, however, that unceasing endeavor is imperative if the ultimate result is to be reached--the liberation of the old homeland.</p>
   <p>After the elections the appointments of various committees, and the settlement of routine business, the meeting was adjourned.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0319.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the afternoon session telegraphic congratulations and letters were read, among which the one sent by the Czech National Alliance expressed thanks for the support accorded to the Alliance up to the present. A similar communication was received from the Association for the Maintenance of Czech Free Thought schools. Proposed adjustments of the bylaws were debated until the meeting was adjourned for the afternoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
