<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-29">Dec. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Joint Meeting of Bohemian Benevolent Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-29">Dec. 29, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A JOINT MEETING OF BOHEMIAN BENEVOLENT SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A joint meeting of Bohemian benevolent societies was held in the Pilsen Auditorium yesterday at 2:00 P. M.</p>
   <p>Mr. Macal, who acted as a representative of Bohemian benevolent societies at the State League of Benevolent Societies meeting in Springfield last October, reported that the meeting was very interesting and useful, and that it was very interesting and useful, and that it was very thoroughly discussed in our newspapers. Proposals submitted to the meeting by the League of Bohemian Benevolent Societies were gratefully received, and gained the general approval of all delegates. He remarked that the officers of other than Bohemian benevolent societies could learn a great deal from us, particularly because the Bohemian societies know how to produce larger profits than are customary with societies run by nationals of other countries.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian proposals were passed on to various committees of the State <pb facs="5418478_5_0451.jpg" n="2"/>League for study and the drafting of recommendations for their adoption. This applies particularly to the proposal concerning the joint ownership of shares by husband and wife.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
