<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-09">May 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning a New C.S.P.S. Building</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-09">May 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING A NEW C.S.P.S. BUILDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have been following certain items published in our Czech press, many of which had all the characteristics of a "puff"--following for a purpose. We are also in receipt of a communication from the Robert H. Wickers Lodge of the C.S.P.S. (Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost, Czecho-Slovanic Aid Society), and of a letter from the Tenth Ward Taxpayers' Association. We wish to submit these to our Czech public and especially to call their contents to the attention of the various C.S.P.S. lodges.</p>
   <p>In the resolutions passed by the above-mentioned organizations, and also in the news items, the erection of a new building for the C.S.P.S. and the Free Thought Czech language school is ardently advocated, with the emphasis on "modern and filling all requirements". An appeal to all Czech organizations is to be made, regardless of affiliation, "to become members of the patronat (board of sponsors) and help toward the creation of a 'Czech <pb facs="5418478_5_0212.jpg" n="2"/>National House,' a Czech community center".</p>
   <p>This Czech community center is to be built in the so-called "Czech Pilsen" district, which, by the way, is gradually ceasing to be Czech and will in the long run lose its character as such. It is consequently advisable to weigh the circumstances before the project is undertaken and to submit the results of former experiences to the interested societies of which the treasuries will be affected by the outlay. The danger exists that the investment involved in such a building might never prove profitable.</p>
   <p>One duty devolves upon all those who are promoting this venture. They should furnish proof that construction must be started now, for just now we live in a restless, turbulent time.</p>
   <p>Many a Czech enterprise in Chicago has failed that was begun by individuals <pb facs="5418478_5_0213.jpg" n="3"/>who knew how to work up the enthusiasm of our public. Eager to make money, they forgot to analyze the possibilities of profit, and it was usually the hard-working class that lost.</p>
   <p>In the case under consideration it is not the individual worker's money which is involved but the money of the lodges to whom hard-working people belong. The right thing is to point out the complications that may result from precipitate action.</p>
   <p>The fact should be pointed out that there are three other large halls almost in the center of the "Czech Pilsen," the Pilsen Sokol Hall, the Bohemian-American Hall, and the Pilsen Auditorium.</p>
   <p>Many of those who are promoting the erection of a new building will retort that the Pilsen Sokol Hall belongs to an individual body; that the BohemianAmerican <pb facs="5418478_5_0214.jpg" n="4"/>Hall is Catholic; and that the Pilsen Auditorium [Pilsen Brewery Park pavilion] is the "accursed haunt of bazaars, the curse of which is a result of the irrational and insane behavior of certain individuals". But why do we need a gorgeous, costly edifice when there are many of this type which are fighting desperately to pay off the mortgages with which individuals and organizations are burdened?</p>
   <p>Why can't we combine with the Pilsen Sokol, or buy the Pilsen Auditorium, which we could, perhaps, acquire for one third of the original price? Or why not join the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, of which the building is not yet finished, or [make arrangements with the owners of] the John Hus Memorial Building, which has enough of its site left for an annex?</p>
   <p>Why build and compete with others who themselves only vegetate? Why attempt to create a splendid structure when no capital is here, and only the site is owned by us?</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0215.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>One cannot depend nowadays upon gifts or even upon interest-free loans. Promises are given with ease, but the execution of them generally lags.....</p>
   <p>The above reasons prompt us to caution our brotherhoods to think twice before they make a decision.</p>
   <p>For Lodge Number 24 of the C.S.P.S.</p>
   <p>The Committee on Resolutions</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
