<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-25">Dec. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs Gymnasium Dedication Ceremonies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-25">Dec. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOKOL HAVLICEK-TYRS GYMNASIUM DEDICATION CEREMONIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The gymnasium of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs on Lawndale Avenue and 26th Street was dedicated yesterday. It is a dignified headquarters for this society belonging to the Fuegner-Tyrs Sokol Circuit. The festivities were attended by a remarkable number of sokols and friends of this Society.</p>
   <p>Blues and Grays were present, thereby indicating that the festivity was considered a holiday not only by members of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, but by all sokols who are striving to achieve mutual unity.</p>
   <p>The afternoon program provided not only beautiful enjoyment, but an abundance of the finest entertainment.</p>
   <p>The evening was dedicated to an informal entertainment lasting until late <pb facs="5418478_5_1203.jpg" n="2"/>in the night.</p>
   <p>The festivity was both a moral and financial success, which was, of course, to the credit of the arrangements committee.</p>
   <p>It was a select program and was carried out beautifully from beginning to end. The festival began with a lively march beautifully rendered by Solar's Band. Then the president, Mr. Vlach, welcomed the guests and gave a brief history of this monumental building which has now been turned over to the Czech people. At the conclusion of his speech, he was given the keys to the building by the architect Mr. Novy.....</p>
   <p>The overture "Frantisek Palacky" was then played by Filipovsky's Band, after which, Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan, the principal speaker of the occasion, appeared and in a well-planned speech called attention to the <pb facs="5418478_5_1204.jpg" n="3"/>purposes this monumental headquarters is to serve; he described the remarkable generosity and daring enterprise of the Society in building such a beautiful and costly structure. He expressed the hope that the building, which is in all probability the largest Czech hall in America, would soon be completely finished. His words were received with great enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs Hall is the largest we have here. It is three hundred square feet larger than the hall of Sokol Chicago, but it has no galleries. A remarkable piece of architecture is carried out here, in that the ceiling over this gigantic hall is unsupported by any column and nothing interrupts the view in the hall.</p>
   <p>A spacious stage, with complete and modern equipment, enhances the beauty of the hall. There are also cloak rooms, dining rooms, barrooms, kitchens, <pb facs="5418478_5_1205.jpg" n="4"/>dressing rooms, etc. When the two wings of the building have been constructed, it will actually be the largest Czech hall in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
