<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-06">May 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs Adapt American Method of Organizing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0330</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0330.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-06">May 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS ADAPT AMERICAN METHOD OF ORGANIZING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The organ of the Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost (the abbreviation C. S. P. S. is often used) Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Society is advocating the installation of a special organizer in a capacity similar to that office in the great American organizations. One of our Czech organizations had accepted this system several years ago and found it satisfactory. The organizer travels throughout the country founding new branches, and enlarging smaller ones, at the same time he endeavors to strengthen the finances of the Society by arranging lectures and other agitatory means, and, finally, he duly publishes reports concerning his activities.</p>
   <p>The C. S. P. S. had had an organizer for the State of Illinois at one time; his tenure of office was only temporary. We do not venture to predict whether an organizer will be able to produce results in the large towns as Chicago or New York, which have Grand Lodges, and where the business of the organization is conducted along lines essentially different from those followed in the <pb facs="5418478_5_0331.jpg" n="2"/>country districts, in which the approach of the organizer is easier.</p>
   <p>....The outlay concomitant with the wages and expenses of an organizer may also be considered. In New York, the Grand Lodge has taken upon itself the promotion of a campaign for an increase of membership which is producing excellent results. The goal set is the acquisition of one thousand new members. If this figure can be reached, present conditions being considered, the success will be surprisingly brilliant, indeed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
