<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-06">Jan. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of Cemetery Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-06">Jan. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF CEMETERY ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the Sbor Zastupcu Cesko-Narodniho Hrbitova (Bohemian National Cemetery Association) was held yesterday evening; vice-chairman Frantisek Mencl presided in place of Chairman Hladovec, who is sick.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read; as were the bills payable presented by the financial secretary, Mr. Husak. Included among these bills was one totaling $3,550.51 for wages to fifty-two workingmen employed on the cemetery grounds during the month of December.</p>
   <p>Among the letters read was one from Dr. Mueller. He sent his regrets for not attending the meeting, and thanked the Bohemian National Cemetery Association for the floral gift sent him in acknowledgement of Dr. Mueller's oration at the cemetery last Memorial Day. Mr. Kroc also sent his apologies for his inability to be present.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0370.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The secretary read the names of the delegates of the many organizations represented in the Sbor Zastupcu Cesko-Narodniho Hrbitova.</p>
   <p>The Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani (Council on Higher Education) and the Zdruzeni Ceských Svobodomyslnych Skol (Federation of Free Thought Schools) thanked the Sbor Zastupcu Cesko-Narodniho Hrbitova for its yearly contribution.</p>
   <p>It was agreed by the delegates to donate $500 to the Ceska Utulna A Sirocinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage).</p>
   <p>The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Benevolent Association) is applying for a yearly contribution. It was agreed to answer by letter that our organization cannot comply with the request.</p>
   <p>The executive committee recommended a change of ownership of the following lots: Jan and Marie Samek to Vojtech and Anna Sery; Ferdinand and Anna Roth to Anna Sklenicka.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0371.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The executive committee presented a report relative to the repairing of the Union Army monument for $260. The committee was ordered to proceed with the repairs.</p>
   <p>The executive committee along with the building committee announced that the columbarium will be opened to the public in March.</p>
   <p>In reference to the acquiring of titles to the lots in front of the crematorium the committee in charge given assurance that that matter will soon be settled, and that the steps in front of the crematorium will be finished to the satisfaction of the committee.</p>
   <p>The financial secretary placed before delegates a letter received from Belgium, with a check enclosed; this check had been sent to Belgium in the year 1914 to pay for an order which they in Belgium, could not fill, and so they returned the check. It was agreed that, for the present, the financial secretary should keep the check.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0372.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Manager Tuma spoke of the visitors he entertained--representatives from the convention of the "Society for the Incineration of the Dead," held in Detroit, Michigan. These representatives, according to Mr. Tuma, were very agreeably surprised with the working of the cremation plant, considering the short time that it has been in operation--about a year.</p>
   <p>Mr. Evzen Frydl announced that the month of December had been the best in the sale of bonds issued to pay for the crematorium; sales amounted to $2,600.</p>
   <p>Mr. Tuma said that he was asked by representatives of two German societies whether a written agreement could not be made relative to the incineration of the members of said societies. It was agreed to notify those two German societies that they may incinerate their dead, but no written agreement will be given them.</p>
   <p>Because yesterday's meeting preceded the yearly one, the nomination of officers for the coming year was in order, and the following were placed in nomination: chairmen, Mr. Jan Pecha and M r. J. Budilovsky; vice-chairman, <pb facs="5418478_5_0373.jpg" n="5"/>Mr. Frantisek Mencl; secretaries; Messrs. Novak, B. V. Vacek, and V. J. Filip; financial secretaries; Josef J. Yurka and Victor H. Cerny; board of directors to fill the office of Josef Smejkal; Josef A. Smejkal, Frantisek Petru, and Antonin Zahrobsky. Board of directors for a one-year period to fill vacancy: Evzen Frydl, Josef Ringl, Frantisek Boucek, and Vaclav Psenicka. Mr. Pecha had accepted the nomination for chairman. He resigned his position as member of the board of directors, where he was to have served another year; that position has to be filled, and the following were nominated: Messrs. K. Kopecky, Tomas David, and J. Spevak. The following gentlemen were nominated to represent us on the auditing committee: Machacek, Jan Klaus, Brezina, V. Sedlacek, J. Chobot, and J. Rothbauer.</p>
   <p>After announcing receipts of $9,544.19, expenditures of $10,600.18, and a balance on hand of $18,229.73, the meeting was ordered adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
