<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-27">Jan. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-27">Jan. 27, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The C. B. J. (Ceska Bratrska Jednota, Czech Brotherhood) is the only benevolent society which employs a special organizer and which thrives very well considering these times of war. The C. S. P. S. (Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost, Czecho-Slav Benevolent Association) discussed the institution of an organizer's office without coming to a decision. This tends to show that the need for such an office is not recognized, or that the results obtained are out of proportion to the expenditures involved.</p>
   <p>Opinions differ on this point, and it is to be noted that members of the Western branches do not favor the employment of an organizer, although one was appointed at their recent meeting.</p>
   <p>One of our correspondents singles out an example where the organizer acquired <pb facs="5418478_5_0258.jpg" n="2"/>two new members; this cost his organization two hundred dollars. This report is being denied by the official organ of that society, with the declaration that the organizer had brought in twenty-one new members during the time in question and that this did not represent his sole work. It is being pointed out that the acquisition of new members does not comprise his entire activity. He has to see that old members are kept within the ranks of the organization. This often proves a hard task for any brotherhood, particularly when the relentless necessity of raising the dues looms.</p>
   <p>Such is the nature of the work that confronts the organizer, and whether he or anyone else performs it, the Fact remains that every organization has a big job on its hands to preserve its standing membership. The reports of many organizations reveal the large number of persons quitting, or others stricken off the list of members. This condition did not mean serious harm in former times when the ranks of the organizations were quickly replenished. There was, in general, a larger gain than loss in membership.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0259.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no valid reason why members of our organizations should change, for our brotherhoods can certainly compare with all others, and many excel, in just and economic management and security as well.</p>
   <p>In addition to this, there are Czech organizations where one can feel at home. Their membership means social security for the family, and at the same time, active co-operation in national patriotic enterprises in which all our organized groups participate. The organizer of the Western Czech Brotherhood is supposed to keep the membership intact. This, however, is also the duty of each individual member.</p>
   <p>We have mentioned several times the "League for the Protection of Youth," which sends out its stool pigeons regularly to spy on social gatherings and entertainments. The reports published by them are highly colored, the results of alleged observations of immorality and the sale of liquor to <pb facs="5418478_5_0260.jpg" n="4"/>minors, soldiers, and sailors.</p>
   <p>No one must think that such news as this is not worth taking notice of. These people jeopardize our social entertainments. They blaze the path for further propaganda and the revocation of the bar license at our social affairs.</p>
   <p>Clubs, and other associations giving entertainments, ought to be mindful of this and guard against disorderly conduct and violation of the law. This is urgently recommended during these times of high-pressure "dry" propaganda.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Americka Jednota (Czech-American Union) has organized a special agitation committee with Brother Moravek as chairman and Brother Chrencik <pb facs="5418478_5_0261.jpg" n="5"/>as secretary. All the lodges are to be represented in this committee by zealous members who are interested in the development of the Union.</p>
   <p>The Czech-American Union has also introduced the insurance of children, which offers another opportunity for agitation by enthusiastic members. The department for child insurance is busy. The terms on which the insurance is offered are now so attractive that no one should wait any longer. The insurance secures not only the child's future, but it keeps the child within our ranks in preparation for membership later.</p>
   <p>Lodge Vltava, No. 17, of the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Czecho-Slav Union) announces that the initial fee has been suspended for the next three months. This is an inducement for prospects in this lodge of 415 members.</p>
   <p>F. Lukes, 3045 South Kenneth Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
