<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-19">Jan. 19, 1922</date><title level="a">Annual Meeting of the Utulna a Sirotcinec</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0983</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0983.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-19">Jan. 19, 1922</date><title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF THE UTULNA A SIROTCINEC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the delegates to the Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's
Home and Orphanage) took place at eight o'clock last night in the hall of the
Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies), located
at 18th and May Streets. The meeting, which was called to order by the chairman, Mr.
Vojtech Suchy, was well attended by the delegates, who followed the course of the
meeting in which a number of important questions came up for discussion with great
interest.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the previous meeting were adopted as read, and thereupon letters
addressed to the board of delegates were read. These letters, besides announcing the
various New Year's donations, contained the names of newly accredited delegates from
the various societies and organizations, the representatives of which are members of
the board of delegates to the Utulna A Sirotcinec. These representatives are as
follows: For the board of directors of the <pb facs="5418478_5_0984.jpg" n="2"/>Jednota Cesko-Americkych Zen (Bohemian-American Ladies' Union), Mrs. Anna Kroc;
for the lodge No. 119 of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies' Union), Mrs.
Marie Starek; Cesko-Slovanska Bratrska Podporujici Jednota, Cislo 35 Rad Kardas
(Lodge No. 35 of the Czecho-Slavonic Fraternal and Benevolent Association), Mr.
Josef R. Fencel; Loze Cislo 1 Jednoty Taboritu (Lodge No. 1 of the Taborites), Mr.
Jan Cervenka; Sbor Berta Zasmucka Cislo 40 Jednoty Ceskych Dam (Lodge No. 40 Berta
Zasmucka of the Bohemian Ladies' Union), Mrs. Marie Vyhnanek; Velko Vybor Sesterske
Podpurne Jednoty (Grand Lodge of the Benevolent Sisterhood), Mrs. Frantiska Zahour;
Sbor Jaroslava, Cislo 8 Jednoty Ceskych Dam (Jaroslava Lodge No. 8 of the Bohemian
Ladies' Union), Mrs. Marie Krist'an; Cislo 129 Jednoty Ceskych Dam (Lodge No. 129),
Mrs. Bozena Stefek; Sbor Ctilada Cislo 13 Sesterske Podpurne Jednoty (Lodge No. 13),
Mrs. Anna Kosander; Dvur Cesky Lev Cislo 1 Cesko-Americkych Lesniku (Court of the
Bohemian Lion No. 1 of the Bohemian-American Foresters), Mr. John V. Budilovsky;
Dvur Sumava Cislo 9 Cesko-Americkych Lesniku (Court of Sumava No. 9), Mr. Frank
Frish; Rad Darwin Cislo 61 (Order of Darwin No. 61), Mr. Kazimir Jezek; Velkodvur
Cesko-Americkych Lesniku (Grand Lodge of Bohemian-American <pb facs="5418478_5_0985.jpg" n="3"/>Foresters), Mr. Jakub Batka; Velkorad
Cesko-Americke Jednoty (Grand Order of the Bohemian-American Union), Mrs. E. M.
Hrisny; Sbor Sarka Cislo 62 Sesterske Podpurne Jednoty (Lodge No. 62), Mrs. Karolina
Souhrada; Rad Karel Havlicek Cislo 87 Ceskoslovanske Podporujici Spolky (Order Karel
Havlicek No. 87 of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Association), Mr. Josef Haller;
Hlavni Loze Cesko-Slovanske Jednoty (Grand Lodge of the Czecho-Slavonic Union), Mrs.
Ruzena Fivka and Mrs. Anna Sykora; Rad Rip Cislo 41 Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici
Spolky (Order of Rip No. 41), Mr. Vaclav Illich; Loze Pokrok Chicaga Cislo 34 Ceske
Sesterske Jednoty (Lodge Progress of Chicago No. 34), Mr. Josef Rolenec; Dvur
Trocnov Cislo 15 Cesko-Americkych Lesniku (Court Trocnov No. 15), Mr. Oldrich Kozak;
Dvur Klacel Cislo 3 Cesko-Americkych Lesniku (Court Klacel No. 3), Mr. Josef Kodl;
Dvur Bila Hora Cislo 7 (Court of the White Mountain No. 7), Mr. Frank J. Petru; Rad
Jiri Washington Cislo 66 Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Order George Washington
No. 66), Mrs. Marie Podolak; Rad Cesko Delnicky Cislo 73 Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici
Spolky (Order of Czech Workingmen No. 73), Mrs. Josefa Chott; for the Rad Kristof
Kolumbus Cislo 193 Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Order of Christopher Columbus
No. 193), Mr. Josef Spinar; <pb facs="5418478_5_0986.jpg" n="4"/>Loze Volnost Cislo
33 Cesko-Slovanske Jednoty (Lodge Freedom No. 33), Mr. Josef Vejvoda; Telocvicna
Jednota Sokol Tabor (Sokol Gymnastic Union Tabor), Mr. Jan Lehman; Sbor Bojyne
Svobody Cislo 74 Jednota Ceskych Dam (Lodge of the Goddess of Freedom No. 74), Mrs.
Rosie Tejcek; Klub Ceska Vlast (Club Bohemian Homeland), Mr. Jan Hanzl; Sbor Bozena
Nemcova Cislo 18 Sesterske Podporujici Jednoty (Lodge Bozena Nemcova No. 18), Mrs.
Marie Stepanek; Sokol Chicago, Mr. Frank Stepanek; Rad Caslav Cislo 205
Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Order of Caslav No. 205), Mr. Frank Stepanek;
Damsky Odbor Plzenskeho Sokola (Ladies' Auxiliary of the Sokol Pilsen), Mrs. Barbora
Scheffel and Mrs. Emilie Hrisny; Sbor Svornost Cislo 33 Sesterske Podporujici
Jednoty (Order of Concord No. 33), Mrs. Josefa Sedlacek; Sbor Columbia Cislo 79
Jednota Ceskych Dam (Lodge Columbia No. 79), Mrs. Karolina Smolar; Sbor Zdenka
Havlickova Cislo 20 Jednota Ceskych Dam (Lodge Zdenka Havlickova No. 20), Mrs. Anna
Broucek; Sbor Premyslovna Cislo 5 Jednota Ceskych Dam (Lodge Premyslovna No. 5),
Mrs. Marie Hell; Loze Kristof Kolumbus Cislo 9 Cesko-Slovanske Jednoty (Lodge
Christopher Columbus No. 9), Mr. Anton Zrust; Rad Turnov Cislo 151 Cesko-Slovanske
Podporujici Spolky (Order of Turnov No. 151), Mr. Josef Baloun; Rad Pravda Cislo <pb facs="5418478_5_0987.jpg" n="5"/>37 Cesko-Slovanskych Podporujicich Spolku
(Order Truth No. 37), Mrs. Frantiska Bauman; Rad Praha Cislo 13 Cesko-Slovanske
Podporujici Jednoty (Order of Prague No. 13), Mrs. Karolina Vodak; Rad Jiri
Podebradsky Cislo 24 Cesko-Slovanskych Podporujicich Spolku (Order of George of
Podiebrady No. 24), Mr. Vaclav Budilovsky; Sbor Cesko-Slovanskych Vyslouzilcu (Order
of the Czecho-Slavonic Veterans), Mr. Tomas Hejna; Svobodna Obec (Free Thought
community), Mrs. Antonie Jiricek; Spolek Plzenskych Rezniku (Pilsen Butchers'
Association), Mr. Jan Srcha and Mr. Frantisek Mathauser; Rad Vernost Cislo 8
Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Order of Loyalty No. 8), Mrs. Anna Bulovec;
Velkorad Statu Illinois (Grand Order of the State of Illinois), Mr. Vaclav
Machalicky; Sbor Palma Vlasti Cislo 56 Jednota Ceskych Dam (Lodge Palm of the
Homeland No. 56), Mrs. Antonie Grasl; Rad Vysehrad Cislo 48 Cesko-Slovanske
Podporujici Spolky (Order of Vysehrad No. 48), Mr. Ludvik Pinc; Sbor Ratolest Miru
Cislo 76 Jednota Ceskych Dam (Lodge of the Branch of Peace No. 76), Mrs. Josefa
Sidlo; Rad Chicago Cislo 130 Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Order Chicago No.
130), Mrs. Johanna Kara; Sbor Ulastimila Ruzickova Cislo 93 Jednota Ceskych Dam
(Lodge Ulastimila Ruzickova No. 93), Mrs. Frantiska Kolar; Loze Radbuza Cislo <pb facs="5418478_5_0988.jpg" n="6"/>11 Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Lodge Radbuza No.
11), Mrs. Terezie Vrchotka; Loze Karel Havlicek Cislo 18 (Lodge Karel Havlicek No.
18), Mrs. Ruzena Doktor; Loze Hvezda Severni (Lodge Star of the North), Mrs. Anna
Cadil; Sbor Ceske Vlastenky Cislo 70 Jednota Ceskych Dam (Lodge Bohemian Patriotic
Women No. 70), Mrs. Lizzie Sramek; Velkorad Cesko-Slavanskych Podporujicich Spolku
Statu Illinois (Grand Order of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Association of the
State of Illinois), Mr. Jakub Janda and Mr. Josef Fencl; Dvur Svatoupluk Cech Cislo
30 Cesko-Americkych Lesniku (court of Svatopluk Cech No. 30), Mr. Frank Kroc; Sbor
Vlast Cislo 19 Jednota Ceskych Dam (Lodge Homeland No. 19), Mrs. Josefina Koula.</p>
   <p>The chairman, in his opening address, greeted the newly elected delegates and
impressed them with the importance of their duties to the institution. Our
institutions require good leadership, and it is the hope of the chairman that with
the installation of the new delegates, a great deal of new talent has been acquired.
The chairman's speech was followed by the reading of the report of the investigation
committee. Mrs. Frantiska Nartinek, who is an aged woman, <pb facs="5418478_5_0989.jpg" n="7"/>was recommended and accepted as an inmate of
the institution. Mr. Frank J. Petru reported that the New Year's contributions for
our two institutions brought over $8,200. This report was enthusiastically received
by the delegates. Mr. Petru further reported that Mr. Lawrence Klein, who is the
executor of the estate of the recently deceased Mr. Saul Klein, whose whole sale
store is located on Halsted Street and Canalport Avenue, informed him that the
deceased left the amount of thirty thousand dollars for various charitable causes.
Of this amount there now remains some five thousand dollars, and of this latter sum
the greater part will go to our institution...</p>
   <p>Mr. Petru further reported that a certain Tom Hurray of 112 North LaSalle Street
contributed $25 to our institutions. The letter accompanying this gift is not
without interest. It appears that on August 17, 1920, Mr. Hurray needed a
transfusion of two quarts of healthy human blood. This was sacrificed by our
countrymen, Mr. Frantisek Pavlik, and thanks to him, the life of Mr. Hurray was
saved. To commemorate that event in his life, Mr. Hurray promised to contribute the
sum of twenty-five dollars annually. Mr. Petru further reported <pb facs="5418478_5_0990.jpg" n="8"/>that....a corner of the property belonging to
the Sirotcinec was sold at last. It was purchased by Mr. Ferdinand Pechar, a stone
mason whose workshop is situated on the ground belonging to the institution. The
purchase price was $5,500, and the purchase itself was transacted by Mr.
Petru.....</p>
   <p>The reading of the minutes of the last meeting of the board of directors followed.
The minutes revealed the following facts: Mrs. Alma Marek made a proposal in the
name of the Krouzek Dam Ceskeho Sirotcince (Ladies' auxiliary of the Bohemian
Orphanage) to the effect that the said auxiliary, with the permission of the board
of directors of the Sirotcinec, would furnish necessary clothing to the orphans for
an annual small fee of three dollars per child, the sum to be collected from the
relatives of every child. If it can be proved that the relatives of the orphan are
unable to pay that small fee, the members of the auxiliary will furnish the clothing
at their own expense. This much-appreciated aid proposed by the Krouzek Dam Ceskeho
Sirotcince was accepted, and the chairman, Mr. Vojtech Suchy, took the opportunity
to thank this ladies' auxiliary for the aid which they have already given. The
administrator <pb facs="5418478_5_0991.jpg" n="9"/>of our institution was requested
to inform the relatives of orphans about this new prevision and to make all the
arrangements necessary for its effectiveness....</p>
   <p>The Krouzek Dam Ceske Kalifornie (Ladies' Auxiliary of the Bohemian California
District) arranged an annual gift distribution among the inmates of our
institutions. The gifts were distributed on Thursday, December 29, and were
especially generous. Therefore, not only the inmates, but also the administration
tration are very grateful to the ladies' auxiliary.</p>
   <p>It was further reported that the society Tabor has donated a carpet valued at $698
for the playroom of the institution. The purchase price of the carpet also included
forty chairs and tables, all this having been obtained at a much lower cost than
what was asked by some firms, and the bargain is entirely satisfactory.</p>
   <p>It was decided to insure our offices against theft to the amount of $2,000, <pb facs="5418478_5_0992.jpg" n="10"/>and the policy is to be issued by the Western
State Bank.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Suchy reported that a certain Edward Straka wishes to adopt an orphan whose name
is Dorothy Suchy. The chairman refused this request and the board of directors
agreed with him since the girl in question was committed to our care by the Juvenile
Court. The case will be handled by that court on January 20, the girl's relatives
will be duly informed, and no action will be taken until after the decision of the
court is handed down.</p>
   <p>The next case reported was that of an inmate, Mrs. Krbec, who desires to become a
secretary of the society Palma Vlasti Cislo I Jednota Ceskych Dam (Palm of the
Homeland No. 1 Bohemian Ladies' Union). The society also wrote to the board to issue
papers authorizing Mrs. Krbec to assume the position she desires. It was decided to
answer that letter as follows: The board of directors has no objections whatever to
Mrs. Krbec's occasional visits to the meetings of the said society, but she may not
accept any office or other function. This is a ruling made for all other inmates of
the Utulna and no exceptions can be made.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0993.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>Jan Kolnik, who has four of his children in the Orphanage, is ill, and, according to
a letter from his physician, is unable to work, and therefore also unable at present
to pay for the children. He asks for leniency. It was moved by Mr. Janda to grant
Jan Kolnik's request and to recommend this case for support to the Juvenile
Court.</p>
   <p>The committee on industrial schools reported that at the present time children are
being taught sewing, embroidery, music, and various other domestic arts;
preparations are being made to enlarge the curriculum.</p>
   <p>The contributions made by various organizations and individuals were gratefully
acknowledged. Among these, the following deserve mention; Twenty dollars were
contributed by the Sbor Vetev Ceske Vlasti Cislo 5 Ustredni Jednota Cesko-Americkych
Zen (Lodge No. 5 of the Central Union of Bohemian-American women). This amount was
to be used for the purchase and decoration of a Christmas tree. Mrs. Marie Liska
collected $20 among the members of the Jednota Ceskych Dam. This sum, too, was
devoted to the same purpose, so that <pb facs="5418478_5_0994.jpg" n="12"/>the
children had a really fine Christmas tree. The lodge Plzen No. 272 of the Odd
Fellows and the lodge Bohemia Rebekah of the Independent Order Of Odd Fellows
contributed Christmas baskets. Mr. Dusek of 2152 West 21st Street donated candies;
Mr. Dobias, a baker, donated baked goods. The lodge Josef Havlicek of the Jednota
Ceskych Dam No. 129 contributed some Christmas gifts. The ladies of the Klub Ceske
Besedy (Bohemian Get-Together Club) contributed toys worth $25 for the game room.
The lodge Praha No. 231, Independent Order Of Odd Fellows, contributed a variety of
gifts. The Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Charitable Association), through Mr. Stanislaus
Loula, a plumber, contributed 34 head of poultry, 22 loaves of bread, and boxes of
Cracker Jack. The pupils of the McCormick School gave various toys. The lodge
Rebekah No. 165 of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows contributed $200 to the
music fund. Mrs. Millie Tetrev gave $100 for the game room. The Chicago Charitable
Corporation, 3255 Lincoln Avenue, gave $300.</p>
   <p>All of these gifts, each accompanied by a brief remark by the chairman, were duly
noted and accepted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0995.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>The next item on the program of the meeting was a discussion concerning the reserve
fund of our institutions. This fund was used during the building of our Sirotcinec.
After a lengthy debate in which the chairman, Mr. Janda, and Mr. Novak participated,
it was decided that this fund should not be less than twenty thousand dollars, and
that all subsequent bequests should be added to it. The current bills of the past
month were presented and approved. The gift of $300 made by the Chicago Charitable
Corporation through the kind intervention of Mr. E. F. Wieboldt, who is its
secretary, was gratefully acknowledged.</p>
   <p>The election of officers for the ensuing year then took place. The results were as
follows: Because of unquestionably valuable services rendered to our institutions,
Mr. Vojtech Suchy was re-elected to the chairmanship; Mrs. Gruenwald was made
vice-chairman; Mrs. Bozena Krabec, secretary; Mr. Frank J. Petru was re-elected
treasurer. The following members were elected to the board of directors: Mmes.
Lorenz, Hrisny, Sedlacek, and Scheffl, and Messrs. Charvat, Janda, Trnka, and
Hajsman. The following were elected to the auditing committee: Jan L. Novak, Marie
Stepanek, and Oldrich Kozak. The <pb facs="5418478_5_0996.jpg" n="14"/>following
make up the investigation committee: Mr. Oborny and Mr. Vilimek, and Mrs. Wajner and
Mrs. Spramek. The entertainment committee will be elected at the next meeting.</p>
   <p>This memorable meeting adjourned after the reading of the report of expenses for the
past month, which amounted to $2,473,50; the receipts for the past month were
$4,848.57.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
