<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-15">Apr. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">For a Good Cause</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1394</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1394.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-15">Apr. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FOR A GOOD CAUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The druggist, Mr. Louis Scheffel, mailed us a check for $5 which is to be transmitted to the Utulna A Sirotcinec in the name of the Chicago Retail Druggists Association. The latter organization has a special fund for the purchase of flowers for the graves of deceased members; the recently deceased member, Mr. Vojta Vavra, expressed a wish before his demise, however, that no flower offerings were to be made, and therefore a gift of ten dollars was made for a good cause. Of this amount five dollars was given to the Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old Peoples' Home and Orphanage) and five dollars to the Sirotcinec Svateho Josefa (Saint Joseph's Orphanage, at Lisle, Illinois). The gift for the Saint Joseph's Orphanage was mailed to the publishing office of the Narod. We may add that the Bohemian druggists of Chicago are very active in the aforenamed druggist's association, and that this year they have three Czech officials--Messrs. Louis Scheffl, Frantisek Dubsky, and Frantisek Kara.</p>
   <p>Five dollars was mailed to us by M. T. [only initials given] for the Ceska <pb facs="5418478_5_1395.jpg" n="2"/>Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association).</p>
   <p>Three and one-half dollars was mailed to us for the benefit of the Dr. Alice Masaryk Fund for the War Orphans of Czechoslovakia and for the starving Russian children.</p>
   <p>Mr. Josef Suchyna sent us two dollars which is to be used for some good cause.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Anna Subrt, of Table Rock, Nebraska, sent one dollar for the Stodola family.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
