<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-29">June 29, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Workers Trapped into Slave-Labor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1225</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1225.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-29">June 29, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN WORKERS TRAPPED INTO SLAVE-LABOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.2--A certain Joseph Chmelinsky, a Pole, of 687 West Eighteenth Street inserted in the newspaper some time ago an advertisement reading as follows: "Wanted, Two hundred men to work in sugar-beet fields in Michigan. Families preferred. Transportation free both ways. Gangs shipped from Chicago to-day and Monday. For particulars apply at 687 West Eighteenth Street between 9 a.m. and 6 p.m. Jos. Chmelinsky." The advertisement gives such an impression of reliability that no one would suspect that there was a catch in it. And yet according to several communications received from North Branch, Michigan, written by fellow-countrymen of ours who answered Chmelinsky's advertisement and were sent to Michigan, variable slavery awaits those who report for work. We consider it our duty to print the essence of one of these letters as as warning to all our compatriots. We believe that it would be a good idea to send some one out to them to investigate conditions and report before the rest of the gang decides to leave home. An excerpt of the complaint follows:</p>
   <p>"We are being treated worse than slaves. Those who will not work for thirtyfive <pb facs="5418478_5_1226.jpg" n="2"/>cents an hour for thirteen hours in succession get nothing to eat the next day. When it rains, and there is no work in the fields, the employers telephone to the stores, and when we come to buy, our credit is cut off, for the entire village has been built by the company and is dependent on it. On these days no store will sell us any goods even for ready cash. And so we are starving here. We request the editor to publish this to keep our fellow-countrymen from coming to the state of Michigan and falling into this trap, where there is nothing but hunger and toil. When we get back to Chicago, we will relate the rest of our experiences. Kindly publish only the initials of our names, which are given in full below."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
