<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-01">Oct. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Business Manager of the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0764</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0764.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-01">Oct. 1, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE BUSINESS MANAGER OF THE BOHEMIAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND ORPHANAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Having been requested by the board of directors of the Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) to accept the position of business manager of that institution, I hesitated at first; for to leave my old position as a business manager of a lithograph company, a position which was a steady one, with an assured future, was a considerable step to take. In short, it was difficult to make a decision. After having discussed the matter at some length with the directors and with my wife, the love for my fellow men won me over, and I decided to accept the offer made by the board, and to help those people who need help most, and who return love for love bestowed upon them....</p>
   <p>Since the attitude of my wife was the same as mine I went to join that institution in which parentless and friendless children are being cared for; where a love for their fellow men and a love for their country is being inoculated in them; where they also receive training which will make them useful citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0765.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I went also to join the aged inmates of that same institution, the "superannuated" fathers and mothers who come here to seek rest.....My heart beat fast when I entered the portals of the institution and saw both the aged and the parentless,....I promised them all that I would love them and help them. It was hard for me to hold back the tears which filled my eyes, and not wishing to cause them pain by such a show of emotion, I left them hurriedly to betake myself to the place where my actual work was to begin. I sat down at my desk and looked at the book containing the names of our self-sacrificing people; and while viewing this record I realized that I too am to bring in as many sacrifices as possible. I am glad that I accepted the position, and that I shall have an opportunity to help those who need help.</p>
   <p>That the Czech people really care for their countrymen who are inmates of this institution is manifested by the gifts received by the Utulna during the month of August and up to September 22, 1922. I take this opportunity to publish <pb facs="5418478_5_0766.jpg" n="3"/>the list of benefactors for the period stated above, and ask all those whose names and gifts do not appear, due to some oversight, to let me know.</p>
   <p>Our people also take great interest in the entertainment of all our inmates. Thus, for instance, the inmates of the Sirotcinec-- 36 boys and 20 girls--were taken by Miss Anna Lorenz, their nurse, to see a ball game at Cubs Park, and all expenses associated with this were borne by Mr. Otto Pelikan, 2600 South Lawndale Avenue, Mr. Frank Kohout, 3634 West 26th Street, and Mr. Anton J. Cermak. These gentlemen also provided the refreshments for these children. The management of the Utulna hereby expresses its thanks for their great kindness. There were other ways in which our people have shown their interest in the welfare of our little ones. On "Cermak's Day" a huge cake was delivered to the Sirotcinec; we cut it into 100 parts thus having enough cake for all the children.....The children and the management are most grateful for this gift, especially to Mr. Kvidera who came at such a late hour to deliver the delicacy. [Here follows a list of contributors and the amounts contributed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0767.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The list is one-eleventh of a column long, the total amount of contributions made being $175.39.] Mrs. Anna Karas, 2252 South Clifton Park Avenue donated some old clothing....; Mrs. Bily of 3024 West 26th Street donated five pillows, one dozen blankets, three pairs of slippers, ten pairs of men's underwear, fourteen shirts, four aprons, two women's jackets, one winter overcoat, and one topcoat. I thank you all in the name of the board of directors of the Utulna.</p>
   <p>Jan Patak,</p>
   <p>Business Manager</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
