<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-22">June 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian Charitable Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-22">June 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the directors of the Bohemian Charitable Association was held last night in the Pilsen Pavilion at Twenty-sixth Street and Albany Avenue. Judge Joseph Z. Uhlir presided over the meeting. The secretary being absent, his task was taken over by Mr. J. Docekal. The first order of business was the reading of the minutes of the previous meeting and these were approved as read. Next came the reading of communications received, the majority of which were requests for aid and as usual these were given careful attention. The auditing committee then gave a report for the month of June and from this report it appeared that the Association received a mere forty-eight dollars during the month and disbursed with $257.30. This screaming disproportion calls directly to our more well-to-do people, to continuously and under all circumstances remember and support the Charitable Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0533.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During the month there were forty-three applicants for aid. Thirty of these cases were given assistance. Five cases are waiting the completion of the investigation and nine cases were rejected.</p>
   <p>After the requests for aid were disposed of, the discussion turned to the Tag Day which is to be held on the Fourth of July. The directors were notified yesterday that the ladies, to whom this great collection for our poor was entrusted, have already held several meetings and are of the opinion that perhaps the days of the Havlicek monument unveilling ceremonies would be better suited for the purposes of the Tag Day. However, the directors decided to hold to the arrangements already made. We are in complete agreement with this and confidently expect that there will not be a single Bohemian in Chicago on that day who will not cheerfully allow himself to be Tagged, and who will not make as generous a contribution as his means will permit.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0534.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It appears from preparations being made by our ladies that from morning to night on the Fourth of July, all crossings, parks, and frequented places in Bohemian communities will be occupied by collectors. No one will be molested, no one will be urged, because it is expected that everyone will be conscious of his duty and will contribute. It is understood. of course, that the participation of our young ladies is expected and those who would like to dedicate a day's work for this noble purpose should send their names and addresses to the chairwoman of the women's committee Mrs. A. Cervenka, 2416 Clifton Park Avenue. Girls from fourteen years upward may apply. A meeting of the women's committee will be held in Pilsen Pavilion the last Friday before the Fourth of July.</p>
   <p>We add that the ladies who make the largest collections will be rewarded with beautiful useful premiums donated for that purpose by Messrs. J. F.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0535.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Lalla, Roman Sedlacek, and the Slavonic-American Bank. Let us hope that other businessmen will join in this noble endeavor. Receipts of the evening were forty-three dollars. The meeting ended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
