<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-20">June 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian-American Foresters Society Increased by Two New Courts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-20">June 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN FORESTERS SOCIETY INCREASED BY TWO NEW COURTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two new courts were added to the Bohemian-American Foresters Society. They were initiated in a festive manner Saturday evening in Mr. Soukup's Hall on West Twenty-fifth Street. The two new courts are named "Budoucnost" and "Snezka." The first being a men's society, the second a women's society. Both number 150 members. Messrs. Budilovsky, Hajek, and Zahrobsky officers of the grand court were present and conducted the ceremonies.</p>
   <p>The reader will no doubt be interested in knowing that the members of the new courts are all former members of Lawndale Lodge No. 2034, Modern Brotherhood of America, who, being dissatisfied with the Grand Lodge of that organization in so far as the payment of death benefits was concerned, decided to withdraw and became members of the Bohemian-American Foresters. As we have been told, this action was taken after a stormy meeting, where <pb facs="5418478_5_0537.jpg" n="2"/>it was argued before the members of the Lawndale Lodge that the Grand Lodge of the Modern American Brotherhood had treated them with unusual generosity, that it had wronged no one, and that if in some cases it did not pay death benefits, that it was justified in doing so and that all those lawsuits to compel it to do otherwise were meaningless. However, the members did not want to understand this in that way and apparently thinking that they would be better off in a strictly Bohemian Unity, they reorganized and joined the Foresters.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jan Subert is president and Mr. Vaclav Pitlik is secretary of "Budoucnost" Court. Mrs. Anna Charvat is president of "Snezka" Court.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
