<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-05">Dec. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Collection for the Benefit of a Blind Hero</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-05">Dec. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A COLLECTION FOR THE BENEFIT OF A BLIND HERO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of the Ludvikovci (Frantisek Ludvik Dramatic Association) started a collection for the benefit of one of the young and talented actors, Mr. Frantisek Boleslav, who lost his sight in action. Regarding this collection, members of the Ludvikovci issued the following statement:</p>
   <p>"When this gifted and popular young member, Mr. Frantisek Boleslav, became blind, the Bohemian dramatic community suffered a great loss and a crushing blow. This man of sound health and bright ideas is condemned to eternal darkness and must live upon charity.</p>
   <p>"Christmas time--days of joy, days of love--is a time when our memories turn <pb facs="5418478_5_1681.jpg" n="2"/>back to the days of our childhood, and unintentionally all of our sentiment, touched by the festive mood, urges us to perform a good deed. Now the season is nearing.</p>
   <p>"Just recently Mr. Rudolf Suva, a member of the Ludvikovci, received a communication from the invalid actor. Everybody who listened to the reading of the communication was deeply touched. The pen with which the poor blind man's communication to his friend was written set down words expressive of genuine distress. In response, a collection was started in order to provide a Christmas present for the unhappy fellow actor.</p>
   <p>"We most sincerely appeal to professional actors and also to our supporters. Contribute your talent toward the Christmas present for Frantisek Boleslav and send your contribution to Rudolf Suva, 2530 South Sawyer Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. All contributions will be acknowledged in our newspapers."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1682.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>So far the following countrymen have contributed: [There follows a long list of names and amounts.] Total, thirty-nine dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
