<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-04-20">April 20, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Old Peoples' Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-04-20">April 20, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD PEOPLES' HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Already there has been much complaint about the indifference of our citizens toward the "Home." These complaints were not, and are not, without substantiation. Everywhere, in everything, we see an almost staggering indifference to the undertaking, the importance and benevolence of which are generally recognized, and, which formerly was so enthusiastically and liberally supported. Early improvement is needed for this condition. There are smaller groups of other nationalities here, and they all have homes for their aged poor folk, their own hospitals and orphanages.</p>
   <p>We have been preparing over a period of years, for the foundation of a "Home," and now we are worse off in the matter than we were three or four years ago. We are drowsy and indifferent. How much patriotism, charity and generosity there formerly existed among us! How much money Bohemian Americans, especially Chicagoans, have sent to the old country in support of the undertakings and institutions of the national societies! How <pb facs="5418478_5_1164.jpg" n="2"/>generously we have supported our countrymen, in the old country, whenever they were stricken by some elemental calamity! Now we care about nothing except the most diversified forms of amusement, and at the very most, we decide, at times, upon a manifestation of mutual hatred among ourselves, (between Liberals and Catholics.) On our national field almost all fruitful work has ceased. Almost nothing happens for this reason, however, there is so much more criticism undermining and tearing down. We do not consider this sad condition in our national life as permanent but we cherish the hope, that there will soon be a change for the better. The present lack of interest and dullness is probably only the result of former great drives. We needed a rest, and perhaps we have taken more of it than was really necessary, therefore, let us go to work. Let us remember that we have three undertakings which deserve our fullest support. They are: The "Home for the Aged." the "Orphanage," and the "Singing School for Children." Everyone should have the realization and success of these undertakings at heart, and work for at least one of them at each opportunity. Then, let our public also participate and we shall be able to expect the completion of at least one of our chief undertakings in a short time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
