<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-14">Apr. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Building of the Bohemian-American Hospital Sold at a Profit</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-14">Apr. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE BUILDING OF THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN HOSPITAL SOLD AT A PROFIT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The office of the Pilsen Brewery Company witnessed a meeting last night which decided the fate of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice (Bohemian-American Hospital). The meeting, which was attended by the trustees of the Bohemian Hospital, was conducted by Mr. Jan A. Cervenka. The results of this meeting will be found interesting to our local readers as well as to those who reside outside of Chicago. After a seven-year period of inactivity, caused mainly by the war and our fight for national independence [of Czechoslovakia] the realization of building our own Bohemian Hospital seems certain.</p>
   <p>The contributive strength of our people should not be dissipated by factionalism. It was decided that it was the duty of every good Bohemian to support the cause of Bohemia's independence. That great cause has been accomplished; it now rests with us to think about our own local needs. Among these, according to the opinions of our leading citizens, the erection of a Bohemian hospital <pb facs="5418478_5_0646.jpg" n="2"/>is all-important, and it was for this reason that a meeting of the trustees of the projected Hospital was called. The various problems which confronted us before seek their solution again. Mr. Frank G. Hajicek, as a past secretary of the [dormant] organization read the minutes of the last meeting, and was immediately followed by the remarks of the president who explained to the assembly the various steps taken connected with the sale of the hospital property. The building which was purchased by the trustees some time ago was to house the Hospital. It is located at Albany Avenue and 14th Place, and, as it was later ascertained, does not meet the requirements of a hospital building. The trustees, therefore, decided to sell it. This they succeeded in doing after some time, and the property was disposed of through the medium of the well-known realty firm of Cermak and Serhant for the purchase price of $28,400. The building was bought by the Jewish Day and Night Nursery. The various expenses connected with this transaction--commission, war tax, documentary stamps, etc.--totalled, $1,725 leaving the sum of $26,647 as clear profit. The total sum, however, which is in the hands of the trustees reached $30,002.16 and is now deposited in Lawndale State Bank, a Bohemian banking institution of <pb facs="5418478_5_0647.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago. The great economy of the trustees of the Hospital is attested by the fact that during the entire period of operation the organization's expenses amounted only to $199.25.</p>
   <p>At Mr. Hajicek's suggestion it was unanimously decided to call a public meeting in which the general public could take part, and in which the detailed financial statement would be read. This will afford everyone an opportunity to express his opinions and to make further suggestions as to what steps are to be taken in building the long-delayed Hospital. Such a meeting will most probably be called this month, and will be held in the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Company on 26th Street and Albany Avenue. The gentlemen who compose the board of trustees are of the opinion that the money which they hold in trust is the property of our Czechoslovak people, and that only these people have the right to dispose of it in the interests of the Hospital. All other steps, such as the calling of a public meeting, were left to the trustees themselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
