<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-08-18">Aug. 18, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Bohemian People of North Berwyn</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-08-18">Aug. 18, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Bohemian People of North Berwyn</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear patrons and friends: If we follow the social life in our community which has grown fast during recent years, we notice that we miss one thing--a building that would satisfy our requirements. The Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Oak Park (Gymnastic Association of Oak Park), which always meets the requests of our people and lends its small building for any good cause free of charge, is noticing that the present building does not meet the requirements at this time and is not sufficient for further social activity. Therefore, the Sokol Oak Park appeals to you, our dear patrons and countrymen, for aid in the form of a small monetary loan which would be secured on the building. Such loans would help the Sokol Oak Park to erect a building worthy of us. In its children's classes, our association drills 150 boys and girls who need more space <pb facs="5418478_5_1169.jpg" n="2"/>for their body and moral development. This is impossible under the prevailing circumstances in the small, unsatisfactory building.</p>
   <p>Dear friends! Our old homeland is free because of our efforts and our contributions. Why not contribute toward such a good cause as the development of our youth? You certainly feel happy when you see these youngsters, who are healthy, developing their strong arms during the drill. Calisthenics is recognized by the whole progressive world as the best protection against any sickness. There is no reason why we should not give our children the opportunity, as our great poet Jan Neruda said, to harden themselves until everyone is as hard as a rock, and then our nation will be like a boulder.</p>
   <p>If we take into consideration the social life of our community, we must admit that every one of us, no matter who he is, is a social creature. Every one of us, occasionally likes company and entertainment. If such entertainment is held in a roomy and comfortable place, everybody enjoys it. In our <pb facs="5418478_5_1170.jpg" n="3"/>settlement commonly called Oak Park, which is predominantly settled by Czechoslovaks and where nearly all of us own our own homes, such a small loan, which would be used for the erection of a public building,would not hurt us, but would only be to our advantage.</p>
   <p>If we look at our near-by Bohemian settlements--"Czech California" or Cicero or even our Bohemian settlement in the south part of Berwyn--we must notice that each settlement has several public buildings and that the social life in those communities is improving. We know from experience that everybody likes to live in such a settlement. Because of this, the valuation of property is increasing. There is no reason why we should wait when there is a chance to develop our settlement by means of a small loan.</p>
   <p>Three years have passed since our association tried to unite and co-operate with all the other Bohemian societies in order to erect a new building. But <pb facs="5418478_5_1171.jpg" n="4"/>our efforts were not fully understood at that time, and now we are forced to ask our people for aid. But we hope that with the support of our people we will be able to erect a building which will do honor to us all.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we appeal to you, our dear patrons and countrymen, and we especially appeal to our societies to help us in this task in order that we will be able to accommodate you better when you hold your meetings and entertainments. We extend our gratitude for your past favors, and we ask you to consider this proclamation when our committee calls on you.</p>
   <p>For the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Oak Park,</p>
   <p>The Finance Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
