<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-03">May 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Utulna Svateho Benedikta</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1004</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1004.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-03">May 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE UTULNA SVATEHO BENEDIKTA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special meeting of the executive committee of the Utulna Svateho Benedikta (Saint Benedict's Home) was called by Reverend Innocent Kestl. The meeting was held on Monday, April 25, 1921, in the Saint Vitus School, Paulina and 18th Streets. The meeting was presided over by Reverend Prokop Neuzil in the presence of Reverends Innocent Kestl, Anastaz Rebec, O.S.B., Joseph Stedronsky, E. Sladek, O.S.B., Martin Krizka, and Frantisek Bozenek. The following were also present: Mesdames Frantiska Slama, Rosalie Nedved, Antonie Serpan, Messrs. Vaclav Radous, Antonin Hodous, and Vaclav Rezny, architect.</p>
   <p>The order of the meeting called for the election of a new secretary, because the first secretary and Mrs. Paulina Janik, a member of the executive committee of the Utulna Svateho Benedikta, had resigned. Mrs. Janik's resignation was accepted and Mrs. Magdalena Filip was elected to take her place on the executive committee. Mr. Antonin Hynous of Cicero, Illinois, was unanimously elected as the new secretary. The order of the meeting also called for the selection of a <pb facs="5418478_5_1005.jpg" n="2"/>name for the Utulna Svateho Benedikta. It was resolved that the institution should be known under the name of Domov Svateho Benedikta pro Starce a Stareny (Saint Benedict's Home for the Aged), and under this name our institution will be incorporated. In conclusion, the matter of remodeling the building was brought up. The building will be thoroughly remodeled at a considerable cost. To raise funds for this purpose, the Chicago district of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America) intends to arrange a great autumn festival in Ceska Kalifornie (Bohemian district in Chicago) for the benefit of the Domov Svateho Benedikta.</p>
   <p>With pleasure we inform our people that many patrons have already been secured for our institution. Through the efforts of Reverend Prokop Neuzil, a bequest of $1,000 was secured. The Damsky Pomocny Spolek (Ladies' Aid Society) contributed the sum of $62.08. A bequest of the late Marie Vlcek amounted to $300. Other contributions totaled $53.05.</p>
   <p>Further contributions may be sent directly to the superintendent of the Saint <pb facs="5418478_5_1006.jpg" n="3"/>Benedict Home, Reverend Edward Sladek, 1818 South Paulina Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>May the Lord reward all the generous donors. With regards to all,</p>
   <p>Reverend Frantisek Bozenek.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
