<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-21">Dec. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Report of the Meeting of the Board of Directors of the Old Peoples Home and Orphanage [Association]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-21">Dec. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF THE MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF THE OLD PEOPLES HOME AND ORPHANAGE [ASSOCIATION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by the president, Mr. Frydl, at the appointed time. Because numerous letters were received from Czech societies in reply to the Association's request that they indicate whether they are for or against the idea of building a tavern on the grounds of the Old Peoples Home and Orphanage, it was moved that a committee be appointed and authorized to examine the letters and report the result. All the letters were turned over to the committee, which then retired to an adjoining room to take care of the matter.</p>
   <p>The meeting then proceeded with the regular order of business and the minutes of the previous meeting were read and approved as read. Then followed the reading of communications in which societies announced the names of newly elected delegates to the Association as follows: [A list of names of lodges together with the names of the new delegates is given.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1119.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In so far as could be ascertained from the mass of correspondence received, the following Christmas contributions, gifts, and payments were received: [there follows a list of names and amounts contributed]. Total, $681.45. Disbursements at the institution during the past month amounted to $243.36.</p>
   <p>At this time the committee which was canvassing the letters in reference to the tavern returned and announced that thirty-nine were opposed to the tavern, forty-one were in favor of it, and ten had left the matter to the discretion of the Association; of the ten, one was not considered and the other nine were cast in favor of the tavern. The principle objectors were the women's organizations. The sharpest protest against the tavern was made in a letter sent by Mr. John Kralovec. The final result was forty-five votes against and fifty-two votes for the tavern. However, since it was announced that many societies had not yet held meetings and therefore were not able to express their wishes in the matter, it was finally decided to postpone action on the matter until the next meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1120.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Receipts of the evening were $1,664.25. Bills payable were set over until the next meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
