<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-18">Apr. 18, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Humanitarian Work of the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-18">Apr. 18, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">HUMANITARIAN WORK OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK LEGIONNAIRES OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"In order to inform the public that the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago are taking care of their brothers, who by reason of injuries or sicknesses contracted while in the army, found themselves in hardship, we take the liberty to refer to these gifts from the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago: Mrs. Tykalsky, a widow of a brother legionnaire, received the sum of $75; Mrs. Kalcic, a widow of a brother legionnaire, received the sum of $25; Mrs. Hrachovsky, a mother of a brother legionnaire who is a patient in the County Hospital, received the sum of $25; brother Kalous received the sum of $50; brother Divina received the sum of $50; for the benefit of the Doctor Thomas G. Masaryk Fund, the sum of $104 was sent to Prague; for the benefit of the Doctor Alice Masaryk Fund the sum of $62 was sent to the same place. Eighteen of our brothers were aided by loans representing the sum of $900."</p>
   <p>This report was sent to our office by Jan Svadlenak, financial secretary of <pb facs="5418478_5_1752.jpg" n="2"/>the above-mentioned organization, with the request that it be published in our newspaper.</p>
   <p>We willingly fulfill the wishes of the Legionnaires and we hope that our public, after reading this, will form their own conception about the activities and ideals of the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago. This organization does not care to exist only as an ordinary society, but it wants to prove by its activity that whenever and wherever it is necessary, it is willing to work with love and enthusiasm not only for national and cultural causes, but also for the cause of humanity. Therefore, we expect that the Czechoslovak Legionnaires will be supported in all their undertakings by our public, who in that way will prove that the sacrifices made by our legionnaires for the liberation of the Czechoslovak nation are acknowledged. It will also prove that the work which is being done by them and the work which they are willing to do among us in the future, is fully valued and recognized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
