<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-25">Oct. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The New Building of the Sirotcinec</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0858</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0858.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-25">Oct. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW BUILDING OF THE SIROTCINEC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Half-tone, three column-half of a page, architects drawing of proposed orphanage]</p>
   <p>An exhibition of the handicraft of the inmates of one of our principal charitable institutions will be opened today. The young inmates of the orphanage--not only girls, but boys, too--have worked hard during the whole year and have made a large number of objects which are now exhibited and for sale to our public.</p>
   <p>The exhibition has a double purpose: To acquaint our general public, which is at the present time the only support of our institution, with the work done by the inmates of the orphanage in their spare time, and to secure financial help. The money paid for the objects on display will go to swell the very low funds of the building committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0859.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since the exhibition has been arranged for the benefit of the new building it is only fitting that we should offer, in addition to a picture, some information concerning it.</p>
   <p>The building, which will face Crawford Avenue, will stand fifty-six feet from the street and will be entirely fireproof. Its largest dimensions will be 108 by 96 feet, and it will accomodate 160 inmates, that is eighty boys and eighty girls. The boys' and girls' quarters will be separated, and the children will meet only in the dining room. For each forty children, there will be one nurse, or four nurses for the whole building. Three or four women will be employed in the kitchen.</p>
   <p>The building will have two stories, an attic, and a basement. The basement floor will be two feet under the level of the ground. Both stories and the basement will be twelve feet high. There will be steam heat, electricity and gaslight.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0860.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There will be two fireproof stairways leading from Crawford Avenue and two on the east side of the building. These latter passages will be connected with a balcony and a hall leading to the old building which will be used exclusively for hospital purposes.</p>
   <p>The walls will be of pressed brick; the building will be covered with a tile roof.</p>
   <p>The price of construction is calculated not to exceed $50,000.</p>
   <p>[A detailed description of the building floor plans, etc., follows.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
