<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-29">Feb. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Former Bohemian Societies Building Transformed into Boys Club House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1172</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1172.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2 (Polish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-29">Feb. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FORMER BOHEMIAN SOCIETIES BUILDING TRANSFORMED INTO BOYS CLUB HOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The former Ladimir Klacel Hall, at 19th and Leavitt Streets, which was one of the oldest Bohemian societies' buildings, soon will be transformed into a clubhouse for boys of that neighborhood. Many years ago, at the time the building was erected, it was recognized as an urgent necessity for the growing Bohemian settlement called "U Vapenek" (By the Limestone Quarry). However, in the course of time, the stream of our Bohemian population began to turn in other directions, especially westward, where the new, large Bohemian settlement, Ceska Kalifonie (the Bohemian California), was growing up. The settlement "U Vapenek" ceased to be the Bohemian center. The trustees of the Ladimir Klacel Hall, who struggled with unfavorable fate for a long time, could not meet the payments and pay the interest regularly. Finally, the unavoidable happened and the building had to be sold. A few years ago the Ladimir Klacel Hall was sold to a <pb facs="5418478_5_1173.jpg" n="2"/>certain Polish-American citizen and in a short time Ladimir Klacel's bust disappeared from the front of the building and was replaced by the bust of Chopin; from then on the building was known as the Chopin Hall. It appears that it was a losing proposition even for the new owner, as a dance hall, for recently it was reported that the building was turned over to the Union League Club and will be conducted as a center for boys from 7 to 17 years of age.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
