<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-12">May 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Cesko-Slovanska Jednota</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0207</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0207.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-12">May 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Cesko-Slovanska Jednota</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Czecho-Slav Union) in its latest plenary meeting adopted child insurance with an 18-year age limit, and in the April meeting the creation of a child-insurance committee was decided upon. In regard to this the organ of the Union published the following information:</p>
   <p>"Child insurance is a novelty for our brotherhoods and is one of the most important items of our future activity. Few new immigrants, or none, arrive in these days; the brotherhoods must seek to find future members among those of our prople who already are settled here. The acquisition of children as members is therefore a very essential step toward [the achievement of] this aim.</p>
   <p>A child belonging to our organization can be more easily approached for membership than an adult outsider. Children will pay twenty cents per month, and the <pb facs="5418478_5_0208.jpg" n="2"/>benefits will be be graded according to the time for which the child has belonged. The initiation fee will be fifty cents, which will be used for expenses connected with the registration.</p>
   <p>In order to put the system into operation, at least five hundred children must be signed up for insurance, as required by the State authorities who issue the permit. This figure is not too high to be reached by a large brotherhood. For a child two years old who has been insured for a period less than one year the death benefit will be $15, and so on up to $200, if the insurance has been paid 17 to 18 years. When the insured has reached his 18th year, he will be expected to join as a full-fledged member of the Brotherhood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
