<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-06">Oct. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Proclamation Made by the Czechoslovak National Council</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Abstract)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-06">Oct. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A PROCLAMATION MADE BY THE CZECHOSLOVAK NATIONAL COUNCIL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Abstract)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Czechs and Slovaks have fully performed their duty during the most critical period in the history of our nation. Thanks to these great examples of devotion and love shown by our Czechoslovak people in America, the great struggle for the freedom of our nation ended in victory. A just and equitable history will some day evaluate all the work and sacrifices of the Czechoslovaks of America in the interest of the revolution.</p>
   <p>The American Czechoslovaks sacrificed not only their material wealth, but their own blood; for the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of America, who were the quintessence of the sacrifices made by our people here for the sake of liberation, contributed the revolutionary activity of the American Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1307.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Czech and Slovak organizations of America, which until recently turned all their attention and support to the old homeland, face a new task today. If the work of our American countrymen is to bear good fruit they must do one more thing to finish their revolutionary activities in behalf of their old homeland. This last job, which faces us all, is to care for our suffering and invalid Legionnaires. Thus our last revolutionary deed will be to keep our word--to aid those men who sacrificed their lives and health in order that the republic might be made possible. Many of these invalids have families depending on their support. The suffering of the former Legionnaires and their families is something that will require the aid of all the Czechoslovak people of America. The problem is not only a material one, dealing with the actual aid of the suffering men and their families, but a moral one, since the honor of the Czechoslovak people of America is at stake.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak National Council of America which represents all of the <pb facs="5418478_5_1308.jpg" n="3"/>varied Czech and Slovak organizations in this country, regardless of organizational philosophy or religious creed, recognizes this moral obligation. In its last plenary meeting, held on May 20, 1922, the Council decided to start a collection which is to be the last all-national revolutionary activity in behalf of our suffering countrymen. This fund will be sufficient to care for both the indigent Legionnaires and the families of the men who fell in battle.</p>
   <p>The collection was entrusted to a special committee of three delegates to the Council.....The success of it, however depends on the full recognition of the task and tireless effort and support of all the Czechoslovaks in this land.</p>
   <p>Fully convinced that there will not be any national-conscious Czechs or Slovaks who would miss this opportunity to pay his share of this last revolutionary tax, the Council is ready to launch this activity and start the <pb facs="5418478_5_1309.jpg" n="4"/>collection. Our slogan is: "The Czechs and Slovaks of America for their own suffering Legionnaires!"</p>
   <p>Should we be successful in collecting the sum of $100,000, we shall have ample funds to care for both the invalids and their families.....The Czechoslovak Legionnaires left the United States, their families, and their livelihood without any privileges or guarantees. After serving for two years in the Czechoslovak army, they returned without any means. Among those who returned were 107 invalids, many of whom are crippled for life. Some of these had their health either partially or totally affected by the exigencies of war. Many of the men did not return at all; that is, 97 of them are known definitely to have been killed. This latter group left both widows and orphans here. Of the invalids, 35 are serious cases, 72 are less so. Only 32 of the invalids are being cared for by the Czechoslovak government; the rest look forward to a sad and bitter future.....</p>
   <p>For the Czechoslovak National Council:</p>
   <p>John A. Cervenka, president;</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1310.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Dr. J. Stybor, secretary.</p>
   <p>For the Narodni Vybor (National Committee) of the collection for Czechoslovak Invalids:</p>
   <p>Lada Krizek, secretary;</p>
   <p>Reverend Oldrich Zlamal, president;</p>
   <p>Josef Kacir, treasurer;</p>
   <p>Josef Andel, accountant;</p>
   <p>F. Vainer</p>
   <p>Josef Bendl,</p>
   <p>Antonin Hobl.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
