<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-31">May 31, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Financial Report of the Committee of the Czechoslovak-American Commercial Expedition to Czechoslovakia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1345</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1345.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-31">May 31, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FINANCIAL REPORT OF THE COMMITTEE OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK-AMERICAN COMMERCIAL EXPEDITION TO CZECHOSLOVAKIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Committee of the Cesko-Slovensko-Americka Obchodni Vyprava Do Cesko-Slovenska (Czechoslovak-American Commercial Expedition to Czechoslovakia) hereby submits its report to the members of the Expedition. The report is the result of a meeting held on board the steamship "George Washington" on Wednesday May 10, 1922.</p>
   <p>The expenses of the Committee were as follows:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Newspaper ads</cell>
     <cell>$201.20</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Printed matter, etc</cell>
     <cell>78.75</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>An American flag to be presented to the Prague chamber of commerce</cell>
     <cell>68.90</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance paid for insignia</cell>
     <cell>43.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Cablegrams sent Bremen and to Czechoslovakia</cell>
     <cell>13.86</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total expenses</cell>
     <cell>$406.21</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1346.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance left in the treasury</cell>
     <cell>$479.60</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>(The aforesaid balance is all that remained from the five-dollar per capita fees paid by every member of the Expedition for defraying such expenses as hereinabove specified.) A gift of $649.40 was made to the expedition committee by Mr. F. J. Skala; the gift is to be used for charity [in Czechoslovakia]. The grand total remaining in the treasury is $1,129.00.</p>
   <p>This amount shall be distributed among the most needy charitable institutions of Czechoslovakia. Following the recommendations made by the Chicago consul of Czechoslovakia, Dr. J. F. Smetanka, the committee decided to give two-thirds of the above sum to the Ceskoslovensky Cerveny Kriz Czechoslovak Red Cross), the Ceske Srdce (Bohemian Heart [a child welfare organization]), and to a fund for the repatriation of the Pobelohorske emigrants. The remaining one-third shall be distributed among other charities whatever these may be....The committee reserves the right to dispose of the remaining one-third for such charitable purposes as it will see fit. Alderman Mr. Anton J. Cermak also donated 5,000 <pb facs="5418478_5_1347.jpg" n="3"/>Czechoslovak crowns to the committee which is to dispose of them as it will see fit. Mr. Jan Pecha, president of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) has $500 which he received from the Cemetery Association. He is to distribute that amount among the Czechoslovak charities with the reservation that part of it is to go to the Bohemian legionnaires. Mr. Pecha decided to give $200 to the Bohemian legionnaires' fund, and the balance to us [the Committee]. Our treasurer is to use that money for the most urgent charitable work. The committee decided to include Mr. Pecha as a member of the Committee which will supervise the distribution of all funds. Mr. Jan A. Sokol, an accredited member of the Ceskoslovenska Obchodni Komora V Chicagu (Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce of Chicago) was also appointed a member of the Committee.</p>
   <p>Before leaving Chicago to join the expedition, Reverend Vaclav Vanek, arranged a charity concert in his church. Outstanding Czech artists such as Mr. and Mrs. Vaclav Jiskra and Mr. and Mrs. V. Machek co-operated with Reverend Vanek in this venture. The concert netted $195 which sum was distributed as follows: To the president of the expedition Mr. J. K. Valha $50 to be used for the <pb facs="5418478_5_1348.jpg" n="4"/>erection of a monument ot the great Hussite warrior, Jan Zizka Z Trocnova; $50 to Mr. V. Jiskra for the Czech legionnaires residing in his home town; $50.00 to Mr. J. Dusek for the indigent families in Domazlice, Czechoslovakia; $45 to Attorney K. Vesely for the poor people of his home town in Czechoslovakia. These gentlemen sold the tickets to the concert, and their wishes must be respected. The current expenses connected with the concert were defrayed by Reverend Vanek himself, so that every dollar received shall go to the causes specified.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank J. Zajicek, of Chicago, in response to an appeal made by the Deyluv Ustav Pro Slepce V Praze (Deyl's Institute for the Blind, in Prague) took with him three machines for the school of that institution. The machines are worth $500. Besides that Mr. Zajicek took with him 36,000 Czechoslovak crowns as a gift to the Prague Institute for the Blind. The American Red Cross undertook to ship the machines without charge, and the Chicago Board of Education made a gift of maps for the blind valued at $250.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1349.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Committee respectfully submits [the above] report. According to it there are about $1,600 in cash which shall be devoted to Czechoslovak charities It would do credit to the members of this Expedition if the above amount could be increased by $400 so that $2,000 could be devoted to charities in Czechoslovakia. We still lack these four hundred dollars. There are some wealthy countrymen among us who have joined the Expedition, and who still love their native land. Therefore, let us prove that love by making a collection which would raise $400.....</p>
   <p>It is with great pleasure that we are able to report that all of the members of the expedition, barring a few and very minor instances, were entirely satisfied with the arrangements made by the Committee of the Expedition. The advantages of such a joint expedition are many. Not the least important of these are the joint traveling via the Wabash and the Lackawanna Railroads, the expediting of all the baggage belonging to the members to and from the trains and to the steamship without charge, the information retailed, the counsels given, the medical care given by our Bohemian physician, Dr. O. S. Pavlik, who <pb facs="5418478_5_1350.jpg" n="6"/>also joined us as a member of the Expedition--all this was done free of charge. The Committee is pleased that good humor prevailed throughout. Everything has gone well thus far. Let us show by our collective behavior that nothing but harmony exists among us, so that everybody may say that the Commercial Expedition arranged by the Czechoslovaks was successful, a statement that could not be made concerning other such expeditions which took place in the past.</p>
   <p>J. K. Valha, president,</p>
   <p>Reverend Vaclav Vanek, secretary,</p>
   <p>Josef Dusek, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The report of the Committee was accepted with great satisfaction by all those present, and upon the recommendation made by the secretary it was decided to collect the sum of $400 from the assembled members....[Names of those contributing and the amount of each contribution are omitted in translation. It appears that only $307 was collected and the committee hopes that the $93 <pb facs="5418478_5_1351.jpg" n="7"/>required will be supplied by other members who were not present at this meeting. The article continues with a description of the trip made to New York City, impressions gained in that city, various and usual experiences on board the steamship "George Washington," etc. These are, for the most part, items which do not reveal anything very significant concerning the life or activities of the Chicago Bohemians. These travel memoirs have been written up in greater or less detail by Mrs. Josefina Beranek and are two and two thirds of a column long.].....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
