<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-27">July 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian-American Foresters Celebrate an Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0388</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0388.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-27">July 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN FORESTERS CELEBRATE AN ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jednota Cesko-Americkych Lesniku A Lesnic (Bohemian-American [Men and Women] Foresters) belong without a doubt among the most important factors of our public and national life. The organization has been active here for sixteen years already, following diligently its program of helping humanity, and doing charitable deeds, and our countrymen will remember how the organization commemorated its first entry into the public life. This was in 1899, when the Bohemian chapters (camps) of the mother organization seceded, taking on voluntarily an obligation of $8,000, which sum was properly paid out in death benefits to the heirs of members who, without this help, would have been in difficult situations. This was a fine demonstration of true brotherly love which will always be remembered by our public.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, quite natural that the organization has become exceedingly <pb facs="5418478_5_0389.jpg" n="2"/>popular during the years of its activity, and that it has grown both in size and power. Now it is an organization standing on a very solid foundation, and if it will continue as it has up to the present time, which we do not doubt it will, it has the best possible chance of taking a place among the strongest of our fraternal organizations.</p>
   <p>The Cesko-Americti Lesnici A Lesnice had their anniversary celebration at Pilsen Park this year.....</p>
   <p>It was preceded by a parade which started at the Cesko-Anglicka Svobodna Skola (Bohemian-English Free Thought School) on 18th Street, and which was swelled on the way by contingents which joined it at the building of the Ladimir Kacel School and Vojta Naprstek School. Other organizations taking part in the parade were the Sokol Slavsky, Sokol Komensky, Cesko-Americky Sokol (Bohemian-American Sokol), and smaller groups of representatives of many other Free Thought organizations.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0390.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The principal ceremony of the celebration was the unveiling of the flag which took place in the Pavilion in the afternoon.....</p>
   <p>The ceremony was followed by hours of visiting and fellowship which, however, was considerably affected by the shadow cast on the whole of Chicago, and perhaps on the whole nation, wherever there are human hearts accessible to compassion with sorrow and pain, by the terrible catastrophe of the Steamship "Eastland" in which so many perished.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
