<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-19">May 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-19">May 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The problem of merging all our brotherhoods is at present being discussed by our organization papers. The consensus of opinion is that the union is necessary, especially under present conditions. One sign propitious to the merger is becoming evident. No voices are raised against the proposed combination as they were some time ago. This shows that the opposition has decreased or has altogether vanished.</p>
   <p>Since the time when the first attempts toward a merger met with failure many changes have taken place. The war has made the position of our fraternities difficult to maintain. It will be increasingly hard, not only now but for many years hence, to gain in membership, so that the fraternities may expand and stand on a firmer basis. One may expect new members only from our adolescent youth of Czech descent. Some progress has been made in Chicago recently in the creation of Youth organizations and clubs from which our <pb facs="5418478_5_0205.jpg" n="2"/>fraternities may draw for membership. The patrons who maintain our Free Thought Czech language schools have done meritorious work in this direction. The adoption of children's insurance by our brotherhoods would also help very much in raising a stock of prospective members. It should be introduced into all our brotherhoods, although it is very doubtful whether this system will be able to compensate for the losses which have accrued from the decrease in immigration, for from the immigrants the majority of our members came until the war broke out.</p>
   <p>There can be no question about the expediency of attracting our youth at an early age. Our boys and girls are, however, gradually drifting away from our Czech community life. In former years they were influenced by the constant stream of new immigrants, the number of whom is now much diminished. Changed conditions demand incessant efforts on the part of everyone of us; they call for more intensive agitation and compel us to find new ways for the maintenance and the expansion of our Czech brotherhoods.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0206.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this general struggle for the existence of our brotherhoods the necessity of a merger is becoming more pressing than ever, and it is finding more protagonists than formerly.</p>
   <p>It is expected that concrete proposals will be made in the near future, and that when this is done, the merger will constitute the most important item of debate at the coming annual meeting of our oldest and biggest aid society, the C. S. P. S. (Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost--Czecho-Slav Aid Society). Communications from many lodges indicate that the time most favorable to a merger has come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
