<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-03">May 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Czech National Cemetery Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-03">May 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECH NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During last night's meeting of the Czech National Cemetery in the C. S. P. S. (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Association) Hall, the financial report for the past month was approved.</p>
   <p>Seventy-three workmen were employed by the Cemetery last month and received $3,806.94 in wages. The request of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Association of Czech Free Religious Schools), to be permitted to sell their picture cards in the National Cemetery on next Decoration Day, May 30, was granted. It was further resolved to furnish coal for the Czech Orphanage and Old People's Home, for a price commensurate with the lower amount the cemetery pays for coal wholesale.</p>
   <p>A petition for aid submitted by Mrs. Anna Gruber was referred to the investigator. The woman's husband had committed suicide from despair over an incurable disease, which had kept him unemployed for over two years and had thus consumed the family's resources.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0335.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was announced that an agreement had been reached with the Cemetery workingmen who are to receive for a nine-hour day from 38 to 26 cents per hour with regular employment, while those temporarily employed are to receive 24 cents.</p>
   <p>The purchase of coal, needed mainly for flower beds and greenhouses, presents a difficulty, inasmuch as prices have risen from $2 to $3.35 per ton for lump coal at the mine. Several Czech-American coal companies, invited to make bids to the Cemetery, have failed to respond.</p>
   <p>The Cemetery has purchased a Ford truck for $638. It is considered a good investment for the price, and it is being used for delivery of flowers from the greenhouse.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
