<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-27">Aug. 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian Charitable Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0521</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0521.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-27">Aug. 27, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN CHARITABLE ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular meeting of the Directors of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) was held on Friday in Pilsen Park. The meeting was called to order by the chairman of the Board of Directors, Mr. Joseph Uhlir at eight o'clock in the evening. Members present were: Messrs. Cermak, Cervenka, Docekal, Hajicek, Loula, Novak, Petru, Sedlacek, Sokol, Triska, Turek and Uhlir.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the previous meeting of the Directors could not be read because the secretary, Mr. Furst, was not present. A motion, that Mr. Sedlacek be named acting secretary of this meeting, was approved. Mr. Sedlacek then accepted this function. The reading of correspondence was the next order of business. Most of the communications were requests for aid or work, and had for the most part already been taken care of by the Executive Committee, and by the office of the Association. The others were recommended for favorable action. Two of the letters embraced requests which do not come into the field of activity <pb facs="5418478_5_0522.jpg" n="2"/>covered by the Association, and were turned over to Alderman Anton J. Cermak for personal action. All other communications were noted, and those which concerned contributions were referred for answer.</p>
   <p>Mr. Docekal then read his report. The report showed that the Association handled 137 cases, of which eighty-one were new cases. Of these eighty-one cases, fifty requested aid and thirty-one work. Eight of all these cases were rejected, the others taken care of satisfactorily. In five cases in need of medical attention, Doctor Tetrev, Doctor Kolar and Doctor Napieralski gave their services. Attorneys Klenha and Pisa performed legal services in three cases free. Receipts for the past two months were $1232.80. [List of contributions given] Disbursements for July and August $366.95. Three bills against the Association were ordered paid.</p>
   <p>On the motion that the Association hold a dance, Messrs. Uhlir, Cermak, Cervenka, Loula, Sokol, and Novak took part in the debate. It was finally decided to hold a dance sometime in November, and a committee of three elected consisting of <pb facs="5418478_5_0523.jpg" n="3"/>Messrs: Petru, Sokol and Loula. Finally it was resolved that a Directors meeting be held regularly, and that the Executive Committee be called within fourteen days. There being no further business to transact, the meeting was declared closed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
