<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-22">June 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Report of a Regular Monthly Meeting of the Board of Delegates to the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0939</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0939.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-22">June 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF A REGULAR MONTHLY MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DELEGATES TO THE BOHEMIAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND ORPHANAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the Sbor Utulny a Sirotcince (board of delegates to the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) took place last night in the lower hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies), 18th and May Streets. The meeting....was more spirited than usual; at times, one may say, even stormy, but the debates were all to the point and harmony prevailed among the delegates. The meeting started punctually at 8 P. M. having been opened by Mr. V. Suchy, the president. The secretary, Mrs. Bozena Krabec, read the minutes of the previous meeting which were approved as read.</p>
   <p>The reading of correspondence followed. Vaclav J. Petrzelka informed the board that twenty books, in the Bohemian and English languages, were donated by him to the Sirotcinec for its library. The management of the Svobodomyslna Skola F. Zdrubek (F. Zdrubek Bohemian Free Thought School) announced that on July 1, 1922, it will conduct its graduation exercises, and asked that the boys' orchestra of <pb facs="5418478_5_0940.jpg" n="2"/>the Sirotcinec be permitted to play on that occasion. This request was granted. The Premyslovna Lodge No. 5 of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies' Union) informed us that Mrs. Anna Vanourek, who could not take an active part in the tag day activity for the benefit of the Utulna, made a collection of $14 in its behalf among the members of her lodge....which will be turned over to the treasurer of the board at its next meeting....(The aforesaid sum had been turned in.) The Pravosvav Trojan Lodge No. 5 of the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Czechoslovanic Union) sent $13 in honor of its departed member Mrs. M. Janosik. The management of the F. B. Zdrubek Bohemian Free Thought School sent a letter in which the management was "sorry to hear about the proposed discontinuance of instruction for the children belonging to the Sirotcinec" and desired to know "why this should be so when the F. B. Zdrubek School and its management have always done their duties toward the Sirotcinec". (To make this matter clear to our readers we must mention the fact that the Sirotcinec decided to organize its own school. Some of the delegates opposed this move, but it was finally decided to investigate the whole matter and refer it to the board of directors of the Utulna.) The Social and Benevolent Ladies' Circle of Bohemian California <pb facs="5418478_5_0941.jpg" n="3"/>[A Bohemian district in Chicago] sent $5 to the Utulna in lieu of inserting a notice of sympathy for the death of Mrs. Marie Kodidka....also $2.50 was enclosed in lieu of purchasing tickets to a concert to be given by the Lyra Society for the music fund of the Utulna.</p>
   <p>The reading of correspondence finished, the office manager, Mr. B. Fiser, presented all the current bills which were approved. Thereupon the secretary read applications for admission to the Utulna and the Sirotcinec. The Utulna admitted the sixty-three-year-old John Serbin, an unmarried man, of Grant Works [sic], Minnesota, but since his case has not yet been thoroughly investigated, the proper committee will do so. (The aged man in question brought $2,500 with him.)</p>
   <p>The following requests for admission to the Sirotcinec were handled by the board of delegates: Robert Kozel, age 3 years and 9 months, whose divorced mother is employed as a telephone operator and resides at 1052 Springfield Avenue; <pb facs="5418478_5_0942.jpg" n="4"/>Vladimir Pachman, age 5 years, and Vlasta Pachman, age 7 years, whose father resides at 2608 Ogden Avenue; three children belonging to Mrs. Augusta Tomany, (the said lady omitted, in making her application, to give her address and should, therefore, make inquiries of Mr. Frantisek Vilimek who is a member of the investigation committee and resides at 1818 South Throop Street); and finally the case of Josef and R. Koukola of 2412 South Springfield Avenue.</p>
   <p>It was announced in this meeting that the now disbanded society of Ostrostrelci (Sharpshooters) donated its silk American flag together with the shrine in which it is kept in the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky hall to the Utulna.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, the secretary of the executive committee, Mr. Josef Trnka, arrived to read the minutes of the last meeting of the board of directors. The minutes were as follows:</p>
   <p>"A contract made with the Kaspar State Bank in behalf of the reserve fund of <pb facs="5418478_5_0943.jpg" n="5"/>the Utulna a Sirotcinec was fully entered into and signed for the bank by Mr. William Kaspar, president, and by Mr. Smrcka, secretary. It was signed by Mr. Vojtech Suchy, president, and Mrs. Bozena Krabec, secretary of the Utulna. This contract is in substance the same as it was when proposed at a former meeting of the board of delegates and by whom it was approved, with the recommendation that some of its wording be made clearer for the better understanding of the parties involved. The trustees of the bank received $12,000 in cash, and two notes--each having a face value of $4,000--the total being $20,000. The entire transaction was handled by Messrs. Vojtech Suchy, Antonin Charvat, and F. J. Petru. It will become operative on July 1, 1922, and will continue for ten years or until the fund reaches the sum of $50,000. The contract is in duplicate; one copy to be retained by the bank, the other by the officers of the Utulna. This report was fully approved by the board of delegates. Mr. Petru collected the amount of $2,000 on the matured bonds issued by the West Side Hospital together with the interest accrued thereon. Since the bonds were a gift of Mr. and Mrs. Fucik who stipulated that the interest therefrom be used for the <pb facs="5418478_5_0944.jpg" n="6"/>purpose of providing clothing and other necessities for two children of the Sirotcinec who are absolute orphans and have no one to care for them. It was decided that Mr. Suchy and Mr. Petru should care for the safe-keeping of the money and deposit the interest accruing thereon, that is, $60 in the treasury of the Utulna to be used for the purposes for which it was originally intended. Interest accruing on the aforementioned notes, two of $4,000 each, was $440, and was collected by Mr. Petru.</p>
   <p>"Beginning on July 1, 1922, Dr. Karel Stulik, Jr., will serve as the house physician of the Utulna. This matter was approved at the last meeting of the Sbor and the board of directors. The contract in all its details will be handled by Mr. Antonin Charvat. The contractual agreement with Dr. Stulik, Jr., is to last till the end of this year. His work and medical supervision will greatly benefit the inmates and further the progress of our institutions. And will be regularly reported on to the Sbor and the general public.</p>
   <p>"The installation of a radio receiving set was reported. The set was placed in <pb facs="5418478_5_0945.jpg" n="7"/>the playroom where the inmates will be able to listen to lectures, concerts, etc. in the evening.....The set is said to be one of the best available, and is a gift of Mr. Mrizek, owner of the Atlas Baking Company, to whom the inmates and the board of directors are grateful.</p>
   <p>It was reported that the children of the Sirotcinec took part in the Memorial Day celebration at the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) where they recited several poems. Following that celebration Judge Righeimer paid a visit to the Sirotcinec and was pleasantly surprised by the neatness, cleanliness, and the general equipment of the place. The children, too, were dressed for the occasion and made a good impression upon the visitor. For this, thanks are due to the Damy Ceskeho Sirotcince (Ladies' Aid Society of the Bohemian Orphanage). The children's orchestra gave a concert that same afternoon, and their zeal and devotion to this new phase in the life of the Orphanage was clearly noticeable. The orchestra is under the leadership of Mr. Rubringer, and according to a report, his orchestra will play at a public meeting in the near future. It was <pb facs="5418478_5_0946.jpg" n="8"/>further reported that the new playgrounds for the children is now ready for use. New apparatus has been provided and the entire equipment valued at $650 was likewise furnished by the Ladies' Aid Society. The grounds answer all requirements fully.</p>
   <p>"Fifty children had a picnic at Riverview Park....; and at this juncture permission was given that they also take part in another picnic which is to be arranged by the Sdruzeni Svobomyslnych Skol (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools), and will take place in the Cook County Forest Preserves. The children will be given refreshments. Permission was also given for the children's orchestra to play during the convention of the Slovanska Podporujici Jednota (Slavonic Benevolent Union) on August 23, 1922.....The Utulna admitted an aged woman, Mrs. Vana, on May 13. One of our steady benefactors, Mrs. Rinn, purchased various carpets and other room equipment for those rooms which she maintains at her own expense. The Sbor of the Bohemian National Cemetery donated plants and flowers of various kinds to be planted in front of our building.....At the present <pb facs="5418478_5_0947.jpg" n="9"/>moment there are 93 children in the Orphanage and 36 aged people in the Home."</p>
   <p>The item concerning the contract made with the Kaspar State Bank brought forth a lengthy and lively debate, but since every member had a chance to study its wording and features, the contract will now remain in full force. The treasurer, Mr. F. J. Petru, reported that he received a check for $1,856.56 through the First National Bank. This sum was the result of the tag day operations in behalf of the Sirotcinec. He received $23.20 from those ladies who could not take an active part in the collection; this makes the total from that source $1,879.76 a greater amount than in any previous year....</p>
   <p>A parcel of land belonging to the institution and located on Springfield Avenue was offered for sale; a debate concerning this item was rather lively but it was decided to leave the matter in the hands of the board of directors which will investigate it further and make its report at the next meeting.....According to the report of the office manager, the income during the past month was <pb facs="5418478_5_0948.jpg" n="10"/>$4,161.74 and the disbursements for the same period amounted to $14,149.49 (this included the $12,000 turned over to the Kaspar State Bank for our reserve fund).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
