<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-02">Apr. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Collection for Joseph Spika Closed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1767</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1767.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-02">Apr. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">COLLECTION FOR JOSEPH SPIKA CLOSED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The collection for the benefit of Joseph Spika; our dear legionnaire, has been brought to a close. Spika is still lying in the County Hospital where we discovered him sometime ago. We may be well satisfied with the results accomplished.....</p>
   <p>From March 13, 1920, until Wednesday evening, the closing day of the collection, donations deposited in our office amounted to $460.30. Sometime ago, 30,000 Czechoslovak kronen were bought with part of this money for Joseph Spika, which were sold to us without profit by Mr. Rudolph Vacek, banker, who himself then donated $10 for Spika. We bought the kronen through Mr. Vacek because his was the best proposition offered. In addition, two 100-kronen Czechoslovak certificates and war stamps worth $4 were also deposited in our office. Kronen bought for Spika were deposited in the Bohemian Bank in Prague, Czechoslovakia, and will be given to him upon his return home. The money order is held by us and will be given to Spika together with $76.30, the remainder of the collection, on the day of his departure.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1768.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our report does not cover all of the donations for Joseph Spika; the amount is much larger. As far as we know, the sum of $154.36 was collected for him by Narod, a Bohemian newspaper, which money came almost entirely from the St. John Nepomuk Parish. In addition to this, money was given to Spika in the County Hospital. Of this amount, we have reported only the sum deposited with us by Mrs. Anna Jansa, Spika's sister. She herself is keeping some money for him at her home, but how much we cannot state. We only know that on his departure from Chicago, Joseph Spika will have about $300 in his possession; therefore, he will be provided with sufficient aid for a beginning. He is congratulated for this not only by us, but by all who helped to make this collection successful. It is to Spika's credit that we must remark that he did not want to keep the collection all for himself. A long time ago, he asked us to stop the collection for him, on account of many other collections which are undertaken for more important projects and causes. To prove that he really meant it, he wanted to give the larger amount of money, which his sister is holding for him, to his unhappy comrade--Alois Rajtura, also a Czechoslovak legionnaire from Siberia, who returned to his home in Sobeslav, Czechoslovakia, as an armless invalid. But on our advice he did not give a large amount; <pb facs="5418478_5_1769.jpg" n="3"/>he gave only $25. But nevertheless, by this act he proved the good fellowship that existed and still exists among Czechoslovak Siberian Legionnaires.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
