<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-11-17">Nov. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The New Building of the "Cesky Settlement"</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three column-quarter of a page, view of new building]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1195</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1195.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-11-17">Nov. 17, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW BUILDING OF THE "CESKY SETTLEMENT"</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three column-quarter of a page, view of new building]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Ceska Plzen" (Bohemian Pilsen) will soon have one more beautiful building. It is the new building of the "Cesky (Bohemian) Settlement" on Center Avenue. It will be completed in the very near future, but the work inside the building will not be finished for another three months. It is being built by our well-known contractor, Mr. Matej Strnad, according to the plans of Architect H. B. Wheelock. The building covers two lots (44 by 100 feet), and another lot adjacent to the building (25 by 100 feet) will be used as a children's playground. The entire lot is 79 by 100 feet and cost $11,500. The building will cost $30,000 and furnishings $2,000. The ground was paid for by a lady who does not want her name to be published. Until now, $19,500 has been raised, so that an additional $11,000 for the building and $2,000 for furnishings and equipment is still needed.</p>
   <p>When completed, the building will have three stories and an English basement.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1196.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the basement there will be a room for the janitor, an electric laundry to be used by poor women of the neighborhood, a gymnasium 40 by 53 feet for both boys and girls of the neighborhood, and bathrooms with showers.</p>
   <p>In the front part of the first floor there will be an office, a reading room, and a clinic where a number of physicians, both men and women, will hold consultations and give treatments to the poor. In the rear there will be a hall for lectures, sermons, etc.</p>
   <p>The second floor will house a kindergarten 24 by 40 feet, behind which there will be a music hall and a cooking school.</p>
   <p>On the third floor, in addition to a kitchen and a large dining hall, there will be ten rooms for the Settlement workers' quarters.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian Settlement in the Pilsen district is known for its successful <pb facs="5418478_5_1197.jpg" n="3"/>humanitarian work. It is beehive of activity of a social and religious nature, and its principal aim will be moral and social uplift for families living in the neighborhood.</p>
   <p>In its present temporary quarters, the Bohemian Settlement houses a number of classes and clubs which are affiliated with the Settlement. Seventy children attend the kindergarten, 90 girls attend the cooking school, 250 children the Sunday school, and the English evening classes are attended by 75 boys and girls. It is also the meeting place for two womens' clubs. Every Wednesday night there is a Bohemian lecture with stereopticon slides, every Sunday night a Bohemian sermon. Twice a week music and singing classes are held. Several girls' clubs and one boys' club meet there. Twice a week the dispensary is open with several physicians in charge. There is also the Penny Savings Club in which eighty Bohemian children save their pennies.</p>
   <p>The temporary quarters of the Bohemian Settlement are at 1827 South Center Avenue. They accommodate forty meetings every, week, with an average <pb facs="5418478_5_1198.jpg" n="4"/>attendance of 1,308 persons. Reverend Vaclav Vanek is in charge of the religious activities of the Settlement. Since his arrival in Chicago two years ago, these activities have assumed tremendous proportions.</p>
   <p>The moving spirit behind the Settlement work is Miss Helen I. Duncan, who is assisted by Mrs. Emilie Baumruck, Miss Alice Rowell, and a number of other helpers. The Bohemian Settlement has saved many children of Bohemian and other nationalities from physical and moral ruin and has returned them to their mothers after the children left their homes. Morally and financially the Bohemian Settlement has helped many a family in the Pilsen district where there are so many neglected children loitering in the streets. Its activities will become a real blessing for the district if the management succeeds in learning to understand the spirit of the Bohemian people, and if the Settlement remains a Bohemian institution.</p>
   <p>The new building of the Settlement is being paid for by ladies of the Chicago <pb facs="5418478_5_1199.jpg" n="5"/>Womens' Presbyterian Society, whose purpose is the promotion of Christian social service. Mr. Howell of Evanston is largely responsible for the success in collecting funds for the Settlement.</p>
   <p>The house will be a real Huss (John Huss) house, and all its service will be in the spirit of the teachings and charity of Huss.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
