<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-23">June 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">For the Future Generations</title><title level="a" type="sub">Societies and Individuals, Who Contributed Something toward Sokol Chicago's New Hall, Are Assured That Tidings about Them Will Be Preserved for Future Descendants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_1215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-23">June 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE FUTURE GENERATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Societies and Individuals, Who Contributed Something toward Sokol Chicago's New Hall, Are Assured That Tidings about Them Will Be Preserved for Future Descendants</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The building committee of Sokol Chicago has done everything possible to furnish Bohemian California with a gymnasium and hall that would satisfy all modern requirements. From plans, according to which the construction will be carried out, it is seen that it will be one of the finest Bohemian halls in America. Provisions will be made so that not only the Sokols will find it one of the best-equipped gymnasiums, but so that amateur players will have a stage which will enable them to suitably appear before the public. Other Bohemian lodges will also have headquarters in the building. Even the lodges with large memberships will be able to hold their meetings and satisfy all prescribed rituals there.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_1216.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The interior fittings of the hall and lodge rooms will be luxurious and supplemented with dignity by the strong, joyful impression called forth by the enormous building.</p>
   <p>In brief, the Sokol Chicago Hall will be such that not only the Sokol, but all Bohemian California, all Bohemian Chicago, will be proud of it. It is an enormous undertaking and will cost about $45,000.</p>
   <p>Sokol Chicago does not have such great means but it is depending upon other Bohemian societies and our generous countrymen, who recognizing to what advantage and to what honor the new building will serve all Bohemian people, surely will not withhold their aid from so deserving and undertaking.</p>
   <p>This hall will become the focus of Bohemian life: it will become the center of our national efforts; in it sokols, amateurs, and societies will <pb facs="5418478_5_1217.jpg" n="3"/>look after the preservation of our adolescents for the Bohemian people; it will cultivate Bohemian culture and the Bohemian language. Whoever is concerned about these things, let them give a helping hand towards their realization.</p>
   <p>A building, so sturdily constructed as the Sokol Chicago Hall will be, will bring the glory of the Bohemian name to future generations. In the cornerstone, which will be laid an June 26, the history, societies and individuals who acquired some merit in service for the Sokol building, will be preserved as future mementos of Sokol Chicago and the local Bohemian community. Those societies that would like to have their memorial notes placed in the cornerstone should not delay but should apply immediately. Everyone, be it an individual or a society, who contributes for the construction of the building will be entered on the memorial paper that will be placed in the cornerstone just before it is laid. Those who still wish to make a contribution may do so in the <pb facs="5418478_5_1218.jpg" n="4"/>clothing establishment of Novak and Sebek at Twenty-second and Troy Streets. The office will be at this address during the entire period of construction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
