<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-20">Jan. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_5_0273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_5_0273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-20">Jan. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We reported in another issue that the Department for War Insurance in Washington, D. C., sent an inquiry to all benevolent societies for a statement of their attitude toward insurance of members who are in the Army or Navy. Heads of our organizations were called to Washington to declare themselves in this matter. It is obvious that the Government is determined to protect the soldiers who are members of these organizations.</p>
   <p>The main offices of the C. S. P. S. [Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost (Czecho-Slav Benevolent Association)] sent the following letter to the Government office at Washington:</p>
   <p>"Our organization has no special bylaws in the contracts entered into now or earlier which would refer to members in Army or Navy service of the United States. These members enjoy the same rights and privileges as all others. We did not raise their premium because of war risks. Many of our lodges make voluntary contributions for the benefit of enlisted men. These payments are not imposed <pb facs="5418478_5_0274.jpg" n="2"/>or obligatory. We are enclosing the statutes of the C. S. P. S. and copies of contracts. We do not employ any solicitors and therefore issue no instructions for them.</p>
   <p>"We are the oldest benevolent society in the United States. Our organization was founded as early as 1854. We expect to be able to fulfill all our obligations concerning risks resulting from this war."</p>
   <p>This communication was the answer to an inquiry of November 20; it was mailed November 27. The position taken by the C. S. P. S. in relation to enlisted men is stated in it intelligibly.</p>
   <p>When this position is changed in the next full meeting of the C. S. P. S., it will be necessary to notify the Treasury Department in Washington.</p>
   <p>Let us not decide too early. We should not place an obligation upon the shoulders of the C. S. P. S. to pay for soldiers and sailors. The organ of our <pb facs="5418478_5_0275.jpg" n="3"/>brotherhood shows that we have 311 soldiers and sailors on our books. Their number will surely increase to 400 by the end of January. This would mean a monthly deposit for 400 enlisted members, besides the nonenlisted members.</p>
   <p>Not one cent should be taken from the fund for death benefits or the reserve fund for the purpose of extending loans to members to enable them to make the emergency payments.</p>
   <p>Special payments would be necessary to take care of the soldiers' benefits.</p>
   <p>Do you know who would have to make them? The older people who have been members for a long time. That would not be just. Let us be satisfied, and let us not do what we could not afford.</p>
   <p>Nonetheless, we shall pay death benefits for fallen soldiers and sailors. They are doing honorable service for the liberation of mankind from the tyranny of <pb facs="5418478_5_0276.jpg" n="4"/>autocratic militarism, and for the rescue of our beloved old homeland from the talons of the Hapsburgs. More cannot be demanded of us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
