<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. VIII, No. 33,
<date when="1931-03-14">March 14, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The 25Th Anniversary of "Obilic"</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. VIII, No. 33,
<date when="1931-03-14">March 14, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE 25TH ANNIVERSARY OF "OBILIC"</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, March 1, 1931, the Serbian Benevolent Society "Obilic" celebrated its 25th anniversary at the National Hall, 1802 S. Racine Avenue, Chicago.</p>
   <p>For this important event a rich program had been arranged, which started at about 4 P. M., when the hall was well filled.</p>
   <p>Among the girls we saw many dressed in Serbian costumes who danced the "Kolo," (national dance), till finally the president of the society, Mr. Skokic, stepped on the stage.</p>
   <p>In a short speech the president, secretary and founder of the society gave a general review of the origin, the purpose, and the work of the society in the last 25 years, and its present standing.</p>
   <p>The officials of the society were followed by delegates of various <pb facs="5420779_2_0616.jpg" n="2"/>benevolent, singing, and dramatic clubs who came to congratulate "Obilic" for its success, and urge the need of cooperative work among the American Jugoslavs, which made a very good impression on all the intelligent members of the audience.</p>
   <p>As it would be impossible to give a description in detail of all eighteen numbers of the program, I must confine myself to simply mentioning the groups that participated in it. They were the "Tamburica Orchestra Sar Planina," the mixed chorus of the Serbian Singing Society "Sloboda," from South Chicago; and the women's chorus from the Singing Society "Radicevic."</p>
   <p>The trio (two violins and banjo, played by Savo &amp; Stevo Galovich, with Mary Lalica) earned ample applause. The duet, "Dalmatinski Saskas," was sung by Nada Sulich, soprano, and Mary Duich, contralto. Nada Sulich sang two solo numbers. The audience liked her singing very much.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0617.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mary Duich also sang a solo. Her voice and diction were pleasing and clear. A violin solo remarkably well played was given by N. Bisich.</p>
   <p>The program was concluded with the dancing of the "Kolo." It was a very charming picture to see the young men and women dance these dances with rhythm and grace; their bodies swayed to the tunes of the string orchestra.</p>
   <p>The only thing that spoiled to a great extent the enjoyment of the program was the noise of the audience. These people, who kept on talking while the program was in progress, showed their ignorance and lack of good manners. A more unruly crowd could never be imagined anywhere.</p>
   <p>To celebrate the 25th anniversary is a great achievement. The membership of "Obilic" is only 148, which after many tribulations have a tidy sum of $14,000 in the bank, which is proof enough of the perseverance and the unity of its members, who mutually assist one another morally and materially.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0618.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>May this society keep on their good work under the banner of liberty, equality and fraternity, the only one under which the Jugoslav nation can find happiness and peace.</p>
   <p>Reporter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
