<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Hrvatska Zastava</title> Vol. XIII, No. 10,
<date when="1916-01-13">Jan. 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Six Words</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Hrvatska Zastava</title> Vol. XIII, No. 10,
<date when="1916-01-13">Jan. 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SIX WORDS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago Professor Harper returned from Russia, the bearer of a wonderful message consisting of six words, quoted in Russian as follow: "Njet Vodky, njet revoljucii, njet mira." These six words are of extreme importance for us Slavs. These words elevate our hearts, inspire our souls with new hopes, stimulate us to renewed efforts.</p>
   <p>These words are our guaranty that right is bound to win in the long run over wrong, and that we Slavs are going to triumph and that the modern Huns - the Germans, Hungarians and their allies, the Turks, as well as the Mongolian Bulgars - shall not have the fiendish satisfaction to dance rejoicing on our graves.</p>
   <p>"Njet vodky," (no liquor) are the first two consoling words. The accursed "vodka," or liquor, was ruining the body and soul of the Russian people. First it was the Jews, the worst enemies of Slavdom, who had the monopoly to poison with this fiendish fluid the noble and honest Russian people.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0125.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the Russian bureaucracy,spoiled through the German influence, found out what great profits could be derived from such devilish trade, the government, disgracing the Russian name and humanity in general, took the sale and production of "vodka" into its own hands. The Russian government, for the sake of sordid gain, has been poisoning and wrecking its own people, knowing that an exhausted, drunken people cannot win the war. Tsar Nicholas arrived at the conclusion that the abolition of "vodka" would win the war, and with one stroke of his pen stopped the production and sale of liquor. All the Russian people have changed since. Former miserable slaves became the dread of their enemies. There is no whiskey in holy Russia, but sacred patriotism, and enthusiasm for human and Slavic ideals.</p>
   <p>"Njet revolucii" (no revolution) are two more consoling words from our Slavic mother Russia. It is not difficult to foment a people, hungry and drunk with poisonous liquor. The Huns of modern times, the Germans, have been figuring that their Jewish agents would easily foment a revolution among the Russian people against their native country as they have already lost everything <pb facs="5420779_2_0126.jpg" n="3"/>through drink. They figured that with Jewish help they would be able to subjugate all of Russia and bring her under the influence of their Germanic culture. But thank God, "njet revolucii," the Russian people are guarding their homes, and in guarding their homes they are guarding us other Slavs, too, so that the modern Huns shall not extinguish our holy Slavic fire.</p>
   <p>"Njet mira" (no peace). Indeed, that is true. There shall be no peace until justice reigns supreme. No peace until the Slavic enemies have broken down. The Russian people are going to sacrifice their best sons and all their possessions in order to throw off the chains of bondage from the Slavic body. Our holy mother Russia is not going to stop until the last Slavic mother ceases to bear serfs. When every Slavic mother shall bear free sons and daughters on free Slavic soil, then there will be peace and until all enemies of Russia and Slavdom are on their knees.</p>
   <p>"Njet mira" (There will be no peace)</p>
   <p>Rev. Max Relic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
