<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 76,
<date when="1924-06-26">June 26, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Foreigners</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0763</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0763.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 76,
<date when="1924-06-26">June 26, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">FOREIGNERS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Secretary of State Davis writes a series of articles in the newspapers in which he brings out banalities against workers who come from the East and South of Europe. People from this region of Europe he puts in a lower category, and wishes by that to explain his reactionary standpoint. The bourgeoisie believes such trash because the economic situation of this country is bad: the foreigners are blamed for it.</p>
   <p>The main reason for the economic crisis is the fact that a small minority controls all the industrial output and is not willing to allow anyone to make use of it if the profits are not big. As long as such conditions exist crises will occur even if the population of America diminishes to one half of what it is.</p>
   <p>But who are those workers against whom the American bourgeoisie is clamoring? You will find them wherever there is hard work and danger.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0764.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We see them leaving their bones, their lives and health in American mines, on railroads and tunnels. For all their hard work they are persecuted, hated and maltreated.</p>
   <p>The Secretary of State Davis himself is a foreigner, but he belongs to a higher class, so that does not matter.</p>
   <p>How will the foreign workers overcome this shame and injustice? Not by lamenting, but by actual struggle. Only with actual participation in the political life of this country, in a common fight with the American workers, in workers' unions and workers' political parties will the working class be able to secure its rights and destroy this system of slavery, which requires from the workers more and more sacrifices, giving them only an existence and maltreating them as exploited humanity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
