<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. IV, No. 46,
<date when="1922-02-18">Feb. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">America's Shame</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. IV, No. 46,
<date when="1922-02-18">Feb. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICA'S SHAME</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In prisons of the United States there are hundreds of convicts sentenced to 5, 10 or 20 years for no other reason than expression of their opinion. In those prisons are Communists, Socialists, I. W. W.'s, and Anarchists. There are even some who do not belong to any political party, but who belonged, and do belong, to some Christian sect and were put in prison because they opposed war.</p>
   <p>The war is ended. Diplomatic relations have been established between Allies and central powers, while only a small number of the political prisoners has been released. Among them the greatest political criminal is Eugene V. Debs.</p>
   <p>When they released Debs, the American holders of power thought that was all that they could do. For in the release of Debs were interested political parties, liberal societies, unions, and persons of influence.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0096.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The government was obliged to set him free or be a target for abuse by holding in prison an old man who sincerely and determinedly stood up against bloodshed. But what will be done with the lesser prisoners? Must they,because they are not like Debs, remain in prisons?</p>
   <p>To show the narrow-mindedness of those who govern in America, especially Presidents Wilson and Harding, here are some statistics:</p>
   <p>Up to June 30 of 1921 they released, during one year, 485 criminals out of 641 applications. Mercy was granted to a great number who committed gross crimes. Among them were murderers, thieves, and embezzlers. A year before 664 applications were submitted and 639 criminals released. Some of them were German spies, others cheated the government during war, some of them were cheaters in other ways. Such men were released, laws and sentences were overlooked for them, yet there was no compassion for political transgressors.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0097.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Civilized men are not surprised at brutalities against political prisoners by the governments of Jugoslavia, Poland, Rumania, etc. We know that there are barbaric countries which have barbaric governments. But intelligent men, who do not know conditions in America, would be surprised when they would know how political prisoners are treated here, as if America takes after Spain, tsarist Russia or Japan.</p>
   <p>Americans would do better if they talked less about their "Americanism" and false greatness and took care to introduce a little more order and justice. The prevailing conditions are a shame for a country which is a Republic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
