<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 38,
<date when="1915-09-01">Sept. 1, 1915</date>
<title level="a">Protection of Women and Children</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 38,
<date when="1915-09-01">Sept. 1, 1915</date>
<title level="a">PROTECTION OF WOMEN AND CHILDREN</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"We fight for country and home. We fight to protect our wives and childen!</p>
   <p>This is the moral excuse for war adopted by all soldiers, at least, by most of them. They believe it, while in truth they fight for financial and business interests of the ruling class. There are many other false excuses for war. The slaughter in Europe destroyed this weak belief that war is waged for the defense of home and the protection of wife and children.</p>
   <p>Before the war neither the home, wife nor children needed any defense against an outside foe.</p>
   <p>The French children were not threatened by German fathers, the German home was not menaced in a Russian neighborhood.</p>
   <p>The only enemies who menaced the home, wives and children of Europe, were constant inside enemies, poverty, sickness, crime and economic exploitation.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0131.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such enemies war cannot overcome. War can only increase them. These enemies can be overcome and destroyed by a long lasting peace and struggle to create new conditions over the world.</p>
   <p>At the moment when the men of Europe entered the war, they left their homes, their wives and children unprotected from crime, to terror, annihilation. The ruins of Polish and Belgian houses, thousands of homeless childen, mistreated women, are proof how war protects home, women and children!</p>
   <p>Most deplorable is the fact that inside enemies increase. In countries suffering from war, these enemies dominate at will and nobody resists them.</p>
   <p>While men are killing their brethren they have no time to fight against sickness, crime, social unrest, theft and exploitation.</p>
   <p>From England comes news about the big death rate among children. Medical service is not available. The doctors are with the soldiers. The milk is kept from the use of others with the exception of soldiers. Add to it extreme poverty which is what causes the children to die from want of every kind.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0132.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Is the fight on the battlefield for child protection? In devastated Belgium hundreds of children died. There was no food, no warm clothing, not any of the care necessary to children of tender age. The children in Poland suffered most, because everything was burned and wrecked.</p>
   <p>One dispatch from the Eastern front said about Poland:</p>
   <p>The land is devastated in an area of 40,000 sq. miles. Two million cattle were requisitioned. There is no milk and the children die. No medical service whatever.</p>
   <p>That is the true meaning of those words "We must fight for the home, for our wives and children."</p>
   <p>To pass by such things lightly is possible only to those who consider it quite moral that one thousand men may die to let ten men get rich. A man with regard for justice and morality must oppose any war. Never is war a sacred or good thing. Was is just..... a crime!</p>
   <p>Which women and children benefit from war? Thos who may have to feed a <pb facs="5420779_2_0133.jpg" n="4"/>crippled father? Those who may have to beg around universally instead of living in their homes.</p>
   <p>Today some patrictic fools are against those who request an end of shipments of arms to Europe. They do not see that by shipment of arms they push thousands of new victims to death, that they peril thousands of innocent childen.</p>
   <p>All those men who favor any war are not prudent beings, but common fools. To prove that just look into history. For a thousand years wars were conducted but they never brought that liberty and salvation of different"fatherlands!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
