<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 22,
<date when="1937-06-02">June 2, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Children's Home Chorus Will Broadcast Program Over Wls</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0521</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0521.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 22,
<date when="1937-06-02">June 2, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">CHILDREN'S HOME CHORUS WILL BROADCAST PROGRAM OVER WLS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several years have gone by since our singing chorus has had a radio program. Through the efforts of our director of singing, Mr. Stephen T. Pipich, we again have a scheduled program on the radio. This time, however, our program is limited to fifteen minutes.</p>
   <p>We shall broadcast on radio station WLS on Saturday, June 5. The time of the broadcast is 10:30 to 10:45 A. M.</p>
   <p>The chorus has worked hard on its numbers and feel deserving of this broadcast.</p>
   <p>The numbers we are going to sing are as follows: "Medley of Croatian Songs," "Life is a Song," "Guards of the Evening," "Long, Long Ago," and "My Mother."</p>
   <p>We hope that all our Croatian friends and members will be listening <pb facs="5420779_2_0522.jpg" n="2"/>to our fifteen-minute broadcast.</p>
   <p>At this time of the year our eighth grade pupils of the Croatian Children's Home School are concentrating on graduation. As it is customary, the pupils have planned a graduation program. The number to be graduated is nine: four girls and five boys.</p>
   <p>The eighth grade pupils, together with students of the lower grades, are working on numbers which they will present on graduation day. A grade school teacher is instructing her tap-dancing class for a special number in which Anna Vori is to be featured. This alone will be an outstanding number, not mentioning the scene when our graduates will step upon the stage in their graduation clothes to receive their diplomas.</p>
   <p>The graduation is to take place in our gymnasium at 2:30 P. M. on the afternoon of Sunday, June 6. There will be no charge for admission and everybody is more than welcome.</p>
   <p>Anna Sjurekovic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
