<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1927-06-02">June 2, 1927</date>, No. 44. Vol. IV
<title level="a">"Mass Meeting"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0753</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0753.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>NOVI SVIJET</title>,
<date when="1927-06-02">June 2, 1927</date>, No. 44. Vol. IV
<title level="a">"Mass Meeting"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Representatives of various of our cultural and benevolent groups held a conference April 21st for the purpose of making plans, concerning the legislation aimed against foreigners in this country. A temporary committee of eight was elected, with instructions to call a mass meeting for American citizens of Jugoslav extraction so that all together could take necessary steps against such bills. In first place there is the bill in congress now, according to which admission of our immigrants would be based on the number of entrances in the year of 1890, which would curtail our peoples chances of coming here as our immigration of 1890 was very small, and the new law would reduce our quote to about twenty admissions. Another bill in congress is to stop all foreign language newspapers. A third bill calls for registration of all aliens who are not American citizens.</p>
   <p>There are similar bills, which may become law, as in the past many such laws were enacted, if aliens themselves, rather American citizens don't start section to prevent it.</p>
   <p>Against those laws is the whole worker's press in America, there are also free thinking organizations who are willing to aid us in the struggle. Before all it is necessary that the foreign born come forth supporting their countrymen.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0754.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Considering all this, a temporary committee is calling a mass meeting, Saturday, June 4th, in the Croatian Sokol Hall 1903 S. Racine Ave. The delegates of all our organizations as well as individual citizens of Jugoslav origin are cordially invited, the admission is free to all.</p>
   <p>Following the thorough discussion a resolution will be introduced, which will be sent to Chicago congressmen, to the government and congress. The meeting starts at 8:00 P.M.</p>
   <p>Brothers Jugoslavs, our national and economic interest demand of us to answer this urgent call and work together for our collective and individual future.</p>
   <p>Temporary Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
