<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1925-11-19">Nov. 19, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Operetta</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0293</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0293.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1925-11-19">Nov. 19, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">OPERETTA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Croatians and other Jugoslavs from Chicago and vicinity had an unusual opportunity to see an operetta in their own language, which was masterfully played.</p>
   <p>The name of the operetta was "Caricine Amazonke", it depicts the period during the reign of the Russian Empress Catharine II. This operetta is well-known to the world and most Jugoslavs have seen it in larger cities in Europe. Now the Croatian singing club "Zora" has undertaken the task to learn this play, and show it in one of the largest Chicago theatres: the Eighth Street Theatre.</p>
   <p>We are at liberty to say that this work was done by amateurs as there is not a single professional singer or actor among the players. In spite of this handicap the sternest critic must agree - allowing some minor technical errors - that the operetta as a whole was played beautifully.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0294.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Moreover, the play must satisfy those who have seen the performance few times before and in bigger theatres where professional actors and famous singers play. Don't misunderstand us. We think the impression of the performance of the play in general, which the hearer of such a production will receive, when he hears and sees the whole play, will be good.</p>
   <p>Our American colonies have few good singing choirs, and no professional actors at all. Therefore, it is pleasing to discuss, that we also can succeed, naturally with great effort, cooperative work and public support.</p>
   <p>Everyone played his part well and we may mention all the singers by name if it were not for the space, they were all wonderful. The cost of preparation for such an operetta is large - the hall, costumes, music - ballet, coaching etc. Therefore it is hoped that Zora is going to give us at least once a year a real entertainment.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, our public should extend their support in this undertaking which is really a great cultural entertainment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
