<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 15,
<date when="1937-04-14">April 14, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Activities of the Dramatic Club 'Nada' (Hope)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0307</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0307.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 15,
<date when="1937-04-14">April 14, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVITIES OF THE DRAMATIC CLUB 'NADA' (HOPE)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Croatian people in Chicago and all over America will be interested in these few lines about the work of the dramatic club "Nada," our best known group of Croatian theatrical dilettantes in America.</p>
   <p>It is worth mentioning important changes effected at the last meeting of the club members regarding the activities and organization of the club.</p>
   <p>It was decided at that meeting that the dramatic club "Nada" will remain and will be conducted in the future as an independent organization. As such, the club will have the opportunity to use all mental and material assets for one purpose, that is, propagating, developing and perfecting our national Croatian theatrical art in this country.</p>
   <p>It will make it possible to offer to its active members, literature on the theatrical art.</p>
   <p>* Official Organ of the Croatian Fraternal Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0308.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In other words, to the members will be given facilities to become more exact in their roles, to perform with more understanding and refinement.</p>
   <p>Subjects of intellectual value in general will not be forgotten.</p>
   <p>In the comfortable club rooms there will be given lectures and discussions about important questions of the day. Admission will be free to all who want to benefit by them. The club's library was enlarged and a reading room was installed for members and their friends. The club will also give entertainments for its members and the public.</p>
   <p>An inventory will be taken of the property of the club, to be able to furnish prompt service to other clubs and societies who inquire about plays, stage equipment, etc.</p>
   <p>Club meetings are held each second Thursday at 1726 S. Racine Avenue. To effect all planned changes and problems, a new committee was elected, with the determination to work hard to make the club "Nada" not only <pb facs="5420779_2_0309.jpg" n="3"/>a first class dramatic assembly but a real educational and cultural organization.</p>
   <p>Herewith we invite men and women who feel the urge for the stage to join us as members.</p>
   <p>Those who want to help in our cultural work directly or indirectly can also become members.</p>
   <p>We just want to indicate that "Nada's" members will be seen this season in a few performances on the stage. They will present the drama "Ciganin," (Gypsy), at the entertainment of the society "Slavonija," April 25, 1937.</p>
   <p>The public will be informed about all the activities of the club "Nada" in time.</p>
   <p>Ivan Jurinic, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
