<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. I, No. 15,
<date when="1908-07-10">July 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">The Workingman's Fight for Right Is Coming Out Well</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. I, No. 15,
<date when="1908-07-10">July 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORKINGMAN'S FIGHT FOR RIGHT IS COMING OUT WELL</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Till now it was impossible to say that the fight of the American workers was in the right direction. There were many faults but the biggest, the unpardonable one, was the neglect to lead the fight on political ground, on which ground the working classes of Europe have made great successes.</p>
   <p>The American worker laid stress to fight through trade unions. Organized in trade unions the American working classes fought for better working conditions, better wages, shorter hours, etc. Strikes in many places were organized and by and by the conditions were improved. But what happened? In spite of many successes in the fight, the workers are in bad circumstances, the conditions are getting worse day by day. Working hours are lengthened, wages reduced. In one year more was lost than was gained in ten years. The unions are paralyzed. The cause for all that trouble is the method of the fight.</p>
   <p>In the trade unions' fight there was no backbone. There was nothing done to make the accomplished gains permanent. There was nothing done on a political ground. Politically there was neither fight nor success.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0042.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The American worker thought that he lived in a free country and did not watch nor see how enemies of the working people robbed them of freedom. While the American workers neglected an independent political action, the capitalistic class took and holds all the political power, more than in any other country. For that reason said class is oppressive and arrogant. For that reason the rights of the people in America are abridged. Just on account of its political power the capitalist class in America dominates everything. Any movement of workers is persecuted. Against the strikers they send the police and the army. The Supreme Court declared even a boycott illegal. All that shows the mistake that the working class made by not leading a political fight along with the trade union movement.</p>
   <p>But things changed recently. The working people see their way clear. They admit that along with the trade union movement there must be a fight for political rights. In all workingmen's circles they talk about an independent political action and the Socialist Party is growing rapidly.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0043.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The working class is convinced that it cannot trust the empty promises of the capitalists. It has to have its own politics. It must vote for workingmen's candidates, who in turn will take care of workingmen's needs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
