<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Memorial Book, First All-Slavic Singing Festival</title>,
<date when="1934">1934</date>.
<title level="a">Foreword by Dr. George Kolombatovic, Royal Consul General of Jugoslavia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Memorial Book, First All-Slavic Singing Festival</title>,
<date when="1934">1934</date>.
<title level="a">FOREWORD BY DR. GEORGE KOLOMBATOVIC, ROYAL CONSUL GENERAL OF JUGOSLAVIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The idea in giving an All-Slavic singing festival is a lofty one as much from the musical as from the national standpoint, because the singing societies of the Slavic nations here in a foreign land will show through their various Slavic songs the kinship of melodies among all the Slavic groups.</p>
   <p>Likewise, the All-Slavic Singing Festival will also show the entity of interests in national politics and the necessity for a closer cooperation of all the branches of the great Slavic race here in this country as well as in our fatherlands.</p>
   <p>To the Slavs as the youngest race belongs the future of the world, because by their qualities and numbers the Slavs, who after the World War gained their national liberties, are able to succeed in every field of human enterprise if they act unitedly in defense of their sacred national rights, which had been denied them in various forms and manners through the many past centuries of subjugation by oppressive older nations.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0265.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>May this All-Slavic Singing Festival realize these wishes, which are equally dear and close to the heart of every Slav, no matter to what branch of the great Slavic race he may belong.</p>
   <p>Dr. George Kolombatovic</p>
   <p>Royal Consul General of Jugoslavia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
