<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1924-12-04">Dec. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Central Educational Committee of the Chicago Croatian Lodges</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0542</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0542.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1924-12-04">Dec. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">CENTRAL EDUCATIONAL COMMITTEE OF THE CHICAGO CROATIAN LODGES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the regular meeting of the Central Educational Committee, held November 10 in the Croatian Sokol hall, the plan to establish a school for illiterates was discussed and approved. The Committee has now provided a hall and an instructor, and as soon as a sufficient number of illiterates enroll, the school will begin. Those who wish to attend are urged to report to the secretary of the Committee as quickly as possible, so that the school can get under way.</p>
   <p>The Committee has also established a library, where those who want to may secure books. But since the Committee is terribly handicapped by lack of funds and is thus unable to buy many books, the Jugoslav libraries in America are requested to donate as many books as possible.</p>
   <p>Several lodges belonging to our two fraternal associations have, for some reason, failed to join the Central Educational Committee. This imposes a heavy burden upon the Committee, whose purpose is to promote the cause of education <pb facs="5420779_2_0543.jpg" n="2"/>in our group. More could be done, our effort would meet with greater success, if more of us were enlisted in our work. The annual lodge meetings are near, and it is the duty of the lodge members to discuss the Central Educational Committee and to see to it that the lodge joins the Committee. New delegates should be selected, or old ones reappointed.</p>
   <p>The Committee meets every third Monday at 8 P.M. in the National Croatian and Sokol hall, 1907 South Racine Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
