<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. IV, No. 12,
<date when="1921-06-25">June 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Utopia</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0100</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0100.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. IV, No. 12,
<date when="1921-06-25">June 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">UTOPIA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the grandest "utopias" is the international peace and disarmament. Never before had the governing classes talked so much about peace as during the World War. They told the people just to bring the war to a victorious end, then will follow a kingdom of peace, happiness and prosperity.</p>
   <p>The first step for peace is disarmament. But how to achieve that?</p>
   <p>All capitalistic powers are "ready" to said step, but one does not trust the other, no one wants to be the first to take that step.</p>
   <p>Hardly is a man to be found who likes war for war's sake. But there are many who consider war as a means to show "heroism" to "keep up moral forces." All who defend war in this manner do not like to be enmeshed in war. No. Such stay away from actual war. They just look at others lose their lives, while they make profits out of the misery <pb facs="5420779_2_0101.jpg" n="2"/>of others.</p>
   <p>In this country recently there has been much talk about disarmament. Some congressmen propose just a limited "armament." That means they want an army of certain size, a strong navy, but at the same time they appeal to the government to arrange a conference of American, English, Japanese and other representatives, to talk disarmament.</p>
   <p>The President in his message to Congress declared that caution forbids us to disarm alone. In that manner all powers try to excuse the existence of their armies and navies.</p>
   <p>The fact does not lay in the "caution" but in the sincere will to disarm and take the greatest burden off the population's shoulders.</p>
   <p>We do not see that sincere will, because it does not exist.</p>
   <p>Peace is impossible if it rests on controversial interests. International peace is a utopia as long as the industries are governed <pb facs="5420779_2_0102.jpg" n="3"/>by few plutocrats and masses of population are outlawed.</p>
   <p>Capitalism is based on profit, profit, is connected with the markets. Capital seeks enlargement of these markets all over the world. Capital is international. International conflicts are therefore created on account of markets. As long such conflicts exist, there is no international peace, and no country without army and navy, without warships, cannons and machine guns.</p>
   <p>If we hear a politician talk about disarmament, we have to ask him if he is for capitalism or against it. If he is for capitalism and private ownership, for differences in our economic and social structure, for the system as it is today, then he is either a hypocrite or of a limited mind.</p>
   <p>For disarmament and international peace are only men, who are against private ownership and profits.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
