<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Calumet</title>,
<date when="1934-08-27">Aug. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">About 10,000 Attend Croatian Day Held at East Side Forest Preserve</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0793</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0793.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Calumet</title>,
<date when="1934-08-27">Aug. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT 10,000 ATTEND CROATIAN DAY HELD AT EAST SIDE FOREST PRESERVE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About 10,000 Croatians celebrated Croatian Day yesterday at the East Side Forest Preserves. The parade, which wended its way through the South Chicago business district, attracted thousands of onlookers.</p>
   <p>Several thousand Croatians marched in the parade, headed by motorcycle officers.</p>
   <p>At 11 A. M. at the East Side Forest Preserves solemn high mass was celebrated. Rev. Jerkovich preached the Sunday sermon. The "Velebit" Singing Choir of South Chicago offered sacred songs at the divine services.</p>
   <p>After the solemn high mass the jubilant participants in South Chicago's first Croatian Day were served dinner by young Croatian ladies attired in native garb and with tamburica music swelling the air for the diners under the oaks. The festive crowd mixed folk-songs with their dining.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0794.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dancing to the strains of tamburica music was one of the popular features.</p>
   <p>At the track and field meeting, contests were arranged and prizes awarded.</p>
   <p>Alderman Wm. A. Rowan was the principal speaker. Several Croatian speakers were introduced, among them Dr. A. Jelich, prominent Croatian statesman.</p>
   <p>The Croatian Day Festival, held last evening at the Croatian Auditorium, 96th Street and Commercial Avenue, was attended by a crowd that packed every inch of space in the upper and lower quarters.</p>
   <p>A Plymouth automobile was given away to a happy winner in the windup of the Croatian Day celebration.</p>
   <p>The Croatian Day Committee extends its fullest appreciation to every individual or group who assisted in making South Chicago's first Croatian Day a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
