<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1916-03-01">Mar. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Accursed Foreigners Again</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1916-03-01">Mar. 1, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE ACCURSED FOREIGNERS AGAIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In recent times in the United States, like mushrooms after rain, many patriotic societies have sprung up, of which the purpose is to save "the fatherland" from the enemy.</p>
   <p>The last word in patriotic foolishness and raving is the "National Committee for Americanization". Behind this committee for capitalistic interests, working as its agents, are sold-out newspapermen and unscrupulous politicians. They think that America cannot prepare for slaughter as long as 13 millions of immigrants are here who are not citizens and have no deep feelings for their "fatherland".</p>
   <p>So it has been discovered that these foreigners ought to be "educated" and made over into citizens and impregnated with the "ideals" of this free Republic.</p>
   <p>These people are unorganized, dispersed all over the country, knowing neither <pb facs="5420779_2_0783.jpg" n="2"/>its laws nor its language; they are of various nationalities and various religions. As long as such diversity and ignorance prevail, these people will remain strangers to American conditions, and they will be a great danger when the defense of our country is at stake.</p>
   <p>For that reason they must become united, and in their hearts must be planted love for country and common ideals against all external and internal enemies.</p>
   <p>We have no objection to the state's spending more money to teach the foreigners the language and the laws. But if that is to be accomplished, the foreigners must have better working conditions and not be treated with contempt and arrogance.</p>
   <p>Then, too, those institutions must not be shown to the foreigner as ideal for which he left his native country, such as the army, for instance. If the patriots plan to unite the foreigners under the flag of militarism and defense, they will be disappointed.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0784.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The unification of the working masses not only of America but of all the world will be possible only under the standard of Socialist Democracy, international solidarity, brotherly love, and holy peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
