<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Hrvati u Americi</title>, 1st Volume, <date when="1927">1927</date><title level="a">Number of Croats in Chicago and Their Cultural Center in America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0757</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0757.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Hrvati u Americi</title>, 1st Volume, <date when="1927">1927</date><title level="a">Number of Croats in Chicago and Their Cultural Center in America.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is hard to determine the actual number of Croats in Chicago. By the census taken in 1920, 9963 Jugoslavs were reported, but we are more than sure that there are 40,000 Croats alone in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The map of Jugoslav colonies in the United States prepared by the emigration office in Zagreb, Croatia, shows 125,000 Jugoslavs in Chicago and vicinity. Because of such a number Chicago was destined to become the center of our cultural life in America. The first pioneers of the so-called American "iliric era" came here. Under the editorship of Jhon Kovacevic the first Croatian newspaper in America, Zora, was founded, followed by the Chicago Sloboda, edited by Nick Polic. Georg Mamek later edited Branik, and Dr. A. Biankini started Hrvatska Zastava, later the Jugoslovenska Zaatava. Most Croatian newspapers had their beginning in Chicago. Up to now some forty have appeared. Chicago is the seat of the first Croatian lodge in the new world, - the Club Strosmayer - which in 1892 became a fraternal order.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0758.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago gave America the first Croatian Sokol in 1908, also the first Croatian singing society, Zora, was born here.</p>
   <p>Chicago is also the center of two of America's most important economic institutions. The fraternal order, Croatian Union of Illinois, united with the Fraternal Union of Pittsburgh, Pa. This organization and the First Croatian Building and Loan Association play a very important part in Croatian life in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
