<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. IX, No. 17,
<date when="1931-11-28">Nov. 28, 1931</date>
<title level="a">Protest</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0605</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0605.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. IX, No. 17,
<date when="1931-11-28">Nov. 28, 1931</date>
<title level="a">PROTEST</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because the official agent Mr. George Kolombatovic, representing the Belgrade military dictatorship, tried to tie our lodge to his Fascist machine in presenting a program for the relief of the poor.</p>
   <p>Our members met on November 15 and discussed his plot, and our executive committee was ordered to publish the following protest:</p>
   <p>"An announcement in the Chicago Daily News of October 29, stating that lodge number 209, C. F. U., participates in preparation of a carnival, which is only a preliminary campaign to the celebration of a military regime in Jugoslavia, is untrue and was inserted into said paper by the servants of the Belgrade government and without a permission or authority of our lodge.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, our lodge is most vigorously protesting against this <pb facs="5420779_2_0606.jpg" n="2"/>sinister and unauthorized announcement and declares that it has nothing in common with the preparation of said carnival as our members are well aware that this affair will not benefit the poor and unemployed people, but will favor American magnates and the Belgrade military dictators.</p>
   <p>"Our lodge supported and will always support in the future the struggle of the working people against poverty and tyranny, but will not allow employers' tyrants to use them politically.</p>
   <p>"Further, our lodge invites all Croatian fraternal unions' lodges to support the demands of the unemployed which will be presented by a special delegation to the United States Congress on December 7, 1931. At the same time our lodges should support the revolutionary struggle of our brothers in Jugoslavia against military dictatorship."</p>
   <p>Lodge 202 C. F. U. of Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>M. J. Brzovic, President.</p>
   <p>G. M. Skokie, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
