<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 20,
<date when="1920-08-21">August 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Just Let Them Do It</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 20,
<date when="1920-08-21">August 21, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">JUST LET THEM DO IT</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The city of New York spent 250,000 dollars for radium. That was a sensation and many disapproved it. The city, to excuse itself, declared that radium is the only remedy for cancer of which New Yorkers suffer a great deal.</p>
   <p>Only unintelligent people could reproach authorities for trying to do something to alleviate misery and to stop a malady like cancer.</p>
   <p>These same people who reproach the city of New York for spending $250,000 to cure cancer, accept with joy the news that the Federal Government appropriated hundreds of millions of dollars for cannons, warships and ammunition. What does that mean?</p>
   <p>People are pleased if something is done against health, life and progress, but dislike it if the same thing is done for health and civilization.</p>
   <p>If the state spent just one tenth part of the money that it is spending for militarism and preparations for war for cultural purposes, as for the fight <pb facs="5420779_2_0206.jpg" n="2"/>against tuberculosis, cancer, even against social diseases, the society would have a different appearance. There would be more health, happiness and beauty. But the state omits it or if it does spend money it is with remonstrations from certain circles, and then the sum of money is so small that it is not worth to mention.</p>
   <p>People like better to wreck and soil than to build and clean. They are directed by the present social order with its institutions and organs to act that way. They are guided by the church and school, political platforms, newspapers and social education. It seems that all this is done because the interests of the governing class demand so.</p>
   <p>Through sickness, ignorance and disorderliness of the masses, the governing class is able to make millions and hold the destiny of the working people.</p>
   <p>Who has the right and courage to condemn those progressive and sincere workers and intellectualists who with all their power attack in this class struggle to win equal rights and equal liberties for all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
