<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VIII, No. 67,
<date when="1925-06-04">June 4, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Women (Comrades) Join Our Organizations!</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VIII, No. 67,
<date when="1925-06-04">June 4, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">WOMEN (COMRADES) JOIN OUR ORGANIZATIONS!</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A half century ago participation of women in hired work was considered improper. But this viewpoint is forgotten today. A half century ago, in "cultured" states, which were developed industrially only a few tens of thousands of women were employed. Today the number of employed women nearly reaches the number of men. Today millions of women offer their working abilities, for minimum pay, to keep themselves and their families.</p>
   <p>In Europe and America, according to statistics, over sixty million women are employed. That is an enormous army of working slaves never counted before in the history of mankind. Wherever it is possible to employ a woman instead of a man the capitalist will do it. A woman according to her nature and education is without resistance against oppression and exploitation.</p>
   <p>The capitalist way of production with a steady tendency to exclude men from work, whenever possible, threw women in factories, ill-smelling shops and mines. The women joined the ranks of hired slaves just as men.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0191.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A logical sequence of that must be the joining of women in the struggle, on all lines, united with their men comrades. But that does not happen. Very few women are represented in organizations in proportion to their number as employed workers.</p>
   <p>In Jugoslavia, according to 1923 statistics, 26,007 women were employed. Quite a number for the factories and shops of the land, but of that number there is not one per cent organized.</p>
   <p>The aversion of women to join organizations is in close relation with their wages. The greater part of working women in Jugoslavia does not earn more per week than 100 dinars. This situation discourages women from trying to better their conditions by joining organizations with men workers, but they try it in a quite undignified manner; either by prostitution, or becoming spies and informers for their employers - as a last resort there is suicide left.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0192.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This moral, material and physical degradation of women workers and their miserable economical condition will continue as long as women consider themselves inferior in the class struggle for betterment of living conditions, and as long as they will not force their employers to honor them just as they do men workers who work and create things.</p>
   <p>For that reason all working women must join their respective organizations. The more organized workers there are, the more solidly they stand together, the better results will be accomplished.</p>
   <p>Only in unity and organized struggle with men workers will women escape exploitation and secure better working conditions and wages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
