<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>First All-Slavic Singing Festival</title>. Given by United Slavic Choral Societies,
<date when="1934-12-09">Sunday, December 9, 1934</date>, Chicago: Nat'l Print. and Publ. Co., 1934. P. 95
<title level="a">"Yugoslavs in the United States"</title><title level="a" type="sub">Their Contribution to American Culture and Civilization</title> By Jurica Bjankini

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0838</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0838.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>First All-Slavic Singing Festival. Given by United Slavic Choral Societies</title>,
<date when="1934-12-09">Sunday, December 9, 1934</date>, Chicago: Nat'l Print. and Publ. Co., 1934. P. 95
<title level="a">"YUGOSLAVS IN THE UNITED STATES"</title><title level="a" type="sub">Their Contribution to American Culture and Civilization</title> By Jurica Bjankini
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Claims were often advanced that among the crew on Columbus' caravels were some sailors from the Yugoslav dalmatian litoral, although facts to prove the claim are wanting, but not so hopes that the rich library of Dubrovnik might finally yield such substantiating facts.</p>
   <p>In August, 1586, the first "white child" was born in British Colonial America and named Virginia. This was in Sir Walter Raleigh's second colony on Roanoke Island, the 350th anniversary of which was just recently celebrated in American history. The colony was under the command of John White, who upon leaving it hurriedly, returning only in the spring of 1590, but then only to find the colony completely destroyed and all the colonists disappeared. As <pb facs="5420779_2_0839.jpg" n="2"/>White describes..."One of the chief trees or posts at the entrance had the bark taken off, and five feet from the ground, in fair capital letters, was graven CROATAN, without any cross or sign of distress.</p>
   <p>It can be conjectured that a Croatian ship calling at this first permanent settlement in America left its imprint on the tree, or even salvaged the entire settlement from the destruction that was taking place and hurriedly left only the name of their ship, the Croatan on the tree, but that it met destruction by the elements or some other way later, as no trace was ever found of the colonists in question. Whatever the facts, an island in the group off the coast of North Carolinais named, in deference to this historical bit, to the present day, "Croatan". This constitutes the first recorded history linking America with Yugoslavs, or their Croatian branch."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
