<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jugoslavenska Zastava</title> Vol. XV, No. 281,
<date when="1918-06-02">June 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Zvijezda (The Star)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0339</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0339.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jugoslavenska Zastava</title> Vol. XV, No. 281,
<date when="1918-06-02">June 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ZVIJEZDA (THE STAR)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Soon it will be five years since the first Croatian theatrical association was established in Chicago under the name "Zvijezda," (The Star).</p>
   <p>Five years have passed and yet a great number of Croatians in Chicago do not know that "Zvijezda" exists, or its aim and purpose.</p>
   <p>"Zvijezda" is not a political but a theatrical association with the purpose of bringing plays written in Croatian language before the Croatian public. Its members may belong to whatever political party. That is unimportant. The main thing for each member is to attend the rehearsals punctually, to follow instructions of the teacher, to be willing and have ability to play. Each member does not decide what shall we play, but "how must I play it." Another thing is that we have a great number of intelligent young men and women, who not only are not members of our theatrical organization, but they do not attend the given plays. Yet, those who do not bring anything toward the success of our stage are the sharpest critics.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0340.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is easy to understand that members of a theatrical ensemble have many hardships to endure. Attending to their private work, they have to spend evenings at rehearsals, which last late in the night. Giving their best to the public they are criticized often unfavorably and besides have to pay the bills.</p>
   <p>We hope all that has been said will be understood by the public and that our coming season in connection with our fifth anniversary will start with a more active membership and with a more numerous public. This anniversary coincides with the convention of the National Croatian Union.</p>
   <p>"Svijezda" will be prepared with an excellent program for that occasion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
