<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Chicago Tribune</title>
      <date when="1934-07-08">July 8, 1934</date>
      <title level="a">Silver Jubilee Fete Planned by Little Croatia. 10000 So. Chicagoans to Attend Picnic.</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>The Chicago Tribune</title>
     <date when="1934-07-08">July 8, 1934</date>
     <title level="a">SILVER JUBILEE FETE PLANNED BY LITTLE CROATIA. 10000 SO. CHICAGOANS TO ATTEND PICNIC.</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Picturesque little Croatia, approximately three miles around and with 96th Street and Escanaba Ave. at its hub, will celebrate its 25th anniversary with a colorful old Country picnic Sunday August 26, in Eggers grove 114 St. and Ave. D.</p>
   <p>At least 10,000 Croatians are expected to be present in native costumes--fancy full skirts and blouses, braided shirts and breeches. All will speak Croatian, although some of them know French and some can speak English fluently.</p>
   <p>The Rev. Spiro Andrijanich, pastor of the Croatian Roman Catholic Church will assist with the program. Masses will be held under trees.</p>
   <p>"Every Croatian is requested to join in the festivities and demonstrate to Chicago the beauty and simplicity of our people", Father Andrijanich says. For those who do not have native costumes, women of the church are now making garments. These costumes are to be saved and worn at our future celebra <pb facs="5420779_2_0747.jpg" n="2"/>tions.</p>
   <p>TRY GROWING TOBACCO.</p>
   <p>Nearly every Croatian in South Chicago who has a small garden tries his luck at tobacco raising after he is through with his toil at the steel mills. Back in the old country where the climate is similar to Chicago's, much tobacco is raised, so it should grow here, says Mr. Brunski, one of the picnic directors. And tobacco is not the only thing the Croatians of S. Chicago try to raise, for, according to Mr. Brunski, a big family is the pride and joy of every man. Instead of wanting more boys than girls, however, the South Chicago Croatians want more girls, because, it is said, more than five-eights of all children born are boys.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
