<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1929-04-27">April 27, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Announcing May Day Red Week</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0390</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0390.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1929-04-27">April 27, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">ANNOUNCING MAY DAY RED WEEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>May Day will be celebrated beginning April 28, to May 5th. Because the first day of May falls on Wednesday, which is a working day, and because an enormous amount of American labor is unorganized, we will not celebrate May Day in an organized fashion. Organized labor, especially in European countries, will leave factories, on that day machines will be stopped. Whistles and factory noise will cease. The power of the creators of wealth will be sensed and will again prove that no wheel in the factory can turn without the workers aid.</p>
   <p>It is regrettable that here in America at least not at this time, these principles cannot be observed. In some places, however, May Day will be observed Wednesday, that is, on May 1st. Some workers will leave factories and celebrate May Day as its customary in European countries. In other places they will celebrate on April 28 or on May 5, because these dates fall on Sunday.</p>
   <p>For our Jugoslav workers, however, the week of April 28 to May 5 should be the time to build a strong labor movement as we have never done before.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0391.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The best way to celebrate the workers' holiday is to devote it to the labor movement. The Jugoslav proletariat has only one labor paper in America, the Radnik. This paper can prosper and be useful only with the full confidence and cooperation of the Jugoslav proletariat. The Jugoslav proletariat has no interest in supporting various bourgeoisie papers who, whether directly or indirectly, zealously serve the ruling classes. Only one paper is left for them to support, enlarge and continually work for, and strengthen, - the Radnik.</p>
   <p>Our readers and sympathizers have a task ahead of them this coming week. The job is to visit other workers who do not read Radnik and acquaint them with the movement and get them to subscribe to Radnik.</p>
   <p>The May Day number is coming in a large edition, an eight-page special. You ought to order now several extra numbers for the agitation.</p>
   <p>If every reader brings one new subscription this week, it will mean a double circulation for Radnik. This is possible, every comrade is <pb facs="5420779_2_0392.jpg" n="3"/>capable of getting one or more new readers. Celebrate May Day constructively.</p>
   <p>M. Krasic</p>
   <p>Manager</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
