<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1931-03-07">Mar. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Philosophy of the Second Generation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title>,
<date when="1931-03-07">Mar. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE SECOND GENERATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A lecture and discussion took place Friday, February 27 at the Jugoslav Free Forum, with Mr. T. Cotton, director of the Foreign Language Information Service of New York, as the principal speaker.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cotton defined the term "second generation" to mean the offspring of parents of foreign birth who reside here as aliens or as citizens. He referred with concise brevity to the ancient Greeks and Chinese, to the Romans and other nations which had at some time achieved a high degree of civilization. He pointed out that each of them had received other peoples into its midst, had taken over the best in their cultures, had adopted their most useful customs, and had emulated their finest traits, thereby enriching its own native civilization. The speaker urged that this hospitable reception of "foreign" elements should be practiced by America, which is nothing more than a mixture of various nationalities and races....</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0749.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Cotton also urged the children of the foreign-born to learn, in addition to English, the language spoken by their parents, since they have such a ready opportunity to acquire a knowledge of two languages. It was likewise his opinion that the children should make their own the best that their parents have brought over from the old country--its poetry, its music, its beautiful dress, and its high ideals--and should acquaint the American public with these aspects of the culture of the Old World. In this way, he said, a twofold purpose would be served: first, the children would know two languages, and would thus broaden their mental horizon, their culture, and their knowledge of languages; and second, American civilization would be enriched. (We don't always find ourselves in agreement with all this talk about high ideals. We have observed too often that the English element here regards itself as superior to all others, and that the Germans consider themselves the most cultured, ueber alles.--The Editor.) In this way, he continued, the prejudices of chauvinist Americans against foreigners would be dissolved. Americans would realize the significant contributions the immigrant could make toward increasing <pb facs="5420779_2_0750.jpg" n="3"/>the cultural wealth of America, and in this way a more advanced civilization would gradually emerge.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cotton urged his audience to participate in the ensuing discussion. The response was gratifying; some agreed with his views, others disagreed. Several people maintained that his ideas were not feasible in view of the obstacles offered by the American school system and American public opinion.</p>
   <p>One of our well-known leaders, George Mamek, in a brief talk, criticized sharply the cruel, materialistic philosophy of life professed by most Americans, who think in terms of their pocketbooks, and forget their souls. It is in that spirit that they bring up their children, and it is that philosophy which gradually communicates itself to the immigrant, especially to the one who comes here to improve his economic condition. Mr. Mamek's words were enthusiastically acclaimed. After considerable further discussion, the following resolution was offered:</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0751.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Our Credo</p>
   <p>"1. We believe the presence of a variety of people stimulates creative cultural activity.</p>
   <p>"2. We believe our children should be brought up in such a way as to develop their individuality.</p>
   <p>"3. We believe our children should know, at the very least, two languages and two cultures.</p>
   <p>"4. We believe that the organizations of the foreign born are the best medium for cultural assimilation and transformation.</p>
   <p>"5. We believe the children should join their parents in these organizations of the foreign born.</p>
   <p>"6. We believe that this credo is in the best interests of our children and of our new country, America."</p>
   <p>Everyone must certainly have benefited from this lecture. It stimulated many <pb facs="5420779_2_0752.jpg" n="5"/>to think, and that in itself is a big gain. Our only regret is that there were not more people at the lecture, especially young people, since the principal topic was youth, and our young people could have profited by attending.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
