<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 26,
<date when="1920-10-02">Oct. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">How to Achieve It</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0775</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0775.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 26,
<date when="1920-10-02">Oct. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">HOW TO ACHIEVE IT</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is figured that there are in the United States seventeen million persons of foreign birth. Six millions of them are not able to read, write or speak English. Seven million of them like rather to talk and to read their own language than English.</p>
   <p>These figures scare some of the Americans. They wonder why these people do not learn English. The Americans are the only people in the world who care little or not at all for foreign languages. If they know English they believe that the world is theirs. Other languages are vulgar, unnecessary and funny. There exists fanaticism and chauvinism regarding language like regarding the fatherland. These same people would like to have foreigners, as soon as they reach America, to be able to master the English language. That is impossible. Languages are not learned easily if they are not taught in childhood. That is known to all those who either in school or by their own study acquired knowledge of languages. Besides foreigners are not welcome here very well. They are compelled to mix with their fellow nationals, and just for that reason have no opportunity to learn English.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0776.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If there would be more congeniality, less pride and exposing of Americanism, the foreigners would like America better than they do. How could they love America when they are persecuted, made fun of, when they are scorned. Theirs is the hardest and dirtiest work.</p>
   <p>Only economic and civic equality could draw foreigners to America and make them learn the English language little by little, of which the cultural wealth is certainly great. This fact is not comprehended by millions of foreigners, because they are broken by excessive work, besides they suffer from social unequality, national fanaticism, false pride, many of them consider themselves to be just temporary residents, nursing hopes to return to their own country as soon as possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
