<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 23,
<date when="1937-06-09">June 9, 1937</date>
<title level="a">(Official Organ Croatian Fraternal Union) Children's Home of the Croatian Fraternal Union. Post-School Season Finds All Boys and Girls on the Farm.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 23,
<date when="1937-06-09">June 9, 1937</date>
<title level="a">(Official Organ Croatian Fraternal Union) CHILDREN'S HOME OF THE CROATIAN FRATERNAL UNION. POST-SCHOOL SEASON FINDS ALL BOYS AND GIRLS ON THE FARM.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among other news of the Children's Home, we believe that our members would like to hear something about our farm. There are about twenty-five acres of our own land under cultivation and thirty-five acres which are rented every year close to our farm. In the last six years our farm has improved very much and, although we have only one man taking care of the farm work which includes the fields, garden, cows, horses, pigs and chickens, our products are increasing every year.</p>
   <p>A few years ago we had only six cows. Today we have twelve milking cows and five heifers. We have two horses, which are considered the best in this part of the country. Every summer we have about fifty young pigs which are used in the Home. Every spring the Home used to buy 500 small chickens.</p>
   <p>Our grade school will be out this week and the children will be assigned to do some work in the garden and fields. The bigger boys will have to help with the hay and harvest and the smaller boys and girls will help in weeding and picking <pb facs="5420779_2_0655.jpg" n="2"/>the vegetables.</p>
   <p>This year our work will be organized under special supervision of a man who will divide the children in groups and supervise the work. Our superintendent has many other things to do, which makes it impossible for him to stay with the children when they have to do garden work. To tell the truth, many children have to be closely watched at work, otherwise they turn everything into play. Those who will not perform their work properly will be deprived of the swimming pool privilege.</p>
   <p>Our committee bought a new Allis Chalmers tractor, a disc and corn planter which makes our farm work much more productive.</p>
   <p>John Kirasic and</p>
   <p>John Crlencic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
