<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danica Hrvatska</title>* (Croatian Morning Star), No. 62,
<date when="1932-06-11">June 11, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">First Concert of the Croatian Singing Society Hrvatska (Croatia)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danica Hrvatska* (Croatian Morning Star)</title>, No. 62,
<date when="1932-06-11">June 11, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST CONCERT OF THE CROATIAN SINGING SOCIETY HRVATSKA (CROATIA)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With great interest the Croatians of the West Side of Chicago awaited the first concert of the newly organized Croatian singing society "Hrvatska." It was felt that the success of this concert meant whether the society will remain in existence or not.</p>
   <p>Because the singing society "Hrvatska" was organized to bring into its folds all singers, ladies and gentlemen, who are not to be helpers or mere onlookers at so-called Jugoslav celebrations, to the detriment of their own Croatian name, it is easily understood that there were such "patriots" who wished failure. Now that success has come, they will try to belittle this success and acclaim by the public.</p>
   <p>The president of the society, Mr. J. Cizmezia, at the concert on Sunday, August 26th, in his introductory speech gave the aim and purpose of the</p>
   <p>* New York City <pb facs="5420779_2_0269.jpg" n="2"/>society, which is to cultivate Croatian singing, to serve for education and culture and by its work keep up Croatian consciousness and pride.</p>
   <p>The Croatian Ladies' Club sent a basket of flowers with a card attached to it reading, "The Croatian Ladies' Club is pleased with the progress of Croatian culture in America and congratulate the Croatian singing society "Hrvatska" at its first performance, wishing success and to be worthy of their to us so dear a name, Hrvatska (Croatia)."</p>
   <p>After the greeting of the president, the curtain was drawn up and the newly organized Croatian singing society appeared before the public for the first time. The public was silent for the first few moments as they were enraptured. Then they burst into enthusiastic applause to greet the bearers of Croatian song. It is said that the first impression is lasting. But the impression was not only good but excellent. We hope and wish it will remain.</p>
   <p>The stage offered a delightful spectacle: thirty female singers, dressed <pb facs="5420779_2_0270.jpg" n="3"/>in modest but elegant dresses of the same style, like real sisters. The ladies chorus, presided over by Mrs. M. Devich, decided to wear dresses of the same color and style at this concert.</p>
   <p>The first number on the program was rendered by the male chorus; the second, by the ladies chorus; the third, by the mixed chorus of the society.</p>
   <p>The conductor, Mr. Ivan Horvat, did his best to instruct the singers in such a short time in very difficult songs. When the mixed chorus finished with the song "An Evening on the Sava River," the ice was broken for singers and hearers. The singers were rewarded with enthusiastic and stormy applause. It was like a christening under the fire of ambition for the furtherance of Croatian song, Croatian thinking, Croatian existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0271.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Thus on the West Side of Chicago on 18th Street, in the most populated settlement of Croatians, appeared in public for the first time the Croatian singing society "Hrvatska" with the slogan: With Culture to Liberty. God grant it.</p>
   <p>Karlo W. Batrinski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
