<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. IV, No. 5,
<date when="1921-05-07">May 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Immigration</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0861</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0861.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. IV, No. 5,
<date when="1921-05-07">May 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IMMIGRATION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Soon a law will be passed to restrict immigration to the United States. According to that law just a certain percent of people from different countries will be admitted to America.</p>
   <p>The purpose of this law is to curb immigration and end unemployment. They think that unemployment is caused by a great number of workers.</p>
   <p>Without doubt the American Congress has great politicians and diplomats, above all great economists.</p>
   <p>One paper remarks: "Those who are against immigration have no brains. This country needs one hundred million more people. Now we cannot sell goods to Europe, but if we had another hundred million inhabitants here, we could sell to them."</p>
   <p>Would a greater number of population lower wages? No. When in America there were four million people, wages were 50 cents per day. Cost of living was <pb facs="5420779_2_0862.jpg" n="2"/>lower and the worker lived as good as today. The increase of population did not lower wages. Increase to two hundred million of population would increase wages; more people, greater production, bigger markets, more property.</p>
   <p>In fact a great flood of immigrants would not harm the workers. On the other hand, it would help them.</p>
   <p>The immigrants would make up that great army of workers, by which the capitalist were able to crush any struggle of resident workers for a better existence.</p>
   <p>Today there is great unemployment. Numerous immigrants would increase it more. That would make the immigrant think as well as the resident worker that in a capitalistic land, however rich, there is no existence; the less conditions will improve as long as this system prevails.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0863.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It seems that the American capitalists fear this possibility of making workers think. There were times when immigrants were welcome; today they are feared, are becoming dangerous for America.</p>
   <p>America is a vast and rich land which could, under more rational management, feed a few hundred millions of people. But to have it cultivated that way, more working hands are necessary.</p>
   <p>The trouble is not that there are too many workers, but too few. Now there are too many because the industrialists, bankers and merchants are not able to export their wares and products to foreign countries, while the workers are not paid enough to consume all the produced goods. That is what makes an overbalance of produced goods and working power.</p>
   <p>Now to improve this situation.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0864.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The workers must take over the government, take over the means of production and transportation. Then they will solve the problem of unemployment, immigration and all other questions which hover like dark clouds over present day humanity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
