<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. V, No. 38,
<date when="1912-09-05">Sept. 5, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">One Step Forward</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. V, No. 38,
<date when="1912-09-05">Sept. 5, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">ONE STEP FORWARD</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The office of our paper Radnicka Straza (Workingmen's Guard) was moved to 1829 Blue Island Avenue, Chicago. The moving of our office needs some explanation.</p>
   <p>This moving is not a common moving. It is a very important step. The Central Committee of the Croatian Section acted in accord with the committees of the Serbian and Slovenian Sections of the South Slavic Socialist Federation. In the same offices there are located now the editor and administration of the newspaper Proletarec(Proletarian), the Slovenian organ of our Federation.</p>
   <p>Soon there will be located a third paper, Narodni Glass (People's Voice). That will fulfill a long cherished wish to have all three Socialist papers under one roof. That will facilitate our work, which will be more effective better united.</p>
   <p>At this occasion we want to remind all that the Central Committee decided that our paper, starting with the New Year, will be issued in 8 pages weekly.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0475.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If we take into account the present financial standing of Radnicka Straza, which standing, if not so rosy, is better than in former years and if we can depend on the cooperation of our comrades, it appears to us that we will be able to issue our paper in eight pages weekly without great difficulties.</p>
   <p>But, we know, our hopes are not facts. We need action, the cooperation of our friends, of those who wish to make our newspaper bigger and better, and, is there one who does not wish that?</p>
   <p>The enlargement of our paper depends upon the increase of subscribers. Comrades, work with all your might to make our organ, your organ, bigger and better!</p>
   <p>Work for our press, Radnicka Straza, Narodni Glass and Proletarec!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
