<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VI, No. 33,
<date when="1923-09-08">Sept. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">1,800 Immigrants Deported</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0848</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0848.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VI, No. 33,
<date when="1923-09-08">Sept. 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">1,800 IMMIGRANTS DEPORTED</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Their steamer docked a few minutes before midnight of September 1st. They will be deported as belonging to the quota for August.</p>
   <p>How imbecile and inhuman the immigration law is, was demonstrated by the newest occurrence, which will end in deportation of 1,800 immigrants who were brought to the door of America to be returned to their homeland by decision from the lowest to the highest instances. Their only fault is the fact that they arrived at the American shores a few minutes before midnight of September 1st on the steamers Esperanca, Esthonia, Braga and Byron. The captains of said ships raced to the shores to enable their travelers to be counted in the September quota of immigrants. Bad luck wanted that they arrived a few minutes sooner and the immigration officials booked then on the August quota, which was filled.</p>
   <p>Many believed that the mental limitation of the immigration officials <pb facs="5420779_2_0849.jpg" n="2"/>would not be so great as to prevent such a tremendous mass of people access to the shores on account of a trifling mistake. But it happened differently. The Secretary of Labor and his officialdom won a great victory. Eighteen hundred persons were forbidden to land.</p>
   <p>It is for us to state that this procedure was an unheard of act of brutality in our century of civilization and progress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
