<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>. Vol. X, No. 48,
<date when="1917-11-07">Nov. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Emigration to Europe after the War</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0871</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0871.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>. Vol. X, No. 48,
<date when="1917-11-07">Nov. 7, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">EMIGRATION TO EUROPE AFTER THE WAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The news is going around that after the war two or three millions of people may leave the United States.</p>
   <p>Steamship companies receive numerous requests for information as to whether it will be possible to go to Europe immediately after the termination of the war.</p>
   <p>Immigration Commissioner Howe says that during the first year after the war over two millions of immigrants will leave for Europe. Other officials of the Bureau of Immigration claim that the emigration to Europe after the war will be three to four millions. It is clear that America will feel badly this emigration to Europe.</p>
   <p>The steamship companies report that they have received requests from over one million people anxious to leave for Europe. Many employers from the West report that a great number of workers from the lands of the <pb facs="5420779_2_0872.jpg" n="2"/>Central Powers want to return home. A movement exists to prepare these peoples for their return home. The banks report that Poles, Italians and Russians save as much money as they can to return home. The reasons for this are many. Many want to see their parents and relatives, of whom they did not hear for many years.</p>
   <p>In America there are about 15 million of people today who were born in Europe. For most of them it was impossible to hear anything about the fate of their relatives and that makes them anxious to go and see how it looks at home.</p>
   <p>Many will return on account of family properties, left in many cases without male owners, which properties will come into the possession of those who return from America.</p>
   <p>The economic conditions in Europe after the war will not be much worse than here in America. There is the possibility that the European governments <pb facs="5420779_2_0873.jpg" n="3"/>will forbid emigration after the war, to keep those who are able to work at home.</p>
   <p>The English government has plans to distribute lands to soldiers. Germany also will keep her sons at home. To Scotland and Ireland many hundred of thousands will return.</p>
   <p>Thus after the war America will feel the loss of many workers who will try to find better opportunities for their existence in Europe. Whether these workers will fare better in Europe nobody can tell. The main thing is they expect great changes in Europe and live in the hope that the economic conditions there will be better than here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
