<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 41,
<date when="1924-04-05">April 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Second Convention of the Jugoslav Section of the Labor Party</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 41,
<date when="1924-04-05">April 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">SECOND CONVENTION OF THE JUGOSLAV SECTION OF THE LABOR PARTY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On March, 1924, delegates of the Jugoslav Section of the American Labor Party met to consider the activities of the past year and to ponder about their future work and duties toward the Jugoslav proletarians in the United States. The convention lasted four days; fifty-five delegates were present who represented all our sections from Los Angeles to New York.</p>
   <p>After the election of officers and different committeemen, Comrade Ruthenberg, representative of the Central Executive Committee of the party, took the floor. "Our aim," said the speaker, " is to destroy the capitalistic system, to break up the power of the capitalistic class, to restore the government of the workers and farmers. That is our aim, that is our only salvation."</p>
   <p>The secretary reported about the activities of the past year.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0056.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Daily Worker received from the Jugoslav Section of the party more support than was expected, the secretary said. The campaign for the defence of foreign-born workers was most effective. From August 1923 to March 1924, twenty-four sections were established. The membership of the Jugoslav Labor Party is estimated to be over 1,500.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Mr. Fisher, editor of Radnik. He explained the difficulties when the paper started to be published thrice a week. The aim of the editor is to make Radnik an aggressive political organ.</p>
   <p>Then resolutions on different subjects were adopted. A new committee was elected. Comrade Bogosavljevic was on his way to the West to travel to Russia and he took with him greetings to the Jugoslav workers at Kazbas in Russia.</p>
   <p>The convention ended its duties with great unanimity of purpose. A new spirit and willingness to work were manifested everywhere.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
