<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1915-12-01">Dec. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Zora (Dawn) in the Service of Russian Czarism</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0919</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0919.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1915-12-01">Dec. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ZORA (DAWN) IN THE SERVICE OF RUSSIAN CZARISM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Thursday, November 25, in the Pilsen Auditorium the Zora (Dawn) Croatian Singing Society gave its entertainment and concert.</p>
   <p>It was announced in advance that this affair would be attended not only by our doctors, lawyers, and clergy but also by the representative of his majesty our Russian father, the representative of Czar Nicholas, the consul Wolf (a true Russian)!</p>
   <p>In came the doctors, the lawyers, and the clergy. Finally in came his excellency the Russian consul.</p>
   <p>The concert began with the Croatian anthem, greeted with applause as the audience rose to its feet. Also his excellency did rise--the Russian consul. To repay him for his courtesy and to show their fidelity to the Russian Czar, Cora intoned the Russian hymn, "Boze Carja Hrani" (God Protect Our Czar).</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0920.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the singing the audience burst into deafening applause, and especially great was the enthusiasm shown at the table of his excellency, the consul.</p>
   <p>Did those present think for a moment how the Russians, the common people, suffer in Russia under the rule of that bloodthirsty Czar to whom 'Zora' sings, "God Protect Him"?</p>
   <p>Is it not just that "brother of yours," the Russian Czar, who stifles any liberal movement as unmercifully as Francis Joseph of Austria-Hungary does?</p>
   <p>For the singing of the Russian hymn Zora expected a little donation of only fifty dollars, but an even hundred dollars was presented to it by the Russian consul Wolf.</p>
   <p>When little services are rewarded like that, we are sure that Russia will not let down the patriotic Croatian and Serbian press which must be considered as as advance agent for Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0921.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Here we are able to apply the words of the immortal Lincoln:</p>
   <p>"You can fool all the people some of the time; you can fool some of the people all the time; but you cannot fool all the people all the time."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
