<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jugoslavia</title> Vol. XII, No. 9,
<date when="1922-09-16">Sept. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">To the Immigrants</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0853</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0853.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jugoslavia</title> Vol. XII, No. 9,
<date when="1922-09-16">Sept. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE IMMIGRANTS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Brother immigrant, you who come for the first time here, we greet you from our heart.</p>
   <p>Look, a blessed sun shines on you, good will is all around you. Brother, this country is good; this state is good, where you have come, where with courage and hope you may start a new life.</p>
   <p>Do not fear, brother, do not fear the uncertainty and the unknown, the possibility of defeat, because this country will like you. Do not fear, brother, but have confidence in yourself and in your strength and step on American soil with an invincible faith in a country which is beautiful, good and free. This country will understand you, will return your love if in love you do approach her.</p>
   <p>Look around, brother, here is everything great, gigantic. You are not yet used to these tall buildings, the skyscrapers. Brother, these buildings were built by men just like you are, who, poor and unknown <pb facs="5420779_2_0854.jpg" n="2"/>came from the old country.</p>
   <p>Here everybody is an immigrant or the child of an immigrant. The great and powerful who own millions today did not bring with them anything but their determination and common sense, their busy hands which were able to create, which were able to strike when it was necessary.</p>
   <p>It is not true that there are no more possibilities here today. It is not true that life is harder than it was before. Do not believe him who will say to you that here is the bitter bread, the hard life. Do not trust him. Because here is open to you every road, every door, every career. Before you is that grandiose life, this powerful state, which will give you the possibility to live, to work, and to be happy.</p>
   <p>Here you are your own master, you are a gentleman, a real man, you are just as good as the owner of millions, and you have not to now if you pass somebody in a guilded carriage, someone of a royal family.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0855.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>You have not to take your hat off before anybody, only before your God, brother. All is yours, what you make by your work and thinking capacity. Do not fear, brother. That is your country, which is accepting you among her own hundred millions, just like a mother takes a returning child.</p>
   <p>Be not afraid, brother. You will efface the black and doleful memories which accompanied you from the old country. Do not care what happened abroad. A new man you are now, the Atlantic voyage changed you, from today alone count what you know and what you do. It may be that you are ignorant, that you will find out soon. The life and school abroad put in your head things which are of no value here. That makes no difference. You will start to learn anew, because you have intelligence, because you have power, because you have tenacity, you are the one whom they need here. You will master life. You will live in palaces and rides in automobiles; to achieve that you must have self-confidence and not waver for a second.</p>
   <p>Always be of good cheer. Here they do not like people who despair and <pb facs="5420779_2_0856.jpg" n="4"/>worry continually. Here the only person is lost who is his own grave-digger.</p>
   <p>Do not fear, brother. Underscore your former life with a double line and start anew.</p>
   <p>What you did before does not count. You must forget all. Open your life to a new spirit, to new impressions. You will start here like a big child who must learn everything from the start. Just that beginning from the start will give you force and elasticity. We greet you on the sill of a new life and new fortune.</p>
   <p>America bids you her welcome. America encourages you that you will fare well in this country. Keep up your chin, be well disposed, smiling. Step on these shores of this gay, young and rich country. God and fortune brought you here; your courage, your own strength will carry you along.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
