<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 19,
<date when="1937-05-12">May 12, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Why We Must Join the Croatian Fraternal Union</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0597</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0597.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 19,
<date when="1937-05-12">May 12, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">WHY WE MUST JOIN THE CROATIAN FRATERNAL UNION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We must interpret our union the way it really is. Many talk against their own organization. They do it out of ignorance. They do not read the official organ, they do not read the by-laws, they do not attend meetings, but at some other place they gossip against the fraternal union.</p>
   <p>If you ask someone why he did not attend the last meeting, he will be in a dilemma as to what to answer. The answers are mostly self-invented thoughts, such as: "I think my reserve is exhausted. I did not pay dues for so long. I am out of the Fraternal Union." All these excuses are wrong. If a member did not receive a note from his secretary he still belongs to his local, or he will be invited to pay up before he is dropped from membership. The members forget the union until they need it.</p>
   <p>Many say insurance is better than the Croatian Fraternal Union. Why?</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0598.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In an insurance company the children are insured for ten cents per week, that makes forty cents per month. The Croatian Fraternal Union insures for 25 cents per month. From this union there is a benefit for the first year of $25; from an insurance company, $15. I think it is clear why each member of any family should join during this membership drive. There is no initiation fee, doctor's fee or other expense.</p>
   <p>Many fathers are the only members of a family who belong to the Union. If each of these fathers brings his whole family into the Croatian Fraternal Union, we will have 150,000 members.</p>
   <p>Then, fathers, register your children in the Union. By that you will have three benefits: your family will get insured, you will receive all the benefits given by the Union and you will double the ranks of our union. For that reason join the Croatian Fraternal Union.</p>
   <p>Jerkobezic</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
