<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. P. K. Kufrin</title>, 2334 S. Drake Ave., Chicago, Ill., by Philip Matkovic,
<date when="1937-06-22">June 22, 1937</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0254</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0254.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. P. K. Kufrin</title>, 2334 S. Drake Ave., Chicago, Ill., by Philip Matkovic,
<date when="1937-06-22">June 22, 1937</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Paul Kelecic Kufrin, world famous sculptor, graduated in Zagreb, Croatia, in 1905. Two years later he entered the United States, where he followed his art. As a young artist, back in 1917, he made a bust of Lloyd George, British War Premier, which attracted to him the attention of the artists of the world. He received many complimentary notices in the world press. La Revue Moderne de la Vie, an international artists magazine, made favorable comments on his work on his work on several occasions.</p>
   <p>At the international exposition (The World's Fair) in Chicago in 1933, he received first prize, a gold medal, for his bust of Clarence Darrow.</p>
   <p>His bust of President Franklin D. Roosevelt is now displayed in Toman Library, 27th and Pulaski Road. All Chicago newspapers printed complimentary articles on his work in the Sunday issues of June 20, 1937.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kuprin designed all the brass decorations for the Federal Reserve <pb facs="5420779_2_0255.jpg" n="2"/>Bank of Chicago. He also completed the relief decorations of the Assyrian Arts Room in the Field's Museum.</p>
   <p>He refuses to have anything to do with the Jugoslav regime. Being a Croatian, he does not approve of the way his country is treated by the Serbs, and they, in turn, interfere with his commercial work through their representatives and sympathizers here in Chicago. He is a member of the Bohemian Artists Society and the American Arts Club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
