<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. IX, No. 2,
<date when="1931-08-08">Aug. 8, 1931</date>
<title level="a">Branch Number 1, Croatian Radisa Ends Connection with Federation of Croatian Radisa of America</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. IX, No. 2,
<date when="1931-08-08">Aug. 8, 1931</date>
<title level="a">BRANCH NUMBER 1, CROATIAN RADISA ENDS CONNECTION WITH FEDERATION OF CROATIAN RADISA OF AMERICA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Branch No. 1, Croatian Radisa, in Chicago, condemns the self-styled action of the Central Committee of the federation of branches of Croatian Radisa in America and Canada. By breaking the by-laws and besmearing the name of the executive president as well as violating the trust of the branches, the Central Committee displayed its selfishness and absolutism, lack of respect for order and peace, as well as interest in the purpose for which the Croatian Radisa is dedicated, not to mention the poltical partiality which they in so unjustified a manner have pulled into the federation to its detriment.</p>
   <p>Branch No. 1, after a reasonable and sincere effort to solve the difficulty with the Central Committee in a just and becoming manner, is convinced that the committee does not care to respect the by-laws, and that with such a committee work and solidarity is impossible.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0610.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Therefore, at their regular meeting held last July 28, Branch No. 1 unanimously decided to quit the Federation B. C. R., and, in the future, work independently for Croatian Radisa. This we announce to all the branches in America and Canada, and to the public in general.</p>
   <p>V. Kovacic, president.</p>
   <p>G. Horvatic, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
