<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1928-01-24">Jan. 24, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">An Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1928-01-24">Jan. 24, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">AN EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The gentry, priests and their lackeys with other misleaders are preparing a more intense compaign against progressives and Communists. We notice continuous and increasing attacks in the columns of Hrvatski List &amp; Danica, Hrvatski Glasnik, and a few more Croatian newspapers. Their bitter attacks are especially directed against those with Radnik in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Those who had the opportunity to follow the development and procedure of the last C. F. U. convention should have been convinced as to what happened.</p>
   <p>While a few years ago a real understanding prevailed among the working class, they knew the way to render their imitators in a manner that would not prevent their rising again in some other form.</p>
   <p>Since then workers have learned much from them. They also learned in other struggles to benefit their own interest, to fight for their rights.</p>
   <p>We may mention here about conditions after the first C. F. U. convention. As soon as they manipulated control of the majority, the clerics with <pb facs="5420779_2_0621.jpg" n="2"/>their aid, immediately decided on action to eliminate at all cost anything that is progressive, regardless of what side it comes from.</p>
   <p>An enlarged committee of C. F. U. is in session at present. Our clergy expects a lot from it; they may get it, it wouldn't surprise us.</p>
   <p>But as far as workers are concerned, they don't expect much. We know what they did in the miners' strike. We have had experiences with their organ, Zajednicar, which ridicules our fight between labor and capital, and their assault on the International Labor Defense.</p>
   <p>Members of C. F. U. should not expect better executives from the present central committee; they are not to be found there.</p>
   <p>The only way out of this predicament is for members to take daily a more active part in current business affairs of lodges, and to educate them-selves so that they can better understand conditions in general and will <pb facs="5420779_2_0622.jpg" n="3"/>know the gentlemen of C. F. U., so they will be able to supervise their work and eventually take over the management.</p>
   <p>All who have the progress of Zajednicar at heart and feel injustice and corruption in their ranks, must sooner or later find their place among progressive lines.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
