<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 38,
<date when="1915-09-01">Sept. 1, 1915</date>
<title level="a">Grown-Ups Idle -- Children Work</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 38,
<date when="1915-09-01">Sept. 1, 1915</date>
<title level="a">GROWN-UPS IDLE -- CHILDREN WORK</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Five years ago I started to work for Gutmann and Company in Chicago. This company pays $1.50 per day for ten hours work. The company, probably on account of bad times, started to exact more work from the workers at the same rate of pay. At the same time children from 14 to 15 years of age were put to work. They work ten hours per day and get $4.50 per week.</p>
   <p>Two such boys put out of work of two grown-up workers and receive half of their pay.</p>
   <p>Last week the factory inspector came to see about the boys and the company was in a bad fix. The factory inspector could order the boys laid off -- all of them cheap labor.</p>
   <p>The foreman told the boys that the inspector will put them in jail if he finds them here. The boys were induced to leave the factory as long as the inspector was there.</p>
   <p>Of course it all was a fake, and the inspector knowing it well. If the <pb facs="5420779_2_0169.jpg" n="2"/>inspector would not have made known his coming how could the company have known about it and have hidden her little slaves that the inspector could not see them?</p>
   <p>But all laws of today are a fake. For that reason they do not give to the worker any protection. For that reason the workers have to struggle to become lawmakers in our society and not slaves like they are today.</p>
   <p>May we add, there is not oppression or lawlessness just in one or other company but in all companies, everywhere because such is the system.</p>
   <p>The workers have to declare war on that system, leave alone different leaders and their newspapers, read their Socialist papers and prepare them-selves to destroy that system.</p>
   <p>Every worker has to enter that struggle in the interests of his children, who as cheap child labor, take away the bread of their fathers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
