<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VI, No. 34,
<date when="1923-09-11">September 11, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting against War</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0092</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0092.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VI, No. 34,
<date when="1923-09-11">September 11, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING AGAINST WAR</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jugoslav, Greek, and Italian associations of the Workers Party held a protest meeting against war preparations between Italy, Greece and Jugoslavia. The meeting was held at Carriers Hall, in Chicago, and was a success which displayed solidarity among Italian, Greek, and Jugoslav workers. All these workers registered complete disapproval of the policy their respective governments are pursuing. This meeting showed a true picture of the feeling of these people against Pasich, Venizelos, and Mussolini. The workers of these lands cannot allow (themselves) to be dragged to the battlefields in the interests of those who exploited and oppressed them. Every effort toward the making of war must be met by the workers' motto: "Death to War!"</p>
   <p>The following resolution was adopted:</p>
   <p>Today we are witnessing the development of European capitalistic states, three of which are ready to grab one another by the throat and throw their peoples into dangerous war, which would undoubtedly end with the <pb facs="5420779_2_0093.jpg" n="2"/>massacre of thousands of workers for no other purpose than to keep up a blood-thirsty fascist regime and through a mercenary system exploit the working class.</p>
   <p>All these governments, Greek, Italian, and Jugoslav, have a record of suppression of the freedom of speech, press, and assembly. They have practically abolished the little power possessed by parliament and also general elections. They established and maintain an iron dictatorship, based on white terror, complete abolition of trade unions and political labor parties; destruction of workers printing presses, mass persecutions and attacks on workers throughout these three states.</p>
   <p>We, Jugoslav, Greek, and Italian workers, gathered at this open mass meeting in Hod-Carriers Hall, Chicago, hereby declare:</p>
   <p>That we have nothing in common with the aims and purposes for which those powers are preparing war.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0094.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We most energetically protest against imperialistic nations throwing our fellow workers into another war.</p>
   <p>We invite the workers of the world, and especially from Italy, Greece, and Jugoslavia, to do everything in their power to stop these imperialistic plans, and to struggle against the fascist terror.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
