<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 37,
<date when="1924-03-27">March 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Protest Meeting of Jugoslav Workers of Chicago</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0772</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0772.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VII, No. 37,
<date when="1924-03-27">March 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST MEETING OF JUGOSLAV WORKERS OF CHICAGO</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, March 23, the Council for the Defence of Foreign Workers and the Educational Committee called a protest meeting at the National Hall.</p>
   <p>The response of Jugoslav workers was good. That shows that these workers feel the importance of bills introduced in different legislatures of the United States, which are against foreign-born as well as against domestic labor.</p>
   <p>The hall was packed with people. There were three speakers. Two spoke in Croatian; one in English. After the speakers finished, the following resolution was adopted:</p>
   <p>Resolution: Adopted by the Committee for the Defence of Foreign Workers and the Educational Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0773.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whereas there are before Congress twenty-five different bills which are against foreign-born workers; and,</p>
   <p>Whereas these bills have as a purpose to restrict the immigration of foreign workers to this country by registration, photographing and fingerprinting, etc., and some of the procedures will be used against workers already residents of these United States; and,</p>
   <p>Whereas the bill No. 4098 goes as far as to force workers residing here or coming here to live in certain localities decided in advance and remain under surveillance of the Justice Department, and of other laws; and,</p>
   <p>Whereas these legal measures have just one purpose: to make the workers slaves of their employers, thus to lower wages and disrupt workers' organizations and for that reason will add to the misery of the working class; it is hereby <pb facs="5420779_2_0774.jpg" n="3"/>Resolved: To call all workers, native born or foreigners, to join in the Workers' Councils for the defence of foreign laborers. We urge foreign-born laborers to join unions and united to lead a fight against these bills and measures, introduced solely for the benefit of employers against workers, and it is further</p>
   <p>Resolved: To send one copy of this resolution to the members of Congress and state senators with the request that they vote against said bills. One copy has to be sent to the press for publication.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
