<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. II, No. 1,
<date when="1924-08-07">Aug. 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Right Figures, Good Friends!</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0688</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0688.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. II, No. 1,
<date when="1924-08-07">Aug. 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">RIGHT FIGURES, GOOD FRIENDS!</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten years ago the now deceased H. C. Jankovic started action to erect a home for orphaned children and disabled feeble old folks. He was the first who thought of that, and with a few associates he proceeded to organize the Association of Croatian Orphanages in America. Like any new undertaking so did this one encounter opposition. From experience we know that our people lost millions of dollars in various gold mine shares. There are thousands who invested all they had so that they could be gold mine owners. It is no fun for anyone with two or three hundred dollars to become shareholder in such a corporation.</p>
   <p>There were also various other investments where our people intrusted their hard earned money to speculators. The Croatian people are fortunate with such "friends," who would take one's last dollar for their own personal profit.</p>
   <p>With all those drones it is little wonder that people do not trust in <pb facs="5420779_2_0689.jpg" n="2"/>bona fide undertakings. The home for Croatian orphans is the noblest act of our people in America. Even if slow, it is moving ahead, and for the building of the home $100,000 there are already collected, and building of the houses has started. Six houses size 33 x 99 feet each. The basements are dug out, and cement is being poured in their construction.</p>
   <p>All the work is directed by the Central Board of Directors of the Croatian Orphanage.</p>
   <p>To make the matter more understandable, I will mention that said board pays all collection to some company in Michigan, and they send their man to handle the work and other detail. He is said to be an expert.</p>
   <p>According to my information the weekly pay of that man is $75. One contractor digs the foundation, another will build the basement walls, then the carpenters. The houses will be made of wood. Since it was planned before and the blue prints were made for a structure of $200,000, from which sum we are very far, we have changed plans. But there is urgent necessity to build an orphanage, and we started with the work, as I stated before.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0690.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In spite of the work having been started, the executive board has not as yet rendered an estimate of the cost of these six houses.</p>
   <p>This, like all other buildings, has a definite estimate of cost, and every expert builder is able to give a correct estimate of the work entrusted to him. Our people are paying the bill and demand to know what is being done with their money. "Once burned, always careful," is an old saying. Our people do not believe anymore in empty phrases, they demand exact accounts.</p>
   <p>It is up to the executive board to give out an account of the building. People, in their lodge meetings, are asking for it in vain and get no satisfactory answer because the figures are kept as a great secret.</p>
   <p>We do not need inspectors nor pay their expensive transportation and wages because of the needs of poor children.</p>
   <p>We hope that the executive board will understand this notice and do its duty; otherwise we will start cleaning rank. There are plenty of us for that job.</p>
   <p>Marka Smicikas</p>
   <p>Chicago</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
