<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. XI, No. 39,
<date when="1934-09-29">Sept. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Protest against Illegal Resolution Adopted by the Central Committee of the Croatian Fraternal Union</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0661</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0661.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. XI, No. 39,
<date when="1934-09-29">Sept. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST AGAINST ILLEGAL RESOLUTION ADOPTED BY THE CENTRAL COMMITTEE OF THE CROATIAN FRATERNAL UNION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In minutes of the last meeting of the Central Executive Board we found a decision which is contrary to the constitution and by-laws of not only the Children's Home, but the Croatian Fraternal Union which owns the Children's Home.</p>
   <p>According to this decision an American Catholic society should be allowed to send a priest once a month to the Children's Home to teach them the catechism.</p>
   <p>Paragraph 4 of the Croatian Fraternal Union's by-laws says that it is forbidden to spread or agitate either religious or political propaganda, and in the Children's Home's by-laws it is stated that the children in the Home are allowed to visit church on Sundays, but the children <pb facs="5420779_2_0662.jpg" n="2"/>that desire not to, or if their parents or guardians so desire, the administration or manager of the home should not mix in, nor have they right to order or force children in any manner.</p>
   <p>We think with great confidence that the above excerpts from the by-laws of the Croatian Fraternal Union and the Children's Home are in place, and the management has observed them, which helped it to develop and succeed so much, which was impossible six or eight years earlier.</p>
   <p>Children's church-going was never interfered with before. If they wanted to go, the bus was provided every Sunday morning.</p>
   <p>This way they satisfied both those who wanted to go to church and those not wishing to go. Children were forbidden to participate in any celebration or concert which was not in direct contact with the Croatian <pb facs="5420779_2_0663.jpg" n="3"/>Fraternal Union or the Children's Home.</p>
   <p>The best example is a recent incident, when the children were not allowed in the celebration of "Jugoslav Day" at the World Fair in Chicago. And it was right. The management observed that rule, so did its executive committee and there is not one example in the home's history which could show that in the name of a home they acted in any political or religious matter.</p>
   <p>The Children's Home pursued this course in the past and accomplished great success, and proved to us members of the Croatian Fraternal Union that this is the only right and successful way.</p>
   <p>According to the by-laws and based on facts which at times speak clearer than the law, the central committee of the Croatian Fraternal Union is <pb facs="5420779_2_0664.jpg" n="4"/>wrong when it adopts such a resolution. This kind of decision can only be made by the Union's convention or a referendum vote by union members.</p>
   <p>Concerning the above, the central committee of the Jugoslav Educational Association demands - in the name of the members of the Croatian Fraternal Union who belong to our association, that the central committee of the Croatian Fraternal Union reverse their decision at once, but if someone desires to push it on the union and spread in it,or in the Children's Home, religious teachings, let them bring it up before the next convention and at the same time ask for the abolition of Paragraph 4 of the Croatian Fraternal Union's by-laws.</p>
   <p>Any attempt by the central committee to carry out their decision and bring the priest to the home will be considered a violation of union and home by-laws, and publicly prove deliberate interference with the <pb facs="5420779_2_0665.jpg" n="5"/>management of the home which does its work to the general satisfaction.</p>
   <p>Let us not create more disagreements in union ranks; it interferes with normal development.</p>
   <p>Should we allow priests to bring in a religion, it stands to reason others will bring in politics; some may demand Croatian nationalism; others may expound Pan-Jugoslavism, Communism, or any other religious or political creed.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile enemies of the Croatian Fraternal Union and the Children's Home, see destruction in it and that is what they want.</p>
   <p>To end the disagreement, we repeat, there is no room in the Croatian Fraternal Union, nor in the Children's Home, for religion and politics.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0666.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It should remain only as a benevolent, educational and humanitarian institution.</p>
   <p>Anyone wishing to put through some political or religious creed is an enemy of the Union and the Children's Home, whether he is doing it intentionally or unconsciously.</p>
   <p>We think that the central committee acted thoughtlessly in this case, and we are reminding them of a mistake, demanding them to recall their decision. Otherwise we will hold them responsible for the bad consequences arising out of their illegal decision.</p>
   <p>The Central Committee of the Jugoslav Educational Federation of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
