<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-05-25">May 25, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Protest by Croatians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0735</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0735.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-05-25">May 25, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST BY CROATIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Almost four hundred sturdy Croatians met in a hall at Center Avenue and 18th Street, in order to protest against the licentious ruling of the Hungarian government and its henchmen, the baneful Khuen-Hedervary in Croatia. Conditions there are known to our people from newspaper reports. Martial law exists in many towns today. The soldiers shoot people without mercy and whoever is arrested is tried and hung mercilessly. This is the reward of the Croats for having defended the Emperor and his government in 1848, against these same Hungarians, who today are oppressing them, and this because they are defending the rights given them by law. There are no rights in Austria-Hungary and as a Croatian student predicted: "There will be no rights for the Slavs in Austria until the hoofs of Cossack horses beat upon the market-square of Vienna."</p>
   <p>The meeting of our Croatian brothers was dignified. The chairman was Mr. Juraj Mamek; vice-chairman, Ivan Bozie; treasurer, J. C. Jankovic, secretary, T. Lackovic; auditor Stivelic. Before the meeting was called to order, voluntary donations were brought to the treasurer's table. It was impressive, the way those hard, <pb facs="5420779_2_0736.jpg" n="2"/>calloused hands contributed for the home-land, how willingly and how enthusiastically they contributed money earned by sweat and blood upon the altar of their "Home-land". Each of them gave at least a dollar, though we know, that Croatians are mainly workingmen and that they have no wealthy people among them. In the meeting the following was accomplished: The resolutions committee consisting of Messrs. Dr. Bianki, Pavel Hajdic and Ivan Bozic composed two telegrams; one directed to the National Defense Committee at Zahreb calling on the brothers to continue the fight for Croatian rights; the other to Franz Josef, present Emperor of Austria, in which he is called upon to put an end to the reign of the Hungarian monster in Croatia. There was collected since Thursday by means of subscription sheets and in the meeting a total of $355.80 and $51.00 for telegrams. Certainly a distinguished showing of the conscientiousness of our brother-men.</p>
   <p>One more word. It is our duty as Bohemians, to make collections for the benefit of our Croatian brothers and help them in their battle with the savage Hungarian hordes. Croatians live among us, associate with us, and participate in all our national undertakings. At the protest meeting, when martial law was declared in Prague, they took part in our meeting, spoke at the meeting and collected contributions for us. They celebrated Bohemian Day with us in 1893 contributing <pb facs="5420779_2_0737.jpg" n="3"/>almost $1000.00 for the occasion. However it is now time that we showed, that we sympathize with the unfortunate Slovak nation, which is being set upon, destroyed and murdered, and that as true Slavs we stand with them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
