<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VIII, No. 1,
<date when="1914-12-16">Dec. 16, 1914</date>
<title level="a">About Benevolent Societies</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0649</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0649.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VIII, No. 1,
<date when="1914-12-16">Dec. 16, 1914</date>
<title level="a">ABOUT BENEVOLENT SOCIETIES</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We want to say to our new members that comrades and other workers should become members of the benevolent associations for insurance in case of sickness, accident and death.</p>
   <p>Our immigrants suffer without such organizations in case of sickness or accident. Their families get nothing in case of death of their father, son or husband.</p>
   <p>To avoid such calamities it is necessary for the workers to join the benevolent organizations. We do not claim that they are perfect, but because a member contributes a certain amount to the society while he is working he has the right in case of need to request what is his according to the by-laws of the society.</p>
   <p>There are many working men who bring the excuse that it is hard to keep up the dues in such an organization. Wages are small and there is much <pb facs="5420779_2_0650.jpg" n="2"/>unemployment. That is true. There are so many poor workingmen. But there are many who would be able to pay if they out unnecessary expenses. Somebody will ask, what are unnecessary expenses? Here they are: Alcohol, tobacco, cards.</p>
   <p>These are quite unnecessary expenses which kill the worker's health and his pocketbook. Many a worker spends for beer or tobacco more than the amount for dues in an organization.</p>
   <p>A man must be his own friend because we know very well the consequences which arise if a man dies and leaves a family without support.</p>
   <p>For that reason it is important that a workingman gets insured.</p>
   <p>Comrades, take care of yourselves so as not to become a burden to your comrades in case of death, sickness or accident.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
