<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. X, No. 12,
<date when="1917-02-28">Feb. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Protest Meeting of Jugoslav Socialists</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. X, No. 12,
<date when="1917-02-28">Feb. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST MEETING OF JUGOSLAV SOCIALISTS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday the 18th of February a council of secretaries of all branches of the Federation in Chicago called the members for a Socialist meeting. Speakers were Etbin Kristan, Joseph Zavertnik, and N. Sonnenschein, candidate for alderman of the 10th ward.</p>
   <p>The following resolution was adopted:</p>
   <p>"The meeting of Jugoslav workers in Chicago, held February 18, 1917, expresses in principle its standpoint against wars of the capitalistic order, acknowledges the conclusions of the Internationale, which order each Socialist Party to work against war. Vigorously we protest against the work of those who are fanning up war, and their newspapers which misuse the critical situation to push the United States of America into war.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0111.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To the workers of America, the adventures undertaken by some capitalistic circles in the interests of huge profits, do not promise any benefits or gains, on the contrary great burdens will fall on the shoulders of the workers. All the sacrifices in lives and health the workers must bear. Economic crises, unemployment and high prices will oppress the workers. The accumulated debts of war, the workers will have to pay.</p>
   <p>The United States cannot profit by participating in a European war. A small circle of international capitalists would acquire great gains, which will throw the whole country back and hinder any progress.</p>
   <p>Keeping peace is in the interest of the working class, the democracy of the United States; for that reason it is not only a Socialist but also a civic duty to do all possible to avert war.</p>
   <p>The Jugoslav workers do not want to be traitors of their class. They <pb facs="5420779_2_0112.jpg" n="3"/>assert that their work for keeping peace has nothing in common with treason against the country in which they live, but that the true interests of the United States of America are damaged and treason is committed by those who, from pure and great egotism, drive the States to war, misery, financial and cultural catastrophe."</p>
   <p>At the meeting the fact was accentuated that the causes which make military crises a chronic disease must not be forgotten.</p>
   <p>As long as society rests on capitalistic foundations the world's peace is in danger day and night.</p>
   <p>The only security is the collapse of the capitalistic system. Protesting against the attempts to enter war the meeting calls the Jugoslav workers to enter into the Socialist Party, to create a mighty resistance against capitalism; by destroying capitalism, the cause of war will be destroyed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
