<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Memorial Book</title> 
      <title level="a">Anniversary Celebration with Concert and Dance Given by
       THE CROATIAN AMERICAN RADIO CLUB
       <date when="1937-03-28">Sunday March 28, 1937</date> at the National Brotherhood Hall
       1202 S. Racine Avenue</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0523</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
      <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0523.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Memorial Book</title>
     <title level="a">Anniversary Celebration with Concert and Dance Given by
     THE CROATIAN AMERICAN RADIO CLUB
     <date when="1937-03-28">Sunday March 28, 1937</date> at the National Brotherhood Hall
     1202 S. Racine Avenue</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>

   <pb facs="5420779_2_0524.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Appreciation is herewith expressed to our loyal advertisers and members for their hearty support in making this program a success.</p>
   <p>May we further request that members and friends of the Croatian American Radio Club of Chicago patronize our advertisers and program sponsors for their daily needs.</p>
   <p>We pledge our continued support and service to those in whom we have inspired confidence for the past two years through our regular Saturday programs and Special Anniversary Celebrations.</p>
   <p>With sincere thanks,</p>
   <p>The Committee.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0525.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Motto: Give, O Lord, that in Unity Croatians have the opportunity to be led, able to achieve Greatness, Culture and Liberty.</p>
   <p>Nothing great will come by itself. All material and spiritual benefits are achieved by steady and continuous work of man. All such achievements are a product of man's brains and of his energy.</p>
   <p>A nation great on cultural fields, progressive in creating material wealth, just the same as one man alone, does not become so over night, but by steady employment of all energies hidden in one individual. Some times years will go by before results in this direction are noticeable.</p>
   <p>We Croatians, as a nation, can not be an exception from other nations.</p>
   <p>If we want to keep step with other nations to succeed in gains of material wealth or of greater cultural standards, then we all have to cooperate and bring all our individual forces and capabilities into action for greatness and progress of our Croatian nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0526.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Especially we, living in a foreign country, have to bear that in mind, we, who live and work in contact with other nationalities, and are witnesses of their power, their prominence and their prosperity.</p>
   <p>Our glorious past, our splendid traditions are witnesses and proof that we were a nation of heroic feats, of brawn and of intellectual ability.</p>
   <p>Grasping our situation as well as knowing our duty, which we have to consider toward us and our Croatian immigrants, who live close to descendants of other nationalities, we realized that we have a great opportunity to demonstrate the cultural standards of the Croatian people by means of the radio.</p>
   <p>Two years ago, here in Chicago, we established the Croatian American Radio Club, with the purpose of influencing culturally and educationally the Croatians who live here.</p>
   <p>We bring and explain to our audiences educational matters, matters of <pb facs="5420779_2_0527.jpg" n="5"/>importance from our national history and according to our ability bring musical productions of Croatian composers.</p>
   <p>Bringing over the radio Croatian creations we improved the cultural standard of our people. Next to that we made known our cultural achievements to other nationalities and there is no doubt that we are known and appreciated by those other nationalities, as a people greater and better than ever before.</p>
   <p>Our sincere and burning love toward our homeland Croatia as well as toward men of our Croatian nationality bore great results during the two years of existence of our Croatian radio hours.</p>
   <p>In this educational and recreational Croatian radio broadcast are centered more than fifty Croatian cultural, benevolent associations and political organizations, and close to one thousand members.</p>
   <p>In the third year of its existence the Croatian American Radio Club declares <pb facs="5420779_2_0528.jpg" n="6"/>that our homeland Croatia is worthy and deserving of sacrifices and care on our part and that we must love it with all our soul and heart.</p>
   <p>Love toward the Croatian homeland burns like a torch on the altar, flames and roars in our hearts in this to us foreign world.</p>
   <p>Drawing us to glorious, great things, forever worthy of the Croatian name, of honor and of the so often with glory crowned Croatian flag.</p>
   <p>PROGRAM</p>
   <p>1. Star Spangled Banner Croatian anthem.</p>
   <p>2. Address by the club president.</p>
   <p>3. "Our mother's tongue." recitation.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0529.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>4. Music pieces by the Children's Band of the Croatian Church and School of St. Trinity.</p>
   <p>5. "National Dances," Tamburica orchestra.</p>
   <p>6. "Taking Leave," song.</p>
   <p>7. "Valz," danced by a girl dancer.</p>
   <p>8. "Dalmatian Seaman," song solo.</p>
   <p>10. "National Dance," danced by a girl.</p>
   <p>11. "Croatian National Songs," accompanied by guitar.</p>
   <p>12. "Medley of Croatian Songs," sung by the Croatian Singing Society "Hrvatska."</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0530.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The Croatian American Radio Club broadcasts from 4 to 5 P. M. each Saturday over station WGES, 1360 Kc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
