<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. IV, No. 45,
<date when="1922-02-11">Feb. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Our Misguided Workers</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0903</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0903.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. IV, No. 45,
<date when="1922-02-11">Feb. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">OUR MISGUIDED WORKERS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our editor received a letter from two Serbian workingmen from a town in Illinois. We cannot reproduce that letter because it contains words which are not fit for print.</p>
   <p>Along with offensive words goes the threat that both workers will come to Chicago and kill the editor. The letter states that we may publish it if we wish.</p>
   <p>Concerning that we have this to say: The reason they want to kill the editor of Znanje is the fact, as they say, that the newspaper assails the Jugoslav state and the Jugoslav people. The first statement is true, the other statement is false. Znanje does not assail the Jugoslav people nor does Znanje consider the Jugoslav people and state to be one and the same thing.</p>
   <p>Both Serbian workers claim to have read an article in No. 42 of Znanje <pb facs="5420779_2_0904.jpg" n="2"/>which caused them to write.</p>
   <p>By the way, this article was not written by the editor, but sent to Znanje by a Serbian student at Belgrade.</p>
   <p>Both Serbian workers would have much trouble if we gave this letter to the American postal authorities. We did not do that because we think they are victims of misguided patriotism. They are not responsible for what they write. They do not know that in America it is very dangerous to send threatening letters by mail. They are ignoramuses who only know that Znanje assails the Jugoslav state. They read in their patriotic Serbian paper that Jugoslavia is the best, most powerful, and the greatest state in the world. Because they are unable to judge for themselves, they think it must be so. They are of the opinion that everything is a lie that is written about the atrocities of police and gendarmes in Jugoslavia.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0905.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Any of our working men who is in correspondence with his relatives in the old country sees and hears how everybody is complaining there. Very few are satisfied, except profiteers who made money fleecing the population, who live in luxury now and glorify their "free" country. That means the state is praised by war profiteers, usurers, grafters and bribed newspapermen, whose duty it is to extol the Jugoslav government.</p>
   <p>There are many Jugoslav newspapermen who a few years ago praised the late King Nicholas of Montenegro, but called him a traitor afterwards. Such men do not act according to their conviction, but according to the situation in which they are, and in the interests of those paying them.</p>
   <p>Workers able to write such letters as we received, were educated by the newspapermen we described above.</p>
   <p>If they would read our newspaper and would not listen to the enemies <pb facs="5420779_2_0906.jpg" n="4"/>of the workingmen's press, they would notice that we stand always in defence of the Jugoslav working people.</p>
   <p>In each number of Znanje you will find descriptions of conditions in some of the European states, where we point out disorders and tyranny of the governing class. Not one of those classes is assailed less than the Jugoslav governing class. We stand up for the defence of the Jugoslav working people, as we do for the people of any other land.</p>
   <p>For that reason it is silly if some working men claim that we assail the Jugoslav state. We assail the existing bad conditions for the working classes in all the bourgeois states, not only in Jugoslavia.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
