<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 19,
<date when="1920-08-14">Aug. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Foreign Languages</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0431</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0431.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 19,
<date when="1920-08-14">Aug. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">FOREIGN LANGUAGES</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago, in the legislature of the State of Oregon a new bill was introduced to forbid the existence of the foreign language newspapers and magazines.</p>
   <p>The high patriots of the State of Oregon tried to bite (?) themselves, if we believe the statement of Professor Rasmus B. Anderson, American of Norwegian origin, who was American ambassador at Copenhagen.</p>
   <p>Professor Anderson says: "The people who speak just one language live in a house which has just one window; they live with one thought; just in one direction. The people who speak several languages have windows on all four sides of their houses and see all what is happening in this world. The great German philosopher and poet, Goethe, was right when he said that a man knowing just one language knows very little about his own."</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0432.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I do not sympathize a bit," said Mr. Anderson, "with this hysterical agitation against foreign languages and foreigners."</p>
   <p>In America are about 1,500 newspapers and magazines, published in foreign languages and the number of copies reaches eight million.</p>
   <p>These papers represent thirty-two languages. They are published in every one of the states. Of that entire press only 4% belong to the Socialists, Communists or I. W. W. Hardly one percent of this press is Communist or Anarchistic. It is considered that 29% of this press is completely loyal and 96% anti-social. In this country there are not more than twenty openly radical newspapers, of which five are published in Jewish. The ultra-radical press is published in the English language in millions of copies and has millions of readers.</p>
   <p>We do not know how accurate are the statements of Mr. Anderson, but one <pb facs="5420779_2_0433.jpg" n="3"/>thing seems to be important, that is, that the ultra radical newspapers are published in the English language and are read by millions of Americans. That means that the State of Oregon will have to prohibit also the English language because mostly in that language the radical propaganda is being spread. If that is the case, what is the use of destroying the foreign language press?</p>
   <p>If the foreigners are considered as radical, who vouches that they will not learn the English language and read newspapers published in English?</p>
   <p>Of course, these "hurrah" patriots, while raving against foreign and imported languages, forget that the English language is also imported.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
