<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Croatian Radio Club First Anniversary Memorial Book</title>,
<date when="1936-04-12">April 12,1936</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.B.2"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Croatian Radio Club First Anniversary Memorial Book</title>,
<date when="1936-04-12">April 12,1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago, just a few years, the Croatian nation at home celebrated the 1000th anniversary of the establishment of the Croatian kingdom.</p>
   <p>One thousand years passed since the Croatian people elected their first king. The heroic, proud and great king, Tomislav.</p>
   <p>Already at the time of King Tomislav (A. D. 925), the cultural level of the Croatian nation was high. The Croatians compared favorably with any other nation of their time.</p>
   <p>In the earliest Croatian history, their outstanding qualities in culture, intelligence and national spirit were noted. These traits have to serve us as an example today, to encourage us and show how we have to work, to sacrifice for the good and welfare of the fatherland and of our people.</p>
   <p>In all branches of science, in all great and different ramifications of <pb facs="5420779_2_0368.jpg" n="2"/>art, the Croatian possess results of their work as a sequence of their perseverance and patience in the most difficult tasks. The Croatians may rightly be proud of the fact that they contributed to science, literature and art, most magnificent works ever conceived by human brains and executed by human hands.</p>
   <p>Croatian literature, among many others, gave us an unsurpassed author, Senoa. A God blessed poet, Preradovic, and many sculptors and gifted composers.</p>
   <p>The unparalleled works in the field of culture and civilization make the Croatian nation an outstanding member of all other cultured nationalities. By these works the Croatians did their part in building up a general, common world, embracing culture and civilization. By these works the Croatian nation was recognized, and must insist on remaining recognized, as a cultural, civilized and progressive nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0369.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Conscious of the enviable position which the Croatian nation holds among other nations as a cultural entity, we, Croatians in a foreign country, assembled around our Croatian Radio Club, which is our cultural and educational center, must watch and be determined that our radio offerings will be always of such a quality that they will do honor and be of pride to that country where we were born, the country of our dreams, of dear memories of our youth. Of a country where our dearest live. The country of our famous ancestors who, sword in hand, conquered, and with their blood sprinkled our beautiful, never forgettable homeland, Croatia.</p>
   <p>One of our great poets showed his great love toward the land in which he was born, where he received the first affections of a dear, loving mother. He must have dreamed about happiness and freedom of his home country and his nation when he expressed his thoughts in these beautiful words:</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0370.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>River Sava, River Drava,</p>
   <p>Swiftly to the Danube flow.</p>
   <p>To all the world your waters murmur;</p>
   <p>How their country Croats love!</p>
   <p>(Free translation: Croatian Anthem).</p>
   <p>Managing committee of the Croatian-American Radio Club:</p>
   <p>Jurat Horvatic, President.</p>
   <p>Ivan Covic, Vice-President.</p>
   <p>Stjepan Furlan, Financial Secretary.</p>
   <p>Michael Rasperger, Treasurer</p>
   <p>TRUSTEES: Stjepan Miller, Pres.</p>
   <p>Anton Covic, Martin Furlan,</p>
   <p>Josip Radetic, Ivan Krakas.</p>
   <p>Director of the musical program and announcer: Jurat Absac.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
