<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VIII, No. 125,
<date when="1925-10-17">Oct. 17, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Trades Union Movement and the Jugoslav Workers</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VIII, No. 125,
<date when="1925-10-17">Oct. 17, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE TRADES UNION MOVEMENT AND THE JUGOSLAV WORKERS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was a little over thirty years ago since our Jugoslav workers started in greater numbers to immigrate to this country. Most of them came here with the purpose of saving some money and returning to their home country. With their savings, they intended to pay off their debts, and thus secure their existence.</p>
   <p>In America, the immigrants were confronted with quite a different life and working conditions. From a peaceful village life, they came into a vortex of capitalistic industrial production, where everything was fixed according to the hour and minute. Many could never get accustomed to this life, and they tried hard to leave such an existence. Others became used to the situation and remained without any thoughts of their homeland.</p>
   <p>Because our Jugoslav workers were not tradesmen, they had and have <pb facs="5420779_2_0844.jpg" n="2"/>today great difficulties in getting and holding positions.</p>
   <p>They are mostly miners, steel and saw mill workers. Here they perform the heaviest work.</p>
   <p>Not having a trade, it was not easy for Jugoslav workers to join unions, the more so because the American trade unions served for the working aristocracy of skilled tradesmen. Our Jugoslav workers were compelled to wander from factory to factory, where they performed the heaviest work under the worst conditions. Another disadvantage for an unskilled laborer is the fact that he changes his work very often and the organization of such shifting workers is extremely difficult. Even if there were a possibility of joining a union, our Jugoslav workers are very slow to join organizations, because most of them consider themselves just transients. On the other hand, as former peasants and villagers, they do not feel the necessity for organization.</p>
   <p>But it is different today. Most of our workers learn a trade because they <pb facs="5420779_2_0845.jpg" n="3"/>know industrial life and workers' unions.</p>
   <p>They are interested in political and economic things concerning workers and proletarians. They join unions now.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
