<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Croatian Singing Society "Hrvatska" Memorial Book</title><date when="1930-11-15">Nov. 15, 1930</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE CROATIAN SINGING SOCIETY "HRVATSKA" MEMORIAL BOOK</title><date when="1930-11-15">Nov. 15, 1930</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the beginning of the hardest depression in America a new Croatian Singing Society was organized December 1st, 1931. January 15th, 1932 there were 40 active members, and from that day this Singing Society prospered beyond expectation.</p>
   <p>The first singing lessons were conducted at Howell House, 1831 S. Racine Ave. a short time after the mens' and womens' choruses were organized.</p>
   <p>The first President elected was Mr. Julius Cizmezija. Manager for the Ladies Chorus, Mrs. Mary Devich.</p>
   <p>For over five years, the Society went through more hardships than any other of our Croatian cultural societies were compelled to suffer. The members one by one lost their work, or positions. The banks closed their doors with their savings lost. Life became unbearable for all of us. These bad living conditions were reflected by a poor attendance at singing lessons <pb facs="5420779_2_0274.jpg" n="2"/>and performances of the Society. But the members of the Singing Society "Hrvatska" did overcome valiantly all obstacles. Following their aim on cultural lines, remaining true to their beloved Croatian song.</p>
   <p>The late music Professor Ivan Horvat was the Singing Society's teacher and Conductor from the beginning until his untimely death. Professor Ivan Horvat was a composer accomplished musician and successful teacher.These facts attributed greatly to his successes. Coming 1921 to Chicago Prof. Horvat took over the Croatian singing societies; "Zora" (the dawn) and "Preradovich." He took active part in organizing the Croatian singing societies "Jadrau" "Velebit", "Zagreb", "Radich" and "Hrvatska."</p>
   <p>The most notable musical performances given by Professor Horvat were <pb facs="5420779_2_0275.jpg" n="3"/>The operetta "Momci na brod" (Man the decks), the comic opera "In the Well" and "The Croatian Trilogy". By his cultural work Professor Ivan Horvat will live in the memory of Croatian immigrants in Chicago forever. After death of Professor Horvat, his place as Conductor of the Croatian Singing Society "Hrvatska" was taken over by Mr. Stephen Pipich, a born Chicagoan, graduated from the Auditorium Music Conservatory.</p>
   <p>The Singing Society "Hrvatska" is considered as one of the best organized and most successful Croatian Singing Societies in this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
