<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. IX, No. 30,
<date when="1916-07-05">July 5, 1916</date>
<title level="a">The Jugoslav Socialist Congress</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. IX, No. 30,
<date when="1916-07-05">July 5, 1916</date>
<title level="a">THE JUGOSLAV SOCIALIST CONGRESS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, July 2, in Chicago, the third Jugoslav Socialist Federation's congress convened. After a short formal conference on Saturday evening, regular work started Sunday morning.</p>
   <p>Circumstances did not allow this congress to assemble sooner. Now in serious times its assemblage is of more importance.</p>
   <p>Two important moments have to be marked at present: the World War and the American-Mexican rift. The whole world is dragged into the whirl of this question. Even the Socialist parties are unable to go over these happenings without pointing out that causes which create such crises in the world.</p>
   <p>The congress convened for four days. It was a complete success and finished its tasks in perfect harmony.</p>
   <p>Minutes of the successive meetings will be published later on. At present we bring a survey of the first day.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0058.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The congress was held at the National Hall, west 18th street and Racine avenue. In all, eighty delegated congress members participated.</p>
   <p>The singing chorus of branch No. 6 sang at the beginning the "Workers' greetings."</p>
   <p>Secretary of the federation, Petric, opened the session of the congress, pointing its importance. Comrade Zikich spoke. The welcome address then followed the election of the officers for the meeting.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Bulgar-Macedonian Socialist Federation, the congress was addressed by comrade S. Konstantinov. In the name of Spravenlivost (Justice), and the Czech comrades, the congress was greeted by comrade Beranek. He said that when he came to America there were no Socialist organizations among the Jugoslavs. This congress proves that the Jugoslavs advanced in their fight for the liberation of the working class.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0059.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the afternoon the chief secretary of the federation, comrade Petric, gave his report, which report was accepted.</p>
   <p>Comrade Savs gave a report for the Slovenian section of the federation; it was accepted without change.</p>
   <p>In the name of the Croat-Serbian section, comrade Dubravac referred to our organ Radnicka Straza. The same day comrade Kristan gave his report about the Slovenian official organ Proletarec.</p>
   <p>After that other things were debated which we will publish in the next issues.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
