<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VIII, No. 14,
<date when="1915-03-17">March 17, 1915</date>
<title level="a">Basis for Jugoslavia</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0938</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0938.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VIII, No. 14,
<date when="1915-03-17">March 17, 1915</date>
<title level="a">BASIS FOR JUGOSLAVIA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first Jugoslav congress opened its session Wednesday in the La Salle Hotel in Chicago, but the Croats call it "the Croatian congress," as an indication of solidarity.</p>
   <p>Croats from all over America were present with the intention of discussing ways and means. Some came with sincere wishes to help liberate the people from Austrian rule; others wanted the honor of being recognized in the new Jugoslavia, and in that way clear the road for some profitable position in the new state.</p>
   <p>Chicago's pseudo-patriots led the show. They called the congress, arranged the hall and the program according to their own liking. In the meantime they did not forget to define what constitutes liberty.</p>
   <p>The Chicago's lords evidently did not like the style of Radnicka Straza's writing and they took an opportunity for revenge by not allowing <pb facs="5420779_2_0939.jpg" n="2"/>the Radnicka Straza's reporter to be present at the congress; some other reporters were forbidden, too.</p>
   <p>When Chicago's lords are so intolerant and allow no criticism nor free press, what would they do if they were in real power?</p>
   <p>Maybe their Slavonic blood would prove to be the same as their Slav brother, the Russian "savior"; then all free thinkers, especially Socialists, would finish in some sort of Siberia.</p>
   <p>Imagine the freedom in Jugoslavia with the Chicago lords as a police at the head of it. They would really put Franz Joseph to shame.</p>
   <p>The congress was opened with prayer; even those opposed to church and clergy prayed, maybe they thought that the church and priests will help them by keeping the people in darkness so that they can be better governed.</p>
   <p>After two days of fiery speeches, Dr. Potocnjak declared that this congress was not essential, and that it is not even necessary for this <pb facs="5420779_2_0940.jpg" n="3"/>congress to approve Jugoslavia.</p>
   <p>Dr. Potocnjak said that England, France and Russia agreed to a plan by which Jugoslavia is created if Austria fails. This congress was called only to accept the idea of Jugoslavia and to create good feeling toward the new state.</p>
   <p>The committee of thirty-three persons - eleven of each national group - eleven Croats, eleven Serbs, and eleven Slovenes, was elected -- with what duty, nobody knows! Quite a few dollars more collected...</p>
   <p>The delegates contributed freely; some $200 and up, up to $1,000, but nobody seems to know what to do with the money. Russia and France don't need it; it seems that the Jugoslav committee in London will use it profitably.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
