<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 45,
<date when="1914-10-21">Oct. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Before Important Elections in America</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 45,
<date when="1914-10-21">Oct. 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BEFORE IMPORTANT ELECTIONS IN AMERICA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The pre-election campaign is in full swing in the United States. The Republican, Democratic and Progressive parties started as usual their agitation with promises of better times which never come; on the contrary, conditions are getting worse.</p>
   <p>Crooked politicians, capitalistic agents and representatives of dirty bureaucratism are at work. They came out of their holes. They got into a fighting and reckless mood in order to gain back again their warm places, after which they will hide again until the following elections.</p>
   <p>The third of November, 1914, will be of great importance for the American people. That day representatives will be elected to whom the people give the right to make new laws and to direct the destiny of the American people.</p>
   <p>But these elections have a more important significance for the working <pb facs="5420779_2_0071.jpg" n="2"/>class, the class which has not one representative in the highest legislature of the land. Today laws are made by representatives of the bourgeoisie: capitalists, rich men, lawyers, and great landowners. The working class has nothing to say in the political life of this country, although it supports and is the greatest factor in the country.</p>
   <p>The cause for this deplorable situation rests with the workingman who believed in empty promises of different political speculators and elected to the legislature men who did not care for the interests of the working class, but for their own class.</p>
   <p>The Socialist Party, which is of only recent date here, had only one representative so far, who was defeated at the last elections by the combined efforts of the bourgeois parties. The Socialist Party did <pb facs="5420779_2_0072.jpg" n="3"/>repeatedly show that it was the proletarian party, the party of hired slaves sincerely struggling for a better fate of the working class; for their liberation from slavery and from the unjust system.</p>
   <p>All other parties participated in government before. They did have in their hands the state's machinery and were able to do much for the working class. But it is noted that said parties worked for their benefit and cared little for the working man.</p>
   <p>Under the Republican rule, under Taft and Roosevelt, the workers were treated like criminals. Even political liberties were taken from them, not to mention prosecutions by the courts against organized workers.</p>
   <p>Today, when the Democratic party is in power, America goes through one of the hardest economic crisis. Strikes, unemployment, misery; all that shows a bad situation that the Democrats, like the Republicans, cheated the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0073.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The working class of America saw with their own eyes countless injustices perpetrated by the bourgeois parties. Persecutions by police, the unjust courts, the tyranny of the army and police in West Virginia, Michigan and Colorado, where not long ago soldiers, under the protection of the state, killed innocent women and burned workers' children alive.</p>
   <p>The situation in America became much worse on account of the slaughter in Europe. The working class has to think how to stop the misery and injustice prevalent in America.</p>
   <p>Opportunity is at hand to speak up on November third, at the elections. To show the rich and the political cheaters that the people must be governed differently. Each conscious worker will vote November 3rd for the candidates of the Socialist Party, a party which is struggling for the rights of the oppressed and enslaved in our contemporary society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
