<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1915-03-24">Mar. 24, 1915</date>. Vol. 7; No. 15.
<title level="a">Is That Liberty or Reaction about the "Action" of the Jugoslav Congress</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0810</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0810.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title>,
<date when="1915-03-24">Mar. 24, 1915</date>. Vol. 7; No. 15.
<title level="a">IS THAT LIBERTY OR REACTION ABOUT THE "ACTION" OF THE JUGOSLAV CONGRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On March 10th and 11th - 1915, in Chicago, at the Hotel LaSalle there was staged a big politico-patriotic bluff with the prupose of creating a "greater Jugoslavia."</p>
   <p>The initiator of this tragi-comedy was Dr. Frank Potocnjak, a hollow political figure who introduced himself to the public as representative of "Jugoslav League" at London. The league's purpose is: to influence the diplomacy of Russia, France and England, to help unite all South Slavs into one state.</p>
   <p>Who is able to foretell today when the war will end and when it does end that the Allies will not fight among themselves over the spoils?</p>
   <p>The unification of the South Slav nations can originate only from these nations. The nations must be educated for such an important union. The nations must know why such a union is necessary and how it can be accomplished.</p>
   <p>The gentlemen who propose said unity now, never told or instructed the people <pb facs="5420779_2_0811.jpg" n="2"/>about it before.</p>
   <p>Their appeal to the european diplomacy is a political beggary, which shows their incompetence for national politics, and compromises any honest Jugoslav tendency. The Jugoslavs of America were never told who were the persons of the "Jugoslav League in London? For that reason that "League" must be approached with suspicion.</p>
   <p>For same reason we would like to ask; 1. Is that "Jugoslav League" in the service of the Russian government. Will that government protect the Jugoslav as it protects the best Russian sons who are rotting in Siberia?</p>
   <p>2. Has not Dr.Frank Potocnjak come to America to extract from the blood of hard toiling and suffering Jugoslavs as much money as is possible to extract for himself and for his friends in the "League".</p>
   <p>On the 10th the Congress started with a prayer. Reverend Don Niko Grskovich was elected president who declared that because everybody present knows why this congress convened there must reign here unanimity in everything and no one will be <pb facs="5420779_2_0812.jpg" n="3"/>allowed to contradict. A resolution was read and unanimously adopted about the "Jugoslav" question and unification.</p>
   <p>The resolution was printed next day in the paper "Hrvatska Zastava" (Croatian Flag). The main points of the resolution are that; Croatians, Serbians and Slovenians are of one and the same nationality.</p>
   <p>The Jugoslavs in Austro-Hungary suffer from two governing nations, the Germans and the Magyars. For the above-said reasons it is advisable to form a union of all Jugoslav provinces of Austria-Hungary and Serbia. To accomplish that an appeal is made to the Allies.</p>
   <p>The following objections are offered to the contents of the resolution:</p>
   <p>1. Croatians, Serbs and Sovenes are three different nationalities, they never were one, according to history.</p>
   <p>2. The gentlemen assert in their resolution that in Austria-Hungary reign two nationalities, the Germans and Magyars. That statement is a chauvinistic mistake.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0813.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In Austria-Hungary does not reign any one of its nationalities, but a bloody, incompetent, oligarchy, which oporesses all the peoples inside the borders of that monarchy.</p>
   <p>3. It is not stated in the resolution whether "greater Jugoslavia" is to become a monarchy or republic.</p>
   <p>The gentlemen wanted to mislead everybody. There is a great duplicity shown. At the beginning of the resolution Montenegro is mentioned as a Jugoslav State, at the end only Jugoslav provinces of Austria and Hungary and the kingdom of Serbia are mentioned as the countries to be united in a "greater Jugoslavia". Why was Montenegro left out?</p>
   <p>Before the congress was called there was talk in the Jugoslav press of a federative republic to which will belong also the Kingdom of Serbia. That means this movement of Dr.Frank Potocnjak was directed against the royal dinasty of Serbia. It is said, after the resolution was adopted, that a Catholic priest said: "The Serbians swallowed the hook."</p>
   <p>The evening after the first day of congress many Serbians assembled at the Hotel Victoria for a discussion of the events. Here was decided to send two men Mr.R.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0814.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Radosavljevic and John Palandech to the president Don Niko Grskovic and express their distrust of the purpose of the congress and the text of the adopted resolution.</p>
   <p>II.</p>
   <p>Thursday March 11th the Jugoslav congress was opened again.</p>
   <p>On the complaint of the Serbian delegates answered Dr.Potocnjak. He gave the history of the idea of unification of the Jugoslavs. From among the emigrants in France, Switzerland and England a "Jugoslav committee" was formed with the purpose of exerting an influence on the allied diplomats to settle the Jugoslav question. The Doctor said: You can not ask me to show you documents or to name persons, which are engaged in this delicate matter.</p>
   <p>At the second session of the Jugoslav congress on the advice of Dr.Potocnjak a "Jugoslav committee", for America was elected. As its president they elected Dr. Ante Biankini.</p>
   <p>The congress failed to enact the laws or specify the purpose or duties of the new elected committee for America. However to give "Jugoslav Committee" for America a good start a collection was made which netted $1740.00. After that the famous <pb facs="5420779_2_0815.jpg" n="6"/>Jugoslav congress adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
