<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 44,
<date when="1914-10-14">Oct. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Stand Up! Stand Up!</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. VII, No. 44,
<date when="1914-10-14">Oct. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">STAND UP! STAND UP!</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Comrades, friends, brothers! Opponents of the working class try with all their might to distract the attention of the world to the stage of the European war. To blind the world and lead it from life's real aims.</p>
   <p>We, too, are watching how the war fever is shaking the sick brains of spiritually blind people; of living mummies who succumbed to the wishes of the Holy Trinity: capitalism, church and militarism.</p>
   <p>For everything that capitalism does there are excuses because it has not been admitted that this war was provoked by class interests; that this war, with all of its terrors, bears great changes in the political and economical life of Europe, but also the final downfall of capitalism in the whole world.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, in these most critical moments, it was only the Socialist press which dispersed the mistakes of the bourgeois chauvinistic parties and did stand up in defence of the working man.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0140.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Social democracy demands the abolition of the root of war by destroying capitalism. That is why social democracy wages an industrial war in the factories, where machines smash the bones of workmen; in mines, where explosions destroy our brethren; in shops and fields, everywhere where men, women and children are systematically starved.</p>
   <p>The historical mission of the working class is the liberation from hired slavery under the slogan: "Everything belongs to all."</p>
   <p>A great struggle is waged between between labor and capital in this country today. The laborer fights for the right of his work: a larger slice of bread. Capitalism fights against labor for the right to grab the fruits of others' labors. That is a war bigger and greater than any war fought before: it is a war without recess.</p>
   <p>On that war we have to concentrate our attention, because there is our life, which like a bloody thread, leads us between liberty and slavery.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0141.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Comrades! Radnicka Straza is the only paper in Croatian and Serbian which is enlightening our workers, which inspires fear in the sold, characterless, dollar-patriotic press. For that reason Radnicka Straza must be carried to each worker's home. Today more than ever, it is necessary to hear our voice against capitalistic exploitation and bloody wars.</p>
   <p>Carry the voice of truth everywhere where workers are; wake up your working comrades; bring to them, offer them, our paper Radnicka Straza.</p>
   <p>This paper will call louder than the trumpet of Jericho, "Forward to fight, sons and daughters of Labor, the future is calling you!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
