<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1927-04-06">April 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">For Protection of Women Workers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1927-04-06">April 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">FOR PROTECTION OF WOMEN WORKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of the protection of women workers is not a new question, but it is not solved so easily. Women workers were dragged into industrial production and by that became an economic factor in society, just as are men workers. Industrial production takes them from their homes, from home management and kitchen work, and by pressure of circumstances causes a revolution in family life. As long as the woman was merely a housewife, she was dependent not only on class exploiters, but also on her husband. She expected from him material support for herself and children.</p>
   <p>The capitalistic production wants cheap and plentiful working power; that was what caused women first to be dragged into industrial production; first as competitors to men, finally as steady industrial workers.</p>
   <p>Today we have millions of women who are officials, factory workers, in business, servants, housekeepers for others, etc., even in heavy industries, such as rubber, steel, and mines you may find them. In households and on farms they are complete slaves.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0184.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The living conditions of such women workers compels them to fight in their own behalf. The struggle for women's rights is becoming more insistent and more outspoken in character.</p>
   <p>This struggle has reached a stage where legislatures must take cognizance of and debate women's industrial questions along with those of men.</p>
   <p>The newest picture of how to solve the problems of working women in the United States is as follows:</p>
   <p>January 17, 1927. The Supreme Court of the United States declared the minimum wage law for women in Arkansas unconstitutional.</p>
   <p>In the California Senate a bill was introduced to make the 8-hour day for women a law.</p>
   <p>The State Federation of Labor for California introduced an amendment to this bill to make it possible for any one to report transgressors of the 8-hour law for women.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0185.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This year efforts are being made to introduce the 8-hour working day for the women of Illinois. Nineteen organizations elected a joint committee to work on this proposition.</p>
   <p>The Minimum Wage Commission of the State of Massachusetts fixed a minimum wage for women at $13.50</p>
   <p>Owners of cotton mills in Massachusetts are for a 48-hour week throughout the year. Occasionally this may be extended to 54 hours per week.</p>
   <p>All this is proof that the women's question is under discussion all over the United States of America.</p>
   <p>In connection with this it must be clear to us all that all such legislative proceedings by capitalistic legislatures are not sufficient, because the working hours are too long. Also this success is the result of women workers' struggles for their rights. Though this fight is not organized, it is here, and employers are bound to recognize that fact. To us it must be clear, and <pb facs="5420779_2_0186.jpg" n="4"/>more to working women still, that these legislative bodies never will honor their own decisions against the employers. They trample their own laws, if the laws do not suit them. The woman worker is exploited not only for the allotted time, but for more.</p>
   <p>For that reason it is the duty of the working woman to fight for her own interests. It is her duty to fight for real protection for women. That real protection will be achieved when working women are organized in women's organizations and federations, and together when they fight as a labor party. This, in turn, will protect the women's working power more radically.</p>
   <p>Never lose sight of the fact that a full and real protection of women workers rests only with communism. Communism employs revolutionary methods and actions, professed by the Labor (Communist) Party of America, and the Communist International.</p>
   <p>All class-conscious working men and women must keep this in mind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
