<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. VII, No. 40,
<date when="1930-05-01">May 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">First Annual Celebration</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0708</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0708.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Novi Svijet</title> Vol. VII, No. 40,
<date when="1930-05-01">May 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST ANNUAL CELEBRATION</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday, April 20, 1930, the Croatian women's society "Hrvatska Zena," (The Croatian Mother), had its first public entertainment and with it celebrated its first year of existence. The event was held in the American-Bohemian Hall and was well attended.</p>
   <p>The dance was scheduled for the afternoon and the program for 7 P. M. which actually took place at 8:30. The president, Mrs. Klora Skyorc, opened the program with a laudatory address.</p>
   <p>The program was composed of many various sections. The principal attraction was the dramatic play, "Na Duvanjskom Polju." (The first Croatian king was crowned on Duvanjsko field, 1005 years ago).</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0709.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This fantastic picture symbolizes, and in patriotic phrases depicts, a meeting of legendary fairies on Duyanjsko field, as follows:</p>
   <p>The fairy Majka Hrvatska (Croatian mother) called the fairies from ten districts to the meeting to discuss the destiny of their homeland, based on the glory of Grostian history and to promise a better future.</p>
   <p>The ten Croatian fairies were dressed in native costumes according to the ten original districts. The costumes were beautiful. Obviously more time was given to the decoration. If that much attention and time was devoted to the lines of one's particular part, the presentation could have had more artistic value. The biggest handicap was that fairies talked so law that the public could hardly hear what was happening in the fairies circle. Only about two or three were fairly good.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0710.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The best act on the program was the part where children played "Kolo," (National dance). Eight boys and eight girls, all dressed in national costumes, clasped hands and formed the circle. The Vrbancic Brothers String Orchestra furnished the music. This part undoubtedly would have come out the best if it was not for the interruption. The dance was in proper order and everything was going well when a few priests entered ceremoniously into the hall. Then the whole clan got stirred up and rushed to greet them, how to them and provide proper seats for them. A real riot and disturbance was created and the young dancers and players were neglected. One would rightfully expect, even of a priest, to be more respectful in a case like that, and remain at the door at least until the act was over.</p>
   <p>In the children's dance we must mention the expert leadership of <pb facs="5420779_2_0711.jpg" n="4"/>Danica Hrbanasa in a Russian national dance in acrobatic style and "Naughty Waltz," masterfully presented by Helen Sutler, Gertrude Slirka and little Margie Hans. (She is at present a radio artist). The dance followed the program.</p>
   <p>We stated that this was the first public appearance of "Hrvatska Zena," and will express a few impressions in connection with same. In the first place, with the apperance of the new group, we expected something new in the way of an entertainment, something that would lead us one step ahead, but instead, we were transferred back to the war time delirium from which we have hardly recuperated.</p>
   <p>We heard from one member that the purpose and the aim of the society is exclusive and consists only in helping Croatian poor children and orphans here and in the old country to the complete exclusion of religious and political questions. Very noble purpose, indeed!</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0712.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This affair, however, showed no indication of existing poverty nor did anybody as much as mention the poor. On the contrary, here was where the Croatian would-be aristocracy displayed itself and decorated themselves as in a contest to show how good God was to them.</p>
   <p>Judging by the program and the conduct of the whole affair, it seems that this society has a different purpose more energetically displayed than the original one, that is, the propaganda of Croatian chauvinism among the immigrants. Whether this society as a whole knows it on not, it is obvious that "Hrvatska Zena" is a tool of some newspaperman or some individuals who have been late spreading some patent Croatianism among our people for their own selfish interests. From this we see that many put on good clothes for pure patriotism and display.</p>
   <p>After all, this chauvinism is nothing new, but the issue of old Austrianism, Hungarianism or Pan-Croatianism of the deceased "Hrvatski Savez,"</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0713.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>(Croatian Federation), or war Jugoslavism and many other evolutionary avenues which our quack patriots in America have traveled in the past. The description of this newest patriotic mania of our aristocratic foolishness would be interesting and entertaining if it wasn't so tragic.</p>
   <p>Now we would like to advise the members of "Hrvatska Zena" if they wish to put their new lodge on a strong foundation and if they are sincere in their undertaking and want to devote their activity to the humanitarian purposes which they claim as their aim and which in itself has a large field, then they ought to leave aside the clergy and chauvinism. The history of our immigration in America teaches us that clergy and chauvinism are very bad company and lodges and clubs run by them have a short life.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0714.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>It would be more sensible if "Hrvatska Zena," as a society which took as its duty to help the poor, had devoted more attention to the question of poverty.</p>
   <p>For instance, why are there the poor? what makes men poor and how to remedy misery and poverty? That would be by far more appropriate for them.</p>
   <p>Reporter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
