<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 23,
<date when="1920-09-11">Sept. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Stjepan Doicic in America</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0912</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0912.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Znanje</title> Vol. III, No. 23,
<date when="1920-09-11">Sept. 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">STJEPAN DOICIC IN AMERICA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the year 1912 a young man left America to go to Croatia. Without much noise he left Kenosha, Wis., where he worked and where he left many friends. Most of them did not know that he is leaving for Croatia, many thought he was going to South America.</p>
   <p>Little attention was paid to his leaving the United States, because many Croatians, after working here for three or four years, leave for home.</p>
   <p>But this young man did not go to Croatia to see his relatives or on account of any personal business.He had a different purpose. That young man was returning to Croatia in the hope to be able to assassinate commissary Cuvaj, who was followed by Skrlec and by his act he thought to alleviate the Calvary of his people.</p>
   <p>That young man was a patriot in the fullest sense of the word. What other dollar patriots were just talking about he was ready to put into action, in that unlucky land of Croatia.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0913.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This young man was Stjepan Doicic, then just twenty years of age. He was born in Ludbreg, Croatia. After finishing public school he came to Zagreb as a painter's apprentice. He started to read newspapers and was interested in history and politics. That made him an ardent patriot. Before he reached twenty he came to America. Here he joined Croatian patriotic societies and continued reading of newspapers and literature in general.</p>
   <p>These newspapers bombarded in their editorials Austria-Hungary and the introduction of a commissary in Croatia, without parliamentary rule. When it seemed that Commissary Cuvaj was to hold his position permanently, Doicic decided to assassinate him.</p>
   <p>He arrived in Croatia but did not get a chance to fulfill his intentions. A while after his arrival, a university student, Luka Jukic, attempted to shoot Cuvaj, with the result that it was planned to abolish to rule Croatia <pb facs="5420779_2_0914.jpg" n="3"/>by a commissary and Doicic made arrangements to return to America. But instead of Cuvaj, Baron Skrlec was appointed commisssary, so Doicic decided to stay in Croatia and try his luck on Skrlec. On 18th of August, 1913, Doicic fired a revolver shot at Skrlec, injuring his victim's arm.</p>
   <p>For the attempted assassination of Baron Skrlec, Doicic was sentenced to 16 years in prison. He served in different prisons: Mitrovica, Szeged, Lepoglava, all together over five years after the defeat of Austria-Hungary he was freed. A month ago he returned to America. We asked Doicic what are his present plans in America. He said his intention is to inform the people about the new state of Jugoslavia. He said, "In Jugoslavia is a great disorder. The aristocracy, the clergy and profiteers are taking away from the people all necessities of life." Doicic said he will propose to his people to send to the constitutional assembly at Belgrade, delegates chosen from the Jugoslav immigrants, as it is done by many other foreign nations like Italy and Lithuania. The Jugoslavs in America would be entitled at least to eight or ten delegates.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0915.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Doicic will give a few talks in America about life in Jugoslavia. Workers ought to go to his meetings, to hear what he says and that will open the eyes to those Jugoslavs and Serbians who believe the monarchistic newspapers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
