<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jugoslavia</title> Vol. XIII, No. 6,
<date when="1923-08-25">Aug. 25, 1923</date>
<title level="a">Hard Earned Money for Valueless Shares</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jugoslavia</title> Vol. XIII, No. 6,
<date when="1923-08-25">Aug. 25, 1923</date>
<title level="a">Hard Earned Money for Valueless Shares</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is hard to calculate how much hard earned money the foreigners in the United States spend for buying shares of no value.</p>
   <p>Who could believe that a man will put his money in shares for gold mines or oil fields, which are located in states where the buyer never was or never will be.</p>
   <p>And yet a great number of immigrants throw away their money, induced by a sheet of nicely printed paper.</p>
   <p>Not long ago the Foreign Language Information Service received a letter from the old country in which a brother requested the investigation of the estate of his dead brother, which consisted of shares of seventeen gold mines in the nominal value of $20,000. The heir was willing to sell the shares, but afraid to be defrauded, requested the office to do it for him. He received the answer,that not one of the seventeen companies was registered and could not be found anywhere. The shares could not even bring the value of the scrap paper on which they were written.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0237.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have to understand that in the gold mine for which shares are sold there is not one penny's worth of gold sometimes. The so-called prospector finds a place where, he thinks, there must be gold, he organizes a company of share holders. Most of the shares he retains for himself. With the money received for the shares sold the work is started.If gold is found to reimburse the share holders very well. If there is no gold found the work is stopped. The company exists no longer, all money invested is lost.</p>
   <p>Ninety-nine per cent of one hundred of such gold mines have the same fate. To invest money in such enterprises is very doubtful.</p>
   <p>Nowadays instead of mines, oil field leases are sold on shares. We caution you that if you are not at the place of the mine and you are not versed in that work, do not buy shares of gold or other mines or oil fields.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
