<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 13,
<date when="1937-03-31">March 31, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Resolution Adopted at the Semy-Annual Session of the Supreme Board in March 1937</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0787</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0787.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zajednicar</title> Vol. XXXII, No. 13,
<date when="1937-03-31">March 31, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTION ADOPTED AT THE SEMY-ANNUAL SESSION OF THE SUPREME BOARD IN MARCH 1937</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whereas, there is now before the Senate and the House of Representatives of the United States, a bill to modify the personnel of the United States Supreme Court, embodying changes recommended by Franklin Delano Roosevelt, President of the United States of America, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the intent and purpose of this bill is to so adjust the membership of the Court, that younger men may be appointed form time to time to replace or to aid those passing the age of seventy; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, it is a generally accepted fact that the Supreme Court of the United States, as now constituted has made impossible the enactment and enforcement of laws necessary for the advancement of the laboring people of this country, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, it is plainly evident that the people of the United States on <pb facs="5420779_2_0788.jpg" n="2"/>numerous occasions in the past, have expressed a desire for a more liberal and more humane interpretation of the Constitution, so that it may better serve the interest of all people, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the members of our organization have always opposed reactionary interpretation of law, of government, of government and of constitution, and favor such legislation as would provide a more abundant life for every man, woman and child.</p>
   <p>Be it therefore resolved, that the Supreme Board of the Croatian Fraternal Union of America, representing one hundred thousand native and naturalized citizens of the United States, do hereby declare their wholehearted support of the principles enunciated repeatedly on this subject by the President of the United States, and be it <pb facs="5420779_2_0789.jpg" n="3"/>Resolved, that we direct John D. Butkovich, Supreme President, to convey these expressions of support and cooperation to the President of the United States; to Senator James J. Davis, Senator Joseph F. Guffey, and to each and every member of the House of Representatives from the State of Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>Be it resolved, that a copy of this resolution be spread upon the records of the Croatian Fraternal Union of America, and that it be published in the official publication.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
