<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VIII, No. 112,
<date when="1925-09-17">Sept. 17, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Jugoslav Workers' Bookstore and Our Task</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title> Vol. VIII, No. 112,
<date when="1925-09-17">Sept. 17, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">JUGOSLAV WORKERS' BOOKSTORE AND OUR TASK</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Eleven or twelve years ago our bookstore began to enlarge. Books from the old country were ordered and small booklets printed. Later on larger booklets and even books were printed.</p>
   <p>During the last twelve years books from our bookstore reached the places where Jugoslav workers lived, all over the United States.</p>
   <p>For the success of our bookstore we have to thank our members, who through their work, contributed much. They distributed and sold books and gave financial aid whenever it was necessary.</p>
   <p>Our bookstore in the first place must be supplied with communistic books, but besides them we must have all the literature which is not opposed to Communism. Books from the best authors, such as Tolstoy, Gorky; grammars, dictionaries, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0501.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The last convention of our Jugoslav Section decided to put the bookstore on a more businesslike footing than it has been in the past. It is true that our bookstore is valued at $25,000, but our books were printed years ago and will remain unsold for years. What we need is from ten to fifteen thousand dollars to order books and stationery, because the task before us is to reach the remotest corners with our books, wherever slaves of capital are, to point out to them their true enemy, drag them out of mental darkness, educate new fighters,do away with obstacles which are in the way of the proletarians' liberty. In a word, prepare the working class for social revolution and Communism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
