<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1928-10-31">Oct. 31, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Leader of Jugoslav Educational Association Has Entered the Republican Party Camp</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title>,
<date when="1928-10-31">Oct. 31, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE LEADER OF JUGOSLAV EDUCATIONAL ASSOCIATION HAS ENTERED THE REPUBLICAN PARTY CAMP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>They instruct Jugoslav voters in Chicago to vote for their friends, - the Republican politicians.</p>
   <p>They eventually came out in the clear. Horvat, Kutuzovic, Curcibasic and others. They not only attended secretly Republican meetings and offered their support, but now have come out in the open to work for that party.</p>
   <p>We received a circular together with a personal letter, by Mr. Kutuzovic, in which he spoke about Slavic solidarity and favored the Republican politician Mr. Jaranowski. He said: "He (Mr. Jaranowski) proves his belief in Slavic solidarity by employing a large number of Slavs in his office; he also has in his employ one Croat"(Mr. Kutuzovic). But "if he is elected we may confidently expect him to hire more Croats in his office(in all probability Mr. Cuctkov), they will get jobs, too."</p>
   <p>Mr. Kutuzovic is employed in the Cook County office of Records and Deeds.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0053.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It will be clear to most of us why the leaders of the Jugoslav Educational Association so vigorously opposed the united front with the Jugoslav workers section. The reason was that they are connected with the Republican party. Has the Jugoslav Educational Association guarded against these elements? Did they eject them from their midst? Not at all, as these elements are the very leaders of the association. Novi Svijet is silent and with silence acquiesces that policy. But their members simply try to explain by saying that Mr. Kutuzovic must eat, therefore must earn his bread some way.</p>
   <p>We are not begrudging Mr. Kutusovic his daily bread, but we do care and we are opposed to the fact that such an organization as the Jugoslav Educational Association, counter-revolutionists, mislead workers with lies. We can prove this example and verify our contention that the Jugoslav Educational Association is not a workers' organization but the tail end of the most corrupt bourgeois party in America.</p>
   <p>Recently we invited the Jugoslav Educational Association into the united front to fight together. Today, however, we must openly declare that those <pb facs="5420779_2_0054.jpg" n="3"/>leaders, supporters of the corrupt capitalist party, have no place in any united front, and that it would be the biggest treason to the Communist Party and working class interests. We must unmask those hidden leaders as open capitalists' agents who have no right to be called labor leaders.</p>
   <p>The united front is open only from the bottom, never from the top. There can be only a ruthless fight against traitorous leaders. The united front can be based only on class struggle, never on class deceit. We invite all proletarian elements from the Jugoslav Educational Association to join with us, shoulder to shoulder, in fighting against reactionary and bourgeois agents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
