<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. IX, No. 1,
<date when="1915-12-15">Dec. 15, 1915</date>
<title level="a">Why Complain about Immigrants?</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420779_2_0880</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0880.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CROATIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnicka Straza</title> Vol. IX, No. 1,
<date when="1915-12-15">Dec. 15, 1915</date>
<title level="a">WHY COMPLAIN ABOUT IMMIGRANTS?</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If something is wrong in this country, then the immigrants are blamed in general. Most of the disagreeable things are blamed on the immigrant. Poverty, mental disease, degeneration, lynchings, prostitution -- in short -- all social crimes of our capitalistic order are attributed to immigrants. This assertion is not only brought up by political orators, but also by many very learned men, as are university professors.</p>
   <p>Different investigations proved that many of the mentioned things cannot be attributed to immigrants but, to the contrary, to the native born.</p>
   <p>Statistics published about social problems show that evils cannot be laid to racial differences but to bad economic conditions. It is also shown that a greater percentage of evil is on the side of the native-born than on the side of the immigrants. It is all contrary to the statements of orators and historians.</p>
   <pb facs="5420779_2_0881.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Clear facts disperse myths attributed to immigrants, and here are some:</p>
   <p>The health department of the city of New York published that of one thousand deaths of boys born in American homes, forty-five die before gaining the fifth year. Under the same conditions only twenty-two girls die. In immigrant homes only thirty-nine boys and twenty-two girls. That speaks in favor of the immigrant.</p>
   <p>On the other hand that shows the miserable economic conditions in America, and the longer a family is in this country the more it suffers and the mortality of children increases.</p>
   <p>From a racial standpoint America has to be thankful to the immigrants, because there is one more important fact. If there were no immigrants, the population of America would not increase. It would stay on the same level, or even decrease. Immigrant women bear from 30 to 50 children per 1000. Native-born women bear from 12 to 20 children per thousand. The death rate <pb facs="5420779_2_0882.jpg" n="3"/>for both is 15 per 1000.</p>
   <p>The immigrants are a benefit to this country. America's fate is closely bound to the immigrants. As proof, take American industry, which could not thrive without foreigners.</p>
   <p>Among intelligent people such questions should not come up for discussion, but because there are so many Americans who claim that they feed the immigrants, it is sometimes worthwhile to find out who is feeding who.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
