<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-09-10">Sept. 10, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A Home for One Aged War</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0540</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0540.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-09-10">Sept. 10, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">A HOME FOR ONE AGED WAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While a home for the aged among us Hollanders is as yet a dream, we are happy, as no doubt many others will be, to learn that a practical effort has been made to make a home for one of our aged, namely, for our seventy-two-year-old friend Roelof Stuivenga the founder of "Zelf Hulp," who at this advanced age has become dependent upon the help of friends. Luckily, the old gentleman has many of these. This was proven recently, when the proposal was made to build a home for him on the rear part of the lot at 2437 Huron Street belonging to his son-in-law, Mr. F. Gursch. By donations of the following persons, more than one hundred dollars was collected, in amounts ranging from fifty cents to twenty-five dollars: P. De Vries, F. Gursch, J. Jasper, L. Los, Mrs. R. Los, N. Knol, I. Emmering, H. Wolterding, J. R. Wels, Chas. Liesendahl, Abbinga and wife, Mr. J. Kruisenga, J. Smith, J. Berghuis, J. Brons, M. Krekel, F. Van Derwallen, J. Komen, P. Van Wanroy, A. Heis, and B. Dykstra.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0541.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This sum is being used exclusively for the purchase of lumber and other materials for the building of the home, which is already occupied by Mr. Stuivenga and can be seen by anyone who is interested. It is a simple but tidy home, although it is not yet finished. Sixty dollars is still required to trim it, and to protect the aged occupant against the winters' cold.</p>
   <p>The labor connected with this undertaking is being donated without charge by the carpenters Los, Bring and J. Jasper, who have started this work of charity and hope to complete it. With hearty thanks to those who have supported their efforts thus far, they implore Onze Toekomst to make an urgent call upon the good will of our fellow Hollanders, asking them to make a contribution, regardless of how small it may be, so that this beautiful act of charity may be brought to a successful conclusion.</p>
   <p>Anyone who would like to assist in this cause may send his contribution to the editor of this paper or to L. Los, 1723 North Robey Street, or R. Stuivenga, 2437 West Huron Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
