<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-09-15">September 15, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Opening Day at Chicago Christian High School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-09-15">September 15, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">OPENING DAY AT CHICAGO CHRISTIAN HIGH SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It chanced, last Tuesday morning, that I turned my steps to the neighborhood of 69th &amp; May Street. The newspapers had announced that vacation days were over for many thousands of school children in our land.</p>
   <p>And we had been informed from the pulpit and by church papers that our Christian schools, too, were to open their doors on September 7. Since my duties required my stay for some time in the immediate neighborhood of the Christian High School, I could not withstand the temptation to nose around a bit. I saw virile youngsters open the door and disappear up the stairs of the school building. I saw what I took to be teachers, now and then, step through the same entrance.</p>
   <p>It was after considerable internal turmoil that I finally drew up enough courage to enter the building after them. I had known the former principal, Mr. Fakkema quite well, and for a moment I expected to see him there, but then I remembered that he had undertaken the difficult task of general secretary of the Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0114.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>No sooner had I reached the head of the stairs then I saw the familiar figure of Mr. Dykema, the custodian. For years, now, he has helped to make the students feel at home, and I noticed with interest that both boys and girls grouped about him and greeted him with a hearty Hello Pa! The new principal, Mr. Brjema, I had seen in Roseland once or twice before, But now I wondered how he would handle the situation at school, and I must say, that I was favorably impressed with the expedition and efficiency with which the many problems connected with opening school, were met, under the new administration. It was evident that his colleagues were cooperating wholeheartedly. By this time one of the teachers spied me and very kindly showed me the various rooms and answered my many questions, though they must have seemed somewhat childish to him. I learned that the high school was offering a general course, a teacher's course, a scientific course and a two, three, or four year commercial course.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0115.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was told to me that Miss Bode was the newly-appointed head of the commercial course. And when I got a good look at her I felt that the Board had made a wise choice. Miss Hammekool, Mr. Sietsema, Mr. Swets, Mr. De Boer and Mr. Mauw were back for another year, and the teaching staff again numbers seven. Naturally, I wanted to know whether the school had grown, and I was glad to hear that more than fifty new students had enrolled, and that the total enrollment was now one hundred and sixty students at the least. It has become necessary to have some classes come in the morning and others in the afternoon until larger quarters are secured. (The teacher said something about a "two shift idea," and according to my present understanding, that might have something to do with automobiles, but I did not want to show ignorance by asking about it). What a contrast with its beginning in the old church building at 72nd and Loomis streets. When my guide began enthusiastically to speak about the new building, that was being built at 71st and May streets. I determined to see that also, since I was so near it, anyway. I went my way there with a gladdened heart.</p>
   <p>S. C. Ribbler.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
