<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-01-08">Jan. 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. H. Vander Ploeg's St. Nicholas Speech</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-01-08">Jan. 8, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">MR. H. VANDER PLOEG'S ST. NICHOLAS SPEECH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Record Herald of December 9, 1908, there appears a reprint of the speech, delivered by Mr. H. Van der Ploeg, at the dinner of St. Nicholas Society, in which the Hollanders in America, especially if they are supporters of Christian education, are being put on trial in such a way, that cannot pass unnoticed.</p>
   <p>To my great pleasure, I noticed that Onzetoekomst already reflected on it, in its issue of December 25, in which unreservedly takes up the challenge for Christian education, concerning the reprint of the speech, which appeared in the Record Herald, cited in a broad sense in the above mentioned number of Onzetoekomst.</p>
   <p>The speech of Mr. Van der Ploeg brings out the following points: 1. That the Dutch in America are of a very poor origin. 2. That as a result of this they are backward and even unable to grasp the meaning of education. 3. That the establishment of Christian schools is the ultimate consequence of this.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0170.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>4. That the Christian schools are entirely misplaced and unfit to make Citizens, fit for our American Nation. First we draw your attention to the fact that we champion the name Christian schools against, (as they were referred to by the speaker): Parochial and Private schools. Our Christian schools are not parochial nor private, they are rather the only institutions for elementary education, which can claim the title, Free Schools.</p>
   <p>The speaker stated that the Netherlanders who emigrated to America are of poor origin, that is largely true. It was not often that luxury brought them to America, that is certain, but nearly always betterment of their position, which made them take this long journey, for the rumors that came from here were always encouraging and continually tempted others to come to America. Wonderful opportunities were to be found in America,it would be foolish for any person to pass them up. Therefore it is improbable that their poor origin was the cause of being backward and unable to grasp the idea of higher education.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0171.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is a known fact, that once established in this country, seeing that the manacles of poverty had fallen off their hands, they advanced far beyond those of other nationalities. Or do you think this is an exaggeration? Let us then turn to the facts.</p>
   <p>If it is reasonably correct that Chicago has a population of 2,000,000 people of which 20,000 are Hollanders, this would constitute 1% of Chicago's population. Now study the telephone directory, take carefully from it all the Dutch names, multiply them by 100, and you will find there would be need for a much larger directory than we have at present. Go still another step down the National ladder and compare their love for freedom. This battle for freedom was fought by the Dutch people as a whole, as well as by the individuals and this battle goes on unabated.</p>
   <p>Back in the sixteenth and seventeenth centurys, they fought for religious and political freedom, and from the Netherlands, the Reformation spreaded over Western Europe, its influence was felt far beyond.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0172.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is that love of freedom, which has grown indestructible in the Dutch people. When through the French revolution, unnatural and unbearable bonds were made, then the freedom-loving people could not be held in check, and in 1834, at the separation of church and state, freedom of the church was anew acclaimed. Meanwhile something happened that can be called something new in history. Until now the battle was waged in spiritual, political and national terrain, but the task of making education free had just begun. Our youth was being considered. Elementary education had until now been more or less checked. At first it was Rome, and after the Reformation the Reformed church also took possession of education, and tried to use it to its own advantage. Then came the reaction, and the schools became state-property, and education was not free, except where the free school was established.</p>
   <p>In the Netherlands they are becoming increasingly popular and the public or state schools are gradually becoming the exception whether the free schools are Christian schools, makes no difference.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0173.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The other parties have the same opportunity, but on this point they seem more lax, for when it came to a fight for freedom. The free school is yet in its infancy, and if it is true, as is being claimed that this century is for the child, then you will realize that the child can no longer be tied by unnatural bonds, and they will give to him the freedom to which he can legally lay claim. This can only be accomplished in a free school, which is under the control of the parents. The child belongs to the parents. When a child is born it becomes a member of the family, and the parents have the right, and are responsible for the entire upbringing, and it is an abuse, when the state says to the parents: You are responsible for the entire bringing up of the child, except his education for which I am responsible because it can not be entrusted to you. But the parents who understand their full responsibility, will not turn them over to the state, but will undertake to educate their own children.</p>
   <p>This proves that Mr. Van der Ploeg was wrong when he declared that the champions of the free school, stood in the way of freedom and progress.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0174.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It is just against the enemies of the free school which we are protesting, they are too conservative, too backward on the problem of education to realize, (as the speaker said), the new order of things. I deem it improper to reply to the last point of the speaker, namely that the above mentioned schools are unfit to make good citizens for our American nation, for two reasons. The first because this case was made plain in Onzetoekomst of December 25, 1908. Second because, as Onzetoekomst rightfully pointed out that this teasing is too low, and the honor of the free school demands that we remain silent on that score. I wish to make only one more remark, namely, the entire of Mr. Vander Ploeg speaks of thoughtlessness and carelessness.</p>
   <p>The speaker is well known as a famous lawyer, and has the undivided trust of the entire Dutch element and his influence reaches to far beyond that. Correctness and completeness always earmark his work and it is continually to his honor to do everything complete. It remains a puzzle to the undersigned, how a man like Mr. Vander Ploeg, without studying the case in the least, could make a vicious attack on the Hollanders pet Jewel, as though it were only trash.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0175.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>I also appreciate the value of the public schools but that is no reason why we should throw our ideals overboard. We trust that Mr. H. Vander Ploeg will confess that he missed the ball, and if such is not the case then he will reply to the above article.</p>
   <p>L. De Boer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
