<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-10-13">October 13, 1926</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-10-13">October 13, 1926</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The organ concert, which was given by Abraham Alt of Bolsward, The Netherlands, in Orchestra Hall last Thursday evening, was a complete success. The weather was favorable so a large crowd of Hollanders and Holland-Americans took advantage of the occasion. The attendance was estimated at more than 1,600 persons. As to the organ music and the singing-we loved it, and we owe Mr. Sunhouts and the "League of Societies" of the First Christian Reform Congregation, a word of thanks for the good which through their efforts was given to our race. That Mr. Alt is a master of the pipe organ is doubted by no one. But the fact that he gave us music for a large part of which at least, translated feelings that are alive in our people, and which bring out individuality, made it that much nicer. Our souls could be elevated with the music to Him to whose honor all things must be.</p>
   <p>Among the listeners were reporters from the large daily papers and, at least two of these appeared the next morning with a good report of the recital of the "Dutch organist." There was very little criticism. Both papers bore witness to the ability of Mr. Alt, although they would compare him with American organists, due to the fact that he produced something entirely different from what is given to the American public, as a rule.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0403.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Alt reproduced the art in all its beauty and splendor, just as it was practiced in earlier years, while our present organists allow themselves to be dragged along by the spirit of hilarity and haste, by which art is represented; not in the stately and deft way which marked the concert of Mr. Alt. What struck us in one of the reports was the mention that Mr. Alt's organ music had a classic character, instead of being born or composed by him. His own compositions were not left unnoticed, and made a very good impression.</p>
   <p>The entire program, judging by the hearty applause, was well appreciated. We end with the wish that the League, or any other society, will prepare for us a similar wholesome evening of pleasure and that the public may again respond in the same spirit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
