<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-12-07">Dec. 7, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">[Roseland Mutual Aid Society Elects Officers]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-12-07">Dec. 7, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">[ROSELAND MUTUAL AID SOCIETY ELECTS OFFICERS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The forty-third yearly meeting of the "Roseland Mutual Aid Society" was held on the evening of November 29th in the Knights of Pythias Hall of Roseland. After the President had opened the meeting they proceeded with the smoking program, which consisted of the smoking of famous stogies, which soon so filled the hall with tobacco odor that there was cause for the dropping of many a tear by gentlemen, who were not accustomed to the agreeable odor of stogies. This annual business was indulged in while the election of the administration was in progress. The first thing which drew the attention of the 270 Dutch-Americans was the election of a president. Mr. Bylstra, former President, and Mr. Vos, acting President, was nominated for this office, and the result of the voting was, that Mr. Vos was again chosen to serve the Society another year in a presidential capacity. The one elected on such an occasion is always prompted to make a fitting speech, and Mr. Vos made a good one about a certain cow owned by a certain farmer, who gave as much milk as she could, according to the farmer. Of the three nominated candidates for vice-president, Ed. Elzinga, P. de Young, and Ed Posthuma, the ballots showed Mr. Posthuma to be the one that was elected. And Mr. Posthuma made a speech about many cows, a <pb facs="5420781_1_0278.jpg" n="2"/>calf and a steer, which speech was liked by everyone. For the office of secretary, E. Elzinga, A. Blystra, and J. Bokma were nominated and by an eventual re-election between the two last Mr. Bokma was chosen. Mr. Bokma gave in his speech a story about two Irishmen and a Scotchman. Following this was the election of the Board of Directors. After seven gentlemen were nominated, three directors were chosen by the meeting, namely Fiezenberg, Elzinga, and A. Blystra. P. de Young as Vice-President, A. Blystra as Secretary, and William Dekker as a member of the Board of Directors had served the Society in their respective positions for many years, one longer than the others, but they all had served very well. To them we owe a word of thanks for their sacrifice in this case. The yearly meetings are being attended much more than they formerly were; much, for reason of the congenial company that one meets there once a year. This year the net profit was only $20. We can be proud of the Society in some cases,but certainly not financially, which is of the utmost importance but circumstances sometimes can not be avoided.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
