<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1907-08-30">Aug. 30, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Smoking in Streetcars</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1907-08-30">Aug. 30, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">SMOKING IN STREETCARS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of late one of our newspapers has been publishing several articles regarding smoking in streetcars. Someone made a complaint that the open cars' three back benches where smoking is allowed are often occupied by women, thus depriving smokers of these seats. On the other hand, others criticize the smokers and point out that other fare-paying people have as much right to these seats as the smokers.</p>
   <p>It seems to us that this discussion about smoking in streetcars has been raised in the nick of time. The writer of this article is by no means an enemy of smoking. He does not think that it does any injury or is unhealthy, except in some cases. But the nasty and ill-bred manner in which some gentlemen blow their smoke in the faces of other passengers, deserves everyone's disapproval and demands a severe reproof. Not only the last three benches, but sometimes all the seats of the open cars, are occupied <pb facs="5420781_1_0234.jpg" n="2"/>by smokers. Closed cars' platforms are always taken by men who smoke, so that when a passenger opens the door to leave the car he has to cross through a cloud of smoke. The public ought to protest against this.</p>
   <p>In general, for the sake of cleanliness, the average American is very careful with his smoking at home. He is so polite as to even take his hat off in an elevator when women are present. In a streetcar, however, he is the most impolite and ill-bred creature on earth. No wonder that some of our streetcars look like pigsties.</p>
   <p>Smoking in public where there is a mixed crowd, ought to be forbidden. We hope that the present drive leads up to it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
