<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1911-02-17">Feb. 17, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of Zelf Hulp.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1911-02-17">Feb. 17, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF ZELF HULP.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1. The annual meeting of the burial fund, Zelf Hulp, held last week on Wednesday evening, was one of the most peaceful of that society's meetings. There were only 205 members present, and they were able to preserve order from beginning to end. According to the secretarial report, the society, on January 1, 1911, had 13,627 members; an increase for the year of 468 members. On January 1, 1911, there was $40,969.46 in the treasury; an increase of $1,924.70 since January 1, 1910. Of this sum, $40,881.00 was the required reserve, leaving a balance of $88.46.</p>
   <p>All the outgoing officers, without exception, were re-elected. Even the president, vice-president and treasurer, were re-elected by acclamation.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0485.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A highly important decision was passed and accepted by the board, namely, to change article 2 of the bylaws to read as follows: Persons who are Dutch by birth or descent, or who have married someone of Dutch birth or descent, and who are from three months to 59 years old, can, when they are in good health, become members of this society. This proposal was accepted with the inclusion of two other amendments, which read that not only Dutchmen, but also Belgians by birth or descent can become members and that the children of members, who are not from Dutch descent, may also be accepted as members. Thus children, of other foreign nations, whose parents are members, may join but no others. A few other minor changes in the by-laws were made, but most of the proposals could not be discussed, because most of the members left immediately after the election. As a sufficient number of members did not remain to form a quorum no lawful decision could be made. A noticeable improvement over former years was the fact that there were four ballot boxes instead of one. The election was thus made easier, and the counting simplified.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0486.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are sorry to say that the worthy treasurer of the society, Reinder Mulder, was unable to attend the meeting, because of illness. This was the first time that his place, at a general meeting of the burial fund, was vacant.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
