<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-07-07">July 7, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">[Christian Psychopathic Hospital]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-07-07">July 7, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">[CHRISTIAN PSYCHOPATHIC HOSPITAL]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On July 5th, we paid a visit to the Christian Psycopathic Hospital at Cutlerville, Mich. It was not our first visit as we had been there often. Since our last visit, one building has been completed and an entire new one added, which is a sign of expansion, but not enough expansion. The buildings are overcrowded in the basement. Some rooms were even built in the basement for patients, and the beds are too close together. But under the circumstances, it cannot be different. The administration is anxious to fill all application for space, but is unable to do so. Many applications have been turned back for lack of room, and the lack of room is a consequence of lack of money, and the stinginess of many of us towards this project. A visit to the hospital makes one feel again, what a large gift God has given us, in a healthy brain, and how awful it would be if one had to miss that. For that reason we are called upon to help these unfortunates as much as possible, and show them our charity. In this it is part of our calling as Christians to give to our nervous sufferes and the insane, Christian treatment. We noticed again how orderly and clean everything locked. That the treatment there is unsurpassed we found through one of our friends, A. Vogel, one of the nerve patients, with whom we spoke. Let us remember this institution in our prayers and donations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
