<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-02-23">Feb. 23, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">[Good and Bad Moving Pictures]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-02-23">Feb. 23, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">[GOOD AND BAD MOVING PICTURES]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Christian Reformed church young-men's society in Chicago have hired the large Orchestra Hall, in which it will present a moving picture about Martin Lather and his times, which is the period of the Reformation. The profits will be for the Chicago Christian High School. The leadership of this meeting is assigned to two ministers of the Christian Reformed Churches of Chicago. The Boy's Society, before it started on this venture, asked the advice of the consistory under whose control it stands. The consistory found no reason for objection. We do not speak about the purpose to which the money will be given, because that in itself would not justify the case, if the case were not right in itself. But the venture, in our opinion, should not be rejected. The Boys Society has sufficient guarantee that the pictures, which will be shown on the canvas, will be about Luther and other persons and events of that time, which are educational and proper. That is the first demand that may be attached to such a case. The second demand that the pictures be shown under Christian leadership and in a Christian atmosphere, is also complied with. The leadership is put under our men and the people attending are our own Christian people. Thus we may not place such a showing in the same category with the moving pictures, which are condemned by us all.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0445.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the worldly places they have mostly disorderly and crime building pictures, and they are being shown in a worldly atmosphere. But just because the world misuses God's creation, is no reason why the Church should let go of them. For then we should have to let go of all books, music, songs and all art. For example, what rotten filth there already is in our daily papers. But against this misuse of God's creation by the world God's people show the right use for it. And then it cannot be denied that, pictures whether they are slides or moving, are a gift of God to education. Every one of us has a picture Bible to explain that, which the word of God teaches. And so we have in City Mission, Jewish Mission or Foreign Mission, pictures, which we show to our people. We have also had in Chicago other moving pictures, for example the Christian Charity in Germany. Although there is no evidence against this case, a word of warning is in order, namely, that we know the difference and do not go over from one to the other. That we should not take such a moving picture as reason to go to other bad, worldly, moving pictures. The danger cannot be denied, that there are always young people, who cannot recognize the difference. Against this, earnest warning should be given. And another warning is, that we have not too many of those plays. A picture or slide may be in its place, but that is not the point. As men, Women, young men and young daughters, we must make progress through study and by investigation, in society and in the home. That must be the main object and not the pictures.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
