<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-03-04">Mar. 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Interesting Lectures about the Netherlands</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-03-04">Mar. 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">INTERESTING LECTURES ABOUT THE NETHERLANDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Higgenbotham, well-known lecturer of the Daily News, will give a lecture illustrated with lantern slides next Tuesday evening, March 8, at the large auditorium of the Medill High School, 14th Place and Throop Street. The subject of his lecture will be "The Netherlands."</p>
   <p>This lecture will be given at the request of the Chicago Section of the General Netherland's League, for the benefit of the Dutch public. Although the lecture will be delivered in English, Mr. Higgenbotham speaks so plainly and interestingly that he will be understood even by those whose knowledge of the language is very limited.</p>
   <p>Mr. Higgenbotham has made a special trip to the Netherlands to collect material for this lecture, and therefore it can be expected that his <pb facs="5420781_1_0469.jpg" n="2"/>assertions will be based on reliable data. Besides, we can expect an American to discuss the subject impartially and without prejudice, a thing which, perhaps, cannot be said always of a countryman when he speaks about Holland. We do not mean that a countryman would not tell the truth, but we Hollanders cannot speak as impartially about the Netherlands as an American.</p>
   <p>Therefore, do not stay home this time as usual. The Board of Education has given the hall voluntarily for the use of the lecture, and we have to show that we appreciate its interest in us. Once more--the lecture will be held Tuesday, March 8, at 8 o'clock in the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
