<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1923-06-06">June 6, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago as a Center of the Netherland Civilization.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0426</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0426.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1923-06-06">June 6, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO AS A CENTER OF THE NETHERLAND CIVILIZATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It may sound strange to call Chicago a center of the Netherland civilization but that nevertheless is the truth. Who ever looks upon the proud buildings and no less upon the proud people on Michigan Boulevard at Chicago, will not suspect at a first glimpse that here is a true center of Holland art and culture, but by further investigation it is revealed in its full glory. The Art Institute in the first place, where Netherland art is being shown and admired. On the southwest corner of the main building one may see the names of Rubens, Rembrandt, Van Dyck, Feniers, Hobbema, Ruijsdael, and other famous artists, while inside a great collection of Holland master-pieces of the afore mentioned and of yet later artists are hung on the walls.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0427.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not only is here represented the old school of Rembrandt and Rubens, but also the newer school of Joseph Israels, Mesday, and Maris as well as others. Also the more decorative art such as Delft porcelain and earthenware. But more, also the planning of the Art Institute was for the most part Dutch, because of the most well known and beloved teachers in the drawing and painting was a Netherlander, Mr. John H. Vander Poel, whose book, The Human Figure, can be bought in all bookstores, and today, Mr. Herman Rosse, a Netherlander, known master in the decorative art, is one of the most important teachers at the institute. Further north on Michigan Boulevard is the Chicago Public Library. For a long time the library has had many Holland books as well as some Netherland newspapers and periodicals. The books were badly aged and in a bad condition.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0428.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Recently the library received an exceptionally good collection of Holland books from Martinus Nyhoff, of the Hague, out of which collection is delivered the best of the new Netherland culture: poetry novels, prose, history, travel stories, colonial culture, and so forth. The names of the writers are world famous, Couperus, Van Eden, Multatuli, Heyermans Borel, Buysse, Emants, Helene Swart, Schendel, de Meester, Ouerido, Sable Scharten, Antink, Streuvels, Kloos, de Clerg, Fruin, Derwey, and many others more or less known.</p>
   <p>It was a pleasure to the writer to see the flower of this literature and to recommend it, because the librarian, C. B. Roden, had asked for Dutch advice, and through the medium of the Consul General John Vennema, Mr. C. Grentzebach were enable to give this advice. If only there is no shortage of Dutch readers, then this new collection may bear much fruit. Also the John Grerar Library across from the Public Library, has an exceptional treasure of Dutch books, <pb facs="5420781_1_0429.jpg" n="4"/>possibly a couple of thousand. These books are more on scientific terrain, economics, nature study, technical subjects, history and states archives, in which this library is exceptionally wealthy. For a Dutch student, this collection is invaluable. North of the river is the Newberry Library, which has also a good collection of Dutch history and theology, and in this it has for long excelled. Also there is a number of Netherland periodicals; and you are well treated there. To make the measure full, the University of Chicago has also a good many of Dutch study books, and Dutch knowledge ranks high there. The name of the new president is Ernest de Witt Burton, who favors the Netherlands even as his predecessor, Dr. Judson.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0430.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Chicago has thus a generous supply of Dutch art, culture and knowledge, so may also the existence of a paper as Onze Toekomst be of much joy, as well as the youngest movement which has as its purpose to give to Queen Wilhelmina an Art Album. That the ignorant criticise this, does no honor to the Netherlander, for without the Netherlands and the House of Orange, world history would have taken a different course and a free and Protestant America would have been impossible. Whoever will not honor the Netherlands and her beloved Queen Wilhelmina in this 35 year reign jubilee, has very little conception of the origin from which he sprang or the spring from which he drank.</p>
   <p>A. Oasterheert.</p>
   <p>Representative of the Netherland abroad.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
