<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-04-30">Apr. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Comparison</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-04-30">Apr. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">COMPARISON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Editor: Will you please allow us some space in your widely read newspaper? When we are asked how the public schools are going, we answer, "Excellently." Not only are the taxpayers eager to pay their share, but the parents also are eager supporters, and make a special and individual contribution.</p>
   <p>In Roseland, for instance, there is a school, a public school, where they want certain things done. The city however considers such expenditures unnecessary, so a way has been devised to raise the necessary money. The children will perform a "drill." The majority of the school children, as well as parents and others who are interested, must pay admission to see the show. A great deal of money has already been collected. The sponsors of the public school system certainly support the principle of public education,regardless of how inadequate that education may be.</p>
   <p>We also have our parochial schools, consecrated to Jesus Christ, who died for suffering humanity, and yet it is difficult to collect money for our schools, <pb facs="5420781_1_0203.jpg" n="2"/>for our parochial schools. Our churches are full to overflowing on Sundays. When I think of the meager financial support given to the parochial schools, I am forced to ask: "Christians, what evidence do you give of your Christian beliefs? Do you imagine that simply by going to church, you are giving evidence of your beliefs? Do you not know that the seed of Christian life is a war against the [secular] world, which is a world of sin? In the public schools they are teaching the children to dance, and other such immoral practices. Using our parochial schools as weapons, we must war against the evil that is being disseminated among the children in the public schools. Therefore we say, Prove your faith and show your principles by your deeds. Prove that you believe that you are only the servants of the Lord. Prove that from the earthly possessions, of which the Lord has made you the administrators you will give as much as you can for the Lord, and that includes your support of parochial education. Therefore to arms, men, women, and children, who have allied together under the banner of the Cross, and prove that your interest in parochial education is as fervent as is that of the secular world toward public school education."</p>
   <p>A friend of Christian education</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
