<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1908-07-24">July 24, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Garritt L. Kries Candidate for County Commissioner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0328</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0328.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1908-07-24">July 24, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">GARRITT L. KRIES CANDIDATE FOR COUNTY COMMISSIONER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In this election our people are enjoying the honor of seeing the name of one of their countrymen on the Republican ticket as a candidate for County Commissioner. He is Garritt L. Kries, a man well known to our readers. He is a man who has lived among us for years, and has never been ashamed of being a Hollander; instead he has always regarded it as an honor to be one of a people who once fought for the civil and social freedom of the Middle Ages, and who are still known as the most liberty-loving people on the face of the earth.</p>
   <p>It does not surprise us to learn that Mr. Kries' father, who emigrated from the Netherlands to America before his son was born, sacrificed his life for freedom of his new country as a soldier in the Civil War.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kries was born in Allegan, Michigan, in 1859, and came to Chicago with his parents when he was a child. Mr. Kries belongs to a famous Dutch family <pb facs="5420781_1_0329.jpg" n="2"/>of which every Hollander can be proud. His uncle, A. C. Tris, who came from the Netherlands in 1851, and spent his life doing missionary work among the Jews in New York, was known by practically every Dutchman in America and was respected by all.</p>
   <p>In his youth Garritt Kries was trained as a printer, but he was forced to give up this work because of his health. He opened a grocery store and market at 477 Western Avenue, and has been successfully operating that business since 1892.</p>
   <p>His ability as a politician is demonstrated by the fact that for several years he has been the acknowledged leader of the Republican party in the Thirteenth Ward, and one of the most esteemed politicians of the West Side. He has been asked many times to become a candidate for alderman, but although grateful for the honor he has always declined it.</p>
   <p>This time, however, he has heeded the insistence of his many friends and has <pb facs="5420781_1_0330.jpg" n="3"/>agreed to become a candidate for the office of County Commissioner, mainly because this office administers the public charities, and the interests of the poor, sick and helpless of the county. Mr. Kries knows of no more satisfactory duty than that of keeping the interests of unfortunate people at heart.</p>
   <p>He reared and educated three of his nieces, and has provided a nephew with an education which has enabled him to move in the best social circles. This is an indication that, although he has no children of his own, he is deeply concerned with the welfare of others.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of every Dutchman to cast a vote Saturday, August 8, for our countryman, Mr. G. L. Kries.</p>
   <p>It is seldom that we have the opportunity to recommend a Hollander for an important office--a Hollander who, through education and experience, is qualified for the position--and therefore we cannot place too much emphasis on the fact that the people must not forget to vote for him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
