<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1913-02-21">Feb. 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Christian School at Englewood</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0144</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0144.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1913-02-21">Feb. 21, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHRISTIAN SCHOOL AT ENGLEWOOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Monday evening, February 17th, the Society of Christian Education at Englewood held a very important meeting in the basement of the First Christian Reformed Church at Englewood.</p>
   <p>This meeting was especially important on account of the decisions taken regarding the raising of school money and the defrayment to meet the expenses for education.</p>
   <p>The large attendance furnished proof that the importance of the meeting was clear. There were at least 180 members present.</p>
   <p>A committee, who at the request of the Board had instituted an inquiry of the desirability to change the existing method of raising school money, reported by word of Mr. G. Dekker that at present 190 children are attending the school and that the current expenses for this year will amount to about $5,400.00, making $1.60 a month for each child.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0145.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee made a motion that the school-fee for each child should be put at $1.60 per month, and that a supplementary fund should be created for the support of those parents who are having many children at school and who are not able to pay the full amount.</p>
   <p>Both proposals were carried and a committee of fifteen persons was chosen, which will work as administrators for the supplementary fund.</p>
   <p>The education in some cases will cost much more. One of the members declared to have five children at the school and thus now will have to pay eight dollars a month for school-fee. The sacrifice of the parents, who have done so much for Parochial Education commands profound respect.</p>
   <p>In Englewood existed until now the so-called progressive system regarding the raising of school-fee, being for one child $1.25, for two children $1.75 per month, etc. This will now be changed on forthcoming April 1st.</p>
   <p>At the school in Englewood are working at present seven teachers. Mr. A. S. de Jong is the principal.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0146.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At this meeting were also elected representatives for the approaching federal diet and a determination made not to enter into the proposal of the league to hold, hereafter, one federal diet a year instead of two but to continue assembling every half year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
