<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1921-08-05">August 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Si Vis Pacem, Para Bellum. (If You Want Peace, Prepare for War).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0336</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0336.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1921-08-05">August 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">SI VIS PACEM, PARA BELLUM. (IF YOU WANT PEACE, PREPARE FOR WAR).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of the coming disarmament meeting to be held in the Fall at Washington, D. C., where the disarmament question shall be discussed, we do not have great expectations. At least not as far as actual disarmament is concerned. In the first place, because of the ever growing hate and jealousy among the peoples, such a disarmament agreement constitutes nothing else than blinding one another. Officially they may agree to a certain extent but in another manner they will continue their war preparations. In the second place, armament as well as disarmament cannot be controlled.</p>
   <p>Build some 5,000 airplanes to fly the mail across the country. A beneficial thing. Those machines, with strong motors, bring the mail, say, from New York to Chicago. In a few hours they make the trip, dropping in flight heavy mail bags in the cities which they pass on their given route. But in those 5,000 mail carriers you have also a mighty weapon of war, one of the mightiest to be exact. Those same machines fly like a swarm of birds from off the coast at the coming enemy fleet and drop, instead of mail bags, bombs weighing a <pb facs="5420781_1_0337.jpg" n="2"/>couple of thousand pounds each. And not a splinter of the fleet stays above water. So much for defense.</p>
   <p>Then you have a strong merchant marine. Steamships, who in time of peace spread the commerce of your land over the seven seas and at the same time train many experienced seamen. In war times these merchant ships take on board these bomb-laden mail carriers, and no enemy fleet is safe on sea or in harbor, and there is no enemy fortification or coast defense that is not blown up if the bombs are heavy enough. Last week such a means of warfare was tested. As a target the erstwhile mighty German warship, the Ostfriesland, was used. Bombs of 1,000 pounds T.N.T. were dropped on it. These bombs had some effect. Then bombs of 2,000 pounds were used. These bombs, which were used in the test, missed the ship and fell alongside but when they exploded had such power that through the enormous force of the water the strong steel walls of the warship were crushed as though they were paper cartons.</p>
   <p>Add to this that all factories such as typewriter, needle, mail, etc., in a short time can be transformed for the manufacture of the most accurate bombs; that T.N.T. can be made in numerous industries without detection; that deadly poison gas can be made in paint and whitelead factories, and you see that you <pb facs="5420781_1_0338.jpg" n="3"/>may talk about disarmament and come to lovely mutual agreements but the conclusion does not mean a thing.</p>
   <p>Then they may agree to lessen the building of large warships, which they fear may be sunk at the first opportunity, and possibly we may get our money back a little sooner, but for the real disarmament there is very little hope. Now we hope that Uncle Sam will make 10,000 fast mail carriers, and that our merchant marine may grow in a like measure so that we may be armed when it is necessary.</p>
   <p>In the old days enormous monsters roamed the earth - dinosaurs and the like. These animals were so big that an elephant was, in comparison, like a chicken to a horse. They were conquered by much smaller animals through the use of poison stingers. I have seen a calf being killed by a number of wasps. Let us hope that the U. S. A. will not be such a calf. Let us be armed and they will have respect for us. And let us not give the building of these airplanes into the hands of $1.00 a year men, who during the war have squandered nearly a billion dollars and have not produced a single good and useful machine.</p>
   <p>Van Lonkhuizen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
