<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-02-04">Feb. 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Zelf Hulp</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-02-04">Feb. 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">ZELF HULP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next Wednesday, February 9, the general yearly meeting of the burial fund Zelf Hulp will be held at Handel Hall, 40 East Randolph Street.</p>
   <p>We would have liked not to have mentioned this meeting, but since the board is not following this year the usual method of publishing the meeting, we are compelled to do so. During past years the meetings have been generally announced in Onze Toekomst (Our Future), but it looks as though the board is making an exception this time.</p>
   <p>It is for this reason that we want to call the attention of our readers to the fact that it is of the greatest importance that all franchised members be present to decide upon whom they wish to trust the interests of Zelf Hulp in the future.</p>
   <p>Intentionally, however, we refrain from making any recommendations. Notwith-standing, it would not be difficult in the present circumstances to make a <pb facs="5420781_1_0491.jpg" n="2"/>choice. We are leaving the matter of choice to the opinion of the members, knowing that what has been said by others about this subject is sufficient to serve as a guide in their balloting for directors.</p>
   <p>We know that the public expect our Dutch weekly to give advice on this matter, but people must not take it as ill of us if modesty requires that we refrain this time from recommendation.</p>
   <p>One thing, however, we will say: namely, that we fully agree with the recent decision of the board in the matter of installing a new method of bookkeeping. The system kept by the secretary is not only obsolete and inaccurate, but it is also much too circumstantial. The system can be simplified in such a way as to save half the work and be at the same time more accurate. This would also lead to economy.</p>
   <p>At present two men work regularly in the office. If the secretary could do this work alone, the club would save a lot of money every week.</p>
   <p>Even though in 1909 the so-called free members took up a collection, the surplus <pb facs="5420781_1_0492.jpg" n="3"/>fund has lost about two thousand dollars. A little economy, therefore, should not be superfluous.</p>
   <p>But the installation of a new system of bookkeeping is no child's play. This requires general practical knowledge, which is not possessed by everybody.</p>
   <p>Finally, only this request: that nobody able to come should stay at home; that everybody interested in the welfare of our burial fund should come and cast his vote for such persons as are worthy of the confidence of the public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
