<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-02-09">February 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Zelf Hulp</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-02-09">February 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">ZELF HULP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The report of that society shows that it is in a prosperous condition. Zelf Hulp is one of the few Dutch societies, which has attained a large measure of prosperity. From its founding in 1879, it now counts more than 11,000 members. Notwithstanding the fact that last year more than $9,000.00 was paid out in death benefits, the treasury is in good condition. But we especially draw your attention to the coming annual meeting, when the election of officers must take place. We should not say: "The business is good, it will continue so without me." All those who have the right to vote, should be there.</p>
   <p>Even though the business is going well and on the level, now, your absence could be the cause of the administration of the society falling into hands that are bad. We are loath to imagine such a thing, but it cannot be denied that such a possibility exists. The well being of "Zelf Hulp" depends on the executives who handle the business in the right way, and a Board of Directors, which has the good of the society at heart and does not consider time and trouble too costly to give for the good of all. For this reason, whatever your plans may have been, let these words awaken you, not to stay at home, <pb facs="5420781_1_0517.jpg" n="2"/>but by your presence show that you have the interest of the society at heart. Then vote for officers as well as directors; for men whom you know, that they may have the interest of the society and your interest at heart and apply it consciencitiously. The following items prove the increasing prosperity of the society, which makes further proof unnecessary. Death benefits paid: In 1880, $ 39.00; 1885, $622.00; 1890, $2,415.00; 1895, $5,362.50; 1900, $7,215.00; 1905, $8,720.00. The total death benefits paid during the twenty-seven years of existence of the society amounted to $109,031.50.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
