<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-02-18">Feb. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Age Zylstra for Alderman of the Thirty-Third Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0292</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0292.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-02-18">Feb. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">AGE ZYLSTRA FOR ALDERMAN OF THE THIRTY-THIRD WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our countrymen in the Thirty-third Ward are very fortunate to have the opportunity to vote next spring for a Dutch candidate for the Republican nomination for Alderman. The Dutchmen of Roseland can elect this time a man who will represent them well in the City Council, and they certainly are in need of such a man right now.</p>
   <p>Mr. Age Zylstra is the right man in the right place. Not an aristocrat nor a fine polished gentleman, he is a popular man--a man who through diligence, ability, and will power has worked himself so high up that his fellow citizens cannot but look upon him as a leader, as the only candidate worthy of representing them in the City Council.</p>
   <p>His candidacy is not the work of a couple of friends dreaming that he will bring grist to their mills, as is often the case. No! Mr. Zylstra has the <pb facs="5420781_1_0293.jpg" n="2"/>support of the entire Republican organization, and his candidacy was first urged by the Young Men's Republican Club. This is proof that the young, powerful, and progressive element of the ward sees in him the right person, not only to lead the Republican party to victory next April, but also to represent the Thirty-third Ward in a worthy manner in the City Council.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zylstra is not inexperienced in politics. He profits by the support of such men as E.E. Erstman, one of the principal political leaders of the Thirty-third Ward; Charles W. Vail, the recognized political leader of the town of Lake, and intimate friend of Governor Deneen; and, according to what people say, Governor Deneen himself.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zylstra has lived in Roseland for twenty-eight years, during which time he has held several important positions; he has been Assessor, Deputy Bailiff of the Municipal Court, and Deputy Clerk of the Circuit Court; at present he is Clerk of the Probate Court.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0294.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But we do not have to recommend Mr. Zylstra to the Hollanders of Roseland. Everybody who is acquainted with him knows that he is the very spirit of Dutch-American solidarity, sincerity, honesty, and energy.</p>
   <p>See to it that you don't stay at home on the day of the primary, March 4. Go out and vote early, and make sure that your friends and neighbors, Hollanders, Americans, or whatever they may be, do the same. Let us all vote for Age Zylstra, candidate for the nomination for Alderman in the Thirty-third Ward.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
