<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-02-18">Feb. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Age Zyistra Candidate for the Republican Nomination for Alderman in the 33Rd Ward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0323.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-02-18">Feb. 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">AGE ZYISTRA CANDIDATE FOR THE REPUBLICAN NOMINATION FOR ALDERMAN IN THE 33RD WARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our countrymen in the 33rd Ward are very fortunate to have an opportunity in the spring to vote for a Dutch candidate for the Republican nomination for alderman.</p>
   <p>The Dutchmen of Roseland will nominate a man this time who will represent them in the Town-Council, and they certainly have right thereto.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zylstra is the right man for this office. No aristocrat, but a popular man, one who through diligence, capability, and strength of will has advanced himself, and his fellow-citizens are back of him.</p>
   <p>His candidacy was not set up by a couple of friends. Mr. Zylstra has the support of the entire Republican organization, and his candidacy was launched by the Young Men's Republican Club.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0324.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A proof, that the younger, the powerful, and progressive element of the ward sees in him the right person to lead the Republican party not only to victory next April, but also to represent the 33rd Ward in worthy manner in the Town Council.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zylstra is not a freshman, or inexperienced in the sphere of politics. He has the support of men as E. E. Erstman, one of the principal political leaders of the 33rd Ward, of Chas. W. Vail, the recognized political leader of the Town of Lake, and intimate friend of Governor Deneen, and according to what people say, also the support of Governor Deneen himself.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zylstra has lived 28 years in Roseland. He has filled important offices and positions. Among others, the offices of the Assessor,of Deputy Bailiff of the Municipal Court, of Deputy Clerk of the Circuit Court, and at present he is clerk in the Probate Court.</p>
   <p>We do not have to recommend Mr. Zylstra to the Hollanders of Roseland.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0325.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Everybody who is acquainted with him knows that in him we find the real Holland-American spirit of solidarity, sincerity, honesty, and energy.</p>
   <p>See to it that on the primary day, March 4, you do not stay at home, but go, and vote early, and take care, that your friends and neighbors, either Hollanders, Americans, or other nationalities, do the same, and vote for Age Zylstra, candidate for the nomination of alderman in the 33rd Ward.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
