<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1920-10-01">Oct. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">[Platform of Principles and Action of the Christian Political Organization as Accepted at the Mass Meeting Held September 22, 1920]</title><title level="a" type="sub">Preamble.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0301</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.1.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0301.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 c</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1920-10-01">Oct. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">[PLATFORM OF PRINCIPLES AND ACTION OF THE CHRISTIAN POLITICAL ORGANIZATION AS ACCEPTED AT THE MASS MEETING HELD SEPTEMBER 22, 1920]</title><title level="a" type="sub">Preamble.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(a) We recognize the sovereignty of the Almighty God in every walk of life. (b) We accept without reservation the word of God as to the Christian principles for guiding our political, social and national life. (c) Affirming our faith in the Democratic form of Government, we declare ourselves against all autocratic encroachments and anarchistic propaganda.</p>
   <p>Our Platform.</p>
   <p>1. We especially declare ourselves to be in favor of laws and the enforcements of laws against: (a) Public profanity either by word of mouth or in writing. (b) Public Sabbath breaking. (c) Houses of prostitution, immoral writings, scandalous portraits in newspapers, magazines, movies or on postcards; immoral <pb facs="5420781_1_0302.jpg" n="2"/>plays in theatres, comedies, etc. (d) Laxness in our courts in cases of divorce, murders, holdups, etc. (e) Swindle and bribery by our public servants; usurping of trade, and hasty unnecessary strikes before attempts at conciliation are made.</p>
   <p>2. We demand ability and honesty in every public service and honesty in all dealings with the public. ( b) We demand protection against unnecessary strikes which are a detriment to the public and for that reason propose that all differences, which may come between employers and employees, and which have a bearing on public life, such as public mediums of transportation, be laid before commissions of arbitration instituted and controlled by the City, State, or Federal Government. (d) We recognize the duty of the parents to teach their children and demand that the parents be not limited in their rights to teach the children according to their own conscience and to teach as they will in as far as this is not against the well-being of the State, and if the teachings answer to a certain given standard. (e) We demand that only the teaching of the number of children who attend the public schools, shall be paid for by taxation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
