<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-08-11">August 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The National Union of Christian Schools.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0116</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0116.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-08-11">August 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE NATIONAL UNION OF CHRISTIAN SCHOOLS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Christian Reformed Churches are advised that at the last Synod a letter was received by the Executive Committee from the Board of the National Union of Christian Schools, which read as follows: "Notwithstanding the fact, that the Synodal committee had approved of the request to take up a yearly collection in our churches for the National Union of Christian Schools, the "Stated Clerk" thought it proper to repeat this request, and to lay it before the Synod anew. Heeding this request, we ask the Synod to recommend that in all our churches a yearly collection be taken up for the Union of Christian Schools, preferably on the Sunday before the yearly meeting of the Union, which is held shortly before the opening of the Schools in September. The reasons for this are that our churches have a great interest in Christian education. The growth of the Christian School movement in our land, in our judgment is the foundation of a healthy and reasonable development in church life. We deem it proper, that the collection be taken up just before the annual Union meeting, (shortly before the time that the schools are reopened), because at that time attention is paid to Christian education. The Advisory Committee instructed the Synod to grant this request, and the Synod concurred. On account of this the Christian Reformed Churches are being requested to act according to the decision of the Synod. Mr. Fakhema, who writes about the case, announces that a collection will be highly appreciated, the more so because this year a deficit is in sight. We hope that <pb facs="5420781_1_0117.jpg" n="2"/>the brothers, who spend so much time and talent on this worthy cause, may be made happy through generous contributions from the churches.</p>
   <p>Henry Beets, S. C.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
