<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-10-13">October 13, 1926</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-10-13">October 13, 1926</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p> </p>
   <p>A Dutch musician and artist gave in Chicago a musical program, the report of which will be found elsewhere in this paper. We only mention it here as an example of the truth, known to us all, that in unity there is great strength. The Hollanders have proved by strong unity in the great City of Chicago, that, together, they could promote something good. There happened what has never happened before, that the great Orchestra Hall was filled with Hollanders; that the consecrated music of the Huguenots, the music of our Dutch psalms, the music which was sung many times by martyrs on the fun ral pyre, was heard in the place where usually nothing but worldly tones are heard, that the words of our unequalled Dutch psalms resounded under the mighty arches of the large building. One of the big Chicago dailies wrote, "Orchestra Hall seemed like a mighty Cathedral on that evening, with the consecrated music elevating the hearts." That is different from the "jazz" music of our time. Even the world pauses a while and listens. And we are glad that Mr. Alt, organist of the great Church of Bolsward, made such a good impression even on the master critics of the big Chicago dailies.</p>
   <p>And those critics know what they are about.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0406.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Alt has done honor to the Dutch, which was proved by the reports in the daily papers. So you see, what can be done if we pull together. Mr. Alt was satisfied, the Dutch audience was satisfied, and the Chicago "Apollo Club", which makes the rules for great musical demonstrations, was satisfied. Every one was satisfied. The attendance was 1,600 persons. Total receipts were $1,346.25; total expense for hall rent, advertisements, commissions, etc. $697.50. This leaves a balance of $648.75, of which Mr. Alt gets seventy-five per cent or $486.56 and the league societies of the First Christian Reformed Church, twenty-five per cent, or $162.19.</p>
   <p>A word of thanks to C. Leenhouts, who as President of the League, took the initiative and did a large part of the work and no one was sorry for his $1.00 or 50¢.</p>
   <p>Van Lonkhuisen</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
