<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1920-07-30">July 30, 1920</date><title level="a">Our Privilege and Our Duty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1920-07-30">July 30, 1920</date><title level="a">OUR PRIVILEGE AND OUR DUTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every American citizen of age, regardless of whether he was born here or abroad has the privilege of voting for the man who shall rule the country for the four succeeding years. We do not have to own anything or be a taxpayer to exercise our vote in a City, State or National election.</p>
   <p>Rich and poor may vote and each vote is of equal value. The City dweller has no more votes than the farmer or vice versa. To exercise our vote is at the same time our duty. Each citizen is called upon to do his duty and to do it willingly and diligently.</p>
   <p>In this we must consult our conscience, because it is a responsible task to choose our leaders upon whom so much depends. Ours is a government by the people, because the members of the ruling class are chosen by the people.</p>
   <p>Our form of government has stood the test of time and proved that it is the <pb facs="5420781_1_0284.jpg" n="2"/>best, a republic, which is indeed republican, and which avoids autocratic tyranny and Democratic indifference that must be ours. No Autocratic Government with a bureaucratic president at its head, nor a Plutocratic power which from behind the screens as in a Punch and Judy show, performs at will the manipulation of so many strings, makes our executive officers dance like so many wooden dolls.</p>
   <p>Nor an extremist democracy, which translates Government by the people as meaning: Everyone does what he wishes to do. To neglect our duty is wrong. to make voting compulsory is wrong, but to not exercise this right is unpardonable neglect.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
