<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-03-16">March 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Student Accomplishment</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-03-16">March 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A STUDENT ACCOMPLISHMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is indeed encouraging to note that the students of our Chicago Christian High School appreciate the magnificent new building that has been erected for their use. The following interesting letter from the President of the Athletic Association indicates, that the boys and girls of the C.C.H.S. have tried to do their share toward equipping the new building. S. C. Ribbler</p>
   <p>Mr. Ribbler</p>
   <p>c/o Onze Toekomst</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Ribbler:</p>
   <p>Occupying a prominent place in the catalogue of subjects for conversation among the pupils of the Chicago Christian High School is the new building. It holds unchallenged sway in the realm of student thought. It determines the trend of any lengthy conversation and, seemingly conscious of its power, inspires all with unquenchable enthusiasm. Perhaps we do not feel to the fullest extent the scrifices you are making for us. In fact we know we do not. Nevertheless, we are not entirely unconscious of the burden we are bearing. This is evidenced by the fact that a drive was recently inaugurated by the equipping of the school,-<pb facs="5420781_1_0107.jpg" n="2"/>more specifically the gymnasium. It was at a school gathering in a neighboring hall that the plan was first introduced. The proposition was met with instant acclaim and the eager interest evidenced at the meeting did not expire with time, but grew stronger as the campaign drew to tits close. Not till the last coin had been gathered in did it forsake its lofty level. The students have done remarkably well. Five dollars was the sum each was asked to bring. Only one condition was imposed, that the money brought should be earned "By the sweat of the brow." It was, in many case with difficulty that the student was able to raise their quired amount. Some enterprising young men sold books, others sold papers, beat rugs, delivered orders, cleaned sidewalks, and engaged in all sorts of heretofore unheard of occupations. By tending children, sewing, serving, and engaging in other kinds of feminine usefulness, the girls succeeded in making their five dollars. Then the energetic young women adopted more advanced tactics and began business on a vaster scale - the cake sale grew into being. The gentle shower of hard earned silver now turned with the shifting winds into a varitable deluge. The campaign is over and more than $900 lays ready to be spent for equipment. Because of his capable management of the drive and his inspiring personality, Mr. Swets deserves a large share of the credit for this achievement. Miss Hammekool deserves special mention for her able direction of the cake sales. The sympathetic appreciation evidenced by the entire faculty and Board was a tremendous aid in the accomplishment of this feat. We take this opportunity to <pb facs="5420781_1_0108.jpg" n="3"/>thank our mothers for their splendid co-operation in freely furnishing all the pastry for the cake sales. Above all we owe thanks to Him who is the giver of all good gifts.</p>
   <p>Signed</p>
   <p>Athletic Association C.C.H.S.</p>
   <p>Henry Stob, Pres.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
