<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-02-05">Feb. 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Zelfhulp Election's of Officers, and Contemplated Revision of By-Laws</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-02-05">Feb. 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">ZELFHULP ELECTION'S OF OFFICERS, AND CONTEMPLATED REVISION OF BY-LAWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We wish to call the attention of our readers to the annual general meeting of the "Zelfhulp", which is scheduled to be held next Wednesday evening at Handel Hall, 40 East Randolph Street. This meeting is more important than any other.</p>
   <p>The first question is the election of officers. It is up to us to entrust the administration to capable and honest men, whose integrity is above reproach, or to entrust the "Zelfhulp", with his 12,000 members and a capital of $40,000 to persons who will not devote their time in the organization's interests.</p>
   <p>It is sufficient to make all members, with voting rights, attend this meeting for the sake and interest of the members of the "Zelfhulp".</p>
   <p>Our capital was accumulated by hard-earned money of our working people, who constitute our majority. The new administration must invert our capital in the most profitable and safest way.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0505.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thence the necessity for electing officers whose character and ability are beyond reproach. And at this meeting it is mandatory to discuss the change in our by-laws.</p>
   <p>In the last annual meeting, a committee was appointed for its re-vision. We must not discuss the legality of such a committee, but accept their report. Our present by-laws forbid acceptance of their proposals. We must act on the recommendation at a special meeting. The stipulation, that no radical change in our by-laws can be made without being published and referred to the members two-weeks in advance for their consideration, was purposely inserted in the by-laws.</p>
   <p>We have been informed that, our President plans to call a special meeting immediately after this meeting, the revised by-laws can be accepted without having the slightest idea of its contents by the members.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0506.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are complying with the by-laws, but it is inethical to force an entirely new set of unknown by-laws upon the members. Such a procedure is despotism in the true sense of the word. A revision of the by-laws is a good procedure. By-laws must be changed occasionally to meet the demands of the times, but they should not be forced upon us.</p>
   <p>It is therefore our duty to curb such despotism, and to request that such by-laws be published to the extent that all of us should know its contents before voting.</p>
   <p>Therefore I say again: Members of Zelfhulp, attend! It is your business. The capital in the treasury is your money. Don't let the bosses dismay you with their noises. (Vote for an administration, which has your utmost confidence. You will profit by doing this, because the interest of the society is your own personal interest).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
