<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-01-08">Jan. 8. 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Vander Ploeg's Reply to Editor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-01-08">Jan. 8. 1909</date>.
<title level="a">MR. VANDER PLOEG'S REPLY TO EDITOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago, Dec. 29, 1908.</p>
   <p>Mr. Louis Holstein,</p>
   <p>Editor of Onzetoekomst,</p>
   <p>My Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>I read with surprise your attack on me in Onzetoekomst of December 25th, in connection with your criticism of my address before the St. Micholas Society of Chicago. It is your privilege to differ with me on the question of the value to our people of parochial schools and you also have the right, both as an editor and as a individual to criticise my views upon that, or any other subject. But your statement in reference to me personally, that I cherished a deep and venomous hatred against the Christian education of our young people, caused me to denounce all that was dearest and best in them, is without any foundation or excuse.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0177.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>You read my address and therefore knew how generously I praised our nationality. Among many other things I said is the following: "It will not do to say that these schools are necessary for instruction in the Holland language, or for the purpose of reading the Bible in the schoolroom. The Bible may be and is usually read deily in every well regulated family among our people. In addition to this, the parents who advocate and support these parochial Schools, usually send their children to Sunday School, Catechism and other Church services. Many of them I am forced to say, often make Sunday Service irksome rather than interesting and pleasant for their children, at least it was so in my boyhood days. Let us confess that many of these practices and usages are followed, not from a sincere desire to worship God, but rather because they have been so practised and handed down to us from father to son. We are creatures of a habit, and adaptation to a new environment is often difficult and tedious."</p>
   <p>I do not wish to be considered as saying a single word against the strictest orthodoxy of our Churchs nor against the most faithful observance of the Sabbath day; nor against the deepest study and reverence for the Bible.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0178.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That is part of our inheritance; that is the foundation upon which was built the lasting glory of our people. But this does not require strict adherance to obsolete customs, or the perpetuation of absurd provincial usages.</p>
   <p>The world has always been, and I trust always will be full of change and progress. The great men, who made it better to live in, were men of new ideas and larger conceptions. The progress of the world, the change from the old to the new, our adaptation to the new order of things, is the very essence of our existence. And again: We want to see another descendant of our heroic race become the chief executive of this nation. Not as a distinct Hollander, but as a type of that strong, wise and progressive American Citizenship, that dares and dares again, yes, always dares - with which the possibilities of our race are so pregnant. We do not know what victory or defeat, what success or failure, what glory or shame may be in store for the people of our new and adopted country; but we can rest assured that the men and women of Dutch blood and their descendants will help to maintain and defend its free institutions with that same spirit of self-sacrifice, devotion and valor, which in the 16th and 17th centuries preserved to them the independence of their native soil and won for the people of Holland, the lasting <pb facs="5420781_1_0179.jpg" n="4"/>Why then, did you detach a small portion of my address, and then state that I abused everything that was dear to our Holland people? I have always upheld the good name and glory of our nationality and have always been proud of the fact that I am a born Hollander. My voice has ever been raised and my efforts are always directed for their advancement and welfare, not perhaps as you see it, but as I honestly understand it.</p>
   <p>This does not mean or prove that my judgement is always right, but only that my heart is true to our people. In conclusion it seems to me that it would only be doing simple justice to both of us that my entire address as delivered at the St. Nicholas dinner be published in your paper, so that your readers may judge for themselves whether your accusations are just.</p>
   <p>Yours truly,</p>
   <p>H. Vander Ploeg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
