<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1920-10-01">October 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Report of Political Mass Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1920-10-01">October 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT OF POLITICAL MASS MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mass meeting announced in former numbers of this paper, for the organization of a Christian Political Society was held on Wednesday evening, Sept. 22, in the hall above the Community State Bank, 1637 W. Roosevelt Road, Chicago, Illinois. The hall, although not large, was filled to overflowing, and some had to remain outside for lack of space. On motion of Dr. M. E. Brockstra, Mr. H. Rothof, one of the members of the committee who started the organization, was chosen as chairman of the meeting, because the temporary president of the committee, Mr. F. Hegeman, was out of town. Mr Rothof opened with prayer and in a short speech of introduction, for which he was entirely unprepared and in which he accquainted himself splendidly, explained to the meeting, why the committee was organized and why this mass meeting was called.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0299.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In a few words the speaker pictured the corruptness of politics, and said that Christians should be ashamed to sit idly by. He said the time for unified action has long since come. In particular he pointed out that it is our duty as Christians to take an active part in politics, not for personal gain, but to voice our opinion everywhere that we see corruptness by political officers and in all dealings with the public.</p>
   <p>After this, the speaker asked the temporary secretary to read the minutes of the former committee meetings, so that the meeting would know what had been done to organize. After the reading of the minutes the program of principles and action was read. A motion to deal with this program point by point was <pb facs="5420781_1_0300.jpg" n="3"/>made and accepted with the result that after short discussions, the entire program as it was formulated by the committee was accepted by a unanimous vote. (The platform is on page 8 of this number). "This," said the leader of the meeting, "becomes the basis of the organization." A motion to accept this program as a basis for organizing was made and accepted. Then the business of organizing was taken up. Forty -five persons were immediately enrolled as members. A vote was taken and it was decided that the committee on preparations shall constitute the controlling body. It was empowered to call the next meeting and to bring suggestions for a suitable name for the society. Several other items were taken up after which Dr. Brockstra closed with prayer. The first mass meeting was a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
