<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1923-08-08">August 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Attitude of the Dutch Churches Toward a Carnival Held in Roseland by the American Legion.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0224</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0224.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1923-08-08">August 8, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">ATTITUDE OF THE DUTCH CHURCHES TOWARD A CARNIVAL HELD IN ROSELAND BY THE AMERICAN LEGION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As things stand on Saturday morning, August 4, concerning the much talked of carnival, many rumors are in the air. The local papers claim that the Legion, supported by different organizations as well as thousands of signatures, will go through with the carnival, in spite of the protest of the churches, and will make use of the once issued permit. Further, the papers state that the case is before Judge Sabbath, who will make his decision in the case, whether to prohibit, or to let the carnival go through. Whatever the decision, the carnival must go through says the Legion. And, they say, that the carnival already started, shall officially be opened on Sunday, August 5, at 110th St. <pb facs="5420781_1_0225.jpg" n="2"/>and Indiana Avenue. Those who are opposed are angry at little Alderman Govier, who, they charge, was first in favor, and is now against it, and who now does everything in his power to put the carnival on the rocks, so much so, that the Mayor has said that he would not go against the wishes of the Alderman of the 9th Ward. And so according to all reports it was clear that neither the churches, not the $2,000, which was donated were powerless to curb this sin, and that even politics were powerless, because the decision of Judge Sabbath was in favor of the Legion. It is just as Dr. Hylkema said from the pulpit, Sunday morning, when he made known the decision of the judge, "We can only protest and show our protest by never visiting the carnival, and, we hope above all, that especially our young people will not show themselves there. We concur in this decision and the best we can do against this sinful carnival is to preach the gospel. That and the carnival is to preach the gospel. That and the carnival do not go together.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
