<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1919-09-26">Sept. 26, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Our Christian Schools in September 1919</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Short Regime</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0139</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0139.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1919-09-26">Sept. 26, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CHRISTIAN SCHOOLS IN SEPTEMBER 1919</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Short Regime</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The school year of 1919-1920 is already a few weeks in progress. The idea of this article is to give some particulars of our Christian schools in the Chicago area. There are in the Chicago area now nine schools with the reformed principle; one Christian High school and eight lower schools; five in Chicago proper; and three in the suburbs. The following teachers are in the various schools: Chicago Christian High; Acting principal, Mr. A. Fakkema, two instructors and 60 pupils; Roseland, 110th Place and State Street; Mr. John Vanderark, four teachers and 207 pupils; Roseland, 104th Street; Mr. A. Blystra, principal, seven teachers and 305 pupils; Ebenezer, 1624 W. 15th Street; Mr. H. Kuiper, principal, eight teachers and 337 pupils; Englewood, 7140 So. Sangamon Street; Mr. H. J. Bruinsma, principal, seven teachers and 315 pupils; Timothy School; Trippave, Mr. H. Hendrikse, principal, two teachers and 108 pupils; So. Holland, Illinois; Mr. G. H. Nightingale, two teachers and 100 pupils. Total teachers 46, total pupils, 1632. The teachers are members of the Chicago <pb facs="5420781_1_0140.jpg" n="2"/>Christian Teachers' Association who meet three times a year to discuss teaching problems.</p>
   <p>The different school societies find their unity in the Board of Christian Schools in Chicago and vicinity. This Board meets twice a year to discuss all school problems. At the last Board meeting held, it was resolved to institute a Board of Supervision. This Board shall consist of each local schoolboard and the principals of the different schools. The object of the Board shall be to constitute unity in teaching in the different schools. Through this Board much good is expected; through the medium of this board a moral course in ethics will be opened and opportunity shall be given to Christian teachers to better condition themselves by attending the lessons at Englewood on Saturday morning. So you see, dear reader, that Christian teaching here makes steady progress. We are striving constantly to better the schools for their cause. May the Board protect our schools from contagious diseases which are sometimes causing havoc, among our children; that the parents may be careful in guarding their own and also their neighbor's children in not exposing them through carelessness to contagion.</p>
   <p>Henry Kuiper.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
