<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-01-12">January 12, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Closing of the Saloons on Sunday</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-01-12">January 12, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE CLOSING OF THE SALOONS ON SUNDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Much has been said and written lately, as to whether or not the saloons should be closed on Sunday. Let us say, here and now, that we would strongly favor the closing of the saloons on Sunday. The possibility of this is another question. Then Mayor Dunne was a candidate for Mayor, he was requested by a committee from the "Women's Christian Temperance Union" and representatives of other temperance societies to answer the question: That if he were elected Mayor of Chicago, whether or not he would force the saloonkeepers to keep their doors closed to the public on Sunday? The Nayoral Candidate answered that he was not ready to answer this question, but that he could assure them, the committees, that he would enforce the law as it was actually written.</p>
   <p>Dunne was elected, but the saloons stayed open to the great disappointment of the "Women's Christian Temperance Union". Some assert that <pb facs="5420781_1_0236.jpg" n="2"/>the Mayor does not keep his word and does not enforce the law, and they even call this a wanton violation of the oath which he took when he was installed as Mayor of Chicago. There is, so they declare, a law which prohibits the keeping open of saloons on Sunday and this law is not enforced.</p>
   <p>This declaration is not without good grounds. Indeed there is such a law. Although old, it is not obsolete, but is so covered by political dust and filth that it is hard to find and can,positively not be seen by the naked eye. But the Mayor, and in his name also the Chief of Police, declare that they have nothing to do with the enforcement of this law. It is, so they declare, not a City ordinance, but a State law, which compels the closing on Sunday, and if the State law must be enforced, then they must go to the Governor with their request. The Governor is the man who must take care of that, says Mayor Dunne. The Governor is also deaf to the request. He declares that he was not chosen to act as a bailiff or a policeman. And so things continue. The saloons stay open. No one feels himself responsible enough to enforce the law, be it the Mayor, <pb facs="5420781_1_0237.jpg" n="3"/>the Chief of Police, or even the Governor of the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>Just one question in conclusion: Why do we have so many laws which are being construed as unenforceable? The Sunday Closing law as well as many others, was never enforced and will evidently remain a dead letter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
