<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1908-01-24">Jan. 24, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Progress of Prohibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0220</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0220.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1908-01-24">Jan. 24, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">PROGRESS OF PROHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In one of our newspapers the remark is made that at the moment about 40,000,000 people in the United States are living in so-called "dry" states, counties, or towns, and that prohibition will soon command a much larger territory.</p>
   <p>If the above mentioned statement is true, then the prohibition law prevails among more than half of the inhabitants of our Union. This proves again that if a good cause once finds rest in the people's heart it expands and works as leavened dough "until the whole dough is soured."</p>
   <p>The above-mentioned paper, the Vrije Hollander, complains, however, because the evil is not perceptible in the roots. "Close the distilleries and breweries!" should be the slogan. Only then can people expect results.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0221.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is true enough, but let us observe that as yet we are not that far. This could only become effective through national legislation. And not unless a majority of the population is for prohibition can one expect results.</p>
   <p>We also do not believe in half-baked precautions, and should like to see the evil, caused by intemperance once and for all, put under restraint, but then, people must no longer shout "close the distilleries and breweries," and at the same time say; "But in abstemious use of liquors, we, and millions of others, do not see any harm."</p>
   <p>This is just the mistake. The only way to make an end of the misery, caused through the saloons is, to have them closed forever, and it will be necessary to sacrifice moderate consumption of liquor.</p>
   <p>Through moderate consumption the saloons, breweries, and distilleries maintain their ground, and therefore are assuring the existence of a national evil.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
