<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-04-30">Apr. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Comparison</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-04-30">Apr. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">COMPARISON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Editor:</p>
   <p>Will you please allow me some space in your valuable paper. When we are asked how the public schools are faring, the answer is: Excellent! not only are the taxpayers eager to pay their part but also the parents are eager supporters.</p>
   <p>In Roseland, for instance, there is a school,--a public school,--where they want certain improvements. The city, however, considers them unnecessary; and now they discovered another way to raise money for this purpose. The children perform a "drill". The largest part of the school children, as well as parents and others who are interested, must pay admission to see the show. Already much money has been collected. Those people of the public schools certainly support them.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0165.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We also have our schools, schools with sterling principles. And yet it is difficult to raise money for our schools,--for our Christian schools.</p>
   <p>I wish to ask: Christians, how do you prove your Christian principles? Do you suppose that only by going to church you live up to your principles? Do you know that the essence of Christian life is war against the sinful world? Now in the public schools they teach the children to dance and similar wrong things. Therefore, prove your faith and your principles by your deeds, prove that you believe, that you are only the administrators for the lord, prove that from the earthly possessions, of which the Lord made you administrators, you will secure as much as possible for the Lord's business, among which is also Christian education. Therefore, to arms, men, women, boys and girls who are united under the banner of the Cross, and prove that your interest for Christian education is no less than the one revealed by the world for public education.</p>
   <p>Signed,</p>
   <p>By a friend of Christian</p>
   <p>Education.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
