<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-08-31">August 31, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The New Christian School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0193</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0193.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-08-31">August 31, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW CHRISTIAN SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new Christian school on 15th Street was put in use last Wednesday for the first time. It is a well planned, building, built to meet the demand of the times and the latest building ordinances. It is only natural that on this occasion the children had to celebrate and the celebration was well arranged by the school board. Monday was the day designated for this. At noon the children came with their teachers and a large number of spectators, gathered in the basement of the First Christian Reformed Chruch on 14th Street, which had served so far for class rooms. The hall had been changed into vertible festive auditorium, towards which willing hands of friends of the school had done their bit. And the spirit? You ought to have seen the children. You could read on the faces of those 250 children, what was in their hearts. Happiness as well as thankfulness could be seen on every face. And after they had given sufficient audible proof of their acquired knowledge and the teachers also had spoken a word of thanks and encouragement, the children did real justice to the refreshments which were served to them. When the feast was at an end they all went in a parade to the new school, and then home. In the evening the feast was continued, at a well attended meeting in the Church of the First Reformed congregation on Hastings Street. After the introductory speech by the Rev. Breen came the speakers, the Rev. K. Kuepers of Roseland, and C. De Leeuw of Douglas Park. The first spoke on "be happy with the happy" and the last on the words of Solomon: "Teach the boy the first principles <pb facs="5420781_1_0194.jpg" n="2"/>according to his demands; and when he becomes aged, he shall not stray from them." That the speakers were heard with undivided attention is the best proof that their words fell on "fertile earth".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
