<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-02-12">Feb. 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Teaching of Dutch Culture at the University of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0066</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0066.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-02-12">Feb. 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">TEACHING OF DUTCH CULTURE AT THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Oosterheert last week received the following letter from Dr. Judson, president of the University, which reveals that the agitation for a chair for Dutch learning is not dormant, but is probably nearer its fulfillment than we had dared to hope some time ago:</p>
   <p>Worthy Mr. Oosterheert;</p>
   <p>Your letter of January 25th, concerning the Dutch Chair of learning was handed to me by Dr. Goodspeed. As you well know, I am immensely interested in this subject. It should be well understood, that a part of the work which was proposed by the committee, is already being done by the University.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0067.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The department of History and the department of History of art, are both favorable to the subject. At the present time, no specified work is being done in the Dutch language and literature. It will be a pleasure to me, as soon as the University, finances are sufficient, to add this work to the department of Germanic languages and literature.</p>
   <p>We have no doubt some teachers, who are capable of doing this work, but at the present, all their time is occupied with the work that is now being done.</p>
   <p>With recognition of the interest shown by the League I am yours,</p>
   <p>Very truly,</p>
   <p>Harry Pratt Judson.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0068.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A communication from the headquarters of the administration of the General Dutch League, located at Dordrecht, was sent to the Board of Trustees and University Senate, which read as follows:</p>
   <p>We, the undersigned, Miss E. Baedle, president, National Womans Council, at Rotterdam, and associates, having discovered that a request has been made, by the Netherlanders in Chicago, for the establishment of a chair of learning of the Dutch language and literature and history at the University of Chicago, to the administration of that institution and, Realizing that the above request may strengthen the cordial feeling existing between America and the Netherlands and, realizing the great interest the above notice has arisen in all parts of our land, the 33rd Dutch Language and Literature Congress of August 25-28, held in the Academy-City of Leiden, a discussion for the establishment of the above mentioned chair of learning which was accepted by acclamation.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0069.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We approve the request of the Netherlanders in Chicago and express our wish that your administration may grant them the request. Signed at, Headquarters of the General Dutch League.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
