<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-04-20">April 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Homer Rodeheaver</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-04-20">April 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">HOMER RODEHEAVER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Wednesday evening for the third time in the last seven months, many Hollanders gathered in Orchestra Hall. Last fall it was Mr. Alt of the Netherlands, who was the attraction, and a few weeks ago the Luther film. Both these programs were very good, although the audience, was not wholly able or educated to be over-enthusiastic about them. With the program of last Wednesday evening it was very different. The popular Homer Rodeheaver was there, not to give a classic or historic program, but to give in a simple, informed way, his talents to a common audience. And was it interesting? Ask anyone who was present. As leader of Billy Sunday's musical services and as well as in phonograph records and by his singing over the radio, he is generally known. But to hear him sing, personally, to hear him speak, and to hear him play on his trombone, is certainly a delight. We'd like to have seen the Hall filled to capacity but there was plenty of space, unoccupied. Those who were not there missed something of which they could have had pleasant memories for days.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0400.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All those present were appreciative as was evidenced by the silence which predominated during the different numbers, and the spirited applause, which followed each number. We do not have many such opportunities and that is why we advise everyone to make use of them whenever and wherever they present themselves. Mr. Rodeheaver was supported by his sister, Miss Vivian Tripp and Paul Beckwith. If we are not mistaken they are all busy with Evangelical work, and the holding of Gospel meetings at Aurora, where Billy Sunday is, at present, with his large tabernacle.</p>
   <p>They will be there about six weeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
