<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1908-05-08">May 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Cornelius J. Ton</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_1_0331</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-23">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_1_0331.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1908-05-08">May 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">CORNELIUS J. TON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have recently learned that our countryman, Mr. Cornelius J. Ton, State Representative from the Thirteenth District in the Illinois General Assembly, has declared himself a candidate for a second term in the Legislature.</p>
   <p>We are glad to hear of this for two reasons: First, because it is seldom that we are represented in the Legislature, although the Dutch element has a perfect right to a place there; and second, because during his first term Mr. Ton showed himself to be a man of wisdom and principle, a man who, in our opinion, is destined for a long political career. To strengthen our contention we offer a letter that Mr. George E. Cole, for years president of the Legislative Voters League, wrote Mr. Ton a short while ago:</p>
   <p>"When a representative renders good services and shows ability as you have, the voters of the district are obligated to elect him for a second term."</p>
   <p>Mr. Ton is a member of several important commissions in the Legislature: <pb facs="5420781_1_0332.jpg" n="2"/>Banks and Banking; Drainage and Waterways; License; Municipal Corporations; Parks and Boulevards; and Primary Elections. He is also a member of the celebrated Chicago Charter Commission. He was one of the three organizers of the so-called "Board of Hope," which was directly responsible for the passage of the new primary law. To Mr. Ton is due the adoption of the law that put an end to the deceptive practices of the private employment agencies. He was also instrumental in the passage of the bill to abolish white slavery.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ton is also known as a sworn advocate of the local option law. For that reason the saloon-going element and the United Societies are doing their utmost to prevent his re-election. His opponent is Mr. Kleeman, an advocate of the "open town."</p>
   <p>Therefore, we must insist that our countrymen of the Thirteenth District do everything possible to promote Mr. Ton's candidacy. We urge this, not <pb facs="5420781_1_0333.jpg" n="3"/>because we are afraid that his opponent is more powerful, but because the election of Mr. Ton will lead to the obliteration of the saloon element.</p>
   <p>All Hollanders ought to be proud of a man like Mr. Ton, and should, therefore, "handle their tools without mittens" whenever it is necessary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
