<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Mexicano</title>, Vol I. No 1.
<date when="1934-04-20">April 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0117</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0117.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Mexicano</title>, Vol I. No 1.
<date when="1934-04-20">April 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>approval of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>Fraternal Evolution, Pan-American Association, Mexican Women's Club, C. L. R. Anahuac, 333 Cuauhtemoc, C. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>special meeting was called in which the above societies were represented. A discussion began in order to formulate mutual arrangements for a patriotic celebration and once for all avoid the lucrative aims of some of our countrymen who, without any scruple, have <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>the name of our heroes in the pursuing of their own selfish interests. Such <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>procedure has created many ailments, formente<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>hatred, discord and increased the divisions which in the past have been so detrimental.</p>
   <p>The meeting took place in the social residence of the Pan-American society and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>Club, 1129 So. Ashland Avenue, April 5, 1934. After the discussion of many plans the following was approved.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0118.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>1. To form a permanent Pro-<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>Patrias Committee and that this committee shall be composed of two delegates from each society or group in Chicago and suburbs. The mission of this committee will be to find the most adequate and convenient form to celebrate the most memorable in the history of Mexico. Therefore, the mercantilism will be eliminated from our national celebrations; they will do everything possible to inform the colony that in the holidays of our country there should be no speculation tolerated to inform of the obligations they have towards their heroes, those who fought and, at the cost of many sacrifices, conquered the sovereignty of the country no <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>to us. 2. The treasurer of our Committee will be the Mexican <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>North Wells Street, and any Mexican who wish to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>financially towards the celebration, may send his contribution directly to the Mexican Consulate.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0119.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>by the treasurer <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>That all the reports <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>public through <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>effective <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>our disposal. 3. The Committee shall publish a paper under the name El Mexicano.</p>
   <p>Through this was shall inform the colony of the work done by the committee. Also it <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>education of our countrymen 4. The officer of the Committee shall <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>vice-chairman, secretary, assistant-secretary <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>commissions as may be necessary. The officers will be elected for the period of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>year and the elections should take <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>on April 5th, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>each year. The elections of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>those to be followed will be under the supervision of the Mexican Consul. 5. All the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>may render their services unconditionally. If any delegate should not comply with his duty, his society will<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>asked to recall him <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>send another in his place. The societies may leave their delegates permanently or change them if so desired.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
