<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-09-10">Sep. 10, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Enthusiasm for Indfpendence Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-09-10">Sep. 10, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">ENTHUSIASM FOR INDFPENDENCE CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friday, September 16th, is the day on which an elaborate celebration will take place. This date commemorates Mexico's Independence and marks the two hundredth and twenty second anniversary of the day that the demand for liberty was made in the village of Dolores, Mexico, the home-town of the leader of the movement, Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla.</p>
   <p>The National celebration will take place in Pilsen Park, on the night of September 16th. Cooperating in carrying out the function will be the Morales sisters who, assisted by El Nacional organized the affair.</p>
   <p>All preparations for the function have been completed. Because of the singular importance of the celebration this paper will issue its Saturday's edition in colors and advance its publication one day so that our readers may have it on the day of the festival. September 16th.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0313.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program prepared for the celebration on this occasion is extraordinary. Participants in this program, in addition to the Morales musical band, will be the celebrated "Los Mayas" Orchestra which will play the overture and the Orchestra of Paul Merceles. The official address will be given by our highly esteemed friend Dr. S. G. Meixueiro, who with his power of expression will give us a picture of the greatness and the heroism of those who gave us our land and liberty. A hymn will be sung in honor of those martyrs who fell wounded while fulfilling a sacred duty.</p>
   <p>Magnificient programs and colored posters have been printed for this most worthy affair. In spite of the critical situation which confronts us a great success is anticipated, is as much as the inborn patriotism of all the Mexicans is a sufficient reason for each one of them to accept any sacrifice in order to honor the Fatherland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0314.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Singing and dancing will feature the last hours of the festival.</p>
   <p>The Master of Ceremonies will be the young man Jose O. Velasco, ex-director of the Herald Magazine, who with his usual proficiency will direct each number.</p>
   <p>It is unquestionable that the success of this festival is assured if we take into consideration the purpose for which it is given.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
