<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Voz de Mexico</title>, Vol. I, No. 3,
<date when="1935-12">Dec. 1935</date><title level="a">Unification</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Voz de Mexico</title>, Vol. I, No. 3,
<date when="1935-12">Dec. 1935</date><title level="a">UNIFICATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, this small but sincere newspaper, will bring to all the Mexican people of good faith the opportunity to express their ideas about the unification of the colony.</p>
   <p>It is important to know the real value of unity, something which so many of us have longed for. Unifications is the coordinating force that is used to accomplish certain work and avoid many obstacles.</p>
   <p>Take for instance the locomotive, which we could call a steel monster, but if men had not thought to combine a force with another force,they could not have made it run; therefore, it was the combination of coal, water and oil that made the engine run. It proves that unification is the base of progress. We can cite the World's War as an example.</p>
   <p>Powerful Germany thought itself indomitable. Several nations united and <pb facs="5423405_2_0040.jpg" n="2"/>succeeded in defeating that powerful nation. The Mexican people who reside in Chicago can also succeed if we become united. To do this we must eliminate the spirit of superiority and the egotism so common among ourselves. When we have overcome it, we shall be in a position to find the proper solution for our problems. And when that happens neither our mothers, wives, nor ourselves shall have the need to beg or collect any money to bury our own people. We could also avoid the scarcity of funds to organize the national holidays. We invite all the Mexicans to give their views and opinions in favor of unification. Since all of us came from one family, one country, Mexico.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
