<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1929-05-18">May 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1929-05-18">May 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Herein we publish an article by Mr. Ignacio Valle, well known merchant of our colony. The substance of the article is of extreme interest to all Mexicans residing in Chicago and, in general, to all those who live in the United States. This office wholly adheres to the proposition made by the author of the article because of its great transcendence to the Mexican people and because some day we shall demonstrate to foreign countries that we know how to be united and form part of the civilized communities to which we have a right to belong. Ignacio Valle says: "The fact is amply known to the public that the Mexican Band of Chicago has firmly maintained its principles with abnegation and patriotism in the midst of vicissitudes, because "art" is the supreme vehicle of patriotism among all civilized peoples. Everyone of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> knows perfectly well that the whole artistic personnel of this band is entirely formed by Mexican workers who, <pb facs="5423405_2_0056.jpg" n="2"/>even though being worn out by their daily tasks devote three hours of their spare time in order to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.  In short, theirs is the task of a just and honest <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>work of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>when I say, "our band" it <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> not only in Chicago but <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> as well. In the many concerts they have given in Chicago and in many cities in the states of Michigan and Indiana, they were warmly greeted, having <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> clamorous success in Detroit, where they were heard by our own people and strangers as well. It is only just that we should compensate the work done by the young people composing this musical organization that has honored us; it is just that we bring forth our contributions; it is just also to show them our appreciation with something, even if it is a small thing, so that the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of this philharmonic group can materialize their efforts. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> on a very small scale I would propose to my countrymen in business to contribute with a fixed amount every month, intended to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. A small monthly fee <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> country-<pb facs="5423405_2_0057.jpg" n="3"/>men would be of great fraternal significance for our young musicians. 
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="[illegible]"/>of Chicago es<pb facs="5423405_2_0058.jpg" n="4"/>tablished the components of this young organization would put more courage and could work with more energy; they would improve more and more in their studies; they would see that the Mexican <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> appreciates their work. Then, the citizens of this noble, cultured and hospitable country would be convinced that we are lovers of art; that we cultivate music, literature, painting, and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, that we know how to take part in the concert of progressive and cultured peoples and above all, that we know how to help each other <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> foment the advancement of youth initiating itself in a life of music. With a little concerted effort the Mexican merchants of Chicago we could do much, because it takes but one brick to finish a building. We do not have to cement this building; all that we have to do is to give the finishing touch to put the last brick or stone and the glorious building, which forms the Mexican band of Chicago will be terminated. I hope that this idea will find approval among my fellow-businessmen, and in the hearts of all good Mexicans in general."</p>
   <p>Ignacio Valle,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>May 1929</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
