<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Mexicano</title>, Vol I. No 1.
<date when="1934-04-20">April 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Letter to La Alianza</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Mexicano</title>, Vol I. No 1.
<date when="1934-04-20">April 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A LETTER TO LA ALIANZA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the letter that follows the reader will understand why the Patriotic Committee could not reach any agreement with La Alianza Fraternal Mexicana.</p>
   <p>Comite Pro-Fiestas Patrias,</p>
   <p>1139 So. Ashland Avenue.,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill., April 15, 1934.</p>
   <p>Sr. Tiburcio G. Sanchez,</p>
   <p>Secretary of La Alianza Fraternal Mexicana,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>We wish to inform La Alianza Fraternal Mexicana that after a considerable discussion we arrived at the conclusion that the difficulties of the past will again take place this year.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0284.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That is in regard to the character of our celebrations as a United Front. Our desire and purpose is to work towards the unification of our colony, therefore, under the present circumstances it is impossible for us to accept the conditional terms proposed by your distinguished delegation, that is La Alianza cannot give us its support until the money spent by that society be actually reimbursed by the Patriotic Committee, and that any contract with the orchestra Los Mayas, or with the artists must be solely assumed by the Committee. Since the existence of this Committee is coming into being, it does not seem reasonable to load it with a weight that may serve to obstruct the progress of its work.</p>
   <p>The duties undertaken by this Committee embraces an enormous responsability, therefore, each step taken must be sound and in line with our program. The festival we have spoken of will take place as planned.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0285.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Nevertheless, we hope that in future occasions it may be possible to count upon the cooperation of La Alianza Fraternal Mexicana. In the meantime we shall proceed on our way, each one as best may see fit, but, without losing sight of the obligations already contracted with the colony that we claim to represent. We shall remain once more at your orders. For the honor our country and the dignity of our race.</p>
   <p>Signed, Enrique G. Cervantes P. Chairman.</p>
   <p>Enrique Venegas, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
