<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">March 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Anahuac</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">March 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ANAHUAC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is the name of a new Mexican group that is being organized to do something that no other group has done before. It is concerning something different, and to begin with, there will not be any directing body or fixed dues, neither will be excluded from its program those topics which are omitted by other groups. This society has been already formed.</p>
   <p>Dear reader, don't shrink your shoulders, or sceptically say that this is nothing new to hear of a new group being organized in the bosom of our colony. It would be news if we could hear that something good had been done by some of our existing groups. No dances or banquets which only serve to puffed up with pride, but something worthy of being proud of, something that can show that we are useful, not only good to eat and dance. It is dealt now with a society that will not exploit the impetus, nor our feelings, a society that may help us to live better, amplifying our horizon and indicating the most propitious path during our transition on earth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0126.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There would not be any object in organizing a group to be the same as the others just for the simple pleasure of one being called an organizer knowing perfectly well that this group could get nowhere, nor could accomplish anything, were we to follow the same pathway of those that have been a failure. The organizers of the Anahuac Club before they decided to act upon, they considered the possibility of joining some of the other groups in order to avoid the formulation of a program for a new one. But, after thinking it over and after a conscientious study, they arrived at the conclusion which gave origin to the formation of the "Club Anahuac". They prefer to start at the bottom to point out the way that must be followed in the development of this work without having to wait for the approval of an assembly who never approves innovated measures. The degeneration of our youth is shamefully, and one can hardly believe the state of ignorance in which the majority of our countrymen are to be found.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0127.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All the societies that have existed until now, have left this point completely untouched, the majority are more preoccupied in things that shine, without stopping one moment to see whether their work is constructive or ridiculous. This is to cover their appearance which have been their high hill, They have not realized that one can't get very far when he presents a false front. All this and more has been considered by the organizers of the Anahuac Club, and on these bases the program of this Club has been formulated. This Club shall not have rules or by-laws to violate, neither has stipulated any dues.</p>
   <p>Ours will not be a parliamentary discussion, but we can speak of everything that concerns human life, that is, everything that is discussable. Conferences and debates will be the best forms to be used in ventilating our problems. Absolute freedom of thought will be the motto at every meeting. Each person will have his own place, the place he may be capable to conquer. As you may already see, the constitution of the Anahuac Club, and its program makes this a different organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0128.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As far as the objective is concerned, it cannot be any better. The purpose now is to develop the various elements among our people and expect from it the betterment of our colony, a real improvement and not an apparent one. We must pursue on the route to defeat the worst enemy of the people, "ignorance". Let us see to it, that all whose who may come in contact with our group open their eyes and look at things from the more superior planes, from the point of view of a man that is free.</p>
   <p>In conclusion the "Ahahuac" wants to progress for all. Should the reader wish to affiliate with the "Anahuac" all that he has to do is to come in person to 1139 South Ashland Avenue. Remember that you need no money, the "Club Anahuac" has no treasurer because we do not want to accumulate funds that may provoke greedy people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
