<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-02-17">Feb. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Spanish Masquerade Dance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-02-17">Feb. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SPANISH MASQUERADE DANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The masquerade dance given by the Spanish society of Chicago last Saturday at the Club Room of the Palmer House, resulted a very splendid affair. The people attending were received by Mr. E. Rodriguez, secretary of the society, Mr. A. Bouzo president of the recreation committee and the ever smiling J. Aguilar, assistant officer, who did not have a moment of rest during the entire feast. Their services were extended to all, particularly women for whom these gentlemen always have special care, and were there to see that they would have all the enjoyment of this fiesta without the least obstacle. As it is customary on these festivals, the society had agreed to distribute six rewards to persons wearing the most attractive costumes, three for girls and three also for men. At eleven o'clock the jury in charge took its place and was composed of the following, persons: Faustino Arias president of the society, Miss. Hine, Mrs. Fraga, Dr. D. E. Gonzalez, Rafael Mendez, Jose Sarmiento y Francisco Cadavid.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0141.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the competitors had defiled through the hall, the jury began a deliberation, when this was concluded, the prizes were granted to the following: Misses Sara Cardenas, Ethel Rish and Velia Garcia. For gentlemen, the first prize was given to Enrique Arroyo, second to Ricardo Ornelas, and the third to Rodolfo Garcia. The lucky winners were warmly applauded by the audience and after a short interval, the dance continued until early in the morning. In the near future there will take place another great celebration, the officials already have chosen March 3rd, as the date for such an affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
