<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-02-27">Feb. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">New Cuban Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <!--                    <catRef target="#grp-cuban"/>
    -->
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>CUBAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-02-27">Feb. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">NEW CUBAN ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new Cuban Consul for Chicago, Mr. Ursulo J. Dobal, has taken active part in forming the "Cuban Association", the idea having grown out of his plans to bring together Cuban residents who for one reason or another have found themselves quite disorganized in this city. He did not make this move until he found how many there were to be considered.</p>
   <p>The Consul said that the idea of forming the Association came to him the first of this month and he consulted a group of countrymen with respect to such laudable proposition, and immediately the idea was accepted with warm enthusiasm, principally by our friend of the press Mr. Ramon Gonzales, who as a resident there for some time, took the first steps in going to his friends and securing the names and addresses of a large number of Cubans. Without loss of time the Consul called a meeting which was held last Sunday at 4 P.M. in the office of the Consulate where more than forty persons assembled, without any one wishing to excuse themselves for the impossibility of not being able to take part in the movement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0205.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to information which we have, almost all of those invited came. Those fellowmen who did not come will be given the details of the meeting by those who were present, lack of proper notice due to faulty address was given as the reason of their absence.</p>
   <p>In order to discuss and understand the project of the Consul, at the appointed hour, the Cubans arrived and organized themselves. The meeting was a complete success, as we have been informed, because there was a united spirit of confraternity among those who took part. The project was fully discussed and definite plans made by the assembly. The voting which indicated that the name of the association should be "Asociacion Cubana de Chicago, was unanimous and the name put into use at once.</p>
   <p>In order to get the full purpose and future plans of the association before the members, a Directing Committee of three persons was appointed. This committee personnel included the Honorable Consul, our esteemed Dr. Luis A. Vanrell, and our companion Ramon Gonzales.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0206.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At 6:30 P. M. the meeting ended and everyone went away rejoicing and commenting on the initiative of the Consul who is entitled to much praise.</p>
   <p>He had resolved to form an association that was a need not only from the aspect of national pride but for purpose of social development.</p>
   <p>El Nacional takes pride in the formation of this new association, and extends many wishes for is continuation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
