<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1929-01-23">Jan. 23, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">A Sport with No Fun</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1929-01-23">Jan. 23, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">A SPORT WITH NO FUN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new sport has now been put into practice at our harbors and frontiers. The game is to make a trip either by train or by sea, as the case may be, to some border town of Mexico, only to be sent back from there to the place whence you came. This is the cheap sport indulged in by our border patrols, who by the way, receive orders from higher authorities. Said authorities, under a revolutionary law which has been in force for some time, have the right to say which Mexicans may live in the country and which may only approach its borders, then to return into exile.</p>
   <p>Even the enemies of the administration should be given the opportunity to exercise their citizenship rights. Many of our countrymen who are in exile, had read the good news published in the press. Convinced that hatreds and prejudices had been dispelled, some of the exiles, with great optimism embarked, homeward bound not knowing what disappointments were awaiting them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0516.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On their arrival at the frontier they were met by custom officials who told them, some rudely, some in a friendly manner: You cannot disembark! If the hapless one argues that there is no law which prohibits a Mexican from entering his own country, he is told that nevertheless he may not enter the country. He then tells the custom official that the trip has consumed almost all his savings, that he has given up the position he had abroad and that in the future he would take no part in politics. He further explains that he had consulted the Mexican Consul before leaving and that he was assured by him that there was no obstacle to his return, because every Mexican has a right to return to his country whenever he wishes. Why is that, when one arrive here, the conciliatory attitude described in the press proves erroneous and the information furnished by the Mexican Consul turns out to be deception. Now my situation is desperate. Without me, my family cannot stay here because I am their sole support, and they can't return with me because I am unable to pay the fare for all of us.</p>
   <p>If the custom officer is friendly he will give to the passenger a confidential explanation. - Listen, your name is on this list, and although I feel very sorry for you, I have to follow the instructions, not to let any one whose name is on the list, cross the border.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0517.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But, as I wish to please you, I shall ask for new instructions and as soon as I get the information, I will notify you. This is the only consolation a custom official can give to a Mexican exile, who wants to return to his homeland and finds out, that because his name is on the list, entry is refused to him. In the meantime, the boat is ready to leave and our Mexican must return, with his family or alone, according to his financial situation. He alone will have to solve this problem. He has become the victim of a cruel game because of his trust in promise. Here certainly is a need for regulations.</p>
   <p>By, Jorge Labra.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
