<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1933-02-25">Feb. 25. 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Sociedad Espanola De Chicago in Action</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0171.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1933-02-25">Feb. 25. 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIEDAD ESPANOLA DE CHICAGO IN ACTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The masquerade ball given by Sociedad Espanola de Chicago, last Saturday was a complete success. The dance was given in the beautiful ballroom of the Capitol Building.</p>
   <p>The hall was, gorgeously decorated giving the hall the pleasing effect the Decorating Committee wished.</p>
   <p>Promptly at 9 P.M., the famous Hall of Mirrors where the dance was to take place began to receive our nationals in large numbers. The guests were received by the Messrs. E. Rodriguez and M. Rodriguez, Secretary of the Society and Chairman of the Recreation Committee respectively, who worked untiringly so that this celebration might be a great success.</p>
   <p>As is customary at these festivals the Society arranged to award six prizes to the best masked guests, three for the gentlemen and three for the ladies.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0172.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The judges had a difficult task because there were so many of the guests whose costumes were so smart. It was 11 P.M. when the president of the Society, Mr. M. Puig, accompanied by the judges came out to the ball room floor. The judges were: Mrs. Maria Olle, Miss Minney La Master, Messrs. Miguel Serra, Valeriano Lopez and Ignacio Danile. The first prize for the ladies was awarded to Miss Velia Garcia, the second to the beautiful Ana Maria Gonzales and the third to the very pleasant Miss Winifred Wathall. Awards to the gentlemen went to Messrs Francisco, Carlos and Fernando Fuentes respectively. The choices of the judges were loudly applauded by the crowd and then the dance continued until the early hours of the next morning.</p>
   <p>Music was by The Valencians who are the pleasure of any gathering. The whole affair was a great credit to the Society and its New Directorate who so magnificently planned and carried it to a successful end. In the near future there will be another function given by the Society, in which leading artists of this colony will take part. Among them will be the popular Morales sisters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
