<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-02-17">Feb. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Cuban Night</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-02-17">Feb. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A CUBAN NIGHT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Latin-American Colony of Chicago is preparing to celebrate the 66th anniversary of the emancipation of the slaves (Grito de Baire) of the beautiful "Pearl of the Antilles" (Cuba) when Carlos Manuel de Cespedes ejected the voice of liberty against the ignominious yoke of slavery of the colonists. Now the descendants of the noble race hasten together with their brothers, the Latin-American people in a sincere vehicle of harmony bringing up, therefore, their contingency for tonight, to make of it a gala night, that for many years the oppressed of the beautiful Island dreamed of.</p>
   <p>As guests of honor there will be Carlos Molina, who very gallantly shall present to us with one of his beautiful selections. The honorable Consuls of Latin-America will add splendor to this festival. The dance will be under the direction of Don. Pablo who, with his magnificent selection of tangos and rhumbas will delight his audience until late hours of the morning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0296.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The couple "Quintas-Josefina" who as an offer of the Latin-American Club to the Cuban festival they shall perform the best numbers in the repertory. The young Cuban, Ricardo Cortez, and his partner will dance the real typical Cuban rhumba. The Argentine tango will be executed by the couple "Garicia y Gomar" who conquered many applauses in the "Streets of Paris" at the World's Fair. These and many other attractive numbers will engrave the outstanding memory to those who expect to attend this celebration which marks the principle on the Cuban Independence. Through this we cordially invite all the Latin-Americans of Chicago to be present on the night of February 24, 1934, at the Auditorium Hotel 430 South Michigan Avenue. The program shall begin at 8:00 P.M. and will be preceded by the dance which is to continue until 4:00 A. M. next morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
