<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Liberal</title>, Vol I. No. 2.
<date when="1933-05-13">May 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Clarifying the Errors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Liberal</title>, Vol I. No. 2.
<date when="1933-05-13">May 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Clarifying the Errors</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the object to make known the "Intimate Proclamation of Christ the King a leaflet was reprinted by the Mexican Youth of Chicago. It seemed as an act of destiny that one of these leaflets came into my hands. The original was printed on Dec. 25th 1932 by the Mexican Liberty League for the rights of Man. It was disguised under the Intimate Proclamation of Christ the King in order to provocate and insult the Mexican Government. This is a very ridiculous thing to be tolerated. In view of this fact, I am going to permit myself to point out some of the mistakes contained in the above mentioned. I shall begin by asking the members of the so called Liga Libertad de los Derechos del Hombre, to please go to school first so that they may be able to define words; Citizenship, Revolution, Right and Man. Because in their utmost inconsistent sheet they exposed the ignorance and clearly show the clay from which the coward, and traitors are made of.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0435.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Those who with all pretuberance call themselves Defenders of the Rights of Man. Tell me, gentlemen, "defenders" how can you justify the assertion made in your first paragraph, "that the right of citizenship have been taken away from the Mexican people by the Revolution"? Gentlemen defenders, please take notice that the revolution in Mexico means the enlargement of brains, depuration of conscience and it is the tree where the right of man may fructify. Gentlemen, can you explain the difference between Mexico as an Empire and Mexico as a Republic? According to what reveals in the contexture of your second paragraph it seems that you have not the remotest conception of History, for if you had, you would not blaspheme so stupidly as you do. By making the absurd comparation of the Act of Independence which in reality expressesl "That the Catholic Apostolic Roman Religion" would be the only one to be recognized nationally"; it is also true that this occurred when Mexico became independent from our Mother Spain, today our Sister, the Spanish Republic.
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0436.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This, as it is natural, it was a step that Mexico took, as we commonly say; "It came out from a burning coal, to enter the vivid flames". Because our people continue to be chained to the same slavery since it had to obey a Monarchical Government. Now you still say, that all the constitutions that have ruled Mexico, with the exception of those issues during the revolution have been written in the name of God and with the authority of the Mexican people". I cannot explain myself such an "exception". Do the gentlemen defenders believe that the Act of Independence did not spring from a revolution? Do you also believe that the glorious Constitution of 1857 was not issued in the name of God? Gentlemen defenders, I think it would be worthwhile for you to know that the Laws of all the countries have been issued in the name of God. The most meritorious statesman of the Americas Lic. Don Benito Juarez, in spite of you opposition and that of the Cossacks with of soutane was a real Christian, and his laws have taught us to be Christians and comply with our duties to humanity.
   </p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0437.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Christ came to the world to teach men the Laws of Reform- the (New Testament) to free humanity from the tyranny of those who believed themselves Gods on earth, thereby usurping the rights of Divinity. In a likewise manner, Juarez the Mexican Messiah came to teach us to respect the real God, in other words, gave the Mexican people the right to respect God as a God, and Man as a Man. Undoubtedly, as soon as Christ was informed of this so called proclamation there at the right of "His Father", is repeating the very same words He said when He expired on the Cross; Pardon them God, for they know not what they do.	
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
