<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1933-01-21">Jan. 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Sociedad Espanola De Chicago Gives Dance and Elects New Directorate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1933-01-21">Jan. 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIEDAD ESPANOLA DE CHICAGO GIVES DANCE AND ELECTS NEW DIRECTORATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sociedad Espanola de Chicago, will give the dance previously announced by this leading institution of recreation and charity today, Saturday, in the well known hall on the fourth floor of the Capitol Building which is located at State and Randolph Streets.</p>
   <p>The dance program will be in charge of the young people, with popular Juanito Pineda. They will be assisted by "The Valencians", known for their good music.</p>
   <p>The Valencians orchestra has played for many dances given in the past by Sociedad Espanola, and now returns to add more laurels to its splendid record. The dance numbers never lack the native music of which the young dancers are so fond.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0174.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The dance will commence at 8:30 P.M. and will last until 1 A.M. the following morning. The price of admission will be fifty cents for gentlemen and twenty-five cents for ladies. There will be no other charges.</p>
   <p>There will be another dance in the near future. This dance was unanimously approved last Sunday at the regular meeting of the Society, at which time the President, Mr. Miguel Garriga, the Secretary, Mr. Jose Gonzales Perez and the three directors offered their resignations. This was much regretted and in spite of entreaties on the part of the members that the officers retain their posts, they finally had to accept their resignations. We have watched the work which the Sociedad Espanola has done under their retiring officials and we must admit that their loss is a heavy blow to the institution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0175.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following persons were chosen to fill the vacancies in the Society's Directorate: Manuel Puig, President; Edelmiro Rodriguez, Secretary; Arturo Garcia, Jose Montos, Frank Rodriguez and Manuel Rodriguez, as directors, the last named takes over the Chairmanship of Recreation filled by the present secretary whose productive work is well known. The young man Manuel Rodriguez, is new to the Sociedad Espanola. He took his course in accountancy at the Walton School of Commerce.</p>
   <p>As we understand that it was his desire to become Recreation leader that was the factor which led to his confirmation as head of the Society's Recreation Department.</p>
   <p>The dance classes have been of great benefit to the young people who wish to learn to dance well. They are conducted in the dance hall of the Capitol Building each day under the skillful leadership of the well known international dance master, Professor Jorge Quintas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
