<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-09-16">Sep. 16, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Joyful Patriotic Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-09-16">Sep. 16, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">JOYFUL PATRIOTIC CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Patriotic Celebration will take place at Pilsen Park, 26th and Albany Avenue, tonight and the most artistic elements will take part in the program. It will be doubtless the greatest patriotic celebration that this city, has seen in many years. As said before, it will be the real Mexican people who live in Chicago and adjacent towns that will fill the large Auditorium in Pilsen Park, for it is the common class of people who bear within their hearts the most ardent and noble patriotism.</p>
   <p>The organizers of this celebration; knowing that with banquets and similar undertakings one cannot render due homage to our heroes, thought it best to use the Pilsen Park. We are in complete accord with the organizer's idea, of rallying the vast majority of our countrymen who are eager to be united on so memorable a day.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0353.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Mexican Band of Chicago which is the artistic element is always ready to take part in every festival within the artistic field be it patriotic or charitable, did not hesitate a moment to willingly accept the invitation made to them to participate in the Mexican Popular Celebration, providing the pursued aim would be artistic, patriotic,and noble. That is why tonight we count on an excellent musical organization, eminently Mexican, which will be in charge of some of the musical numbers in the program.</p>
   <p>The Morales Typical Orchestra</p>
   <p>This musical organization which is formed and directed by the Misses Morales is also going to take part in the program of the 16th, (tonight). Notwithstanding the fact that the Orquesta Tipica Morales (The Morale Typical Orchestra) is amply known in our colony we wish to make it plainer, that the said organization is composed of beautiful and cultured girls from our colony which is a guarantee in itself.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0354.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Nothing would be better than the representation of the long-suffering Mexican woman on that night. We can applaud their work furiously and reward it with acclamation, because, when the women undertake such difficult tasks as art, we must not let it pass unnoticed.</p>
   <p>The Theatrical Company of Isabel Reyna, who is at the head of the artistic group which bears her own name, also will take part and we can tell you after it is over, of the wonderful Mexican songs they can sing. If we just mention La Joyita, (The little jewel) and Lupita Murieta, you'll first here two feminine hearts who know how to feel and interpret the vernacular songs of our country as it was intended to by the Lord. Miss Mercedes Figueroa a skilful violinist will let the public know of her value as a soloist. There will be some dances performed by Rosita Mc Dermott and Juan Pineda. Fernandez and Pineda will play a guitar duo and other numbers difficult to perform.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0355.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In general the best artistic elements of the colony will take part tonight.</p>
   <p>Grand Dance</p>
   <p>After the official program of the popular celebration has come to a close, the Mexican and the American National Anthems will be sung by the artists and the audience as well. In spite of the criticism which is being made by our colleague from Indiana, Harbor, there will be a dance after the program, this will last until 3:00 o'clock in the morning.There will be restaurant service and refreshments, etc.</p>
   <p>The organizers of this grand festival have requested us to inform the public regarding transportation, in other words, the Street Car service. The Blue Island Street Car may be taken, this will leave you at exactly half a block from the entrance of Pilsen Park. The general admission will be 50c per person. We shall inform all of our readers of tonight's festival and give them detailed information in our future editions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0356.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Translator's Note:</p>
   <p>I think there are some important facts that deserve mentioning. The Mexican Band of Chicago made history and succeeded as musical organization. It can frankly be said that its success was due primarily to its director, organizer and teacher Professor Francisco Calderon. This self-denying Mexican, was able to organize and turn into a well disciplined body fifty-seven men who compose the Mexican Band of Chicago. All of the musicians are well uniformed and this musical organization has become the pride of the Mexican colony in Chicago. This Band played in some of the States of the Union, such as Michigan, Wisconsin, Indiana, Illinois, etc. However its life was comparatively short and not so pleasant. The Band was betrayed by its beloved teacher who took over one thousand dollars and disappeared from Chicago. This money belonged to the Band, Calderon was the keeper.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0357.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>However, the members of the Band did not become angered by this act, for they were convinced that this sum of money could not compensate the years of work and the time which Calderon had dedicated to them. They felt sorry for the absence of their teacher and pleaded with him to come back. They realized that their ingratitude rather than his ill behavior was to blame and only wish they had done something to aid Calderon financially since music was his only source of income. After Calderon's disappearance the Band had about three different conductors but were not very successful although these conductors were very competent. The Mexican Band continued in existence up to 1931.</p>
   <p>As for the Orquesta Tipica Morales (Morales Typical Orchestra) which was organized by the Morales Sisters, in the year of 1925, this consisted of sixteen young women. All of them wore Mexican costumes and because of their youth partly, they became very popular in the colony.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0358.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>They also played in various Cabarets and Theatres in Chicago and in nearby towns. These young women deserve a great deal of credit for their devoted persistence to the art of music. Although most of them got married and could not continue in their career, the Morales Sisters have kept the spirit of the music alive until today.</p>
   <p>Nicolas M. Hernandez.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
