<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. Thomas M. Lineweaver</title>, Pastor and Director of the Byrd Memorial Center, 9135 Brandon Avenue, Chicago, Ill., by Nicolas M. Hernandez,
<date when="1936-12-04">Dec. 4, 1936</date>.
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0036</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.6"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0036.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Rev. Thomas M. Lineweaver</title>, Pastor and Director of the Byrd Memorial Center, 9135 Brandon Avenue, Chicago, Ill., by Nicolas M. Hernandez,
<date when="1936-12-04">Dec. 4, 1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Records of October 1936, show the activities of the Mexican groups as follows; The attendance of children to kindergarten, 11 girls and 6 boys, ages 4 to 6 years. Primary, 12 girls, 5 boys, ages 6 to 8 years. Junior,28 girls, 19 boys, ages 8 to 13 years. Intermediate, 7 girls, 31 boys, ages 14 to 20 years. Adult Mothers Club, 26 members. Nursery School, 7 girls, 12 boys ages from 2 1/2 to 4 years. Adult English Classes 17.</p>
   <p>Rev. Thomas M. Lineweaver, verbal information: There is the Amapola Club, which has about 12 members, dedicated to sports and social activities. Women's Society, has 8 members. Mexican Mothers about 30, Frente Popular,40, Southern Arrows, 20, Mayas Club,20, Spanish Class,22. All these groups have different activities, such as sports, music, art, and other educational subjects.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0037.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They seem to be backward, I guess that is due to the lack of education and development. They have altruist spirit, in what concerns to their groups. They lack experience in regards to the American life. Their standards are lower than the American's. They are sociable, but not very dependable except those who belong to the Church. They need political and social orientation. I would say that they are contributing as much as any other group to the general welfare of the community. Economically they are not making it. Need more leadership, resources, time and patience, and only through education, education, and more education they can be brought to the American social standard of life. They are willing to learn, although they are little slow in adapting themselves to the new American customs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0038.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>CHURCH</p>
   <p>We also have a Mexican Church here. Luis Velasco, is the Pastor, there are about 60 active members. The Church members are more stable, and dependable. The denomination of the Church is Congregational.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
