<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-02-17">Feb. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Social and Educational Program</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-02-17">Feb. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL AND EDUCATIONAL PROGRAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Recreational Mexican Club celebrated its third anniversary on February 8th with a brilliant program given at the Hull House. The hall was crowded with people who really enjoyed the astonishing conviviality which seldom have been seen in the past, and there were no disturbances registered like those taken place on festival previous effected in the Mexican colony. Everything was orderly. Credit must be given to all the members of this group, and may be taken as an example by other clubs who often organize festivals in the colony.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Esther Henshaw, was the organizer of this fiesta and was greatly pleased because of the conduct observed during the entire festival. A comical play was presented by Ernesto Loranca and the Noranjo brothers who were applauded very much by the numerous people who attended the festival.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0144.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program consisted of the following numbers: 1. A musical selection by the orchestra of the "Club Recreativo". 2. Piano solo by Miss Jovita Murillo. 3. Lamento Soricano and Donde Estas Corazon sang by Mrs. Jesus Tapia. 4. "Trucos" (a game) Pedro Loranca and Pedro Naranjo. 5. A piece by the orchestra. 6. Siboney sang by Miss Garciela Doblado. 7. Comic farce by Ernesto Llorca, Pedro Naranjo and Miss Naranjo. 8. A poem recited by Mrs, Maria Corona. 9, The Mexican tap-dance by the Enciso brother and sister. 10. A speech by Mrs. Eather Henshaw, festival director of the Club Recreativo Mexicano. The commission on order was composed of : Felix Tapia, Miguel Rosales. Claudio Saldana, Toribio Padilla and Pedro Barea.</p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
