<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>, Vol IV. No 11.
<date when="1937-01-03">Jan. 3, 1937</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0398</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0398.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>, Vol IV. No 11.
<date when="1937-01-03">Jan. 3, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">CONTRIBUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How little is your contribution to the Church, if you stop to consider calmly you will know that the amount is very small. One fourth of the amount paid for gasoline goes to the revenue. One third of what you pay for cigarettes is taken in for revenue. How much of this amount do you pay. Kindly figure out how much of this you pay just in one week. Of course you pay these revenues every day, while the Church only asks you to contribute once a week. As a consumer you pay taxes from the manufacturing of an automobile up to the most simple cosmetic. Your automobile license money also enters as revenue. When you pay your light and telephone bills, you are paying such revenues, and lastly you are paying for everything you use. And to God and His Church how little is the amount you really give if we compare it with the total sum of all the other contributions you are making.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0399.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Which is the work that deserves your help most: From what sources do you derive a benefit which could equal one percent of the benefits you receive from your Church: The ancient Law of the Omnipotent demanded one tenth from the earnings of the people. Today the people are paying just a small percentage to the Church while they pay more than ten-percent for revenues. Stop and consider this problem well and do everything that is in your power to extend your cooperation toward the augmentation of the honor and Glory of God.</p>
   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
