<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-02-20">Feb. 20, 1932</date>.
      <title level="a">Festival</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0552</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0552.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-02-20">Feb. 20, 1932</date>.
     <title level="a">FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We had the pleasure of attending a social event of great importance last Saturday night, given in honor of our very popular and esteemed Consul, Mr. Rafael Aveleyra. The affair took place in the residence of Mr. Jesus Saenz located at 1925 Roosevelt Road.</p>
   <p>The function began at an early hour of the night and continued into the early hours of the next day. In addition to <gap unit="word" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> the honorable Consul, we had the pleasure of paying respects to Mr. Saenz and his distingushed wife Mrs. Ines Arismende de Saenz and their invited guests.</p>
   <p>The program was made very lively by the Red Pepper Jazz Orchestra under the skillful leadership of Juan Hernandez which played Spanish, Mexican and Cuban selections to the delight of the dancers who applauded the orchestra profusely.</p>
   <p>The banquet which proceeded the dance was characteristic for its abundant and tasty food.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0553.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the banquet, Amparo Gulierrez, the eight year old daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Agapito Gulierrez, while being accompanied by the orchestra, sang the beautiful Mexican song entitled "<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>" with masterfullness and grace.</p>
   <p>Mr. Almada, from the Consulate, recited a beautiful poetic composition for which he was given loud applause. Our great and good friend Mr. Francisco Reyes <gap unit="word" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, who is known for his genius in poetry recited for the crowd and received loud applause also. He was also the master of ceremonies for this affair.</p>
   <p>The Vice-Consul, Mr. Adolfo G. Dominguez, recited a beautiful poetic composition for which he was loudly applauded. Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> was the principal speaker who gave a short but rousing speech in praise of those who had arranged the affair and in respect to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who continued to show a warm interest in the motherland. He was given a great ovation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0554.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Others who took prominent part in the festival were leading musical artists of our colony led by Mrs. Milla Dominguez, who sang Spanish and Mexican songs and Mrs. Celia Rangel,  talented Mexican pianist who played Spanish and Mexican pieces.</p>  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
