<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-12-05">Dec. 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Sociedad Feminil Mexicana</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0254</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0254.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-12-05">Dec. 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIEDAD FEMINIL MEXICANA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This group of noble an charitable women who know how to safe-guard the welfare of the Mexican children, sacrifice themselves with pleasure for everything that may benefit the children. They go afar to implore charity from the public in order to benefit the thousands of innocent children who have had no better lack that being poor. This feminine society deserves all the support of the Mexican colony. Its existence is necessary for the welfare of the children, besides being worthy of the Mexican woman.</p>
   <p>According to their program of ways and means to obtain funds to aid the children, the society has organized a magnificent dance to be effected at the Hull House, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>South Halsted Street. The funds that may be obtained at this festival will be used to finance a free festival which is to take place at the West Side Auditorium on Dec. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0255.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Auditoriam hall and theatre has for some time been converted into a Mecca for the Mexicans who reside in Chicago and vicinity. December 13th is the second anniversary of the Socieded Femenil, and for this reason a superb program is being prepared, something extraordinary and worthwhile.</p>
   <p>The masquerade dance and awards that we announce for that date, are going to be something sensational and destined to be a prodigy of gayety. Another attraction is the exhibition of paintings at the termination of the dance. At this exhibition there will be an opportunity to obtain a precious piece of work at a very low price and with the assurance that the money paid for it, will be used for a very deserving and humanitarian cause: to aid the Mexican children. Mexico from its columns, calls its readers to cooperate in one from or another to the aggrandizement of this society who with so much ardor is working for the interest of the Mexican. With such groups as the Sociedad Femenil Mexicana, the colony is destined to progress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
