<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title> Vol IV. No 7.
<date when="1936-12-06">Dec. 6, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The Good Neighbor Policy</title>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0531</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0531.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title> Vol IV. No 7.
<date when="1936-12-06">Dec. 6, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE GOOD NEIGHBOR POLICY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under this name. President Roosevelt wishes to hide his hypocrite policy against Mexico under the pretext of not wishing to interfere upon the interior matters of other countries. Such policies have permitted the continuation of a growing wave of attacks and persecutions perpetuated in Mexico by the government, which is nothing more than a group of desperados, who little by little have exterminated all the rights and liberties of the people.</p>
   <p>They assassinated defenseless citizens, have taken from them thousands of urban and agricultural properties under the most futile excuse. If a person should see his neighbor instigating terror and death in his own house, he would not be a good neighbor if he should not do everything in his power to bring order in that house.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0532.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the same manner a president in power cannot be a good neighbor if he overlooks the most detestable crimes committed in neighboring Country. Such is our conception, and therefore, we are in accord with the International Federation of Catholic Alumnac who in their last convention held in Dallas, Texas, approved the following resolutions; "We as good neighbors, vigorously protest against the Mexican Government for the martyrdom and exiling of priests and nuns, closing of Churches, violation of "basilicas" and immortal teachings in public schools. We pledge our vote so that Mexico may have a sensible government and spiritual innovation in the country. We urge the American Catholics to cease the invention of capital in Mexico, through sources of tourism and commerce, until that country becomes as good a neighbor as the United States."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
