<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>, Vol. IV. No. 20.
<date when="1937-03-07">March 7, 1937</date><title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>, Vol. IV. No. 20.
<date when="1937-03-07">March 7, 1937</date><title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Is religion the opium of the people? If things are well considered, this Phrase is in accord with reality but on the lips of the enemies of religion it is an infamous and deceitful affirmation, and dirty lies of the worst specimen. In reality, if we are to consider opium as a drug which medical science places at the service of men to remedy their pains and sufferings, with how much more reason can we say, that religion is the opium of the people. For religion mitigates our sorrows, lessens the misfortunes of our soul, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>our passions and subjects them to the empire of intelligence and good-will. Blessed be religion because when properly administered as opium is administered to the body it brings happiness, in a likewise manner, religion brings joy to our soul.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0387.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But if this phrase: "Religion the opium of the people," is given the damned interpretation as did the German-Jew Karl Marx, and Lenin, and by opium we understand the medicine wisely utilized and not the use made by the drugaddicts who are already without neither will nor action, then it is a lie of all lies to affirm that religion is the opium of the people.</p>
   <p>On the contrary it awakens men from the very beginning to a superior life, impulsing him to work without rest to better his conduct, and facilitating to the effect the only Code of Morality which has as a rational foundation, Love to God. This code is infinitely superior to the best Moral Codes produced by lay philosphy. The beneficial influence of religion is felt not only in the field which is adequate to improve men morally, but also upon the other fields of men's activity. It is therefore religion that has brought to the world the intellectual advancement now found.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0388.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Why art has advanced? Why the advancement of science? The material progress itself, to what is it due if not religion? To what is it due if not religion that by freeing men from their lower passion and submitting his flesh to the soul in order to develop his intellect and imagination and through this sublimation comes the production of master works that we contemplate with wonder.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
