<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-06-04">June 4, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Concecration of the First Methodist Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-06-04">June 4, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">CONCECRATION OF THE FIRST METHODIST CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The First Methodist Church of this city, will celebrate its concecration, tomorrow, Sunday, at 3:00 P. M. The temple is located at Polk and Sholto Streets, and has been renovated and decorated for this special occasion. The pastor of this church, Reverend William B. O'Neil, should be credited for the untiring labor performed.</p>
   <p>The most outstanding figures of the American and Mexican Methodists, will assist at this important religious ceremony. Such dignataries as Dr. John Thompson, pastor of the First Methodist Church of Chicago, Dr. Charles Parking, Dr. Francis Barnum, and Mr. Federick Saenicken, who will no doubt be interested leaders in this religious event.</p>
   <p>The church choir, under the direction of the tenor Salvador Mendoza and Mrs. Josefina Gamboa, will give a well selected musical program, planned by Reverend O'Neil.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0450.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At eleven o'clock A. M. baptisms will be performed and new members will be received. The Methodist Congregational Church of Chicago, at 9135 Brandon Avenue, will give a special program to-morrow morning, at the eight o'clock service, which will be honored by the presence of the Most Reverend O. Bispo.</p>
   <p>Great interest has been created among the Methodist Colony because of having, for the first time, an opportunity to witness such solemn services.</p>
   <p>The Spanish Colony, as a whole, is invited.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
