<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-03-03">March 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to the Mexican Groups of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-03-03">March 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO THE MEXICAN GROUPS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Sisters:</p>
   <p>For some time I have had a desire to remind you of my existence, but since the ambient in which we move has been so turbid during the last few years, I believed the time was not opportune and decided to await until now. It is not possible to wait any longer, because the duty is urging us to move forward. My intention is not to look for any publicity at your expenses, but I am ready to cooperate with you in the work we have under our care and the medium I wish to utilize seems to be the most appropiate and effective so that my oath of adhesion may bear the proper weight. Don't think that I am as frivolous as when I was initiated in my existence, with my four years of struggles and efforts I have grown morally sufficient to gain judgement that many hundreds would like to have. I can now appreciate things more for what they produce, than for its appearance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0133.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I do not shrink any more when I hear the resounding name of any one, for I have one that signifies a lot, even if I am worth a little. Those who know something of my past life may remember that I was baptised with the buffon name "Mamerto", name that I bear with pride for a long time, but which proved disadvantageously because I was judged by the name, by the majority and didn't take my efforts seriously while complying with my work and the value of my enterprises, that is why I have adapted the name of "Asociacion Pan-Americana". Many look at me with suspicion because they say that my name is not a Mexican one, without seeing that my work is so. For instance I have always excluded myself from receiving favors from American Institutions. I have never accepted anything free, not even a hall to hold my meetings, therefore, I have always had my own hall, so as not to be depending upon the "Yankees". Not because I detest them, but because I feel that so long as I owe them no favors, I could'nt be indebted to them in anyway, consequently, I can consider myself independent and free.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0134.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Do you not think that this attitude is honorable since I do not leave any opening for others to humiliate me? My work, efforts and the plan of action have been directed toward the compliance of duty, with plain conscience and knowledge. Whether this has produced the effects we longed for, that is a different thing, let us inquire the fertility of the soil and then judge.</p>
   <p>I shall not make a summary of what I have done, for my intention is not to presume, but my records are available to anyone that may wish to be informed of my work. If I let it be known that I have worked in favor of the Mexicans, it is because I want those who mistrust my name to know that even though my name is not Mexican, my spirit is so. In contrast to other groups who are contended to hear a Mexican name though their actions are not. Because I know that the real the Mexicans who are used to keeping guard over a wake with phosphoric light (not matches) cannot accept favors that denigrate them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0135.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Certain Editorial writer of La Prensa of Can Antonio, Texas, in interpreting the Mexican spirit, said that the Mexicans who were in this country when they did ask for anything, this was work, and not favors. I believe that the work of orientation is one obligation of the Mexican groups who represent the Mexican colony, and it is for this reason, that I send you the present letter. Also to let you know that I am ready to lend you my contingent in the way of studying the best possible form to build a federation, an imitation father, and to see if it is possible to present a United Front when we meet with the question of solving a problem which concerns to the general interest of the colony.</p>
   <p>Let us remember that there is much we can to if our efforts are united, while if we work individually we can only be obstructing each other. We can begin this task of preparing the celebration of our traditional feast of the 5th of May.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0136.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It is very true that there are over two months time, but we also know by experience that it is not very easy for us to come to an agreement. If we want good results out of it we must begin as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>I hope, therefore, that whatever you may think on this respect, whether your answer should come through the columns of El Nacional, or a private correspondence. In the mean time I give you my votes in favor of your prosperity and I take advantage of this opportunity to place myself mutually at your orders.</p>
   <p>Your affectionate Sister,</p>
   <p>Associacion Pan-Americana</p>
   <p>1139 South Ashland Blvd.</p>
   <p>Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0137.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Note: The Asociacion Pan-Americana disappeared at the beginning of 1935. The estability of the Mexican groups depends mainly upon the estability of employment of the elements that originally gave birth to these groups. However, The Pan-American Association during its four years of existence made certain progress in the social, cultural, and athletic fields. The membership included young people from various Spanish speaking countries. Mr. Leon Lira was one of the initiators and most ardent collaborators.</p>
   <p>During the last 18 years many Mexican Clubs, and societies have been organized after a duration of one to six years they have voluntarily or compelingly dissolved. The causes were not always the same. Many well known Americans gave their cooperation in the social activities of this group.</p>
   </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
