<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1933-12-30">Dec. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Summary in the Activities of Our Clubs and Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0148</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0148.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1933-12-30">Dec. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SUMMARY IN THE ACTIVITIES OF OUR CLUBS AND SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the conclusion of 1933, we shall make a superficial review of the most outstanding events that have taken place during the year of 1933. For the year of 1934, we propose to make this section of our paper one of the most interesting and best served, taking into account the collaboration from the various groups of the Spanish language, and culture of the people who are now active in Chicago. The prospect in view is that these columns should serve as an approach to the unity of the Spanish-American people.</p>
   <p>THE SPANISH SOCIETY</p>
   <p>During the concluding year, the senior Spanish group of Chicago reached much greater success in the social activities and labour of Spanish-American confraternity. In their social location on the Capitol Building, many visitors to the Century of Progress were gallantly attended.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0149.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As a veteran and respectable organization, it corresponds to them the honor of proudly represent the Castillian speaking people in the inauguration of the "World's Fair". In commemorating "Columbus Day", this society made the presentation of the most reminiscent program ever to be given in this metropolis by the Spanish speaking people. They brought some artistic figures which represented each and every country of the world in the foremost value and significance. They presented the marathon running champion, the famous Colombian artist Carlos Molina, the Hernandez trio, the marvelous Spanish guitar players; the acclaimed Costarican singer Victoria Gallegos; the Argentinian dancers, Medrano and Donna; the Spanish dancer Jose Alvarez and many other prominent figures in the art who gave honor and brilliance to this festival which left pleasant remembrance in our colony and granted a laurel to this society and to the chairman of festivities, Senor Alfonso Souzo. For the social season the society has acquired the luxurious Club Room in the Palmer House, the desirable Orchestra of Don Pablo with his tango and rhumba Cavaliers. Next year, this society will present to us much greater surprises, for they are trying to break their previous record.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0150.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The growing enthusiasm which is shown every day by the young feminine elements of which this newest Club is formed, it is not an artificial, neither ephemerous one. In the contrary, a sound truth ratifies, that it is a well organized nucleous, worthy of being taken in consideration and seconded with sympathy. We are not talking of one of the many initiatives who are born dead, but of an organization in which everyone of its members enjoying good personal standing in the social sphere, they also have a great capacity for action, which enpowers them for an enterprise of long duration. The definite spirit for organization in their chairman Cuquita Dolago convinced of her fine talent and preparation. The practical collaboration of Rosita Herrera, Margot Maldonado, Laurita Lopez, Beatriz Ibarra, Francis Garces, and Lacha Lopez, also Pepe Rivera the advisor. All of these, vitalizes the daily optimism and enthusiasm without breach.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0151.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>You should see these girls seriously devoted to training and practices at the University of Chicago Settlement, and to hear them discuss with jovial spirit the plans and preparations, which is a surprise, in their next month's social presentation at the Amalgamated Building. To be more explicit, their enthusiasm and jovial spirit are a stimulus of the great ideal of this club; representing our woman, as a column of its origin, as a vigorous sociable element in the sport and social nucleous of this cosmopolitan city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
