<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-20">Aug. 20, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Celebration of the National September Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-20">Aug. 20, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATION OF THE NATIONAL SEPTEMBER FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The President of the Committee for the National September celebration, has just released some important data, relative to the preparations which are being made to celebrate the worthy Fiesta de la Patria, on the 15th of September.</p>
   <p>In past years unscrupulous persons have promoted this celebration on a profit basis. This year Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, Mexican Consul here, cooperating with the patriotic National Festival Committee, has decided that the general admission fee be fixed at twenty-five cents and that children be admitted free.</p>
   <p>The Committee has engaged the famous Chapu Hepec Jazz Band, composed wholly of Mexicans, and the orchestra of the Latin-American Cultural Club of this city to furnish the music. The orchestra from the "Azteec Club has agreed to play without charge on this Memorial Night.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0322.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The celebration is now advertised so as to make sure that, people will turn out in crowds to pay tribute to the heroes who gave us a country of liberty.</p>
   <p>This festival will be held, as in other years, at the West Side Auditorium, located at the corner of Racine and Taylor Streets. This hall has been secured because of the wonderful facilities which it offers to a large crowd, and because of its colorful decoration. An altar of patriotism has been installed and the seat of honor has been reserved for the Honorable Consul of Mexico, who at exactly 11 o'clock on the night of the affair will, eulogize the Heroes of our Independence.</p>
   <p>The President of the Patriotic Festival Committee, said that it was cooperating with several groups of Mexican Clubs and societies so as to be in complete harmony with the various peculiarities of our Colony. Before 11 o'clock on the night of the affair a most select program will be given. On it will appear our well known artists who will sing native songs and dance native dances, which add so much color to these Mexican festivals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0323.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We understand that the Honorable Mexican Consul of Chicago, has taken charge of extending special invitations to several Americans of this city, as he has done in past years. A member of the Committee gave us this information: "For the night of the celebration we should get all the interested people together thereby strengthing more and more our friendly relations with those who are not familiar with our country and its people".</p>
   <p>"From the receipts which will be taken in at the Auditorium, fifty percent will go to charity--- Hull House being the greatest benefactor. This most worthy institution has, through the efforts of its founder and director, Miss Jane Adams, given for many years aid to our countrymen and their needy and distressed families."</p>
   <p>"To advertize this affair as much as possible the Committee has ordered a great quanity of circulars printed. These notices will carry full details of the program and will be distributed in Chicago, South Chicago, Indiana Harbor, Gary, Indiana, Waukegan, Joliet, Aurora and other neighboring cities where our countrymen are very numerous".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
