<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Liberal</title>, Vol I. No 1.
<date when="1933-05-05">May 5, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A Summary</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Prof. F Ortega Rodriquez</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Liberal</title>, Vol I. No 1.
<date when="1933-05-05">May 5, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A SUMMARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">BY PROF. F ORTEGA RODRIQUEZ</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>May 5th of 1862, compared with May 5th of 1933. If we are ready to accept the truth, let us say, that we have not us yet a clear understanding of this memorable day. Many of our countrymen are only waiting for such national days to procure a profit for their own pockets. Of course in some instances the proceeds are used for a good cause. But in many cases this is a false pretext. As we know, there are many days besides our national holidays that we can exploit, for all the causes that we can possibly think of. We need not to outrage the memory of our heroes. We must suppress every tendency aiming to disrupt the unity of our colony. To accomplish so constructive an undertaking we should try to analyze our historical events and obtain an exact meaning for the application of our patriotism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0301.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have faithfully devoted the present issue of El Liberal in order to outline briefly the Mexican situation, and describe the memory of those who were able to save our Country from a second empire with the victory of May 5th, 1862. Due to the fact that Mexico at that time was traversing a difficult economic situation, the three foreign powers, France, England and Spain anxious to receive the payment of a best which Mexico had failed to pay on time, decided to force Mexico, by the use of intervention. Don Benito Juarez, President of Mexico, who knew that several thousands of soldiers had disemoarked in the Port of Veracruz, appointed the able jurist Don Manuel Doblado, to explain to the interventionists the economic situation of the country. Spain and England convinced of the of the situation decided to wait, but the representative of France, Mr. Saligny said "My signature is worth as much as the paper that is written on." The French Army was under the command of Marshall Bazaine and immediately advanced to Puebla where they met stern resistance and defeat by the army of General Ignacio Zaragoza who fought on the hills of Loreto and Guadalupe, Puebla.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
