<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-09-12">Sep. 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">As Regards to the Old Country Festivals</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0333</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0333.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-09-12">Sep. 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">AS REGARDS TO THE OLD COUNTRY FESTIVALS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Mexican colony views with disgust the following facts: It is rumored that Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, Mexican Consul has invited "some prominent Mexican citizens", who form a distinguished group of dealers, professional, and directors of societies, to discuss at the Mexican Consulate, financial support for the celebration of Mexico's Independence anniversary. A Mexican fiesta will be given September 15th.</p>
   <p>Mr. Aveleyra published a letter last year in El Nacional (formerly Mexico), in which he said: "I will not give my support to nor will I recognize officially any festival held by a Mexican Club or Society, unless a dance open to the public is given as a grand finale. If I should attend a festival in which there is dancing, I shall do so without official representation.</p>
   <p>Obviously, Mr. Aveleyra intended to abolish the business made by some unscrupulous people who prosper by the patriotism of the Mexicans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0334.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But the idea is to hold the Mexican festival of September 15th, for all Mexican people, and with the support of Mexicans.</p>
   <p>Mr. Aveleyra forgot to invite all the Mexicans thru the newspapers, he invited instead a select group of them. Hadn't this been the case the Cooperation would have been more effective.</p>
   <p>Nobody knew that there was going to be an official festival and everybody made plans accordingly. The Mexican Colony in Chicago always has cooperated and I do not understand how on this occasion it has not been taken into consideration</p>
   <p>We are Mexicans, both the intellectual and the humble workers; therefore, we must sooperate with our presence and money on this great anniversary. I an talking in the name of the working class, and I protest against this discrimination.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0335.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We can be strong thru mutual aid. In the present case our country's representative is working against our interests.</p>
   <p>It is true the Machiavellian's apothegm: "Divide and reign".</p>
   <p>Professor F. Ortega Rodriguez,</p>
   <p>2318 North Orchard Street,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
