<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Padre Catatina</title>, Pastor of the Mexican Catholic Church, 91st and Brandon Avenue, know as Tempo de Guadalupe, also as St. Judas Tadeus Chicago Ill., by Nicolas M. Hernandez,
<date when="1936-12-10">Dec. 10, 1936</date>.
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.3"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item><item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Padre Catatina</title>, Pastor of The Mexican Catholic Church, 91st and Brandon Avenue, know as Tempo de Guadalupe, also as St. Judas Tadeus Chicago Ill., by Nicolas M. Hernandez,
<date when="1936-12-10">Dec. 10, 1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are 5,700 Mexicans <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> this Church. According to the census of 1935, we have <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Mexicans including  <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> belong to our Church. We have religious services <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> four times a day, every day of the week. We have six religious societies. 1. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, with Sociedad de Guadalupe, with <gap unit="char" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>69 members, 2. Sociedad del Santo Nombre, 420 members, 3. Archicofradia Society <gap unit="char" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>75 members, 4. Infants (children)  <gap unit="char" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>25 members, 5. Terciarios <gap unit="char" extent="3" reason="illegible"/> members, Sagrado Corazon de Jesus 620 members. Society No. 1. Rosario Anaya, is the President, and has 12 officers. No. 2. Roberto Lopez, is the President, and has 15 officers. No. 3. Isabel de Gomez, is the President and has 25 officers. No. 4. Jesus Villa, is the President and has 8 officers, No. 5. Genaro Anaya, is the President and has 6 officers, No. 6. Rumaldo Perales, is the President and has 14, officers. We have classes in English and Spanish for adults of both sexes 4 evenings a week.</p>
   
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0402.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>About 80 adults attend the classes. Also, we teach the following: Singing, music, sewing, drawing, handicraft, arithmetic, physics, sociology, popular science an flower making.I cannot say how many people attend each class, however the attendance varies, because the people work different shifts, most every member attends to some of the classes above mentioned. All of the 8,020 Mexicans are catholics, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> this Church, <gap unit="word" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> non-catholics do not interest us. We have a school for <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, five days a week <gap unit="word" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> about 140 attending <gap unit="word" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. We have catholic charities. I can say that we benefit the City of Chicago by educating the people and making them good citizens; socially as well as morally, to be good workers and faithful to their jobs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
