<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>, Vol III. No 37.
<date when="1936-09-13">Sept 13, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">September 16, 1821-1936 Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>, Vol III. No 37.
<date when="1936-09-13">Sept 13, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">SEPTEMBER 16, 1821-1936 Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Innocent and expiatory victims, they have been and shall remain Catholic citizens who have been vilely assassinated by those desperados so called revolutionaries. They have covered their assassination of peaceful Catholic people, crushed and robbed with fearful despotism to the maximum degradation the heroic Mexican Nation. !Hypocrits! They are celebrating the Independence of Mexico after they have slaved our people; they commemorate our Father Hidalgo and condemn his work; they read the Act of Independence which is in itself a profession of faith and deny its contents. Hidalgo and those who signed the act of Independence as well as the other heroes were believers and Catholics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0414.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Those who now oppress the country by the use of force as their only right, have descended to the level of a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. For them, there is no understanding, that is why they have not only renounced the faith of our forefathers and heroes of <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> against and glorify themselves to that which even the savages through a moral instinct respect and revere the existence of God. And they do not only blaspheme against God, but they also glory themselves upon their crazy atheism threatening God as a pariah, as an inhuman and criminal being. Disgraceful, little by little the whirlwind of the divine ire shall fall upon them and there shall not even be left a memory for those to follow. "The Congress of Anahuac solemnly declared that they shall not profess or recognize other faith than the Catholic Religion, nor they shall permit or tolerate any other; that they will protect with all its power, and will watch upon the purity of its faith and Dogmas".</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0415.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We sincerely invite Cardenas and all his government, the governors and Military chiefs, Senators and Congressmen, to the Minister of Education with all his agents and teachers of Socialist and Sexual education. We extend this invitation to Calles, Garrido and other assassins of Catholics, so that they might meditate in their solitude and exile the real meaning of the Act, and its signification to the Mexican.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
