<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-20">Aug. 20, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Lamentable Death</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0571</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0571.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-20">Aug. 20, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">LAMENTABLE DEATH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Major Jaime M. Venegas, noted military instructor and head of the Purchasing Department of the Mexican Government, under the Carranza Administration, died last Monday night in his residence at 5428 Blackstone Avenue, after several months of grave illness. Major Venegas was born in Mexico City, July 25th, 1861 and came to Chicago, with his family shortly after the defeat of Carranza and the fall of his government. Venegas was an authority on religious music and an accomplished musician. Immediately after his arrival in Chicago he identified himself with Catholic activities, serving as organist at the Holy Name Cathedral and at Saint Mary and Saint Thomas Churches for several years.</p>
   <p>His funeral took place Friday morning from his luxurious residence and was attended by dignitaries from the Catholic Church, consular officials from various Central and South American republics, as well as by prominent Chicago professional and business men.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0572.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A solemn requiem mass was said in Saint Thomas Apostle Church. His remains were buried in Saint Mary's Cemetery in the midst of great manifestations of respect and sympathy. Surviving the deceased are the distinguished lady, Mrs. Natalia Vinda de Venegas, his sons, Captain Benjamin Venegas, who distinguished himself in the Military Air Service of his Country under the Carrenza Admninistration, Francis, James, Louis, Carlos and his daughters Mrs. Ernestina Beatriz Infante, and her twin Imelda, Mrs. Joseph Gonzales and Mrs. Arthur Anndonajin.</p>
   <p>May his remains rest in peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
