<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-27">Aug. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Mexico's Independence Celebrations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-27">Aug. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICO'S INDEPENDENCE CELEBRATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Besides the 15th of September celebration which is to take place Thursday night, another entertainment is prepared for the following night of the 16th. On both nights, after the programs, dancing will take place.</p>
   <p>The organizers of the festival inform us that the celebration will take place at Pilsen Park, the night of the 16th. Outstanding artists will take part in the program which will take place before dancing begins. As it is the custom on this particular night an official speech will be delivered by an outstanding citizen of our colony.</p>
   <p>There will be various song and dance numbers, as well as a colorful parade of cars. We do not know who will furnish the musical program for the dance on the night of the 16th of September, which will occur at Pilsen Park. But we are sure that it will be in care of one of our well known jazz-bands. The spacious hall in Pilsen Park, with its wide windows providing plenty of ventilation is one of the halls most favored by our colony.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0318.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the Bar Room eats and refreshments will be served. During the dance, a shower of confetti will take place which will add brilliance and splendor to the festival.</p>
   <p>The official celebration of the 15th of September will take place at the "West Side Auditorium," located at Taylor and Racine Streets, commencing at 8 P. M. An interesting program has been arranged for this night. The first number on the program will be the official speech given by our Consul of Mexico, Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, who at eleven o'clock sharp will take hold of the sacred insignia of our country and of the Heroes of Independence, praising the names of those brave men who gave us our land and freedom. Mr. William O'Neill will speak for our Colony.</p>
   <p>The official organizers of this commemorable night on Thursday, 15th of September, are fellow citizens whose honesty and honorableness are much respected by the Colony.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0319.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The president of the Organizing Committee of the celebrations of September, has made a special effort to have a patriotic festival, more brilliant and glamorous than the ones that have taken place in previous years.</p>
   <p>In the artistical program of the West Side Auditorium, the night of the 15th, the prominent professor of International Dances, Paco Parafan, will have a part in our theatrical features.</p>
   <p>The Organizing Committee, extended a special invitation to the famous dancer, who accepted the invitation gladly.</p>
   <p>The professor, informs us that for the first time, he will introduce his beautiful dancing partner, Miss Giralda Sevilla.</p>
   <p>Other valuable performers who will take part in the affair of the 15th are: Miss Emma Valle, 7 years old, charming daughter of our outstanding friend Mr. Ignacio M. Valle.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0320.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Miss Valle, will entertain the public with the noted Mexican dance, Jarabe Tapatio. Another beautiful little Miss is Amparito Gutierrez, who will dance an Argentine Tango and Ernesto Loranca will present several comical acts.</p>
   <p>A group of five will sing typical Mexican songs. At eleven o'clock P.M., a group of boys and girls will sing the "Mexican National Hymn, "under the direction of Mr. Apolonio Colunga.</p>
   <p>Mr. Francisco Reyes Mata, president of the Committee, informs us that he has made a special arrangement with the "Chapultepec" jazz-band for this glorious night.</p>
   <p>The "Latin-American Club", has furnished the "Aztece" orchestra. Great joy and enthusiasm reign among our expectant colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
