<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Mexicano</title>, Vol. I, No. 1.
<date when="1934-04-20">April 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Baptist Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Mexicano</title>, Vol. I, No. 1.
<date when="1934-04-20">April 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Baptist Convention</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One hundred and fifty delegates, representing the Mexican Baptist Church from the Middle-West, are attending the Convention. The convention is taking place in the Mexican Baptist Church at 4658 Gross Avenue from April 18 to 22, 1934. The program is as follows: April 18, 7:30 P.M. Devotional Service, conducted by Lucio P. Avila. At 7:45 special music by Century of Progress orchestra 8:00 P.M. Opening sermon by Rev. Ramon Tolsa. April 19, at 9:00 A.M. registration of delegates, Ministerial Conference presided by Rev. Frank Martinez and a theme in charge of Dr. R. C. Schell. 10:00 A. M. special music and singing. 10:10 A. M. Government of the Church by Dr. J. E. Davies. 10:40 A. M. Business meeting. 11:00 A. M. Pauline Ecclesiology by Dr. Carlos L. Detwieler. At 2:00 P. M. A program by the Feminine Association. 7:00 P. M. Service of Praise by Rev. Reinaldo Olivares. 7:15 P. M. Chorus by brothers from Indiana Harbor, Ind. 7:30 P. M. Introduction of visitors. 8:00 P. M. Mexico Today, by Senor Carlos Palacios Roji, Consul of Mexico.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0423.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>April 20, at 9:00 A. M. Commendation Service, by brother Tomas Montemayor. 9:15 "Modern Enemies of the Church" by Rev. Pablo J. Villonueva. 10:00 Business of the Convention. 10:30 The Church and its own support by Dr. E. R. Brown. 11:00 Pauline Ecclesiology by Dr. Carlos L. Deitweiler. 2:00 P. M. Essay: "The Church and the Religious Education" by Rev. F. M. Santiago. 2:30 Music and songs. 2:40 The Cooperative work of the Church by Dr. A. E. Paterson. 3:10 Special Music. 3:20 The Church and the Gospel by Dr. J. E. Davies. 4:00 "Offering of the Church to the Youth" by Rev. Armando Alvarado. 7:30 Service of Praise by brother Benjamin Morales. 7:45 Music by the Orchestra. 8:00 The Church and its Missions by Mr. J. E. Davies. April 21, at 9:00 A. M. Service of Commendation by brother Porfirio Martinez. 9:15 The Church and the Kingdom of Heaven by Rev. Castulo de Lara. 9:30 Special Music by the Century of Progress Orchestra. 10:00 Business Meeting. 11:00 Pauline Ecclesiology by Dr. Carlos L. Detweiler. 2:00 P. M. Service of Praise by brother H. Boones. 2:15 Chorus by the South Chicago Church singers. 2:20 "Challenge of the Cross "Drama by the Baptist Mexican Youth of Chicago. 5:00 "The Church of the future" by Rev. Jose W. Martinez. 7:30 P. M. Service of Praise by brother Jesus de las Paz. Music by the orchestra "Century of Progress". 8:00 The word of the Holy-Ghost and the Church by Rev. Jose P. Ruiz.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0424.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>April 22, 9:30 A. M. Bible School in charge of Rev. Frank Martinez. 11:00 Sermon by Rev. A. B. Apra. 2:00 P. M. Union Association of Baptist Youth. 7:30 Service of Praise by brother Manuel Martinez. 7:45 Music by the Orchestra. 8:00 P. M. Closing Sermon by Rev. Pablo Villannueva.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
