<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Alianza</title>, Vol I. No 3.
<date when="1936-07">July 1936</date>.
<title level="a">What Is Our Mission and Purposes?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Alianza</title>, Vol I. No 3.
<date when="1936-07">July 1936</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS OUR MISSION AND PURPOSES?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Alianza is the official paper of our institution, that has been in existence three months, deserving the approval of its own people, as well as the other people. The program outlined from the beginning, has been carried out, because our mission is to serve our institution, our people and in general the society in which we live.</p>
   <p>Fraternal work, nationalist, of general and mutual respect for our fellowmen to the institutions, and the laws which govern the world in politically and dogmatically, whether in this or in another country, we understand, that it should be the most sacred mission to be undertaken by any good citizen; wishing to be respected as he respects others. Our social and intellectual work, has been very nationalist, and has been the idea of the present executive board. They submitted for approval the names of some prominent people of our colony to be accepted as honorary members of our society.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0085.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The names submitted are: Senor Antonio L. Schmidt, Consul of Mexico, Senor Manuel Aguilar, Vice-Consul of Mexico, Sebastian Rivera, a prominent lawyer, and Rev. Guillermo Baquero O'Neill. They shall come and unite to the phalanx of the Alianza to struggle for a Mexican life in our institution.</p>
   <p>Our social and intellectual life will be intensified with these elements of intellectual prestige. In remembering the great intellect of the flagrant Indian, Lic. Benito Juarez, who said: "The respect to the right of others means peace". Such words were not from a prophet, they were phrases that sprung from the mind of a great statesman who astonished the whole world with his Laws of reform. Were phrases of wisdom from a patriot who knew how to defend the national soil against the invasion from one of the strongest nations of the world That is why we, and every thinking person who love order and morality have followed that slogan exactly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
