<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-27">Aug. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Farewell Functions for Reverend Carlos M Gurrola</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-27">Aug. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">FAREWELL FUNCTIONS FOR REVEREND CARLOS M GURROLA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Baptist Churches of Chicago united, express their gratitude and respect to their Pastor, the Reverend Carlos M. Gurrola, who for the last six years has worked so arduously for the sake of Christianity. They organized a brilliant farewell celebration last Saturday the 20th, at 8:00 p.m. at the Central Church located at Morgan and Monroe.</p>
   <p>The main part of the program were speeches delivered by the Pastors from the Methodist, Presbyterian, Congregation and Baptist Churches of Indiana Harbor.</p>
   <p>They were Reverend William B. O'Neill, Reverend Lacy Simns, Mr. Jose O. Velasco and Reverend J. P. Ruiz, who praised especially the work and the sacrifices made by said Minister, the rest of the program was musical and was very attractive. Mr. Hilario Montemeyor offered the gift made by the Baptist Churches. Reverend Gurrola, was moved by the cordiality and Christian spirit of the assembly. He took his leave in a brilliant speech, for which he was much applauded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0442.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last Sunday, 21st, at 5:00 p.m. the Methodist and Congregational Churches gave a farewell dinner in honor of Reverend Gurrola, on account of his departure from the Centro Social Mexicano, situated at Mexwell and Newberry Streets.</p>
   <p>A dinner in Mexican style was served; it was prepared by the ladies of the Methodist Church. The dinner was followed by a program. It was organized by the pastors of both churches. Mr. Jose O. Velasco served as master of ceremonies. The program was magnificient. The music was provided by the Tipica Orchestra of which Mr. Rocha is the director. The tenors Escobarete and Garcia, sang several songs under the direction of Mr. Rosenda Rios.</p>
   <p>The farewell speech was made by Reverend O'Neill, who also told the assembly that Mrs. Josefina Q. de Gamba, a member of the Methodist Church was leaving for Mexico.</p>
   <p>At the end of the program Reverend Gurrola thanked the sister churches for the homage they had paid him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
