<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-05-08">May 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mexicans Celebrate Independence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0364</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0364.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-05-08">May 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICANS CELEBRATE INDEPENDENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fiesta to celebrate the Batalla de Puebla (Battle of Puebla) was a brilliant affair. A concert and dance featured the celebration which the Mexican colony held at the Ashland Boulevard Auditorium. This was their way of doing honor to the heroic Mexican general, Ignacio Zaragoza, which defeated the forces of Napoleon III on that memorial date, May 5, 1862.</p>
   <p>The festival was arranged by the Mexican Blue Cross of Chicago, aided by its South Chicago and Indiana Harbor branches. The sponsor of the affair, which was given Sunday, May 4, was the Mexican Consulate. It was supported by a large group of the most select of our society, who worked untiringly through the following clubs: Club Ideal, Club Mamerto, Orquesta Tipica Morales, Club Cultural Latina-Americano, Sociedad Obreros Libres de South Chicago (South Chicago Free Workers' Society), and Club Cervantes.</p>
   <p>The promotion of this festival was initiated by the Cruz Azul Mexicana to serve two purposes: a patriotic demonstration, and an occasion to secure funds with which to further the relief work of the Mexican Blue Cross.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0365.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program was masterfully carried out. Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, at 9:30 P.M., began it by introducing the Cruz Azul Mexicana's members who arranged the festival. Then speeches, musical selections, recitations, folk and artistic dancing, and singing, rendered by outstanding persons, featured the program.</p>
   <p>Members of the Consulates of several South American countries were among the large attendance, which made the affair a financial, social, and patriotic success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
