<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>, Vol. VIII. No. 742.
<date when="1934-01-20">Jan. 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Social Activities in the Mexican Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0146</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0146.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>, Vol. VIII. No. 742.
<date when="1934-01-20">Jan. 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL ACTIVITIES IN THE MEXICAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two important festivals will take place tonight. The Spanish society has prepared a very excellent Literary and Musical program to be given at the Palmer House. We consider this an artistic feature, and the most selected, as yet, organized by this society. Now, as on previous occasions, the arrangments committee has taken special care that the program may serve the purpose aimed by this social organization, to make known the art and culture of Spain. In accordance with such purpose they have secured the collaboration of a group of enthusiast and skillful artists, singers and dancers, who will present special numbers in the program and will without a doubt meet the approval of the attendants. The festival will take place in the Club Room at the Palmer House at 8:30 P. M. After the Program, there will be dancing, the orchestra of Don Pablo has been assigned for the occasion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0147.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>LOS MAYAS FOURTH ANNIVERSARY</p>
   <p>The orchestra "Los Mayas" are celebrating their fourth anniversary tonight at the West Side Auditorium. Many attractions will take place there, in order to satisfy the demands of those present. They have promised many things, the music to be played has already been selected by at least a couple hundred girls from our colony. Therefore, the principal part has been secured, since it is the feature that interest the dancers most. However, the judgement passed on the selection of the music by these maidens will be enough to satisfy the different tastes and moods of the people.</p>
   <p>Speaking of temperaments, the Johnies, will be able to draw their own conclusions, as to which one of the girls is the most romantic, which the most sentimental, and who the best dreamer, etc., by the piece she has chosen. At 11: P. M. a division of a large cake will be offered as a gift by this orchestra to the patrons. El Nacional through these lines wants to congratulate the members of this organization, wishing them many more years of existence and many more triumphs in the musical art.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
