<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrapbook of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1927">1927</date>. Special from the Christian Science Monitor Bureau.
<title level="a">Shifts in Chicago Ghetto Are Changing its Complexion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0061</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0061.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrapbook of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1927">1927</date>. Special from the Christian Science Monitor Bureau.
<title level="a">SHIFTS IN CHICAGO GHETTO ARE CHANGING ITS COMPLEXION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One time exclusive Jewish section gradually filling up with Mexicans and Negroes who are active Market men.</p>
   <p>Chicago-Maxwell Street, Chicago's famous Ghetto, is undergoing a change. For years its open-air markets, with wares displayed on the curbs of its narrow street, formed the hub of Jewish immigrant settlements. But the westward movement of nationalities sweeps over the erstwhile Jewish section, and now the Ghetto feels the sifting in of Mexicans and Negroes. Dark-skin ed customers are more numerous, and a few have even taken their posts behind wagons next to the gray-bearded old timers. As the customers go through the crowded street a shrewd salesman calls out as he blocks the passage, pretending to recognize an old customer. "You are the one I sold shoes before. Let me show you a new pair." Safely beyond the clutches of the shoe seller the visitor encounters an intriguing milliner. For quick service a cylindrical shaped gas stove topped with a hat form is <pb facs="5423405_2_0062.jpg" n="2"/>kept burning. Should the hat be too small just a few pulls and twists over the heated form and the hat comes out the right size. The visitor extricates herself when a more affable customer arrives actually looking for a headgear. A large transparent orange hat is pulled down to shade the dark skin of the Mexican woman's smile and the visitor hears on leaving, "That surely is a becoming color for you."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
