<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1929-01-05">Jan. 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Winter's Solstice.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1929-01-05">Jan. 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">WINTER'S SOLSTICE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Very enjoyable and full of excitement was the literary and musical festival which took place at the "Aiken Institute" Monroe and Morgan streets. The occasion was the celebration of the "Winter's Solstice," under the auspicies of the Hon. "Hirman" No. 6 and "Lux-In-Umbra" No. 50, both being Masonic Lodges of Chicago and South Chicago respectively. Perhaps, the organizers of the brothers of these magnificent groups; didn't expect such splendid results as those which were obtained at this reunion. A conjunction of artistic elements and skillful orators participated on this pleasant program, all being very happy in the fulfillment of the same. An overture was played by the orchestra directed by Prof. Medina.</p>
   <p>Jose' Garcia L. made the official address, it was very conscientious and reasonable, and for this he was very much applauded. Raza de Bronce Race of Brass, a poem written by Amado Nervo, a distinguished Mexican poet was recited by Roman H. Fortoso, who had a moment of real inspiration, he was also awarded with an ovation. Other sketches of art and equal attraction followed. Also some songs were courteously offered by Daniel Ramirez, accompanied at the piano by Prof. J. Vazquez.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0475.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There were some variety numbers gallantly offered by members of the Infant Drama and comedy group which was conducted by the intelligent Mrs. Andrea G. de Rocha. After a short interval in which the children were given toys, then, the emblem of the Herman Lodge No. 6 was delivered, amidst a ceremony in which the brothers of the order distinguished themselves with their conduct and good discipline which was evidence of an advanced instruction. But, undoubtedly the highest reward had been reserved for the Hon. Alvarez del Castillo and Yolanda Diaz who made very eloquent dissertation. Alvarez del Castillo in brief but conscientious phrases told us the history of our worthy National Mexican Rite. He placed an emphasis in the fact that the Mexican Rite is legally recognized by the Great Masonic family of the Universe. Thus, weakening the prejudices which some elements try to diffuse without knowing the significance of our Masonic Society. We, the Masons of the world consider ourselves linked by an indestructable fraternal love and for this reason our society has no frontiers, because our members reside in every ambit of the terraqueous globe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
