<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-03-24">March 24, 1934</date>.
      <title level="a">An Answer to the Pan-American</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-03-24">March 24, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">AN ANSWER TO THE PAN-AMERICAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Asociacion Pan-American,</p>
   <p>1139 So. Ashland Blvd.,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Our Dear Sister:</p>
   <p>After meditating upon the contents of your letter which appeared in the columns of El Nacional of March 3, 1934, and placed much emphasis on the invitation that you have extended to us so that we may unite in the celebration of our glorious 5th of May.</p>
   <p>In regards to this we have agreed on the following: Taking into consideration the teachings that for some time we have received from our oldest sisters, and the example they have setforth in regards to the celebration of our national holidays.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0290.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have realized, that all such celebrations have been a precise expression of the wrong conception of patriotism, and we do not want to go to that extreme. The experience advises us on this occasion to comply with out duty, that is, to honor the memory of our heroes, in a loyal and respectful manner and not within that feeble concept of patriotism which is converted into verbosity which for many long years has prevailed in the spirit of our oldest sisters. To such, instead of calling it a manifestation of gratitude to our heroes; we can just as well call it manifestation of tolerance and inculture. Then, year after year, instead of us seeing the Mexican groups of Chicago as the real patriotic flower, we have been able to contemplate only the darnel of a false patriotism.</p>
   <p>It will be different now, if we are really true Mexican patriots, let us set-forth the principle on the route of the real patriotism. Let us learn how to place a definite line, to distinguish that which means a personal welfare and self-advantage, and that which is translated into welfare and advantage for the collective benefit of all and for the honor of our country as well.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0291.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It has been clearly manifested on various occasions, that whenever a society takes the initiative to organize a patriotic celebration, at no time has there been a real honest procedure. Because, always a number of individuals will crowd around, and whose interests are linked to a personal profit; finding therefore, in our national days, a good pretext to satiate all their passions and cupidity.</p>
   <p>We must wipe out all those who exploit in the name of our heroes. Let us celebrate our 5th of May in a worthy and respectable manner; let us build a united front; let us make a general call to our colony and in particular to our professional people, musicians and artists. We must bear in mind that the country belongs to all, and is there for all; for this reason only, we shall celebrate the 5th of May wherever the majority so desire, but, without any charge. Then, it is high time that each one of us should place every effort that we can to comply with our duty,and not merely be awaiting for the national holidays to act.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0292.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>That is if we wait until the day is very close, this means to leave the doors open for those who are unscrupulous and who instead of complying with their duty as patriots, it is just the opposite, their payments increase then. Now, a different plan should be put into effect, let us have an estimate of the cost of the hall, material, program, etc.</p>
   <p>We count upon <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>expert printers and we have no doubt, that they willingly extend their patriotic cooperation. To pay for the rent of the hall and other expenses <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> if all of us contribute according to our circumstances. Since the confidence of the people toward the organizations has decreased <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> are not capable to give us the proper orientation. We must not <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the support of our professional men and other prepared individuals.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0293.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And above all, let the Consulate of Mexico be the treasury, where all of us can send our contribution until the expenses are being subrogated. Therefore we authorize you to inform the other fraternal groups concerning our views and unite with us in order to reach a reasonable agreement.</p>
   <p>Mutually yours,</p>
   <p>Fraternal Evolucion</p>
   <p>Damas Mexicanas</p>
   <p>C. A. B.</p>
   <p>Anahuac</p>
   <p>Necaxa</p>
   <p>333</p>
   <p>Cuauhtemoc</p>
   <p>Flechas Azulez</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
