<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-29">Mar. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Open Grants to Mexicans Who Return to Homeland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_2_0506</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-28">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0506.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-29">Mar. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">OPEN GRANTS TO MEXICANS WHO RETURN TO HOMELAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Mexican Consul, Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, sent us for publication the circular transcribed below. The contents of this circular is of great importance to many Mexicans who plan to return to Mexico.</p>
   <p>Mexico,</p>
   <p>1218 W. Madison St.,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>Honorable Manager:</p>
   <p>(Subject Matter: Open Grants to Those Returning to Native Country)</p>
   <p>Having received a communication from the Secretary of Foreign Affairs, I make haste to send it to you so that it may be given immediate publication in the important tri-weekly which you direct.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0507.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This matter has to do with the modification of the Custom Law which is in force. I have been advised that the change has been made so as to allow those Mexicans who return to their homeland the same exemptions which they enjoyed before this law went into effect.</p>
   <p>This means that our fellowmen may make an account of what they are able to take with them, on returning to Mexico, such as automobiles and musical instruments of whatever nature, and that none of these will be subject to custom duties.</p>
   <p>Those fellowmen who desire to return, or those who have already returned, will not, therefore, have to pay custom duties on any type of household goods which they might carry with them, such as radios, pianos, phonographs and other musical instruments which they might carry to their homeland in order to entertain themselves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_2_0508.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The President of the Republic, Ing. Pascual Ortiz Rubic, did not speak in vain when he said that he would make every possible inducement to his fellowmen in order to encourage them to return to Mexico. Many Mexican families were not able to return to Mexico for the simple reason that the Custom Law did not permit them to pass their chattels without first paying the stipulated custom duties. With the new modification, however, it is hoped that the number of Mexicans who might return to Mexico will increase considerably.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
