<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-10-13">Oct. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Senator Harding</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0972</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0972.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-10-13">Oct. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">SENATOR HARDING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republican presidential candidate seems to be gaining in popularity every week throughout the country, and especially in the Middle West. His keen intelligence, noble personality, and dignified bearing have not failed to make a deep and favorable impression on audiences wherever he has appeared as a speaker. Everybody who has had the opportunity of meeting or hearing him is convinced, that he is worthy of the great office of president of the United States, and that he will steer the right course as captain of the ship of state.</p>
   <p>Among the most remarkable traits of Senator Harding is his practical approach to problems of all kinds, his unprejudiced opinions in regard to the Americanization of immigrants, and his sympathetic understanding of the feelings which lie more or less deeply hidden in the minds of those of our people who were born in a foreign country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0973.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This latter trait was especially evident during a recent visit by foreignborn citizens to his home in Marion, Ohio. On that occasion he won everybody's heart by his friendly attitude.</p>
   <p>A number of Scandinavian newspapermen were among the visitors, and in the course of the day they had a private conversation with the Senator. During the conversation, the status of the foreign-language press was discussed particularly the unnecessary and humiliating regulations to which it is now subjected. As an example, the fact may be mentioned that these newspapers cannot be published without a special Government license; and that across the top of the first page, the following caption must be printed: "Published and Distributed under Permit". The Senator understood fully the foreign newspapermen's feelings in regard to this matter, and declared that as soon as he becomes chief executive, he will remove this and similar war regulations from the statute books.</p>
   <p>It is well known that Senator Harding is himself a newspaper publisher, his paper being the Marion Star.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
