<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-04-07">Apr. 7, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Tenth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-04-07">Apr. 7, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">TENTH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday evening, the Drake Lodge #3, I. O. V. celebrated its tenth anniversary with a social at Spelz Hall, 1630 Clark Street, Lake View. Before eight o'clock, the people began to fill the hall, and at nine o'clock when the curtain was raised, the hall was practically full. Shortly afterwards, every seat in the hall was taken. There was hardly standing room, so great was the number of people who were present at this anniversary, which evidently had caught the peoples' interest as strongly as any of the earlier anniversary socials sponsored by this lodge. The committee on arrangements had done its best to make the social a success, and without fear of contradiction, we state that on leaving the hall that night the audience felt that it had passed a very pleasant evening.</p>
   <p>The Viking Music Corps furnished the music, both during the program and the dance which followed. The Orphei Singing Club, under the <pb facs="5423404_4_1258.jpg" n="2"/>direction of our beloved Mr. Mossberg, gave a very good account of itself, and the numbers presented were strongly applauded. The solo by Miss Marguerita McGue received much applause. Mr. P. Westerberg took his public by storm with his solos, and the public response to the presentations of the singer and comic, Mr. Ernst Ekberg, was of a similar type.</p>
   <p>The program concluded with a tableau,in which vari-colored illumination was used. Seven men dressed as vikings formed the background, while in one of the wings a dozen girls, dressed in white, each with a Swedish flag in her hand, were arranged obliquely outward, and in the other wing a similar number of boys was arranged in an opposite direction. They, too, held flags, and all sang "America"....to the accompaniment of the piano. The animated dance following the program lasted until the early hours of the morning.</p>
   <p>We congratulate the Drake lodge upon the success it has enjoyed to date, and wish it the best of success in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
