<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-09-11">Sept. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Exchange of Students</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-09-11">Sept. 11, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">EXCHANGE OF STUDENTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. K. A. Hjorth, secretary of the National Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture in Foreign Countries, and president of the Vasa lodge Goteborg (Gothenburg) revealed during his visit in this country last summer that plans for the arrangement of study trips by students from both sides of the Atlantic are now under consideration in Sweden.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The National Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture in Foreign Countries is the Swedish mother organization of a similiar society in America, with branches in various parts of the country. There is such a branch in Chicago.] If they materialize Swedish Youth will be given an opportunity to visit America and carry on studies here, and young Americans will <pb facs="5423404_4_1066.jpg" n="2"/>be given similar opportunities in Sweden.</p>
   <p>In the Scandinavian countries there exists at the present time a society called "My Friend Abroad," which is already operating along the same lines. But those in charge of the present Swedish efforts wish to enlarge the scope of this movement, and especially want to make it possible for American students to go directly to Sweden instead of getting there by way of Denmark, where the organizations headquarters are located.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hjorth, in discussing the various phases of the Swedish plan, pointed out the benefits both Swedish and American Youth will derive from visiting one another's countries for the pursuit of specific studies.</p>
   <p>The plan does not represent an entirely new and untried venture. Several years ago, the American-Scandinavian Foundation began the practice of exchanging <pb facs="5423404_4_1067.jpg" n="3"/>students between the United States and the Scandinavian countries, but the opportunities to take part in this exchange have been open only to students in institutions of higher learning.</p>
   <p>A few years ago this newspaper suggested editorially that an exchange of young Swedish and American students be given a practical trial, and the American branch of the cultural society once played with the idea of arranging for an exchange of letters between young students of the two countries. The purpose of such correspondance would be to make Swedish-American Youth better acquainted with the Swedish language and Swedish life in general, and vice versa.</p>
   <p>It is too early to predict whether or not this latest plan, propounded by Dr. Hjorth, will ever materialize, but the idea is a good one. Swedish Youth need to know more about America and about its nationals who have made their homes here; and looking a few years ahead with an eye on the coming <pb facs="5423404_4_1068.jpg" n="4"/>great exposition in Chicago, it is safe to say that a study trip to this country would be a great event in the life of any young Swede, and would prove exceedingly cultural. The same may be said in regard to a visit to Sweden by American students, next year a great exposition will be held in the capital of the Old Country, to which the whole world is invited.</p>
   <p>However, such occasions are rare and only incidental. The important thing is that young people of the respective countries, in as large numbers as possible, be given a chance to benefit from such study trips, for impressions received at that age are apt to remain permanent as sources, not only to pleasant memories, but of practical and intellectual enrichment as well. The brotherhood of men, better understanding of specific racial qualities, and a more vivid cultural exchange are promoted through such study trips.</p>
   <p>Sentimentally we often speak of "hands across the sea". By all means, let it be a handshake between the young hands, which are destined to shape the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
