<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-10-06">Oct. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Svithiod Lodge Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0079</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0079.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-10-06">Oct. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">SVITHIOD LODGE DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.11...........The committee for the "Svithiod Day" festivals, celebrated last June at Good Templar Park, Geneva, held its last meeting in "High Noon Club," 1850 Michigan Avenue Saturday evening, when the final report was presented. Mr. Chas. E. Smith, who as president of the committee has taken many a heavy lift to make this affair a success was in the chair. It was already known that the monetary result was satisfactory, but that it would be overwhelming as the secretary Mr. Bernard Johnson's report stated, no one had ever hoped. Great was the rejoicing, when he announced the receipts to balance with $29,000.00, and the net proceeds to be $19,230.74 with a few small outstanding amounts still to be accounted for. Receipts and disbursements had been audited by a committee headed by Holger J. Rosberg, and on the recommendation of this committee, the report was accepted. The treasurer Mr. Fred Nelson was instructed to split the amount with one third, going to Svithiod's Old Peoples Homes and the remaining two thirds to be divided among the participating lodges, in proportion to the number of tickets each lodge had sold.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0080.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After the meeting, the committee, together with many who has been active during the festivities and a number of invited guests, gathered in the club's dining hall where a luncheon was served and wherein three-hundred persons took part in a very animated spirit.</p>
   <p>Later a program of music and song was presented under the direction of Chas. M. White, and an orchestra played. In connection with the festivities and the athletic events several speakers expressed themselves, such as: Gordon A. Berg, Samuel Peterson, John Sandgren, Gust. Hartelius and others. Representatives from other athletic clubs were heard from. A dance concluded the evening's program.</p>
   <p>Next year's Svithiod Day will be celebrated at Good Templar Park Geneva, Ill., Sunday, June 17.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
