<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-08-23">Aug. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Building Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-08-23">Aug. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">BUILDING ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At 918 Winona Street, just east of Sheridan Road and near the lake, construction has started on an apartment building which will have one unusual feature. The building, which will be six stories high and will contain forty-eight apartments, will be equipped with a roof garden, like those on the roofs of the city's large, modern hotels. The building will be named the Winona Beach Apartments, and it is estimated to cost $400,000. The Admiral Hotel is located a short distance away. Architect John A. Nyden has delivered the plans for both these buildings. They are owned by him and Albin Nilsson.</p>
   <p>During the first seven months of this year, the building commissioner's office has issued building permits representing one hundred and ten million dollars' worth of construction work, on double the amount for the corresponding period last year. Among the latest permits are the following:</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0561.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Nine one-story houses to be erected at 3634 North St. Louis Avenue. Owner, A. Hallman; drawings by G. E. Pearson.</p>
   <p>Store and office building at 429 South Clark Street, estimated to cost $30,000. Owner, C. O. Hanson, who is also the architect.</p>
   <p>Apartment building with stores on the street level, estimated to cost $70,000. The Vagtborg Construction Company has contracted for the brick-work on the building, and Levy Nelson for the carpentry work.</p>
   <p>Two-story apartment building at 6562 Sheridan Road, estimated to cost $30,000. A. Johnson has contracted for the brick-work.</p>
   <p>Two-story apartment building at 5327-31 Christiana Avenue, the drawings for which have been delivered by G. E. Pearson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
