<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-11-24">Nov. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Red Cross and Needy Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-11-24">Nov. 24, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE RED CROSS AND NEEDY CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Anybody who at this time sends in a dollar to renew his membership in the Red Cross, or who signs up as a new member, is taking an active part in the greatest charitable undertaking in the history of mankind. We have especially in mind what the American Red Cross right now is doing for the millions of children in the war-torn countries of Europe."</p>
   <p>This statement is quoted from a circular issued by the Swedish department of the American Red Cross.</p>
   <p>According to the circular, it is virtually impossible for one who has not seen it with his own eyes to imagine the miserable conditions under which some thirteen million children in Southern Europe have been living ever since they were born. Five million children in Serbia, Poland, Austria, and neighboring countries. have nobody to look after them. Their parents died during the war, and <pb facs="5423404_4_0272.jpg" n="2"/>since then they have had to take care of themselves. Neither private individuals nor the governments of these countries were able to do anything for these orphans. The poor children live almost like rats. They must shift for themselves to get something to eat, and to find shelter against rain and wind. If they do not succeed, they die from hunger and exposure.</p>
   <p>In some of the countries mentioned, there simply are no children under the age of four: they have all died in misery. Millions of children suffer from diseases caused by malnutrition, but there is no medicine and medical care available except that provided by the doctors and nurses of the American Red Cross.</p>
   <p>There is still war in many countries, but when the Great War was over, the Red Cross decided to withdraw from Europe. It gradually restricted its activities, until they have now entirely ceased in Belgium, France, and Italy. In other countries, its work among adults has also been curtailed considerably, but the Red Cross will not and cannot give up its work among the hungry, sick, and fatherless and motherless children in Southern Europe. To cease giving them <pb facs="5423404_4_0273.jpg" n="3"/>food, clothing, and medical care now would be tantamount to sentencing them to death--a slow death from starvation or constant exposure, or perhaps a quick death from pneumonia, digestive disorders, or epidemics.</p>
   <p>The Red Cross will continue this work as long as it has the means with which to do it. It is, therefore, of the utmost importance that everybody send in his membership fee of one dollar or, if he can afford it, one dollar for every member of his family.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
