<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-08">May 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-08">May 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.10......Svenska Glee Klubben (The Swedish Glee Club), 470 LaSalle Avenue.</p>
   <p>Svithiod Singing Society, 120 East Chicago Avenue.</p>
   <p>Fria Svenska Arbets Byran (The Free Swedish Employment Bureau), 78 Dearborn Street, rooms 15 and 17, telephone Central 2687, open every day except holidays from nine A.M. to four P.M. Employers in need of help should kindly apply here.</p>
   <p>For Bundet Gustaf II Adolf (The Gustavus Adolfus II Society) meets at Phoenix Hall, 324 East Division Street, the second and fourth Wednesday, each month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1269.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Foreningen Baltic (The Baltic Society) meets the first and third Tuesday of the month at Masonic Hall, Grand Crossing.</p>
   <p>Independent Order of Vikings, Logen Vikingarne (Viking Lodge) Number One I.O.V. holds a general meeting at Odd Fellows Hall, 120 East Chicago Avenue, the first and third Thursday of each month.</p>
   <p>Foreningen Norden (The North Society) meets at Hopkins Hall, 528 63rd Street, the second and fourth Thursday of each month.</p>
   <p>Forsta Svenska Byggnads-Osch Lane Foreningen (First Swedish Building and Loan Association). Head Office and Meeting Room: 161 Washington Street, room 808. Monthly meetings: the third Monday of each month. Lake View office: 1836 North Clark Street. Open the first and third Thursday evenings. Roseland office: 111045 Michigan Avenue, Roseland. Open the last Wednesday evening of each month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1270.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Foreningen Monitor (The Monitor Society) meets at Mahony Hall, corner of Sixty-third and Halsted Streets, the first and third Wednesday of each month.</p>
   <p>Vikingarnes Gymnastik-Och Fakt Klubb (The Viking Gymnastic and Fencing Club) holds its exercises each Tuedsay and Friday at its club-house, 913 Sheffield Avenue.</p>
   <p>Logen Brage (Brage Lodge) Number Three, I.O.V. holds its general meeting at Phoenix Hall, 324 East Division Street, the second and fourth Thursday of each month.</p>
   <p>Logen Drake (Drake Lodge) Number Three, I.O.V. holds its general meeting at Wells Hall, 1631 North Wells Street, the first and third Thursday of each month.</p>
   <p>Logen Agantyr (Agantyr Lodge) Number Four, I.O.V. holds its general meeting at Wismes Hall, corner of Thirty-fifth and Wood Streets, the first and third Sunday of each month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1271.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Logen Frej (Frej Lodge) Number Five, I.O.V. holds its general meeting at Linnea Hall, corner of Buffalo Avenue and Eighty-eighth Street, the second and fourth Wednesday of each month.</p>
   <p>Logen Frithiof (Frithiof Lodge) Number Six, I.O.V. holds its general meeting at Heim's Hall, corner of Lincoln and Graceland Avenues, the second and fourth Wednesday of each month.</p>
   <p>Logen Runan (Runan Lodge) Number Seven, I.O.V. holds its general meeting at Kerwin's Hall, Southwest corner of Garfield Boulevard and Wentworth Avehue, the second and fourth Thursday of each month.</p>
   <p>Logen Fridhem (Peaceful Home Lodge) Number 360, I.O.G.T. meets at 1748 Diversey Boulevard, each Saturday evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1272.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Logen Hoppets Har (Hope's Host Lodge) Number 441, I.O.G.T. meets at Oakley Hall, 1141 South Oakley Avenue, each Saturday evening.</p>
   <p>Logen Idoghet (Industry Lodge) I.O.G.T. meets at Little Phoenix Hall, 324 East Division Street, at seven-thirty P.M. each Sunday.</p>
   <p>Logen Jupiter (Jupiter Lodge) I.O.G.T. meets at Phoenix Hall, 324 East Division Street, at seven-thirty P.M. each Sunday.</p>
   <p>Logen Kronan (Crown Lodge) Number 832, I.O.G.T. meets each Sunday evening at seven-thirty, Linnea Hall, 8743 Buffalo Avenue, South Chicago.</p>
   <p>Logen Svenskarne I Illinois (Swedes of Illinois Lodge) Number 258, I.O.G.T. meets each Sunday at four P.M. Jaeger Hall, Clybourn Avenue and Larrabbee Street.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1273.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Logen Verdandi (Verdandi Lodge) Number One, I.O.G.T. meets at K. of P. Hall, third floor, Arcade Building, Pullman, each Sunday, four-thirty P.M.</p>
   <p>Norden Athletic Club meets at 958 Belmont Avenue, corner of Southport Avenue, every Tuesday and Friday evening.</p>
   <p>Odin Lodge, Number 103, K. of P. meets at the North Side Turner Hall, North Clark Street, every Tuesday evening.</p>
   <p>Skandinaviska Bagare Foreningen (Scandinavian Baker's Society) Number Sixty-two, I.B.C.U. meets at Hert's Hall, corner of Townsend and Locust Streets, the second and fourth Saturday of each month at seven-thirty P.M.</p>
   <p>Skandinaviska Foreningen Enighet (Scandinavian Unity Society) meets at Ahlgrim's Hall, Twenty-second and Robey Streets, the second and fourth Thursday of each month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1274.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Svenska Amerikanska Gardet (Swedish American Guards) meets at Bromstedt's Hall, corner of Sixty-third and Halsted Streets, every Tuesday evening.</p>
   <p>Foreningen Ingeborg (Swedish Ladies' Society Ingeborg) meets at the South Side Turner Hall, Thirty-first Street, the first and third Wednesday of each month.</p>
   <p>Svenska National Forbundet (Swedish National Society) meets at Seventy-eight Dearborn Street, the first Tuesday of each month.</p>
   <p>Svenska Gymnastik-Och Atlet Klubben (The Swedish Athletic and Gymnastic Club) meets every Tuesday and Friday evening at Columbia Hall, 5326 State Street.</p>
   <p>Svenska Vanner's Sjuk-Forening (Swedish Friends' Sick Benefit Society) meets the second Wednesday of each month at the Swedish Methodist Church, corner of Thirty-third and Fifth Avenue, at eight P. M.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1275.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>I.O.S. Storlogen (I.O.S. Grand Lodge Svithiod) meets jointly the second Wednesday in February, every year. The Grand Lodge's Secretary's Hall at Seventy-three Sedgwick Street is open every Wednesday evening seven to nine P.M.</p>
   <p>Svithiod Logen (Svithiod Lodge) Number One, I.O.S. meets at North Side Turner Hall, every Saturday evening.</p>
   <p>Manhem Logen (Manhem Lodge) Number Two, I.O.S. meets at Waswo Hall, 197 West Division Street, every Thursday evening.</p>
   <p>Verdandi Logen (Verdandi Lodge) Number Three, I.O.S. meets at Wells Hall, 1629 North Clark Street, corner of Fletcher Street, the first and third Saturday of each month.</p>
   <p>Mimer Logen (Mimer Lodge) Number Four, I.O.S. meets at Edgewood Hall, 1930 Milwaukee Avenue, the first and third Thursday of each month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1276.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Frithiof Logen (Frithiof Lodge) Number Five, I.O.U. meets at Leddy's Hall, corner of Wentworth Avenue and Thirty-first Street, the first and third Tuesday of each month, eight P.M.</p>
   <p>Gylfe Logen (Gylfe Lodge) Number Six, I.O.S. meets at Linea Hall, 8743 Buffalo Avenue, the first and third Tuesday of each month.</p>
   <p>Bjorn Logen (Bear Lodge) Number Seven, I.O.S. meets at Wm. Moss Hall, East Chicago, Indiana, the first and third Saturday of each month.</p>
   <p>Ring Logen (Ring Lodge) Number Eight, I.O.S. meets at Phoenix Hall, 324 East Division Street, the first and third Wednesday of each month.</p>
   <p>Hilding Logen (Hilding Lodge) Number Nine, I.O.S. meets at the corner of One-hundred and eleventh Street and Michigan Avenue, every Wednesday evening, eight P.M.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1277.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Odin Logen (Odin Lodge) Number Ten, I.O.S. meets at Odd Fellows Hall, Chicago Street, Joliet, Illinois, the second and fourth Friday, each month.</p>
   <p>Thor Logen (Thor Lodge) Number Eleven, I.O.S. meets at Walter's Hall, Chicago Heights, Illinois, the first and third Wednesday of each month.</p>
   <p>Balder Logen (Balder Lodge) Number Twelve, I.O.S. meets at Fifty-first and Armitage Avenue, Cragin, the second and fourth Thursday of each month.</p>
   <p>Logen Svea (Svea Lodge) Number Fourteen, I.O.S. meets the first and third Friday of each month, eight P.M. at Odd Fellows Hall, corner of One-hundred and nineteenth Street and Wallace, West Pullman.</p>
   <p>Stockholm Logen (Stockholm Lodge) Number Thirteen, I.O.S. meets the second and fourth Wednesday of each month at eight P.M. at Oakley Hall, 1144 South Oakley, Avenue.</p>
   <p>(I.O.V. - Independent Order of Svithiod.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
