<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-10-16">Oct. 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Betsy Ross Chapter No. 1.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-10-16">Oct. 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">BETSY ROSS CHAPTER NO. 1.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.11..............American Sons and Daughters of Sweden - a group of women, who will organize similar chapters throughout the country mainly for educational and social purposes and to further and assist in the celebration of the three-hundred anniversary of the landing of the first Swedes in America in the year 1638 - held its first meeting September 22 at the Swedish Club. Mrs. Frank M. Fulton, president of the Ideal Woman's Club gave a long and interesting lecture, and Mrs. Jennie E. Peterson entertained the large audience with a number of songs. Mrs. Frank Torell from American Sons and Daughters' Head-Office had been invited to give a talk on the large national campaign which again is being pushed in behalf of the Jubilee Fund. Mrs. M. Skoglund was the evening's hostess. Great interest in the work at hand seemed to prevail among those present, who all agreed that something great ought to be accomplished with the whole country for a working field.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1076.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The officers of Betsy Ross Chapter No. 1 are as follows: Mrs. F. T. Westberg, President; Mrs. C. A. Carson, 1st Vice-President; Mrs. A. Nelson, 2nd Vice-President; Mrs. C. G. Wallenius, 3rd Vice-President; Mrs. J. C. Mathieson, Recording Secretary; Carl Highfield, Treasurer; Mrs. C. O. Beroth, Assistant Treasurer; Mrs. Hjalmar Lundquist, Corresponding Secretary; Mrs. Gustaf Holmquist, Assistant Corresponding Secretary; Mrs. C. E. Hoffsten, Historian.</p>
   <p>As directors, the following ladies were elected: Mrs. C. Gustafson, Mrs. M. N. Gustafson, Mrs. O. Osterholm, Mrs. John E. Ericsson, Mrs. Peter Peterson, Mrs. Frank Nordquist and Mr. John M. Westerlin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
