<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-08-14">Aug. 14, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Ingratitude Is Our Reward</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-08-14">Aug. 14, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">INGRATITUDE IS OUR REWARD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The chairman of the board of governors, of the American Sons and Daughters of Sweden was interviewed by a Stockholm reporter during a recent visit to the Swedish capital.</p>
   <p>During this interview he stated, among other things, that Swedish prestige in America has been rising considerably during the last few years, and that this happy condition is due chiefly to the activities of the above-mentioned organization.</p>
   <p>Surely, no Swedish-American will begrudge the Society the pleasure which such an assumption--however silly it may be--may give its leaders. But as a basis for it, the chairman pointed out that one of the purposes of the organization is to stand watch over the political interests of Swedish-Americans. He went <pb facs="5423404_4_1070.jpg" n="2"/>on to say that the Swedish-American press does not exert any appreciable influence in that respect.</p>
   <p>That the society is acting as a watchdog over our political interests certainly is news to most of us Swedish-Americans. What fools we have been, imagining that the society's interests are strictly of a cultural nature! Not even Swedish-American newspapers, which gladly, and without any thought of compensation, have given space to the society's lengthy expositions on cultural questions, suspected such a thing. If they had known, they certainly would not have been so generous with their support.</p>
   <p>In national politics the influence of Swedish-American newspapers is not great, and they themselves are the first to admit the fact. The chief reason for this is that the people of Swedish nationality constitute only a small part of the country's population. However, in localities where many Swedes are concentrated the influence of their press is not inconsiderable. But what kind of political influence can the Sons and Daughters of Sweden have with their <pb facs="5423404_4_1071.jpg" n="3"/>twenty-four thousand members, distributed throughout the country? Practically none compared with many a Swedish-language newspaper which has more than twice as many subscribers as the organization has members.</p>
   <p>The chairman's statement that half of the society's membership does not understand Swedish, must be accepted. We think it is a deplorable state of affairs. He also declared that he expected the membership to reach one hundred thousand before the end of 1938. He must know that if his hopes are to be realized the society must in the future, as in the past, seek its recruits among the hundreds of thousands of readers of Swedish-American newspapers, the great majority of whom are not green immigrants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
