<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1909-10-21">Oct. 21, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Laying the Corner-Stone</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1909-10-21">Oct. 21, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">LAYING THE CORNER-STONE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday afternoon the corner-stone of the Viking Temple was laid. The temple is the first one to be erected in America by the Viking Order. It will be built on the Southwest corner of Sheffield Avenue and School Street. At 2 P.M. there were about 2,000 Vikings assembled in Clifton Hall. Led by the two Viking bands, they marched through the most prominent streets of Lake View to the place where the corner-stone was to be laid. Here about 3,000 Swedes, men and women, were waiting to witness the ceremony. Dozens of American and Swedish people joined the crowd to hear tunes of the foster land. The Harmony Choir under the direction of Tom Dahlen thrilled the throngs with its splendid performance. Vice Chairman A. W. Johnson introduced Chairman Frithiof Malquist, who made a short speech emphasizing the significance of the event and then laid the corner-stone. The main address was delivered by Herman Lindsborg. The parade was the most impressive one held by any national group in Lake View. The Vikings of the city and other places were strongly represented. The building will cost $55,000 when completed. The plans were drawn by <pb facs="5423404_4_1175.jpg" n="2"/>a member of the Order, the well-known architect Andrew E. Norman. He will also supervise the construction. The contractors are all Swedish. We mention Plantin, Soderstrom, Colberg, Ekrman, Carlson, Nordberg and Nelson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
