<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-06-27">June 27, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Real Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0756</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0756.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-06-27">June 27, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">REAL ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past week, sixty-six real estate transfers took place in which the buyer, the seller, or both were Scandinavians. The list follows:</p>
   <p>J. W. Forsberg to Fidel Forstnegger, Fifth Avenue, south of 32nd Street. Price, $5,600.</p>
   <p>M. A. Hoagland to George W. Merchant, Oakwood Boulevard, east of Lake Avenue. Price, $5,000.</p>
   <p>B. J. Anderson to Edward Guihlein, Western Avenue, corner of Frankfort Street. Price, $5,700.</p>
   <p>C. Lindell to Henry C. Keiller, Winthrop Avenue, corner of Ainsley Street. Price, $2,100.</p>
   <p>C. Lundquist to W. H. Giesecke, Harding Avenue, north of Diversey Avenue. Price, $1,200.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0757.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>George W. Michael to John M. Carlson, Morse Avenue, corner of E. Ravenswood Park. Price, $1,500.</p>
   <p>C. A. Anderson to Henry A. Hanson, Courtland Street, east of Lawndale Avenue. Price, $3,200.</p>
   <p>F. Wiegsman to Anna Carlson, Clark Street, north of Foster Avenue. Price, $1,100.</p>
   <p>John E. Eberhardt to John M. Westerlin, Wellington Street, east of Blucher Street. Price, $15,000.</p>
   <p>H. Jacobson to John Boda, Austin Avenue, west of Elizabeth Street. Price $3,000.</p>
   <p>O. Nelson to George A. Darwell, Campbell Avenue, south of Franklin Avenue. Price, $5,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0758.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A. Peterson to H. D. Peterson, 15th Street, west of Albany Avenue. Price, $1,500.</p>
   <p>O. Johnson to Christine Rohn, Francisco Avenue, north of Thomas Street. Price, $4,150.</p>
   <p>G. Gettelson to Carl A. Carlson, Magnolia Avenue, north of Francisco Avenue. Price, $2,550.</p>
   <p>Louise N. Anderson to Peter Reder, Peoria Street, corner of Canalport Avenue. Price, $31,468.</p>
   <p>B. Anderson to Lillian L. Olson, Curtis Avenue, north of 110th Street. Price, $1,100.</p>
   <p>G. Johnson to Gustav W. Lundin, May Street, north of 58th Street. Price, $2,200.</p>
   <p>J. E. Olander to Henry Schuman, Pleasant Street, south of Vedder Street. Price, $1.00.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0759.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>C. Anderson to Carl Lundberg, Green Street, south of 59th Street. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>C. N. Johnson to Charles W. Rankin, Sheridan Road, corner of Morse Avenue. Price, $7,500.</p>
   <p>C. W. Rankin to William R. Linn, Sheridan Road, north of Lunt Avenue. Price, $3,250.</p>
   <p>William R. Linn to Charles N. Johnson, Sheridan Road, corner of Glenlake Avenue. Price, $12,500.</p>
   <p>C. A. Hitchcock to Hilda N. Johnson, lot 31, 29th Street. Price, $3,600.</p>
   <p>S. M. Gunderson to James W. Morris, Lexington Street, east of South 44th Avenue. Price, $3,500.</p>
   <p>A. H. Klicka to Eric A. Larson, Monticello Avenue, south of North Avenue. Price, $4,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0760.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>H. Johnson to S. Johnson, Sangamon Street, north of 14th Street. Price, $3,250.</p>
   <p>A. Carlson to F. A. Winkofski, 25th Street, west of South 43rd Street. Price, $2,525.</p>
   <p>Thuber Bergman to Arthur G. Bergman, Dakin Street, corner of Rokeby Street. Price, $16,000.</p>
   <p>B. M. Lange to Augusta M. Ohlson, Winthrop Avenue, south of Balmoral Avenue. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>Victor Lindstrom to Otto L. Nordberg, 51st Street, west of Union Avenue. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Adolph Lindgren to Marie L. Dangremond, Union Avenue, corner of 72nd Street. Price, $13,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0761.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>O. H. Johnson to Ferdinand Morose, Robey Street, north of 37th Street. Price, $1,550.</p>
   <p>S. E. Russel to Amy C. L. Matson, Avenue H., corner of 98th Street. Price, $1,174.</p>
   <p>L. C. Vanuxem to Anna O. Johnson, Wayne Avenue, north of Berwyn Avenue. Price, $1,235.</p>
   <p>J. A. Carlson to August Lind, Sophia Street, east of Franklin Avenue. Price, $3,550.</p>
   <p>S. A. Washburn to John T. Peterson, Jasper Street, corner of Pine Avenue. Price, $1,100.</p>
   <p>Louis Hammarlund to E. G. Pauling, Campbell Avenue, corner of La Moyne Street. Price, $10,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0762.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>C. Alexander to Selma Anderson, Roscoe Street, west of Evanston Avenue. Price, $1,000.</p>
   <p>S. M. Gunderson to Bertha I. Watts, Colorado Avenue, corner of South 41st Court. Price, $4,000.</p>
   <p>P. J. M. Teussamt to Ole A. Nelson, North 43rd Court, north of Hirsch Street. Price, $1,470.</p>
   <p>Wm. H. Barry to August Peterson, Racine Avenue, south of Wilson Avenue. Price, $14,000.</p>
   <p>J. L. Cochran to Nels M. Lorentz, Wayne Avenue, north of Balmoral Avenue. Price, $6,000.</p>
   <p>W. Hammarstrom to Susan P. Heath, Burling Street, south of Webster Avenue. Price, $3,050.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0763.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>C. S. Peterson to Charles Krueger, Cleveland Avenue, south of Center Street. Price, $5,850.</p>
   <p>George A. Neeb to John S. Ahlgren, Star Avenue, corner of 64th Street. Price, $5,750.</p>
   <p>R. Sulecki to August T. Vidlund, Marshfield Avenue, south of 51st Street. Price, $4,500.</p>
   <p>H. J. Wallingford to Carl O. Carlson, Foster Avenue, west of Southport Avenue. Price, $1,133.</p>
   <p>C. Bostrom to Laura E. Hutchey, Lakewood Avenue, corner of Balmoral Avenue. Price, $7,044.</p>
   <p>Seaverus Elevator Company to Abraham Nelson, Fullerton Avenue, west of California Avenue. Price, $1,250.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0764.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>C. J. Rosen to Marie Anderson, Carpenter Street, north of 60th Street. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>H. T. Parker to Oscar Carlson, Center Avenue, south of 60th Street. Price, $1,600.</p>
   <p>Peter Eck to John W. Akerberg, Elizabeth Street, south of 69th Street. Price, $0.35.</p>
   <p>L. S. Peterson to John F. Winter, Gladys Avenue, east of South 44th Avenue. Price, $5,250.</p>
   <p>O. W. Anderson to Bertha M. Burell, Noble Avenue, corner of Kimball Avenue. Price, $4,500.</p>
   <p>M. Hanbold to Wilhelm F. Christianson, Churchill Street, west of Robey Street. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0765.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>S. X. Pearson to John Oman, Indiana Avenue, north of 112th Street. Price, $1,300.</p>
   <p>L. C. Vanuxem's estate to Charles Bostrom, Wayne Avenue, north of Claremont Avenue. Price, $2,730.</p>
   <p>E. Swanson to Barbara Giezen, Clarendon Avenue, south of Irving Park Avenue. Price, $6,500.</p>
   <p>H. C. Larson to William Jordan, Claremont Avenue, north of School Street. Price, $1,800.</p>
   <p>S. O. Olin to Salvatore Russo, Chicago Avenue, corner of Milton Avenue. Price, $7,500.</p>
   <p>E. S. Cummings to Charles A. Lundstrom, Fullerton Avenue, west of Sacramento Avenue. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0766.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>G. Christian to John A. Lundin, Harding Avenue, corner of 29th Street. Price, $1,650.</p>
   <p>F. E. Bigelow to Carl A. Lundquist, Maple Square Avenue, north of Waveland Avenue. Price, $1,425.</p>
   <p>Alma M. Olson to Lizette S. Gunther, Wellington Avenue, west of Dayton Street. Price, $6,000.</p>
   <p>M. McGloue to Carl F. Bjorn, Union Avenue, south of 34th Street. Price, $2,500.</p>
   <p>A. Pearson to Nels H. Gulstrand, Evanston Avenue, south of Foster Avenue. Price, $2,800.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
