<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-03-12">March 12, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Englewood Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-03-12">March 12, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">ENGLEWOOD HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is now one year and a half since the Swedish-American Hospital Society purchased and took charge of the "Englewood Union Hospital." Sometime before this the "Swedish American Hospital Association" which is its lawful name purchased a lot on the corner of 60th and Green Streets with 110 feet frontage. And so on the corner of 60th and Green Streets the past year a massive fireproof five story building fifty feet wide 100 feet long has been erected; the corner stone was layed December 31, 1905 by President A. P. Fors,Pastor of the Swedish Bethel Lutheran Church of Englewood. The well-known architect L. G. Hallberg drew the plans, and the building was erected by the E. P. Strandberg Company. They have just completed the building and it is now ready for occupancy. The building's cost was $900. The management believes that the Swedish men of affairs who made this undertaking possible have for this generation built a monument which shows Swedish foresight. This light and airy pleasant building has room for 125 patients. There are no large wards, only six or seven persons to the ward besides large rooms for two or three patients. It also contains elegant private rooms, as well as maternity wards. For emergency cases one <pb facs="5423404_4_0040.jpg" n="2"/>finds well arranged operating rooms. For all operations we find on the fifth floor all modern arrangements in two large light operating rooms which are equal to the best in Chicago. Here fifteen operation are performed per day.</p>
   <p>Since February 14, 1907 when the new building was taken in use, twice as many patients have been taken in as before. Among the nurses we find eight Swedish and also some of other nationalities. The supervisor Miss Emelia Dahlgren and her assistant Miss Rebecka Johnson graduated from the Augustana Hospital which we know has a good reputation.</p>
   <p>The Swedish-American Hospital Society held their second annual meeting in their own local assembly room, which has been elegantly furnished by the doctors. At this meeting all the members of the management were present, and all were satisfied with the arrangements, as were also the directors. The following named are the directors: A. P. Fors, A. L. Nystrom, Fred Westberg, Senator Carl Lundlurg, Wm. J. Rathje, W. A. Nelson, N. P. Severin, Robert Anderson, H. C. Staves, H. F. Edman and J. A. Fraeger.</p>
   <p>The hospital is already more than half filled and we hope to attract the patronage <pb facs="5423404_4_0041.jpg" n="3"/>of the Englewood people. A great deal of good has been done at the old hospital and also since the Swedish society has taken it over. Now in the new, modern building we sincerely believe greater blessings will be accomplished. It is only one year ago that 315 Swedish women from the Linea Society organized for the purpose of giving their time to aid the poor. Mrs. C. A. Valentine was the organizer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
