<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-09-03">Sept. 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Crime and the Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0403</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0403.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-09-03">Sept. 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">CRIME AND THE PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This newspaper has pointed out time and again that the daily press carries a large portion of the responsibility for the increase in crime among the young people of this city. If, for instance, a young woman has committed a particularly interesting murder, she is usually described by a certain type of newspaper as "the young beauty" or in some other complimentary terms, and an effort is made to present the crime in a romantic setting. This is, of course, done in order to arouse the interest of the reader.</p>
   <p>It is easy to observe that this kind of reporting on murder and other crimes is widely read. Watch the young boys and girls traveling on the streetcars and the elevated trains and you will see that the majority of them are immersed in the reading of an article describing some murder or other vicious crime. The same kind of reading is also popular in the home. Even the newsboys know <pb facs="5423404_4_0404.jpg" n="2"/>how to exploit the public's taste for soul-stirring descriptions of violent crimes, and as soon as the papers are on the street one may hear them all over the city yelling at the top of their voice, "Read all about the sensational murder on the South Side!"--or the West Side, or the North Side, or the Loop, as the case may be.</p>
   <p>Of late, however, so many outrageous crimes have been committed that even the most case-hardened reporters are becoming ill at ease, and when it was revealed last week that two youths, still in their teens,had confessed to the exceptionally brutal murder of a woman, one of the city's morning papers editorially urged parents and educators to take notice of this serious situation, and to take counter measures against the tendency toward crime among the younger generation.</p>
   <p>Such a warning certainly is timely, for never before has the moral training of children and young people been as neglected as it is now. But before preaching to others, one should put one's own house in order. The principal purpose <pb facs="5423404_4_0405.jpg" n="3"/>of a metropolitan daily is to disseminate news, and this news should be based on plain facts, presented in such a manner as to be of constructive and educational value instead of being actually demoralizing.</p>
   <p>The power and responsibility of the daily press are great, greater now than ever before, for not only are newspapers becoming more and more widely read but the majority of people, we are sorry to say, hardly read anything else.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
