<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-12-10">Dec. 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Meeting</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-12-10">Dec. 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AN IMPORTANT MEETING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Vasa lodges of Chicago held a joint meeting last Saturday for the purpose of discussing the organization of a children's club of the same kind that was established years ago by the New York lodges. It will be remembered that in that city Dr. and Mrs. Johannes Hoving have been the leaders in this work among the children, and also were in charge when the club made a very successful excursion to Sweden last summer.</p>
   <p>At this writing, no announcement has been made, and we do not know the result of Saturday's meeting, but we hope that it was fruitful, and that at least a beginning was made which will lead to an organized effort in this important field. Such an activity as this, even though it be undertaken on a modest scale to start with, is in complete harmony with the program and principles <pb facs="5423404_4_1578.jpg" n="2"/>of the Svithiod Order. For its aim is not only to build up a strong sick benefit organization, but also to preserve and strengthen the best in the Swedish national character, and that which is typical of it, so that it may reach "the highest possible degree of usefulness to America," as one prominent Swedish-American once expressed it. And it is obvious that, if we are to cultivate in the New World the qualities that are typically Swedish, we must make an effort to reach the children of the immigrants, the second generation. This reasoning led to the founding of the first children's club in the East.</p>
   <p>Those members of Chicago's Vasa lodges who have children of school age have, we presume, already been approached and asked to encourage their young ones to join such a children's club, unless distance or other obstacles should make membership unfeasible. We will therefore refrain from any additional urging at this time. But we do want to say that the time for establishing a children's club is well chosen. Christmas, the children's holiday, is approaching, and we Swedish-Americans know that our children are more eager at <pb facs="5423404_4_1579.jpg" n="3"/>Christmas time to learn about the old country and life there than at any other time of the year.</p>
   <p>Those parents are wise who at this season seek to acquaint their boys and girls with the Swedish language, history, and culture. This may well be done in a children's club, but it should also be done in the home. Nothing so strengthens the ties between parents and their children as for the latter to learn about the childhood of their mother and father. And an understanding of life in Sweden and of its people is sure to enrich their lives, both today and tomorrow, and will serve as a ballast when the sailing is rough.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
