<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-04-04">Apr. 4, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Employment Bureaus Again</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) Galeton, Pa., March 20, 1905.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-04-04">Apr. 4, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE EMPLOYMENT BUREAUS AGAIN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) Galeton, Pa., March 20, 1905.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of Svenska Nyheter:</p>
   <p>I beg to inquire whether there are any employment bureaus that are sending workers West to California or to Washington, and whether, in such cases, the workers receive free travel to those places.</p>
   <p>Subscriber.</p>
   <p>We received the above letter from one of the Svenska Nyheter's subscribers in the East, and we might of course have replied in a private letter, but since we know definitely that many others have the same question on their <pb facs="5423404_4_0229.jpg" n="2"/>tongues and we believe that they all may benefit by our answer, we prefer to reply through the paper in the present case, presenting our reasons for our readers' benefit.</p>
   <p>Yes, sadly to say, there are employment bureaus that will send workers to California or to Washington (or which at least claim to be sending them to those Western States), but it would be safer to lie down to sleep in a snake's nest than to put one's self in the hands of those bureaus.</p>
   <p>California and Washington are well supplied with workers, and for this reason the employers there, naturally do not need to get workers from Chicago, paying large sums for traveling expenses. The only employers who could, without great monetary loss, import workers from Chicago are the railroad corporations, but even they would naturally hold back as long as they can get their workers at as low a rate out West as from Chicago. On occasions <pb facs="5423404_4_0230.jpg" n="3"/>there have been requests for workers to labor for the railroads in the West, but in every such case something sinister has been the reason. Either a strike has broken loose among the poorly paid workers of the corporations in question, or else the managers of the corporations fear a strike as a result of their having cut the wages of their men. In such cases workers are sought from all over the country. Every inducement is offered, free travel to the place of work included, and soon the required number of men are there ready to work. For a couple of weeks the newly arrived workers may have reason to praise their new jobs, but rarely longer. Very soon the position of the new workers is just as odious as that of the men who went on strike two weeks ago. If any individual among the men complains, he is discharged and left to join the great crowd of unemployed. If the men as a group demand improvements of some kind, the employment bureaus in the large cities receive orders for some <pb facs="5423404_4_0231.jpg" n="4"/>hundreds of additional workers. These latter arrive, but they find no work as long as the old workers have not left their jobs. Thus, at every place of industrial endeavor of any consequence, an army of jobless gather, the presence of which acts as a brake on the demands for improvements by those at work.</p>
   <p>At the employment offices in Chicago it is always claimed that a large number of positions are available. Were a man to seek a position as superintendent of the diamond mines in South Africa, or as gatekeeper in Heaven, or as fireman in Hell, the agent at the employment bureau would be likely to claim that he had these places to fill - for a cash fee.</p>
   <p>Our friend, the letter writer in the East, is sure to get a (promise of) position in California with a (promise of) free trip out there, if he is <pb facs="5423404_4_0232.jpg" n="5"/>still the owner of two dollars to pay the employment bureau. When he has been waiting a couple of months for the promises to be fulfilled he may be informed, perhaps, that for an additional fee of two dollars he may obtain an equally excellent position in Washington.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
