<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-06-12">June 12, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Flag Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1324</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1324.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-06-12">June 12, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">FLAG DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Flag Association, an organization founded in 1897 by nationalistic societies of all kinds, has sent a proclamation to the American people to decorate, the day after tomorrow, June 14, all public buildings, and as many individual houses as possible, with the American Flag.</p>
   <p>It is expected that civil authorities, teachers, and influential citizens will do their best to make this comparatively new holiday as widely and solemnly celebrated as possible, particularly since this Flag Day will be the first for the present century.</p>
   <p>The fourteenth of June is to be marked in this way, as our readers possibly know, because it was on the fourteenth of June, 1777, that Congress decided that the Flag of the United States should consist of thirteen alternate red and white stripes, and, in the left-hand corner (that is, in the upper corner nearest the staff), thirteen white stars on a blue field. Through a new Congressional resolution, dated the fourth of April, 1818, it was ordained <pb facs="5423404_4_1325.jpg" n="2"/>that, beginning the next July 4, the Flag of the United States should consist of thirteen alternate red and white stripes, with twenty white stars in a blue field, and should always, after a new state had been received into the Union, add yet another star, the addition of this new star to be made on the July Fourth following the admission of the state. In accordance with this law, twenty-five new stars have since been added, and in all likelihood, within a few years, the total will be increased to forty-eight, since New Mexico, Arizona, and Oklahoma also now seek to be received as states. Whether or not, later on, even Alaska, Hawaii, Porto Rico and the Philippines will be represented by additional stars on the flag is a question which we must needs leave to the future to answer.</p>
   <p>Whether or not Flag Day will be always celebrated as a national holiday is still said to be doubted. Many seem to think that three such holidays during the short time of five weeks--the thirtieth of May, the fourteenth of June, and the fourth of July--are almost too many, but on the other side it can be said that just at this time of the year, the most beautiful period of spring and early summer, the people not only have more time for, but even <pb facs="5423404_4_1326.jpg" n="3"/>more need for, holiday celebrations. In any case, we hope that this year, everyone who can do so will on the proper day hoist the Star-Spangled Banner, and in his heart exult over the freedom, greatness, and power of which it now, more than ever, constitutes the beautiful symbol.</p>
   <p>Long may the Star-Spangled Banner wave over our homes and those of our children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
