<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-06-06">June 6, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Quota Law</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-06-06">June 6, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE QUOTA LAW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As is generally known, the purpose of our present immigration restrictions is to limit the number of immigrants from southern and eastern Europe, and, at the same time, to encourage immigration from northwestern Europe. When the Dillingham Law, as it is called, was adopted, nobody suspected that its provisions might also prevent the most desirable immigrants from entering the country. Emigration from the northern and western countries of Europe had for several years been so low that it was not considered likely that their annual quotas would ever be filled. But that is exactly what is happening. England, Scotland, Wales, and Ireland have already exhausted their quotas, and Sweden's quota is nearly filled. If emigration from Germany continues at its present rate, its quota will also be filled during the next fiscal year. The law thus seems to have had a more far-reaching effect than was originally intended.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1618.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Congress and the nation at large do not desire to admit an unlimited number of people from southeastern Europe; but they do desire to admit as many as possible from the rest of the continent, because the latter are needed to cultivate the land and to reinforce the western European human stock which is already here. But so far, no member of Congress claims to have a solution for the problem of how to keep out what is considered the less desirable immigrants and at the same time admit those whom we really want and need.</p>
   <p>However, the present law has functioned smoothly, and it may not become necessary to change it, as has been suggested. As conditions in Europe improve, the number of emigrants is likely to decline. Up to now, the Dillingham Law has prevented only a few of the more desirable immigrants from landing here, while it has protected the country against the flood of hundreds of thousands of others who would otherwise have poured into our large cities, overcrowding the slums we already have, and creating new ones.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
