<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1919-02-13">Feb. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Viking Order Storting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1919-02-13">Feb. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">VIKING ORDER STORTING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Storting (Diet) of the Independent Order of Vikings convened on February 7, and continued until last Saturday. It was held at the Viking Temple, Sheffield Avenue and School Street. The fifty-six Fylken (petty kingdoms) from various sections of the country were represented by more than one hundred delegates. They were led by the Grand-Chief of the order, Mr. Arvid Benson.</p>
   <p>The Order has, as mentioned above, fifty-six petty kingdoms, and these petty kingdoms have regional rights in the following states: Illinois, Indiana, Wisconsin, Nebraska, and Minnesota. It has a total of 8,351 members. Beginning this year, new petty kingdoms are to be organized in Michigan, where so many descendants of the northern vikings live and build.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1344.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The treasury which in the beginning of 1918 amounted to $152,452.45, increased $19,688.69, which made a total of $172,141.14. The treasuries of the subordinate lodge had increased $4,007.78, during the year, which made a total of $97,462.98. In the report given to us by the secretary in chief, among other things we read the following: "It is with satisfaction that I dwell upon the financial status of the Order, which of course, is really the foundation upon which we build. July 1, 1918, should be considered a day to be remembered, for on that day our organization became one hundred per cent solvent. This means we had attained that financial status which every organization should have, before its members may feel fully secure. I should like to point out the fact that there are very few organizations that have attained this position. Therefore, it is so much more to our credit that we, as a comparatively small organization, and with a very limited field in which to work, have reached this status. We especially deserve credit because this has been done during a period in <pb facs="5423404_4_1345.jpg" n="3"/>which other organizations had to levy extra assessments on their members in order to maintain more or less, the same position they occupied at the beginning of the year. Because of the epidemic which has raged during the past months, the morality percentage has more than doubled that of a normal year. According to the "National Fraternal Congress Table of Mortality," when we usually had forty-eight deaths, we now have one hundred and six. In spite of this, the assurance and reserve funds of the Order have increased almost $20,000. That under such circumstances it has been practically impossible to organize new lodges, and to take in a great number of new members, should be clear to each and everyone. "Therefore, the executive committee has not made any great efforts in that direction. On August 19, the Order was granted the right to organize in the state of Michigan and it was intended to organize a few lodges there some time last autumn. Because of the influenza epidemic these plans were disrupted and it was thought best to await a more favorable opportunity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1346.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Many of the lodges have worked hard to increase their memberships during the year, especially the latter part, and they have succeeded exceptionally well. Others again, have failed, but perhaps this is a result of the fact that so many of their best and most active members have been away and could not participate in the work. In any event, the majority have done unusually well in preserving their membership. Therefore, today the Order has over 300 more members in good standing than it did a year ago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
