<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-06-14">June 14, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The National League</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-06-14">June 14, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE NATIONAL LEAGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten years ago the Swedish National League was organized in Chicago, and there are many reasons why we consider it both a pleasure and a duty to point out some of the important and beneficial activities in which the League has been engaged during this last decade.</p>
   <p>It grew from the committee which early in 1894 was appointed for the purpose of bringing to justice the two police officers who on Christmas eve, 1893, shot and killed a Swede by the name of Swan Nelson. Already before this purpose was accomplished, the members of the committee organized the Swedish National League, which took over the committee's work and completed it to the full satisfaction of the Swedish-American public. The trial cost the so-called Swan Nelson Committee and the National League close to eight thousand dollars, and this sum was obtained partly from the proceeds of entertainments of various kinds, <pb facs="5423404_4_0206.jpg" n="2"/>partly through voluntary donations by poor but determined Swedish-Americans.</p>
   <p>When the trial was over, Chicago's Swedes were justly proud of a job well done, and the American press gave them credit for having accomplished what had never been done before--bringing about the conviction of two Irish police officers charged with murder, but acquitted at the first trial. At the second trial they were found guilty and sentenced to fourteen years in the penitentiary. The newspapers were jubilant, and from then on the League's future was assured.</p>
   <p>During the ten years of its existence, the League has taken a hand in two other somewhat similar cases. One was the trial of Anton Nelson, charged with having caused the death of a young man. Aided by its attorneys, G. Bernhard Anderson and O. C. Peterson, the League succeeded in obtaining his acquittal. The other is the so-called Nordgren case. John Nordgren has been found guilty of murdering his wife and sentenced to fourteen years in prison. But the League has come to his aid, and <pb facs="5423404_4_0207.jpg" n="3"/>is trying to obtain a new trial, since there is reason to believe that he is innocent of this crime, and that his conviction was due to the incompetence of his lawyer.</p>
   <p>Already early in its existence, the leaders of this organization, which then as now consisted of representatives from Swedish societies in Chicago, realized the desirability, even necessity, of a free employment service through which Swedish men and women might obtain jobs. Again it was up to the League, which tackled the problem with energy and enthusiasm. The undertaking involved a considerable risk, since it was necessary to rent a centrally located office and hire a manager, which requires cash. The League's bank account, like that of all benevolent societies, was low. However, those of the members who had a little money came to its aid; the employment service was established, and within a short time it prospered. It has been a blessing to thousands of our countrymen and women.</p>
   <p>Swedish immigrants arrived here without knowing the language and unfamiliar <pb facs="5423404_4_0208.jpg" n="4"/>with American working methods. Times were what we consider bad, and jobs scarce. Here and there "slave traders" (we call them so because this type of employment agencies, remaining outside of the jurisdiction of the state, accept the customer's money on the promise of furnishing a job without delivering) had pitched their tents, conniving with the large employers, particularly the railroad companies, concerning with the large employers, particularly the railroad companies, concerning the amount and price of the "merchandise" they were to deliver. A worker who could produce a couple of dollars would gladly lay them down, hoping that they would buy a job, but as a rule they bought only disappointment.</p>
   <p>The Swedish Free Employment Agency fought bitterly against these racketeers, and with considerable success. Gradually the employers came to realize that this agency could and did give them better service than any other; requests for Swedish workers increased rapidly from farmers, manufacturers, wholesalers, railroads, etc., and today it enjoys an enviable reputation for efficiency and fair dealing. During last April and May it placed <pb facs="5423404_4_0209.jpg" n="5"/>857 persons--568 men and 289 women.</p>
   <p>During all these years Mrs. Othelia Myhrman has been the manager of the agency. She has been reappointed repeatedly to the position by the board of directors, and to her should go the lion's share of the credit for its success.</p>
   <p>It is true, particularly in a city like Chicago, with two million inhabitants, that "the poor are always with us," and a considerable number of the city's 130,000 Swedes belong to this category, depending to a large extent on the kindness and help of others. Sickness, suffering, and discouragement are frequent guests in their homes. The helping hand of the Swedish National League also reaches this section of our people. One cannot count how many sighs have been transformed into smiles, how many hungry mouths fed, or how many unhappy hearts comforted by the League's permanent relief committee during the past ten years. Some twenty-eight thousand dollars has been distributed among needy Swedish families, and in addition to that, assistance of various kinds, worth <pb facs="5423404_4_0210.jpg" n="6"/>many times as much, has been rendered. We will only mention the many sick and poor people for whom reduced rates have been obtained on railways and ocean liners, and the many incurables who have been placed in homes and sanitariums. Only one who has been following the League's activities through the years can fully appreciate the value of its work.</p>
   <p>The uninitiated may ask where the money for all these charitable activities comes from, inasmuch as no reimbursement is asked for or accepted from those who have received aid in any form. Likely as not, the questioner himself has made his contribution. Everyone who attends affairs arranged by the League is helping in its work. If you attend one of its concerts in the Auditorium, or if you go on one of its picnics during the summer, then you are helping to make it what it is--the greatest Swedish organization in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
