<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-11-05">Nov. 5, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Many Countrymen in Chicago Are Cold and Hungry</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Appeal for Help from the Swedish Relief Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0247</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0247.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-11-05">Nov. 5, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MANY COUNTRYMEN IN CHICAGO ARE COLD AND HUNGRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">An Appeal for Help from the Swedish Relief Committee</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Unemployment, which became very extensive during the summer, has caused many Swedes to be in great need of the necessities of life. Now that winter is approaching their suffering will reach the limit of endurance if charitable people do not extend a helping hand. The savings which they managed to put away when times were good are now gone and many families have reached the point where their members are starving. As the cold season approaches their plight is bound to become worse, especially in families where there are many children. A great many unemployed single men are also destitute, without a home and lacking proper clothing and food. It is difficult for them to get help anywhere, for welfare agencies are primarily concerned with families where there are children and old people.</p>
   <p>When conditions have reached this critical point now, when the warmth <pb facs="5423404_4_0248.jpg" n="2"/>of summer is still lingering, what may be expected during the long, cold winter months, when buildings have to be heated, and the homeless men can no longer sleep under bridges, in the parks, or in such shelters as they are able to find during the summer? Many a young Swede and many a Swedish child may be ruined for life and die a premature death due to privations which they are suffering now, and will have to go through during the coming winter.</p>
   <p>In view of this situation, representatives of Swedish organizations in Chicago met Friday, October 24, and decided to form a relief organization under the name of the Swedish-American Relief Committee, for the purpose of collecting funds, food and clothing for our destitute countrymen. This committee represents three great welfare organizations, namely the newly formed Swedish Church Federation, the Scandinavian department of the Salvation Army, and the Swedish National Association. The latter represents a large number of sick benefit societies. These welfare organizations are to continue their individual activities as usual, and the newly formed <pb facs="5423404_4_0249.jpg" n="3"/>relief committee will operate as a clearing house for relief work among needy Swedes. In order to execute this task effectively it needs the support of the public, and we herewith address Chicago's Swedes, individuals as well as organizations, urging them to help us in our work. Remember that the great majority of these unfortunates are good men and women who under normal conditions are well able to take care of themselves, and constitute a group which ordinarily is a credit to our nationality. But they are now victims of circumstances over which they have no control. Their very existence is at stake and help must be forthcoming immediately.</p>
   <p>Cash contributions, large or small, should be sent directly to the treasurer of the Relief Committee, Henry S. Henschen, president of the Chicago Bank of Commerce, 7 South Dearborn Street, Chicago, Illinois. The Swedish National Association, whose headquarters are located at 3213 Wilton Avenue, and the various Scandinavian units of the Salvation Army will receive clothing, which is greatly needed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0250.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hoping that all Chicago Swedes who are in a position to do so, will comply with this appeal and give generously to their countrymen who are in distress we remain,</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>The Swedish-American Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>Signed: Herbert Hedman, chairman</p>
   <p>J. Mozart, secretary</p>
   <p>H. S. Henschen, treasurer.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: These three names are followed by twenty-seven other signatures, and under the separate heading "Finance Committee" there are forty more.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
