<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-08-01">Aug. 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate Transactions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0732</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0732.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-08-01">Aug. 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Twenty-three real-estate transfers took place in Chicago last week, in which the buyer, the seller, or both, were Scandinavians, as follows:</p>
   <p>A. Lansing to Andreas P. Anderson, Winthrop Avenue, south of Lawrence Avenue. Price, $7,700.</p>
   <p>Peter M. Peterson to Fred Wolz, Commercial Avenue, corner of 97th Street. Price, $8,000.</p>
   <p>C. Anderson to Sweet J. Regue, 40th Avenue, north of Cortland Street. Price, $3,500.</p>
   <p>Charles Busche to Carl O. Pearson, Ridgeway Avenue, south of Cortland Street. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0733.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>H.S. Saxe to Ella G. Anderson, 45th Place, east of Union Avenue. Price,$1,500.</p>
   <p>A.P. Lindholm to Charles Lindgren, Indiana Street, east of North 48th Avenue. Price, $2,500.</p>
   <p>N.G. Johnson to Emma Westelius, Cleveland Avenue, south of Blackhawk Street. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>John P.Larson to Gebbardt W. Zeiger, Sedgwick Street, north of Webster Avenue. Price,$25,000.</p>
   <p>German Evangelical Lutheran St.Lucas Church to Carl A. and Elsa Lundquist, Diversey Street, east of Southport Avenue. Price, $1,800.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0734.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>George O. Gordon to John Larson, Pine Grove Avenue, north of Addison Street. Price, $10.</p>
   <p>Christina Johnson to Frank and Katharina Swift, Peoria Street, north of 60th Street. $4,500.</p>
   <p>August Benson to James and Margareth Connell, Grand Avenue, northwest of Harding Avenue. Price, $1,850.</p>
   <p>Hattie D. Berry to Paul C. Peterson, Harrison Street, east of Sacramento Avenue. Price, $8,000.</p>
   <p>Paul C. Peterson to Edmond J. and Arthur LeClere, Harrison Street, east of Sacramento Avenue. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0735.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A. J. Smith to Victor F. Anderson, Parnell Avenue, south of 121st Street. Price, $3,000.</p>
   <p>Z. C. Anderson to Herman J. Souder, Fairfield Avenue, south of Cortland Street. Price, $3,200.</p>
   <p>A. Lewis to Wilhelm L. Peterson, Hirsch Street, east of California Avenue. Price, $4,200.</p>
   <p>Continental National Bank to Ole Olson, Humboldt Boulevard, east of Albany Avenue. Price, $3,600.</p>
   <p>Hans P. Nelson to John Kontng, Superior Street east of Paulina Street. Price, $12,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0736.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>J. E. Hangesen to Carl Carlson, Whipple Street, south of Dickens Avenue. Price, $2,300.</p>
   <p>V. Soderstrom to C. E. Olson, North 43rd Avenue, corner of Dunning Street. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>C. E. Olson to Anna Soderstrom, North 43rd Avenue, corner of Dunning Street. Price, $2,000.</p>
   <p>E. T. Cederholm to Juliett Lane, Fulton Street, east of Sacramento Street. Price, $1,100.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
