<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-10-29">Oct. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Relief Committee Formed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-10-29">Oct. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH RELIEF COMMITTEE FORMED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Representatives of all the more important Swedish organizations in Chicago met last Friday night in the Hamilton Club. The purpose of the meeting was to discuss ways and means of aiding our needy countrymen who are bound to undergo much suffering during the coming winter unless somebody comes to their assistance.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called by Herbert Hedman and was preceded by a supper. A few days earlier Mr. Hedman had inquired of the directors of the Swedish Club if that organization would lend its support to some relief action. The answer was yes, and Hedman was made chairman of a relief committee appointed by the Club. He presided at the meeting, and explained why it had been called, at the same time referring to statements made by the director of one of the city's largest welfare agencies. Mr. Hedman then asked the opinion of the delegates, among whom were Dr. Peter Peterson, president of the Illinois Conference of the Augustana Synod; Oscar S. Ohlander, grand master of the Vasa Order and former president of the Swedish National Association; Justus F. Mozart, present <pb facs="5423404_4_0252.jpg" n="2"/>president of that Association; G. Sandberg, well-known Methodist pastor; David Brunstrom, pastor of the Lake View Mission church; and Adjutant Franzen, of the Lake View Scandinavian Salvation Army Corps.</p>
   <p>Dr. Peterson told about the welfare work which is being done by the Lutheran churches, and Mozart outlined the activities of the National Association.</p>
   <p>Reverend Sandberg read a letter from Reverend J. P. Miller, in which the latter declared himself willing to direct the welfare work of the newly formed Swedish Church Federation. Both Sandberg and Ohlander declared that, as a rule, Swedes who are in need are too proud to ask for help; they deeply resent being subjected to the investigations which certain welfare agencies find it necessary to make before aid is given, and which remind one of cross examinations by the police.</p>
   <p>After several speakers had related their experiences and opinions in regard to the present situation among Swedish unemployed, the question of the formation of joint Swedish relief committees was taken up. It was pointed out that such <pb facs="5423404_4_0253.jpg" n="3"/>a procedure would not mean that the various Swedish welfare organizations which were represented at this meeting, such as the Salvation Army, the Swedish Church Federation and the Swedish National Association, would lose their identity. But such co-operation would promote a better understanding among the individual agencies, and make possible more effective work. Duplication, for instance, would be avoided so that some needy clients would not receive aid from several agencies, while others receive no help at all. After some discussion it was agreed to establish a co-operative committee under the name of the Swedish Relief Committee, with the following membership: Herbert Hedman, chairman; Dr. Peter Peterson, vice-chairman; Major Soderstrom, of the Salvation Army; Oscar S. Ohlander; Dr. C. G. Wallenius; John C. Anderson, president of the Swedish Club; Justus F. Mozart, secretary; and Henry S. Henschen, president of the Chicago Bank of Commerce, treasurer.</p>
   <p>This committee held a meeting last Saturday in the Swedish Club, and appointed a subcommittee, composed of Dr. C. G. Wallenius, Major Soderstrom, and Justus Mozart, to take charge of distribution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0254.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It was decided that all cash contributions to the fund for the needy are to be sent to the treasurer of the Relief Committee, Henry S. Henschen, Chicago Bank of Commerce, 7 South Dearborn Street, while clothing and food should be sent to the headquarters of the Swedish National Association, 3213 Wilton Avenue, or to one of the Salvation Army's receiving stations.</p>
   <p>The committee is confident that there are many who will want to help the unemployed in some way or other, and it is planning a publicity campaign to make the public aware of their plight. It is expected that donations will soon begin pouring in both from individuals and from organizations. A special subcommittee has been appointed to solicit cash contributions. It consists of Henry S. Henschen, Dr. Julius Lincoln, John G. Anderson, Carl Festin, and Bror A. Larson, and may be enlarged in the near future.</p>
   <p>The Swedish Relief Committee is based on the principle that we Swedes will do all we can to take care of our own, and that we can best achieve this purpose by joint effort. But, as stated above, the individual Swedish welfare <pb facs="5423404_4_0255.jpg" n="5"/>organizations retain their freedom of action, and do not in the least lose their identity by co-operating with this central committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
