<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-16">Feb. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">In Memory of Lincoln</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1303</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1303.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-02-16">Feb. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">IN MEMORY OF LINCOLN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Abraham Lincoln's birthday was observed last Saturday, and many speeches paying tribute to this great man were delivered throughout the country. No praise is too high for him, and both young and old are stirred when his name is mentioned. This is an encouraging phenomenon, for it shows that the American people, even in our materialistic times, still possess the ability to appreciate high ideals and unselfish service, and that we have not forgotten the great deeds of the men who made America what it is today.</p>
   <p>To be sure, we have entered into a new epoch in our national development, and our spiritual contact with the past is not as closely knit as one might wish. There is a tendency among Americans to underrate the value of the simple faith and manner of life of their forefathers. The watchword <pb facs="5423404_4_1304.jpg" n="2"/>now seems to be "Grab all you can get, and the devil take the hindmost". But there is no cause for despair as long as the memory of Abraham Lincoln is alive and bright in the hearts of American men and women. He set an example for all of us; being fearless, just and noble-minded, and personifying the best in American manhood. It would be well if we all would allow the example which he set for us to serve as a guide in all our activities, public as well as private, and if Lincoln's spirit, in full measure, could be injected into present-day Americanism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
