<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-11-23">Nov. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Not Theories, but Practice</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-11-23">Nov. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">NOT THEORIES, BUT PRACTICE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago Professor Gault, of Northwestern University, submitted a report to the so-called morals commission of this city, in which he stated that low intelligence and poor mental equipment in general, together with deficient home training, are among the more important causes of delinquency and crime.</p>
   <p>It seems that the good professor has done a lot of research in order to discover something that is already well known. In the study of crime among young people, their degree of intelligence has, of course, come in for its share of attention, and it would be strange indeed if home training and environment did not greatly influence the young people's attitude towards the world in which they live.</p>
   <p>It seems to us that what is needed now is not long drawn-out investigations <pb facs="5423404_4_0423.jpg" n="2"/>and long-winded reports, but effective action in practical application of well-founded theories based on factual data already obtained. As things are, the miserable conditions continue to exist, while nothing is being done which might lead to prevention or cure, or both. The situation reminds us of the old story about the cow which died while the grass was growing.</p>
   <p>Compulsory schooling and training for a trade or any useful work appear to be the most practical and promising means of preventing and curing delinquency among the young. According to Professor Gault's report, there are now in Cook County many delinquent youngsters on probation. Most of them do not work at all, while the rest have only part-time jobs, or jobs that give no promise for the future.</p>
   <p>If young delinquents were given an opportunity to work, they might be able to stay on the right track, and become happy and useful citizens. But their parents cannot be expected to do much for them, since the former are, in <pb facs="5423404_4_0424.jpg" n="3"/>most cases, just as bad off themselves. It is, therefore, up to society; and obligatory schooling, followed by training for some line of work, seems to be a solution worthy of a trial.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
