<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-03-05">Mar. 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The American-Scandinavian Foundation</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. Judson Elected President of the Local Chapter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-03-05">Mar. 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN-SCANDINAVIAN FOUNDATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. Judson Elected President of the Local Chapter</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago chapter of the American-Scandinavian Foundation held its annual membership meeting last Friday in the Swedish Club, and elected the noted educator, Dr. Harry Pratt Judson, president for the current term to succeed Mr. C. S. Peterson. Dr. Judson, who is professor emeritus of the University of Chicago, has been much interested in the exchange of students between America and the Scandinavian countries which is furthered by the Foundation.</p>
   <p>The meeting was presided over by C. S. Peterson. The secretary, Carl Anderson, read a report on the chapter's activities during the past years. Several festive gatherings were arranged in honor of distinguished Scandinavian visitors to Chicago, among whom were Miss Ellen Brandstrom; Dr. Sven Hedin; the noted Danish physical culture expert, Professor Niels Bukh; and the Norwegian scientist and explorer, Frithjof Nansen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1091.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Other officers are: C. S. Peterson, Carl Antonsen, and Birger Osland, vice-presidents; P. B. Nelson, secretary; and Tryggve Siqueland, treasurer.</p>
   <p>On the recommendation of the nominating committee, it was decided to appoint an advisory board. The following prominent Americans were selected: Dr. Harry Pratt Judson; Dr. Walter Dill Scott, president of Northwestern University; Ira Nelson Morris, former American minister to Stockholm; Mr. Elting, former chairman of the local Council on Foreign Relations and Robert Harshe, president of the Art Institute. Swedish representatives on the advisory board are: Consul Carl O. De Dardel, Judge Harry Olson, H. S. Henschen, District Attorney Edwin A. Olson, and Dr. Anders Frick. The Norwegian representatives are: Consul Olaf Bernts, Judge Oscar Turrison, Andrew Hummeland, and Attorney John Sonsteby. The Danes are represented by Consul Baumann, Henry Hertz, and Dr. Max Henius.</p>
   <p>A proposal by C. S. Peterson that meetings be held once every three months was adopted, and it was also decided to launch a vigorous membership drive. There are now about three hundred members of the American-Scandinavian Foundation in <pb facs="5423404_4_1092.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago and vicinity, but only about one hundred of these have joined the local chapter.</p>
   <p>James Creese of New York, general secretary of the Foundation, was present and addressed the meeting. He informed the members that the State Bank of Chicago had presented the Foundation with a fellowship of one thousand dollars for the benefit of its student exchange program.</p>
   <p>A banquet in honor of Dr. Judson, the new president of the chapter, will be given in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
