<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1895-03-06">March 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Immigration to America by C.F.P.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1002</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1002.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1895-03-06">March 6, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH IMMIGRATION TO AMERICA By C.F.P.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>EDITORIAL: When we scan the Swedish American annals, written and unwritten, our eyes meet a prominent feature: the moral and religious role in life. The moral activity constitutes the field on which intellectual harvests are going to grow and ripen.</p>
   <p>There are half a thousand Christian temples in the west today, Christian temples built by Swedish hands. They bear witness to the faith, which lives in hundreds of thousands of souls. And this faith, what does it say? That there is an inner life in these children of the west of Nordic ancestry, which is expanding more and more and requests more light, more air, and more room. New thoughts are breeding, new feelings are being born, new goals are being raised. Action follows.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1003.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It shows in new higher educational work. The process of evolution continues. The flame of education, fed by the moral ideals, burns brighter, clearer, warmer. And, at the time, there appears a poet here, a sculptor there, a searcher, a thinker, an inventor, etc.</p>
   <p>This influence is now beginning to show itself in Swedish-American life...</p>
   <p>The influence of Swedish immigration upon American civilization and through it upon the whole world, will depend upon the grade of that zeal, wherewith we guard and display the noble Swede in our nature, because it is by this that our valuable heritage may be assimilated into the American life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
