<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-07-16">July 16, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Crime and the Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-07-16">July 16, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">CRIME AND THE PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge Harry B. Miller of Chicago wrote an article in one of our metropolitan newspapers last week, in which he discussed crime and its causes, and the means by which it might successfully be combated. In this article he also touched upon the role of the press in the fight against crime, declaring that, in his opinion, it is the duty of our newspapers to truthfully present the situation as it exists, without misleading the public. But care should be taken to present such material in a dignified manner, and not in a style which may actually make crime seem attractive to the easily impressed minds of youngsters, and tempt them to embark on a criminal career.</p>
   <p>We dare say that certain local metropolitan papers would do well to heed Judge Miller's suggestion. For there can be no doubt that a goodly portion <pb facs="5423404_4_0364.jpg" n="2"/>of the criminal tendencies which have been noted among the city's youth of late has its root in the reading of scandal stories in newspapers and their vivid descriptions of the underworld. Young people just devour such stories, and in many cases the hoodlums and criminals, whose exploits are so interestingly described become heroes to their misguided minds, and a desire is created to become like them.</p>
   <p>What we have said about the crime news material which is to be found in some newspapers, applies also, to some extent, to the editorials. One paper, which claims to be very much up to date, took it upon itself last week to make fun of a statement which Mrs. Thomas A. Edison, wife of the great inventor, recently made regarding the American home. Mrs. Edison declared that many modern women have not learned the art of managing a home, and that this is one of the reasons for the frequency of crime among young people. The newspaper to which we are referring took issue with her, declaring that the American home of today is better than that of any previous time, because all members of the family receive a better <pb facs="5423404_4_0365.jpg" n="3"/>education then could ever be had before, and enjoy any number of conveniences which their forefathers did not have.</p>
   <p>In regard to formal schooling, the American of today probably compares favorably with previous generations. The schools are certainly better now than they were years ago. But they, like many of our modern newspapers, lack the proper moral foundation, and the children's training suffers accordingly. On the whole, the same may he said of the home. There, as in the schools, the goal is to make everything as easy and convenient as possible, and this attitude tends to develop superficiality and an emphasis on appearances, regardless of what is underneath, and in the long run it cannot face to exert a demoralizing influence on the children, whose time, inside the house, is spent eating, sleeping, and reading crime and detective stories. They are not inclined to take advice from their parents, who often, it must be said, have no worth-while advice to give anyway. Likely as not, they themselves are pretty much wrapped up in outside activities and not much interested in home life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0366.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When, on top of this, the newspapers do their best to nourish the ever-present desire for pleasure and adventure, one should not be surprised at the large number of young people who either willingly or by the force of circumstances follow a career of crime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
