<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-09-20">Sept. 20, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish-American Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0054</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0054.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-09-20">Sept. 20, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH-AMERICAN HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During recent years the need of a hospital for our people on the South Side has become more and more apparent to Swedes living in that part of the city. This is particularly true as regards the large Swedish colony in Englewood, in which district one small hospital serves a population of one hundred thousand people.</p>
   <p>Another hospital is now under construction, but it is a Catholic institution, and can, therefore, not be expected to answer to the particular Swedish needs.</p>
   <p>This problem has been the topic of private discussions only, until January 5 of this year, when Pastor Rosen, Dr. Fors, and Dr. Beardsley called a meeting of interested people at N. A. Nelson's office, 159 N. LaSalle Street. The question of a Swedish hospital for the South Side was discussed from various angles, and the result was that the following four questions were <pb facs="5423404_4_0055.jpg" n="2"/>referred to four respective committees which will report on the results of their investigations at a future meeting. The questions are:</p>
   <p>(1) Is there actual need of a Swedish hospital on the South Side?</p>
   <p>(2) What would be the most desirable location for such a hospital?</p>
   <p>(3) On what basic principles should it be financed and organized?</p>
   <p>(4) On what basic principles should it be operated and controlled?</p>
   <p>When the four committees were ready to report, a meeting was again called at the same place, and perfect agreement was reached, except on the question concerning location. It was referred to the committee again for further study, and a new meeting set for March 21. At that time a more complete and encouraging report was received on the question of possible location, and nine men were appointed then and there to start organization proceedings. <pb facs="5423404_4_0056.jpg" n="3"/>The institution will be named the Swedish-American Hospital, and those present at the meeting subscribed ten dollars each for covering of the initial expenses.</p>
   <p>The undertaking will be capitalized at one hundred thousand dollars; this calls for the sale of ten thousand shares at ten dollars each.</p>
   <p>The institution has been incorporated, and Architect Lund has already presented a tentative building plan.</p>
   <p>Pastor A. L. Nystrom, N. A. Nelson, Fred Westberg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
