<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-11-17">Nov. 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The "Educated" Swedish-American</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0968</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0968.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-11-17">Nov. 17, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE "EDUCATED" SWEDISH-AMERICAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In an inquiry concerning advertising, which we have just received from Sweden, the question is asked whether or not it is necessary to advertise in the American metropolitan dailies if one wants to reach the "cultured" Swedish-Americans. By way of explanation, the inquirer goes on to say that he has been informed that the cultured Swedish-American does not, as a rule, read Swedish-American newspapers.</p>
   <p>We hasten to assure our friend that he has been misinformed. However, we should like to know what he means by "cultured". We dare say that Swedish-American newspapers are read by Swedes who quite properly regard themselves as cultured, and also by another type of countryman who is really cultured, but who does not care whether or not he is recognized as such.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0969.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then there is the class of people which considers itself cultured without being so at all. Finally, there are the people who have managed to make, or who have perhaps inherited, a lot of money, and who have, so to speak, bought themselves a position in society. In the last two categories, there are undoubtedly a few who do not bother to read anything in Swedish, and the chances are that they do not read much in any other language.</p>
   <p>In this connection, we want to call attention to a marked hunger for knowledge among Swedish-Americans, which did not exist before they left the old country. The young man and young woman from the farm, at the edge of the forest have put away their catechism and their text-book on Bible history; and reading and further education are the last things they think of.</p>
   <p>Suddenly, they find themselves in a new world, in a new and strange environment, and then the desire for more knowledge awakens. This may be due partly to curiosity, but the young Swedish-American also realizes the necessity for both practical and theoretical knowledge.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0970.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many of our most prominent Swedish-American scientists--and do not think they do not read Swedish-American newspapers--have this impulse to thank for their start on the road which led to useful careers and fame. In the same manner, thousands of less gifted countrymen and countrywomen have acquired knowledge and the advantages that go with it.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, it is a well-known fact that well-educated Swedish-Americans of the second generation, as a rule, read Swedish-American newspapers; while others, who for some reason or other have not acquired an education, are not much interested. This fact has been observed for such a long time and it is such a careful observation that one may now say that whether or not a Swedish-American reads Swedish-American newspapers is a fair indication of his educational standing.</p>
   <p>A Swedish-American of the second generation ought to feel ashamed if he does not keep himself informed of what is going on among Swedish-Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0971.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We know personally Frenchmen and Germans who read Swedish-American newspapers in order to increase their knowledge and widen their mental horizon, and it would be wise for all second generation Swedes to follow their example.</p>
   <p>The inquiry mentioned in the opening lines of this article is a good example of the ignorance and misunderstandings prevailing in Sweden in regard to conditions among Swedish-Americans. In many cases, this misinformation originated with some person who visited in America for a few months, or at most for a couple of years, without having acquainted himself with the true conditions mong Swedish-Americans of American conditions in general. It is impossible for such a person to obtain a true picture of this vast land, and his impressions are, of necessity, the total sum of his own limited experiences. We have often tried to correct misunderstandings caused in this manner, and we have even tried to forgive the offenders. What more can one do?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
