<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1888-12-01">Dec. 1, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">In Swedish Homes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1032</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1032.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1888-12-01">Dec. 1, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">IN SWEDISH HOMES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish Tribune, Chicago, reprints parts of an interesting article from the Providence Sunday Journal, which is very favorable to the Swedes. The title of the article is "In Swedish Homes," The journal says among other things, "Thriftiness" is the distinguishing character among the Swedes, both men and women have a natural instinct to find satisfaction in doing good. They show these qualities, with which they are born, in their clear, unwrinkled foreheads and round innocent faces. Physical activity, however, has formed these types with strong muscles. That is one of the reasons why so many young Swedish women are employed as servants in American homes. The men are all sober, and of high moral quality.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1033.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The young unmarried Swedish women in this country outnumber the married women.</p>
   <p>When a Swede was asked how his country could spare so many of its daughters he answered: "If you lose one, thousands are still left."</p>
   <p>Swedes are so well known in this country, that we do not need to talk about their faithfulness and their pleasant appearance. Some of these women have noble, even beautiful faces. They are all pleasant and simple in their daily lives.</p>
   <p>They find the social privileges in American life so very pleasant that they write home about this all the time. They are skilful in their work and like to have everything in good order.</p>
   <p>Those Swedes who arrive here have a little money. They are stately persons, with blue eyes, blonde hair. Many of the women are real beauties.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
