<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Old People's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0099</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0099.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH OLD PEOPLE'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the Swedish Old People's Home, we learn that many gifts have been distributed among the old folks during the holidays. "The Unknown Woman" again visted the home before Christmas, as she has done for the past ten years. At such times, she generously presented to each woman of the institution five dollars in gold, and the matron ten dollars. Other donations were made to the Home from other residents at this time. Mrs. C. M. Hedman gave coffee, apples, and other things. Mrs. J. P. Friedlund gave each one a box of candy, as did Mr. and Mrs. Aaron Miller. The Ladies Guild gave a pair of hose to each inmate. The regular members gave one dollar to each of the residents, and five dollars was given by them to the directress and others. The items are too numerous to recount in detail.</p>
   <p>The Old People's Home held its quarterly meeting at the Hotel Sherman last week. At that time, the financial secretary read his quarterly report, which showed that the cash in the treasury amounted to $17,617.35 on December 31, 1919.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0100.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following committee on nomination was named at the meeting: John A. Sandgren, Dr. Olga Gustavson, and L. V. Hult. The president of the organization will later name two more members to this committee. At the same time, we hear the regular members intend to begin a campaign to increase the membership through their several clubs. This applies to the men as well as the women, collaborating with the delegates of the organization. The campaign will begin next month. The yearly meeting will be held on the first Monday in April.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
