<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-07-04">July 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Younger Generation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0410.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-07-04">July 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE YOUNGER GENERATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sponsored by Judge Charles F. McKinley, a meeting was held last week here in Chicago, at which the topic "What to Do with Delinquent Boys?" was discussed. The judge told the meeting that, thus far this year, no less than two thousand boys under the age of seventeen had been brought before his court, accused of having violated the law.</p>
   <p>The judge has come to the conclusion that it is up to society to take measures which will alleviate this condition; and, on the basis of his observations, he has submitted a plan, the essence of which is to make the Juvenile Court a crime-prevention rather than a punitive agency. According to his plan, boys who come under the jurisdiction of the Juvenile Court are not to be placed in regular prisons, but in special protective institutions. As an interesting innovation, the judge also recommended the formation of "big brother" clubs, <pb facs="5423404_4_0411.jpg" n="2"/>directed by officers of the Juvenile Court and the police officers who come in contact with these boys.</p>
   <p>The adoption of such measures as these for the purpose of discouraging juvenile crime is certainly laudable, but it is evident that the youngsters will come under the influence of these measures at a rather advanced period in their lives. The boys who are brought before the Juvenile Court have already taken the first steps along the road which may lead to a life of crime. Why not give them a helping hand at an earlier age, to prevent the acts which cause them to be brought before the Court?</p>
   <p>This is vacation time, and the boys are looking for something with which to occupy themselves. The country would be the best place for them, but many parents cannot afford to send and keep them there. These boys must therefore stay in the city, and most of their time is spent on the streets. What are the consequences?</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0412.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We understand that real-estate values in the city are going up, and it might be a good idea for the city to buy vacant lots now and turn them into playgrounds. It should be remembered that young America is being formed in our homes, in our schools, and on our playgrounds. And is not the younger generation worth more than a few building lots?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
