<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1927-09-22">September 22, 1927</date><title level="a">Religion by Prescription.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1927-09-22">September 22, 1927</date><title level="a">RELIGION BY PRESCRIPTION.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Your publisher has all the convenience in the world when it comes to religion. There are two churches in his block and one across the street still closer to his home. If he stands and looks out over the boulevard, he will find a Lutheran church back of him and an Episcopal and a Christian Science church on either side of him.</p>
   <p>Of the three, old Mrs. Eddy's Grecian temple is the one most frequented. On a Sunday forenoon all the adjoining streets are filled with automobiles, and there is seemingly an unending stream of pedestrians walking in the direction of the temple at the northwest corner of Mozart Street and Logan Boulevard. The scene conveys a picture of great prosperity.</p>
   <p>But her colleagues do not suffer from lack of patronage,either. The Lutheran congregation has busied itself for the past two years with the construction of a new church building, which just has been completed. The Episcopal congregation did get their church completed in a much shorter time, and it stands there, beautiful to look at, on the finest site on Logan Boulevard, while the old edifice has been remodeled into a parish house and club rooms. They seem to know how to spell the word "cash".</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1397.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, what is really the advantage of having so many churches within such a limited area? This is an outsider's point of view:</p>
   <p>If he wanders a few hundred paces either in this or that direction, he also will find other churches, outside of which big signs advertise the brand of religion within its walls.</p>
   <p>All of this probably conveys new ideas to the wanderer, who, if he is a stranger around these parts, will ask himself another question: "Why do they not consolidate? It would be much simpler and, besides, considerably much more economical."</p>
   <p>Yes, he ought to try to make a suggestion of that sort to either of these church organizations. Then he would have some fun, if he never had had fun before in his life. Up would jump the devil! No, and again no, each and every one of them dispenses the only true and right belief and none of them will part with one inch of their dogmas. To the last drop of blood they will fight the Devil and his consort, who are housed in all other churches but their own.</p>
   <p>To a certain degree it must be conceded that this state of affairs probably may last, if there is to be religion at all. It is the fighting spirit more than <pb facs="5423404_4_1398.jpg" n="3"/>intellectual - fighting spirit which has created new religions or religious sects, at least here in America, when the adherents have found that the old teachings did not satisfy their hunger for intellectual and moral enlightenment and expansion.</p>
   <p>Such is the state of affairs in the U.S.A. In Europe the religious movement seems to take on a different direction. There they are endeavoring to consolidate and unite the various Protestant religious sects, since the Roman-Catholic church vehemently has refused to enter into any kind of compromises. "Is it consolidation that you want", says Christ's successor on this Earth, "then the Mother Church is ever willing to take to her bosom her strayed children".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
