<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-03-02">Mar. 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Contemptible Campaign Methods</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-03-02">Mar. 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">CONTEMPTIBLE CAMPAIGN METHODS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Politics and religion are supposed to be entirely separate in this country. To mix them would oppose the American sense of fairness and appreciation of spiritual values. But in spite of this laudable attitude, religious considerations seem to have been injected into the recent primary campaign in Chicago, and it is claimed that the opponents of Chief Justice Harry Olson, a candidate for mayor, stooped to such tactics.</p>
   <p>Justice Olson has stated in an interview that one of the reasons for his defeat was the fact that opposing factions made use of such despicable campaign methods. In districts with a predominantly Protestant population the rumor was spread that Mrs. Olson is a Catholic, and that the children of the family attend Catholic schools, while in the localities where Catholics are in the majority, the story was circulated that Olson,as a Protestant, was unfriendly toward them. So anxious were they to defeat him that they did not even shrink <pb facs="5423404_4_1430.jpg" n="2"/>from circulating false rumors in order to do so. For the rumors were entirely false. Mrs. Olson is a Methodist, and the judge himself is a Lutheran, known for his religious tolerance.</p>
   <p>It is said that even some Swedes, who should know better, were influenced by these false rumors. What about the people responsible for such campaign methods? It may not be practical to institute legal proceedings against them, but they certainly are deserving of the deepest contempt of enlightened people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
