<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-10-17">Oct. 17, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-10-17">Oct. 17, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOCIETY FOR THE PRESERVATION OF SWEDISH CULTURE IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago branch of the Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture in America held its fall meeting last Friday night in the Swedish Engineering Society's clubhouse, 503 Wrightwood Avenue. Engineer A. G. Witting, president of the branch, was chairman. F. N. Andren, treasurer, gave an account of the local organization's activities during the summer months, or, in other words, since its inception. It participated in the singers' annual festivities in memory of Linne, the great Swedish scientist, whose monument adorns Lincoln Park. On that occasion, Witting was one of the main speakers. Later in the summer, the Society arranged a Swedish festival in the park adjoining the Ebenezer Church; this event was well attended and very successful in every respect. The local now has about two hundred members.</p>
   <p>Carl Festin, former Grand Master of the Vasa Order, was then introduced <pb facs="5423404_4_1096.jpg" n="2"/>to the meeting. He had attended the convention of the mother organization, Swedish Unity, which was held in Gothenburg, Sweden last summer. He outlined briefly the proceedings at that convention. Several important questions had been on the agenda. Among them was that of the establishment of an international Swedish museum; and it was suggested that some city in Finland, Gothenburg, and Chicago might be suitable locations for branches of such an institution. At the end of his address, Festin told of his impressions of the great exposition in Gothenburg, especially of the participation of Swedish nationals living in foreign countries. This part of the exposition was sponsored by Swedish Unity and its branches in foreign countries. Especially interesting was the Hall of Memories.</p>
   <p>The meeting was entertained with song by the Nordstjernan Singing Club.</p>
   <p>The Society will arrange a Gustaf Adolph evening on Sunday, November 4 <pb facs="5423404_4_1097.jpg" n="3"/>in the Central Lutheran Church. Tickets were on sale at the meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
