<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-06-28">June 28, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">To the Scandinavians of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-V.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>V B</item>
     <item>I C (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>I C (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-06-28">June 28, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE SCANDINAVIANS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never before have world conditions forced individuals to co-operation, drawn them together, as is the case now, in these days. The weak have to protect themselves against the abuses of the strong, and the lower, underprivileged classes are gradually becoming conscious of the fact that they are potentially many times as strong as the so-called upper classes. The tendency is toward socialism; the demand for municipal ownership, for instance, is a typical sign of the times, a step in the right direction. There are already indications that even the gigantic trusts may soon come under the complete control of the Government, and we will then have all the prerequisites of a paternal form of government, which controls everything and everybody. Switzerland, Australia and New Zealand have been in the lead along this road of progress. Therefore, brother Scandinavians, imbued with that same spirit, let us also get together and build a great Scandinavian People's House, here in Chicago, to serve as our social and political center.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0186.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Scandinavian unity is not a new idea. History teaches us, it must be admitted, that Scandinavianism, as practiced during the 126 years of the Kalmar Union, when the three countries were united under one king, was fraught with misunderstanding and strife. But this was due to the misrule of foreign kings and queens, and to the jealousies existing among the wealthy and greedy nobles. However, that was 400 years ago, and we have advanced in enlightenment and civilization, and particularly is this true here in the free West where we don't have even the remnants of Scandinavian class rule--but we do need each other.</p>
   <p>Such changes and improvements as take place in this world are as a rule very much needed and overdue, and such a community center, a Scandinavian People's House has been under discussion several times in the past. The idea has repeatedly shot across our horizon like a beam of light, and we take it as a good omen that it has now been revived by the Verdandi Lodge, Light Bearer, and again presented to Chicago's Scandinavian population.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0187.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Sceptics will declare that the Scandinavians, the Swedes, Norwegians and Danes, and for our present purpose we wish also to include our cousins, the Finlanders, cannot get along together. As part of our answer we will point out the fact that in recent years, during strikes and lockouts in anyone of the countries in question, the labor unions of the others have come to the aid, financially as well as morally, of the strikers, or those subjected to the lockout, and have helped them to hold out until an agreement was reached. Perfect co-operation exists among the labor unions of those countries and when union delegates have occasion to visit their brethren across the border, they always receive a hearty welcome. As far back as 1887, in London, England, a Swedish Workers' Club, two Norwegian and two Danish, united and formed a Scandinavian Workers' Society, which bought its own building and was active for many years with very beneficial results. There would be no difficulties among Scandinavian nationals were it not for a few mischief-makers.</p>
   <p>Our own capital, Washington, boasts a Scandinavian Society, the president <pb facs="5423404_4_0188.jpg" n="4"/>of which is Mr. Sartz, former editor of the Norwegian publication Norden (The North), of Chicago. Both Paris and Rome have their Scandinavian organizations, their membership consisting mostly of students, writers and artists.</p>
   <p>We ought to be ashamed that with a Scandinavian population as large as that of Stockholm, we are not yet able to point to a Scandinavian People's House.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Federation of Labor has recently organized and incorporated a company for the purpose of erecting a Labor Temple at a cost of five hundred thousand dollars. The 150 Scandinavian organizations in our city should be able to finance a similar undertaking, and such a "federation" as we are here proposing would represent a power that would have to be reckoned with in the conduct of the city's affairs, and it would also promote Scandinavian unity in other parts of the United States.</p>
   <p>Such a Scandinavian People's House would become the center of the official <pb facs="5423404_4_0189.jpg" n="5"/>social life of our people, and we tentatively suggest that it should be located as centrally as possible, and should contain modern facilities for theatrical performances and concerts, lecture rooms, lodge halls, class rooms for night schools and a library. In addition there should be a gymnasium, and a Swedish massage establishment, and also a restaurant; we would recommend that no alcoholic beverages be sold in the building. It would certainly be desirable to move the free Swedish labor bureau to such a location, and even to reorganize it into an All-Scandinavian agency.</p>
   <p>There are some 150,000 Swedes in Chicago, and of these, 40,000 do not belong to any church. Surely many of them would like to attend the scientific, historical and philosophical lectures in the projected People's House; the same goes for Norwegians, Danes and Finns.</p>
   <p>We sincerely hope that the great Swedish and Norwegian newspapers in Chicago will not permit themselves to be influenced by selfish interests, but will <pb facs="5423404_4_0190.jpg" n="6"/>give the project their wholehearted support.</p>
   <p>We herewith request every Scandinavian lodge and society in Chicago to send delegates to the mass meeting which is to be held at Jaeger's Hall, Larrabee Street and Clybourn Avenue, July 17, at 8:00 P. M., for the purpose of discussing the plan; a working committee will then be appointed. Every organization should send at least one delegate and the larger ones, one for each hundred of their membership.</p>
   <p>Signed: A. Ahlberg</p>
   <p>K. J. Ellington</p>
   <p>K. G. Fredin</p>
   <p>M. J. Ring</p>
   <p>E. Johnson</p>
   <p>C. E. Kronlof</p>
   <p>A. Holm</p>
   <p>E. Ahlskog</p>
   <p>G. Berg</p>
   <p>J. G. Hamilton</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
