<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-03-08">Mar. 8, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">[Starting Work for a Home for Aged]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1904-03-08">Mar. 8, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">[STARTING WORK FOR A HOME FOR AGED]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. A. W. Stark, secretary of the Illinois Conference of the Augustana Synod of the Lutheran church, has presented this paper with facts concerning the intended home for the aged to be built by the Conference. In substance, the story is that at the latest meeting of the committee, held at Augustana Hospital, all the members except Reverend V. Setterdahl were present. There was strong sentiment in the committee for action in the matter of a home for the aged by the Illinois Conference when it convenes for its annual meeting. The committee feels that the time has arrived for the erection of such a home. It also feels that it should not be difficult to raise the money needed for the building and maintenance of the home.</p>
   <p>A subcommittee, consisting of Reverend Sandahl and Reverend Setterdahl, together with Mr. Ringman, was appointed to make inquiries about a suitable location for the intended home, and to make report concerning these inquiries at the April meeting of the main committee.....The majority of the committee consists of Chicago men. It is, therefore, natural that this city will be recommended <pb facs="5423404_4_1470.jpg" n="2"/>as the location of the home. The treasurer of the committee is Mr. Jonas Erlandson, 1130 Belmont Avenue, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
