<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-05-19">May 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Church Observes Golden Anniversary</title>
[Half-tone, one column, sixth of a page, full face picture of pastor W. E. Pearson.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-05-19">May 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">CHURCH OBSERVES GOLDEN ANNIVERSARY</title>
[Half-tone, one column, sixth of a page, full face picture of pastor W. E. Pearson.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday and Sunday the congregation of the Getsemane Swedish Lutheran Church observed the fiftieth anniversary of the church. On Saturday night, the church choir, assisted by a number of well-known soloists, gave a fine concert in the church. The church is located at Huron and May streets. On Sunday morning, Dr. M. C. Ranseen, president of the Illinois Conference, delivered a jubilee message. The pastor of the church, W. E. Pearson, assisted by Reverend C. O. Bengtson, officiated at high mass.</p>
   <p>In honor of the golden anniversary, a history of the congregation and its activities has been published.</p>
   <p>The founder was pastor P. Ericson, who was followed by A. G. Skeppstedt. The <pb facs="5423404_4_1421.jpg" n="2"/>latter served for two years and then resigned because of failing health, and returned to Sweden. Dr. M. C. Ranseen was pastor from 1879 to 1910.</p>
   <p>During the last few years the Getsemane congregation has experienced the same kind of trouble that has beset other congregations in that district; namely, a serious loss of membership. This loss was due to the fact that so many Swedish families have moved to new homes in other parts of the city. Plans for moving the church further west are now under consideration.</p>
   <p>The pamphlet published in honor of the anniversary contains pictures of the veterans of the congregation, and of its young men who served in the world war. It also contains greetings from former pastors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
