<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-02-28">Feb. 28, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">[Real-Estate Transactions]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0835</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0835.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-02-28">Feb. 28, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">[REAL-ESTATE TRANSACTIONS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following transactions took place: C. G. Hall to Albert Rundblad, Carmen Avenue, 154 feet west of Evanston Avenue, $4,000.</p>
   <p>O. F. Olson to Peter I. Tearto, Throop Street, 55 feet north of 60th Street, $2,500.</p>
   <p>Lars Olson to Rachel Hart, Peoria Street, 148 feet south of 65th Street, $6,500.</p>
   <p>J. Anderson to Anna M. Anderson, Butler Street, 125 feet south of 89th Street, $1,025.</p>
   <p>E. Swanson to Joseph C. Kinney, South 41st Court, northeast corner of 32nd Street, $1,500.</p>
   <p>A. Engberg to George R. Clarke, Greenshaw Street, 200 feet west of Central Park Avenue, $1,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0836.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>H. S. Handin to Emma Lanz, Walnut Avenue, 60 feet south of Bennett Street, $4,950.</p>
   <p>M. Mc-Nulty to John E. Anderson, Carrien Avenue, 188 feet south of Southport Avenue, $2,000.</p>
   <p>M. Ennis to Charles J. Anderson, Belden Avenue, 90 feet east of Homan Avenue, $2,000.</p>
   <p>M. K. Hallgren to Sylvia J. Ames, 64th Street, northwest corner of Lowe Avenue, $5,000.</p>
   <p>A. O. Anderson to John Nelson, Erie Avenue, 249 feet south of 132nd Street, $1,000.</p>
   <p>C. A. Oberg to Ake H. Johnson, Janssen Avenue, 74 feet north of Waveland Avenue, $2,500.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0837.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>J. Olson to Frederick Henrich, Elston Avenue, 175 feet southeast of Rockwell Street, $1,000.</p>
   <p>A. H. Johnson to C. A. Oberg, Seminary Avenue, 187 feet north of Noble Avenue, $1,620.</p>
   <p>F. Block to A. C. Peterson, 110th Place, 363 feet east of Wentworth Avenue, $1,400.</p>
   <p>E. M. Johnson to Sven Lofquist, Fifth Avenue, 220 feet north of 55th Street, $5,500.</p>
   <p>Peter Johnson to Anna Hoff, preceding property (Fifth Avenue, 220 feet north of 55th Street), $1. [Translator's note: This translation follows the text, but I don't understand the transactions.]</p>
   <p>M. Mattson to August F. Eiserblatter, Artesian Avenue, 250 feet south of Potomac Avenue, $7,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0838.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Nels J. Johnson to Otto B. Linde, Vernon Avenue, 313 feet north of 31st Street, $5,000.</p>
   <p>Chicago Permanent B. &amp; L. Association to Louis F. Wickman, Commercial Avenue, $2,000. [Translator's note: No definite location given.]</p>
   <p>S. M. Gunderson to James Spellman, Colorado Avenue, 91 feet east of North Hoyne Avenue, $9,500.</p>
   <p>J. Fischer to Charles M. Anderson, Magnolia Avenue, 194 feet north of Rose-mount Avenue, $2,000.</p>
   <p>M. N. Nelson to Swedish Bible Institute, Ballou Street, northwest corner of Barry Avenue, $1,000.</p>
   <p>William Kent to Ossian W. T. Hultgren, Vincennes Avenue, 280 feet north of 64th Street, $1,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0839.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>A. Johnson to Oscar F. Johnson, Funk Street, 132 feet east of Walnut Avenue, $1,200.  </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
