<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-11-28">Nov. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Newcomers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-11-28">Nov. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH NEWCOMERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the number of immigrants from Sweden began to increase sharply more than a year ago, Chicago seems to have been receiving more than its share of newcomers. It is quite natural that they should prefer to go to communities where they know they will find many countrymen, and it is also natural that we, their forerunners, should look them over rather closely, and make observationsregarding their appearance, conduct, etc. Many of us feel that, on the whole, we may well be proud of these young Swedish newcomers. They are clean-cut and dignified, well dressed and well groomed, and are thus a credit to themselves as well as to their fellow Swedes who have been living here for years, and not least of all a credit to their homeland, Sweden, who sent them forth to make their contribution to the great American melting pot.</p>
   <p>But we regret to say that there are exceptions. Among the new arrivals there are a few individuals who distinguish themselves by qualities of which there <pb facs="5423404_4_1612.jpg" n="2"/>is no reason to be proud. And, unfortunately, they are the ones that attract most attention. For many observers it is difficult to distinguish between the rule and the exception; consequently, the general opinion about Swedish newcomers is not always flattering. The majority are judged by the conduct of a few, which is highly regrettable.</p>
   <p>These exceptions seem to represent a certain hoodlum element, which glories in making passes at ladies on the street and indulges in similar ungentlemanly conduct. Perhaps they got away with that sort of thing in Sweden, but they need not think that it will go unpunished here. The sooner they get their fingers burned, the better it will be for them. It will teach them manners. We understand that some of the offenders already have had their lesson.</p>
   <p>But we repeat that these are exceptions. The great majority of Swedish newcomers are a credit to their countrymen here and to the land from which they came. They have all the qualifications for doing well here in America and becoming an asset to their new country. And they are welcome, not only by us, their countrymen, but by the entire nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
