<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1882-12-27">Dec. 27, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Sweden and the Swedish-Americans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1882-12-27">Dec. 27, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDEN AND THE SWEDISH-AMERICANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>EDITORIAL: There is soon a Sweden in miniature in America. If the immigration continues, let us say six years more at the present rate, the Swedish-American population, at the next census, which will be taken in 1890, will be just as large as that of Sweden a couple of centuries ago.</p>
   <p>There are probably 100,000 Swedes in the State of Illinois, which is a much higher figure than that found in many of the provinces in Sweden. There are Swedes by the thousands in the five states of Illinois, Minnesota, Iowa, Kansas and Nebraska, and they are not scattered, but dwell together in large colonies or communities. One fifth of the Illinois Swedes are to be found in Chicago. Then comes the populous Swedish settlements in Moline, Andover, Galesburg, Princeton, Bishop Hill and Rockford, but there are also dozens of large settlements in every State of the Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1044.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Swedish influence" is therefore noticeable.</p>
   <p>What is more interesting for the population in Sweden to know is how people are faring in the "New Sweden", which is becoming a reality west of the big World Sea? Or maybe our brothers at home forgot the emigrant just as fast as the ship disappears. Impossible, because the tie of relatives is stronger than that. And ties of this kind uniting Sweden with America are so numerous that one cannot travel half a day on a train in Sweden without meeting one or more persons who have children, brothers and sisters or parents in America.</p>
   <p>If it then happens that one is a Swedish-American and has been in America for only a short time and is visiting the old country, then it is quite certain that questions come up regarding the great country "out there". He likes to know what progress is being made, what professions the immigrants have choosen, how they struggle and work and about their recreations and amusements.</p>
   <p>Does not the reading populace in our dear native country get information <pb facs="5423404_4_1045.jpg" n="3"/>re-printed often in the Swedish press than a pitiful picture of distress and misery in America and how the newly arrived immigrant goes begging for bread and work from door to door or perishes in the struggle with the unkind fate. They cast the black mantle of lie over the dawn.</p>
   <p>If some Swedes are travelling and gather together on German, French or Italian soil for a happy celebration with dinners, songs, toasts and speeches, then the columns in the Swedish newspapers are filled with long reports. But, as we have mentioned before the papers in Sweden are silent about us, except when they find adverse things to mention. Why, one might ask? What is the reason for this silence regarding everything that is Swedish-American? Why despise us so greatly, why this decision to ignore those Swedes who are fighting the struggle of life on American soil?</p>
   <p>Well, it might encourage emigration. The Swedish newspapermen probably have these thoughts: If we keep the readers informed about the real facts over there in that Great Republic, then we would betray our native land, and that <pb facs="5423404_4_1046.jpg" n="4"/>is too great a responsibility.</p>
   <p>The future of Sweden depends on the people and if the Swedish folkstock is drawn to America, the future will be dark. Therefore, since law cannot stop the westward march, the press shall not directly or indirectly hasten it's speed." He, therefore, keeps quiet.</p>
   <p>But the stream does not stop. "Westward the star of empire takes its way" in spite of the "patriotic" decision of the Swedish newspapers to keep Sweden in ignorance regarding the Swedes in America.</p>
   <p>If we on this side of the Atlantic had "cooled off" in our love for our native land it might be justifiable if we were criticised for it. But the fact is, that the Swedes in America, no matter how Americanized he might be, never forgets his native land and never ceases to love it.</p>
   <p>He might, through new experiences in this free country, have learned to disapprove much of Swedes, but deep down in his heart he keeps as holy treasures thousands <pb facs="5423404_4_1047.jpg" n="5"/>of dear memories of the time when he was a Scandinavian. This is confirmed by the fact that the Swedish-Americans send home large amounts of money annually to their relatives in Sweden.</p>
   <p>We have questioned several money changers in Chicago and they have informed us that they have sent considerably more than over one million Swedish kronen from Swedish-Americans to their friends in Sweden between Nov. 1st to Dec. 20th. But in addition to sums sent home at Christmas time, at least three times that sum is sent home through bankers in New York, Boston and other cities, and if we add all the money sent home during the year the total sum would no doubt amount to ten million Swedish kronen.</p>
   <p>It would, therefore, seem that people who show so much feeling for their native land, surely should not receive silent despite such as the Swedish Press shows them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
