<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-03-04">Mar. 4, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Illinois Convention of Augustana Synod</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-03-04">Mar. 4, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ILLINOIS CONVENTION OF AUGUSTANA SYNOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Augustana Synod held its 57th Annual Convention last week in the Bethlehem Church. The organization consists of 213 congregations with a membership of 68,000 and 135 ministers. It owns 200 churches and 11 parsonages valued at $2,000,000. The Bethlehem congregation, serving as host for a third time, is 34 years old. The first convention was held in this church 24 years ago, when F. Nibelius was its minister. The second one was held 14 years ago when George Youngdahl was pastor of the congregation. The young energetic S. G. Ohslund is now the minister.</p>
   <p>The convention was attended by 103 ministers and 111 laymen. It was a group of men with a sincere purpose who had gathered here. During the past year the Orphan Home at Andover was destroyed by fire, and the directors of this benevolent institution wish to have a new home built in its place. They wish <pb facs="5423404_4_1457.jpg" n="2"/>to obtain the delegates joint advice and decision in the matter. Therefore they had asked that the convention be held earlier than usual. After the convention had been called to order by the chairman, he read the annual report. It was approved by acclamation. The question regarding benevolent work, especially in regard to homeless children, was particularly significant at this time and quite a coincidence that this question should be uppermost in the minds of the delegates, when just recently the president of the United States had called 200 persons to Washington to discuss the question on a national scale. Future resolutions will be presented to Congress and the Legislature. There is said to be some 200,000 homeless children in the various states. Of the Synod's eight orphanages, the Illinois congregations have two, where nearly 200 children are cared for. If it is the duty of the public to care for the children, then it is particularly the duty of the Christian Churches to do so, because our Lord and Leader said, "I did not come to be served, but to serve, and what you have done into one of these smallest ones you have done into me."</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1458.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Nearly 35 years ago the Augustana Synod organization took charge of the Andover Orphanage. The organization owns over 400 acres of farm land in the McHenry County, Illinois, where the old Home burned. A few years ago a new orphanage was built at Joliet, where at present 101 children are cared for. Besides, the Synod has asked for some $20,000 for an old people's Home. At the time the Andover Orphanage burned and the Joliet home had been built at quite a cost, it was possible to harbor 50 or 70 children. It was the opinion of some that the Andover children should be brought to the Joliet home. This was the problem subjected to discussion for four days. The issue whether to bring up the children in the city or in the country, as well as many other problems, was discussed. At last the question was voted upon, and the "country" received four-fifths of the votes. Here it was decided to rebuild the orphan home at Andover, Ill., and a new group of directors, consisting of twelve persons from various districts, were elected to supervise both Orphanage and the Old People's Home. It behooves all of us to be considerate at least in our attitude toward homeless children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
