<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-12-10">Dec. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Relief Campaign</title><title level="a" type="sub">Contributions are Coming in Slowly</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-12-10">Dec. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH RELIEF CAMPAIGN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Contributions are Coming in Slowly</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting of the Swedish-American Relief Committee last Friday evening, in the Chicago Bank of Commerce, the committee's treasurer Henry S. Henschen, reported that a number of small contributions have been received, but that so far the response to the appeal published in Swedish-American newspapers is far from satisfactory. It was, therefore, decided to repeat the call for aid both in the press and over the radio, again presenting to the Swedish-American public the cause of their destitute countrymen. If the relief work is to be continued on the scale on which it has been started, large sums are required, and there is no other way of getting them than by voluntary contributions.</p>
   <p>The committee is hopeful that the concert, which is to be given Sunday, December 21, in Orchestra Hall by the Swedish Choral Club in cooperation with the committee, will bring in a substantial amount of money. Chicago's <pb facs="5423404_4_0242.jpg" n="2"/>Swedes should take advantage of this opportunity to hear a "Christmas Service in Melody" and at the same time help their unfortunate countrymen, whose Christmas will be a rather sordid one at its best.</p>
   <p>But just buying tickets for this concert is not enough. Every Swede who can possibly do so should make a cash contribution to the relief fund. Remember that the distributing committee puts the money to work as soon as they receive it.</p>
   <p>Some two hundred unemployed are being fed every day by the Lake View Salvation Army Corps, and even though strict economy is being exercised, cash is required to keep this undertaking going. Mrs. Andrietta Wolt, the Swedish National Association's representative on the relief committee, is busier than ever. A steady stream of the needy is passing through her office at 3180 North Clark Street every day, and if anybody doubts that his contribution is being used to good advantage he should pay a visit <pb facs="5423404_4_0243.jpg" n="3"/>to that office, and his doubts will disappear.</p>
   <p>Contributions to the relief fund should be sent to the treasurer of the Relief Committee, Henry S. Henschen, Chicago Bank of Commerce, 7 South Dearborn Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
