<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-11-23">Nov. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish National Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0285</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0285.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-11-23">Nov. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH NATIONAL SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: In previous articles involving this organization, I have consistently called it the "Swedish National League," "league" being the correct translation of the Swedish word "Forbund". In my opinion the term "society" is actually wrong here. But it appears from the following article (in the telegram to the Governor of Utah), that the organization's official English name is the "Swedish National Society of Chicago".]</p>
   <p>A general membership meeting was held Monday, November 15, and was well attended by delegates from the various Swedish organizations in Chicago. Several important questions came under discussion. The Society is planning to distribute Christmas baskets of food among needy Swedish families, and the committee in charge of this work urged all member organizations to contribute to the best of their ability, so that unfortunate countrymen and their families may enjoy some Christmas cheer. Donations and requests for information should be addressed to W. Melinder, 1314 Early Avenue.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0286.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Notices of the progress of this undertaking will also be found in our Swedish newspapers. The meeting placed twenty-five dollars at the disposal of the committee for use in extraordinary cases, and it is hoped that this amount will be multiplied through voluntary individual contributions. The sum of ten dollars was voted for a sick countryman who is in great need.</p>
   <p>The meeting also voted to wire the following appeal to Governor Spry, of Utah, in behalf of the Swede, Joseph Hillstrom, who faces execution: "It was decided at the last meeting of the Swedish National Society of Chicago, an organization consisting of ninety Swedish societies, representing about thirty thousand Swedes in Cook County, to petition Your Honor to have the kindness to commute the sentence pronounced upon Joseph Hillstrom."</p>
   <p>"(Signed) W. Helinder, Secretary</p>
   <p>"1314 Early Avenue"</p>
   <p>The Society's great winter carnival will take place February 11, 12, and 13, <pb facs="5423404_4_0287.jpg" n="3"/>and the preparatory work is already well advanced. Another meeting will be held December 13 for the purpose of co-ordinating the work of distributing the Christmas baskets.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: In this article, the text of the telegram to Governor Spry is printed in English.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
