<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-06-05">June 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The President Has Spoken</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0359</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0359.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-06-05">June 5, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESIDENT HAS SPOKEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last few years much has been said and written about the alarming increase in crime and the laxity in law-enforcement, but when President Hoover discussed these questions in an address before members of the Associated Press last Monday, the speech attracted unusual attention, not only because the Chief executive of the United States was talking, but also because of the undeniable truthfulness and force of his words.</p>
   <p>Every honest, sincere citizen will endorse the statements which the President made on this occasion. Our liberties have to be limited by law, and the law constitutes the foundation and the cornerstone of democracy. A liberty which is not defined and limited by law is not worth much, a contempt for the law and laxity in the enforcement of it are the most dangerous enemies of popular government. When laws are disregarded, and crimes are committed without proper <pb facs="5423404_4_0360.jpg" n="2"/>punishment imposed on the perpetrators, our social structure is undermined, and if such a situation is permitted to exist long enough we shall sooner or later reach a crisis which may lead to the collapse of democracy and a new form of government, perhaps dictatorship.</p>
   <p>Hoover's address contained an admonition to all right-thinking citizens to back to the limit those whom they have appointed to enforce the law. Every man and every woman must realize that the strength of this nation depends on the respect for the law displayed by its citizens. When the people, through representatives, make laws, it is of paramount importance that these laws be enforced.</p>
   <p>If a law comes to be considered undesirable, so that, in the popular opinion, it should be repealed, that goal will be most quickly reached if one sees to it that the law is enforced to the letter. Through laxity in enforcement the number of lawbreakers increases, as does the disrespect for law in general.</p>
   <p>In the opinion of the President the increase in crime and the laxity in the <pb facs="5423404_4_0361.jpg" n="3"/>enforcement of the laws of the land constitute the most serious problem in this country today. In his address he compared the United States with other countries and showed that crime is more prevalent in this country than in any foreign nation. When serious crimes are committed, the perpetrators seldom receive adequate sentences. This is often due to lack of the proper attitude on the part of the judge and the jury. But according to the President the Federal Government now has under consideration certain reforms which are expected to lead to much sharper enforcement of the law. Mr. Hoover stated, however, that the root of the evil must be looked for in other quarters. Many citizens of high standing in their communities express contempt for such and such a law, and their attitude is contagious, causing an increase in the frequency of crime. It is therefore of the greatest importance that the man in the street shall wake up and realize that the fight which is being conducted against crime now in times of peace is just as important as that waged against external enemies in times of war.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
