<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1909-02-25">Feb. 25, 1909</date><title level="a">Report of National Society for 1908</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.8"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1909-02-25">Feb. 25, 1909</date><title level="a">REPORT OF NATIONAL SOCIETY FOR 1908</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The year 1908 has passed, and not since 1904 and 1905 have the Workers' needs in America been so apparent. And many there are, even among our countrymen, who during the past year have known what it is to suffer. This Society during this time has helped many who otherwise would have passed away. Help was given not only to new immigrants, but also to parents who could not manage for themselves without the help of others. During the past year the society helped many find work or whatever was needed. Hundreds of mothers, when all doors were closed to their mates, went out to wash and scrub to keep want out of their homes. During 1908, the Swedish National Society secured work for 1,706 men and 1,638 women, a total of 3,344 persons. Among this group we find all kinds of workers, from the lowest paid immigrant to the highest paid tradesman. Among the employers we find Chicago's foremost manufacturers. Work has been secured in nearly all the States of the Union, even in Florida, Kentucky, Texas, New Mexico.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0301.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among the jobs there were some in Minnesota, Michigan, and Wisconsin woods and farms.</p>
   <p>When work was not available, the society took care of the sick, the needy and the aged by giving them financial help. A total of $1,634.75 was spent in taking care of such cases, of which the following are examples: One poor woman with five children received help to return to her sister in Sweden, who had promised her a home. One woman with three children whose father had returned to Sweden seeking relief from tuberculosis but passed away, was given money for her journey home. Two old persons, two young women, and one father with a family, all ordered by the doctor to return to Sweden, were given help for their voyage. Three persons were aided to go to Colorado for their health. One aged woman was sent to the poorhouse <pb facs="5423404_4_0302.jpg" n="3"/>in Bowmanville. Besides these, 231 were helped with food, rent, coal, and medical care.</p>
   <p>For all this work, the officers of the National Swedish Society received no remuneration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
