<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-04-19">Apr. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Crime Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1922-04-19">Apr. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE CRIME SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Crimes of all kinds have been on the increase during the last few years; and investigations are under way for the purpose of uncovering the causes of this condition and discovering a possible cure. A commission of expert criminologists has been appointed, and its members visited the State prison at Joliet last week. Through conversations with some of the inmates, they tried to determine the latter's attitude toward society and life in general, and what the convicts themselves considered the main reasons why so many men, both young and mature, are tempted to enter upon a criminal career. The result was not sensational, but a few facts were brought out, and the commission learned something.</p>
   <p>A couple of convicts voiced the opinion that a considerable part of the responsibility rested upon society, declaring that nothing is more demoralizing <pb facs="5423404_4_0414.jpg" n="2"/>for a young man who has been convicted of a minor infringement of the law than to be placed in the company of hardened criminals while serving his prison term. Others blamed corrupt officials and rotten politics, by means of which lawbreakers are able to avoid punishment altogether or to get by with serving short terms in the penitentiary.</p>
   <p>All this was not news to the members of the commission. But it was probably useful for them to be reminded of these unpleasant facts. It should have a stimulating effect on the investigators, who are trying to get at the basic causes of the present crime situation and to find means of eliminating such causes.</p>
   <p>The current prevalence of crime is both regrettable and disgraceful, and thorough reform is much needed. Penal regulations must be revised, and, first <pb facs="5423404_4_0415.jpg" n="3"/>of all, the much-abused state parole law must be taken up for thorough revision.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
