<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-06-16">June 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedes! Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-06-16">June 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDES! DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.11......The "Independent Order of Good Templar" which each year celebrates in Good Templar Park, Geneva, Illinois, will also this year draw thousands of visitors to the festivities on the 19th of this month, on the banks of Fox River. Earlier years, Swedish Day celebration has been celebrated with ever increasing popularity, and it is expected that this years celebration will surpass all others, both in elaborate arrangement and attendance. Great preparations have been made for the program, which will consist of a large variety of music, song and speeches. The main speech of the day will be made by Editor Albert Wickman, the well-known "Apostle of Peace," who arrived here several months ago for a lecture tour, which has of necessity been cut short due to Mr. Wickman's illness.</p>
   <p>Editor Wickman, who in Sweden has received the "sobriquet" "The White General," <pb facs="5423404_4_1298.jpg" n="2"/>appears on this occasion for the first time before Chicago Swedes, but has already delivered several lectures in the East; a report from Jamestown, New York, tells how hoefor more than one and one half hours held his audience spellbound with descriptions of conditions in Sweden during the war, when Sweden's neutrality was severely put to trial. He spoke on Sweden as an example of peace loving countries, on the "Versailles Peace Treaty," and the deplorable conditions following it; he gave also a powerful description of the war and the ten or twelve millions of people, who gave up their lives on the "Altar of Mars."</p>
   <p>It is worth mentioning, that loudspeakers will be installed in the park, so that the speeches as well as the song and music can be heard throughout the park.</p>
   <p>Countrymen and women are appealed to not to forget Swedish Day in Good Templar Park, Geneva, Sunday June 19; there will be entertainment for both young and old. Food and refreshments will be served at moderate prices, and automobiles may be parked in the park in reserved places. The trip is made by train over <pb facs="5423404_4_1299.jpg" n="3"/>the Chicago, Aurora, Elgin Electric Railway from Quincy and Wells Streets; by automobiles over Route 6 (Roosevelt Road). Those living on the North Side will take Irving Park Boulevard to River Road, then this to Route 6. From Rockford, Route 5 to Elgin, then Route 22 to Geneva. Posters in appropriate places show the way to the park.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
