<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1909-09-30">Sept. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Old People's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1909-09-30">Sept. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD PEOPLE'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Old People's Home that was built during the Summer in beautiful North Evanston was dedicated last Sunday afternoon in the presence of about five thousand persons. Some of these already knew of this magnificent undertaking through our Swedish societies, and to those who had not known of its existence, it presented a magnificent sight. The location in the first place is as ideal as one could wish. An ideal setting of trees that is found in Evanston makes it unusually pleasant. The building is completed, and is a credit to those who planned it and made it possible. It is practical and tastefully arranged. From the massive basement, which holds the kitchen, to the management office on the roof, we see a well planned building, all of first class material, and first class workmanship. With the large reception room on the first floor, and the whole building divided into small pleasant rooms, which are inviting enough so that any one would want to live in one of them anytime. The furnishing of these <pb facs="5423404_4_0127.jpg" n="2"/>rooms have, to a large extent, been furnished and arranged by individual members of the societies, and this leads to a great variation. Space does not permit us to go into detail, but we will say that the whole thing is especially well arranged and constructed, and stands as an imposing monument to the Swedish people of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The dedication ceremonies were pleasant, and began with music from the Iduna Northern Star, and Viking players, under the leadership of Mr. William Anderson. After a short address of welcome by Mr. John Sandgren, chairman of the Old People's Home Society, the Swedish Song Society under the direction of Joel Mossberg, sang two pretty Swedish songs. Following this, vice-chairman Edwin A. Olson gave an address relative to the Home, and how it was made possible. He spoke of our obligation to those of our own nationality who are helpless and dependent. After music, which was appropriate for the occasion, the chairman of the building committee, Alfred A. Norton, presented the keys of the Home <pb facs="5423404_4_0128.jpg" n="3"/>to Charles Gustafson, chairman of the management of the Home. The Mayor of Evanston, Mr. Joseph E. Paden, gave an address of welcome in warm terms to the City of Evanston, and congratulated the Swedes in accomplishing so large and magnificent an undertaking for those who are needy. Dr. Ludwig Holms then gave a religious address, and asked the heavenly blessing from God on this institution for the old people. Then the Song Society sang the particularly appropriate song, "The Prayer of Strife." Congressman Fred Lundin also gave an address. There was more music, then the closing of this dedication service, which had made a profound impression upon everyone present.</p>
   <p>This Old People's Home Organization has for fifteen years gone forward in its determination, and should be recognized as an outstanding Swedish accomplishment. Those who in the beginning strove against unbelievable obstacles laid the foundation. No one mentioned, no one forgotten. Like those who now stand by and manage to carry on in an actual triumph, <pb facs="5423404_4_0129.jpg" n="4"/>we hope we will always find Swedish people here with minds, hearts, hands, and ready with their mite to continue the support of the Swedish Old People's Home in Evanston.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
