<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-10-10">Oct. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Abolish Ellis Island?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1613</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1613.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-10-10">Oct. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">ABOLISH ELLIS ISLAND?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Complaints have been frequent concerning current practices on Ellis Island, where arriving immigrants are examined and where it is decided whether or not they are to be permitted to enter this country. It is admitted that these complaints are justified in many cases, and Secretary of Labor Davis has just submitted a plan according to which Ellis Island would be abolished as a clearing house for immigrants. He recommends that the selection be made in their own homeland by American officials stationed there for that purpose. Such procedure would save much trouble, and, if it were adopted, immigrants would not have to fear that they might be refused admission after they had reached these shores.</p>
   <p>The plan seems sensible and practical, and might well find many supporters in Congress. But it is doubtful whether the proposal will be adopted, for it is certain to meet opposition in many foreign countries. One European <pb facs="5423404_4_1614.jpg" n="2"/>power has already lodged a protest against any possible procedure of this kind.</p>
   <p>An American immigration station cannot be established in a foreign country without the permission of the government of that country, and since some governments may be expected to refuse such permission, it is not likely that Secretary Davis' plan will materialize.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
