<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1895-02-27">Feb. 27, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Immigration to America</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial by C. F. P.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_1004</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1004.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1895-02-27">Feb. 27, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH IMMIGRATION TO AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial by C. F. P.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is generally known that many prominent men in the United States offer praise to our countrymen, the Swedes, and recognize the significance of their appearance on American soil. The Swedes are, qualitively speaking, one of the republic's most important factors. We will confirm this by mentioning a couple of facts from unwritten annals of the society of the Swedish-Americans. They will speak for themselves in regard to the significance of the Swedish-American nationality. To begin with, let us remember that there are at least one-million Swedes in America, of whom half are immigrants and the other half were born here. About 750,000 are farmers, which is very important to know. The majority of them have - like an outpost of the civilization - pressed themselves forward and westward where they have broken new fields for themselves and their generation. Thus they have laid millions of acres of virgin prairie under the plow in Illinois, Minnesota, Iowa, Indiana, Michigan, Kansas, Nebraska, Wisconsin, Dakota, and other states of the Union.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1005.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our countrymen have, in this respect, been one of the divisions in that great peace army, who, with painful, industrious efforts, have expanded the world and founded a dozen great new states, which in the near future, will each measure up to those in Europe both in spiritual and material wealth. To this we can add what the others have accomplished who have followed other professions; what these 300,000 have done on the field as mechanics and inventors is not insignificant and is of great importance to the world.</p>
   <p>Swedish-Americans take out hundreds of patents annually for various inventions, most of then in the mechanical field, and many of them are of the quality of genius, and of tremen do us importance for the mechanical expansion here and elsewhere. Let us but recall John Ericsson's glorious work when he, in time of need, saved the nation from danger, and changed a terrific defeat on the sea into a most splendid naval victory, the victory of the "Monitor," of which any nation's fleet can boast, over the "Merrimac." In other words, the mechanical genius of John Ericsson saved this nation, at least the coastal cities of the Northern States, who all were in great danger of being shelled by the rebels. Let us also remember something else. The Unionists had once lost the day at the great battle of Shiloh in 1862.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_1006.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Sherman's army began to doubt its ability to close the road to the North, but he gathered the routed companies together again and a new battle was fought, this time successfully, thanks to the fire from a cannon boat on the Mississippi River from a Swedish Battery, which had been formed in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Our nationality was active politically, also, during the same critical period. It is a fact that Abraham Lincoln never could have been elected president of the Republic had it not been for the Scandinavians in the West, who so unanimously voted for him. The result of the election of 1860 and 1864 was dependent on a small majority. If our nationality had been less educated, less liberty loving then it was, less moral; if it had then been less zealous for Lincoln's election, he would have lost. Had he failed to be elected president - well, nobody knows how it might have gone with the Union. It is quite possible, someone might say, that there would have been a compromise between the North and the South, and that the latter would have kept their beloved institution, slavery. That would have been a tremendous blow for the growth of the world for human victory over darkness and force. A few thousand Swedish-American votes cast as one in the political issue weighed the balance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
