<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-09-28">Sept. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of the Home for the Aged</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_4_0130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1909-09-28">Sept. 28, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF THE HOME FOR THE AGED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dedication of the Swedish Home for the Aged in Evanston last Sunday proved a memorable event for Chicago's Swedish-Americans. More than five thousand people came to see the Home, where so many of their aged countrymen will spend the evening of their lives.</p>
   <p>The Home is located in North Evanston, at Evanston Avenue and Grant Street, and already presents a stately appearance even though only its central section is completed at present. The wings will be added later. The interior is just as impressive, affording the residents all conveniences and solid comfort. Various Swedish societies have each furnished a room, and it is easy to see that the competition has been keen.</p>
   <p>The dedication ceremonies were festive and dignified, and included Swedish music and song.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_4_0131.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Several speeches were made by men prominent in Swedish affairs, and the Mayor of Evanston, Joseph Paden, spoke, congratulating Chicago's Swedes on this fine accomplishment.</p>
   <p>The completed section of the Home cost forty thousand dollars, including the ground, and its final cost will be approximately one hundred thousand dollars. Mr. Andrew Sandgren is the architect.</p>
   <p>Much credit is due those men and women who have been the leaders in this great undertaking, and the Home, even as it stands now, is a fine testimony of the sincere reverence with which the Swedish-Americans regard their aged countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
